<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="2CH" style="id">- The JPS Tanakh: Gender-Sensitive Edition</book>
  <para style="usfm">3.0</para>
  <para style="ide">UTF-8</para>
  <para style="rem">RJPS2</para>
  <para style="rem">© 2022 by The Jewish Publication Society, Philadelphia, PA, USA</para>
  <para style="h">2 Chronicles</para>
  <para style="toc1">2 Chronicles</para>
  <para style="toc2">2 Chronicles</para>
  <para style="toc3">2 Chron.</para>
  <para style="mt2">דברי הימים ב</para>
  <para style="mt1">2 Chronicles</para>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="2CH 1" />
  <para style="po">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 1:1" />Solomon son of David took firm hold of his kingdom, for <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> his God was with him and made him exceedingly great. <verse eid="2CH 1:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 1:2" />Solomon summoned all Israel—the officers of thousands and of hundreds, and the judges, and all the chiefs of all Israel, the heads of the clans. <verse eid="2CH 1:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 1:3" /><note caller="a" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1.3–13 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Cf. <char style="xt"><ref loc="1KI 3:4-15">1 Kings 3.4–15</ref></char>.</char></note>Then Solomon, and all the assemblage with him, went to the shrine at Gibeon, for the Tent of Meeting, which Moses the servant of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> had made in the wilderness, was there. <verse eid="2CH 1:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 1:4" />(But the Ark of God David had brought up from Kiriath-jearim to the place that David had prepared for it; for he had pitched a tent for it in Jerusalem.) <verse eid="2CH 1:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 1:5" />The bronze altar, which Bezalel son of Uri son of Hur had made, was also there before the Tabernacle of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>, and Solomon and the assemblage resorted to it. <verse eid="2CH 1:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 1:6" />There Solomon ascended the bronze altar before <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>, which was at the Tent of Meeting, and on it sacrificed a thousand burnt offerings.<verse eid="2CH 1:6" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 1:7" />That night, God appeared to<note caller="b" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1.7 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">appeared to </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or “made contact with.”</char></note> Solomon and said to him, “Ask, what shall I grant you?” <verse eid="2CH 1:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 1:8" />Solomon said to God, “You dealt most graciously with my father David, and now You have made me king in his stead. <verse eid="2CH 1:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 1:9" />Now, O <char style="nd"><char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> God, let Your promise to my father David be fulfilled; for You have made me king over a people as numerous as the dust of the earth. <verse eid="2CH 1:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 1:10" />Grant me then the wisdom and the knowledge to lead this people,<note caller="c" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1.10 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">to lead this people </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Lit. “that I may go out before this people and come in.”</char></note> for who can govern Your great people?” <verse eid="2CH 1:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 1:11" />God said to Solomon, “Because you want this, and have not asked for wealth, property, and glory, nor have you asked for the life of your enemy, or long life for yourself, but you have asked for the wisdom and the knowledge to be able to govern My people over whom I have made you king, <verse eid="2CH 1:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 1:12" />wisdom and knowledge are granted to you, and I grant you also wealth, property, and glory, the like of which no king before you has had, nor shall any after you have.” <verse eid="2CH 1:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 1:13" />From the shrine at Gibeon, from the Tent of Meeting, Solomon went to Jerusalem and reigned over Israel.<verse eid="2CH 1:13" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 1:14" />
    <note caller="d" style="f">
      <char style="fr" closed="false">1.14–17 </char>
      <char style="ft" closed="false">Cf. <char style="xt"><ref loc="1KI 10:26-29">1 Kings 10.26–29</ref></char>.</char>
    </note>Solomon assembled chariots and horses; he had 1,400 chariots and 12,000 horses that he stationed in the chariot towns and with the king in Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 1:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 1:15" />The king made silver and gold as plentiful in Jerusalem as stones, and cedars as plentiful as the sycamores in the Shephelah. <verse eid="2CH 1:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 1:16" />Solomon's horses were imported from Egypt and from Que; the king's traders would buy them from Que at the market price. <verse eid="2CH 1:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 1:17" />A chariot imported from Egypt cost 600 shekels of silver, and a horse 150. These in turn were exported by them<note caller="e" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1.17 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">them </char><char style="ft" closed="false">That is, Solomon's dealers.</char></note> to all the kings of the Hittites and the kings of the Arameans.<verse eid="2CH 1:17" /></para>
  <para style="b" />
  <para style="b" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 1:18" />Then Solomon resolved to build a House for <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>'s name and a royal palace for himself.<verse eid="2CH 1:18" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 1" />
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="2CH 2" />
  <para style="ph">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 2:1" />
    <note caller="a" style="f">
      <char style="fr" closed="false">2.1–17 </char>
      <char style="ft" closed="false">Cf. <char style="xt"><ref loc="1KI 5:15-30">1 Kings 5.15–30</ref></char>.</char>
    </note>Solomon mustered 70,000 basket carriers and 80,000 quarriers in the hills, with 3,600 supervisors. <verse eid="2CH 2:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 2:2" />Solomon sent this message to King Huram of Tyre, “In view of what you did for my father David in sending him cedars to build a palace for his residence— <verse eid="2CH 2:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 2:3" />see, I intend to build a House for the name of <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> my God, to whom I will dedicate it and in whose honor I will make incense offering of sweet spices, regular rows of bread, and the morning and evening burnt offerings on sabbaths, new moons, and festivals, as is Israel's eternal duty. <verse eid="2CH 2:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 2:4" />The House that I intend to build will be great, since our God is greater than all gods. <verse eid="2CH 2:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 2:5" />Who indeed is capable of building such a House! Even the heavens to their uttermost reaches cannot contain [God], and who am I that I should build such a House—except as a place for making burnt offerings? <verse eid="2CH 2:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 2:6" />Now send me someone skillful to work in gold, silver, bronze, and iron, and in purple, crimson, and blue yarn, and who knows how to engrave, alongside the skilled workers I have here in Judah and in Jerusalem, whom my father David provided. <verse eid="2CH 2:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 2:7" />Send me cedars, cypress, and <char style="tl">algum</char> wood from the Lebanon, for I know that your servants are skilled at cutting the trees of Lebanon. My servants will work with yours <verse eid="2CH 2:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 2:8" />to provide me with a great stock of timber; for the House that I intend to build will be singularly great. <verse eid="2CH 2:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 2:9" />I have allocated for your servants, the wood-cutters who fell the trees, 20,000 <char style="tl">kor</char>s of crushed wheat and 20,000 <char style="tl">kor</char>s of barley, 20,000 <char style="tl">bath</char>s of wine and 20,000 <char style="tl">bath</char>s of oil.”<verse eid="2CH 2:9" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 2:10" />Huram, king of Tyre, sent Solomon this written message in reply, “Because <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> loved the people of Israel,<note caller="b" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">2.10 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">the people of Israel </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Lit. “His people.”</char></note> you were made king over them.”<verse eid="2CH 2:10" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 2:11" />Huram continued, “Blessed is <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char>, God of Israel, who made the heavens and the earth, who gave King David a wise son, endowed with intelligence and understanding, to build a House for <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> and a royal palace for himself. <verse eid="2CH 2:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 2:12" />Now I am sending you someone skillful and intelligent, my master<note caller="c" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">2.12 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">master </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Lit. “father.”</char></note> Huram, <verse eid="2CH 2:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 2:13" />the son of a Danite woman, his father a Tyrian. He is skilled at working in gold, silver, bronze, iron, precious stones, and wood; in purple, blue, and crimson yarn and in fine linen; and at engraving and designing whatever will be required of him, alongside your skilled workers and those of my lord, your father David. <verse eid="2CH 2:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 2:14" />As to the wheat, barley, oil, and wine that my lord mentioned, let him send them to his servants. <verse eid="2CH 2:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 2:15" />We undertake to cut down as many trees of Lebanon as you need, and deliver them to you as rafts by sea to Jaffa; you will transport them to Jerusalem.”<verse eid="2CH 2:15" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 2:16" />Solomon took a census of all the resident aliens in the land of Israel, besides the census taken by his father David, and they were found to be 153,600. <verse eid="2CH 2:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 2:17" />He made 70,000 of them basket carriers, and 80,000 of them quarriers, with 3,600 supervisors to see that the people worked.<verse eid="2CH 2:17" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 2" />
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="2CH 3" />
  <para style="po">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 3:1" />
    <note caller="a" style="f">
      <char style="fr" closed="false">3.1–17 </char>
      <char style="ft" closed="false">Cf. <char style="xt"><ref loc="1KI 6">1 Kings 6</ref>; <ref loc="1KI 7:1-22">7.1–22</ref></char>.</char>
    </note>Then Solomon began to build the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> in Jerusalem on Mount Moriah, where [<char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>] had appeared to<note caller="b" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3.1 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">appeared to </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or “communicated with,” via the prophet Gad; see <char style="xt"><ref loc="1CH 21:18">1 Chron. 21.18</ref></char>.</char></note> his father David, at the place that David had designated, at the threshing floor of Ornan the Jebusite. <verse eid="2CH 3:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 3:2" />He began to build on the second day of the second month of the fourth year of his reign. <verse eid="2CH 3:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 3:3" />These were the dimensions Solomon established for building the House of God: its length in cubits, by the former measure, was 60, and its breadth was 20. <verse eid="2CH 3:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 3:4" />The length of the porch in front [was equal] to the breadth of the House—20 cubits, and its height was 120. Inside he overlaid it with pure gold. <verse eid="2CH 3:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 3:5" />The House itself he paneled with cypress wood. He overlaid it with fine gold and embossed on it palms and chains. <verse eid="2CH 3:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 3:6" />He studded the House with precious stones for decoration; the gold was from Parvaim. <verse eid="2CH 3:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 3:7" />He overlaid the House with gold—the beams, the thresholds, its walls and doors; he carved cherubim on the walls. <verse eid="2CH 3:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 3:8" />He made the Holy of Holies: its length was [equal to] the breadth of the house—20 cubits, and its breadth was 20 cubits. He overlaid it with 600 talents of fine gold. <verse eid="2CH 3:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 3:9" />The weight of the nails was 50 shekels of gold; the upper chambers he overlaid with gold. <verse eid="2CH 3:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 3:10" />He made two sculptured cherubim in the Holy of Holies, and they were overlaid with gold. <verse eid="2CH 3:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 3:11" />The outspread wings of the cherubim were 20 cubits across: one wing 5 cubits long touching one wall of the House, and the other wing 5 cubits long touching the wing of the other cherub; <verse eid="2CH 3:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 3:12" />one wing of the other [cherub] 5 cubits long extending to the other wall of the House, and its other wing 5 cubits long touching the wing of the first cherub. <verse eid="2CH 3:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 3:13" />The wingspread of these cherubim was thus 20 cubits across, and they were standing up facing the House. <verse eid="2CH 3:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 3:14" />He made the curtain of blue, purple, and crimson yarn and fine linen, and he worked cherubim into it. <verse eid="2CH 3:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 3:15" />At the front of the House he made two columns 35 cubits high; the capitals<note caller="c" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3.15 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">capitals </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Meaning of Heb. uncertain.</char></note> on top of them were 5 cubits high. <verse eid="2CH 3:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 3:16" />He made chainwork in the inner Sanctuary and set it on the top of the columns; he made a hundred pomegranates and set them into the chainwork. <verse eid="2CH 3:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 3:17" />He erected the columns in front of the Great Hall, one to its right and one to its left; the one to the right was called Jachin, and the one to the left, Boaz.<verse eid="2CH 3:17" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 3" />
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="2CH 4" />
  <para style="po">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 4:1" />
    <note caller="a" style="f">
      <char style="fr" closed="false">4.1–22 </char>
      <char style="ft" closed="false">Cf. <char style="xt"><ref loc="1KI 7:23-50">1 Kings 7.23–50</ref></char>.</char>
    </note>He made an altar of bronze 20 cubits long, 20 cubits wide, and 10 cubits high.<verse eid="2CH 4:1" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 4:2" />He made the sea<note caller="b" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">4.2 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">the sea </char><char style="ft" closed="false">I.e., a large basin.</char></note> of cast metal 10 cubits across from brim to brim, perfectly round; it was 5 cubits high, and its circumference was 30 cubits. <verse eid="2CH 4:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 4:3" />Beneath were figures of oxen set all around it, of 10 cubits, encircling the sea; the oxen were in two rows, cast in one piece with it. <verse eid="2CH 4:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 4:4" />It stood upon twelve oxen: three faced north, three faced west, three faced south, and three faced east, with the sea resting upon them; their haunches were all turned inward. <verse eid="2CH 4:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 4:5" />It was a handbreadth thick, and its brim was made like that of a cup, like the petals of a lily. It held 3,000 <char style="tl">bath</char>s.<verse eid="2CH 4:5" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 4:6" />He made ten bronze lavers for washing; he set five on the right and five on the left; they would rinse off in them the parts of the burnt offering; but the sea served the priests for washing. <verse eid="2CH 4:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 4:7" />He made ten lampstands of gold as prescribed, and placed them in the Great Hall, five on the right and five on the left. <verse eid="2CH 4:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 4:8" />He made ten tables and placed them in the Great Hall, five on the right and five on the left. He made one hundred gold basins. <verse eid="2CH 4:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 4:9" />He built the court of the priests and the great court, and doors for the great court; he overlaid the doors with bronze. <verse eid="2CH 4:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 4:10" />He set the sea on the right side, at the southeast corner.<verse eid="2CH 4:10" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 4:11" />Huram made the pails, the shovels, and the basins. With that Huram completed the work he had undertaken for King Solomon in the House of God: <verse eid="2CH 4:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 4:12" />the two columns, the globes, and the two capitals on top of the columns; and the two pieces of network to cover the two globes of the capitals on top of the columns; <verse eid="2CH 4:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 4:13" />the four hundred pomegranates for the two pieces of network, two rows of pomegranates for each network, to cover the two globes of the capitals on top of the columns; <verse eid="2CH 4:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 4:14" />he made the stands and the lavers upon the stands; <verse eid="2CH 4:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 4:15" />one sea with the twelve oxen beneath it; <verse eid="2CH 4:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 4:16" />the pails, the shovels, and the bowls.<note caller="c" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">4.16 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">bowls </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or “forks.”</char></note> And all the vessels made for King Solomon for the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> by Huram his master were of burnished bronze. <verse eid="2CH 4:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 4:17" />The king had them cast in molds dug out of the earth, in the plain of the Jordan between Succoth and Zeredah. <verse eid="2CH 4:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 4:18" />Solomon made a very large number of vessels; the weight of the bronze used could not be reckoned. <verse eid="2CH 4:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 4:19" />And Solomon made all the furnishings that were in the House of God: the altar of gold; the tables for the bread of display; <verse eid="2CH 4:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 4:20" />the lampstands and their lamps, to burn as prescribed in front of the inner Sanctuary, of solid gold; <verse eid="2CH 4:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 4:21" />and the petals, lamps, and tongs, of purest gold; <verse eid="2CH 4:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 4:22" />the snuffers, basins, ladles, and fire pans, of solid gold; and the entrance to the House: the doors of the innermost part of the House, the Holy of Holies, and the doors of the Great Hall of the House, of gold.<verse eid="2CH 4:22" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 4" />
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="2CH 5" />
  <para style="po">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 5:1" />
    <note caller="a" style="f">
      <char style="fr" closed="false">5.1–14 </char>
      <char style="ft" closed="false">Cf. <char style="xt"><ref loc="1KI 7:51-8:11">1 Kings 7.51–8.11</ref></char>.</char>
    </note>When all the work that King Solomon undertook for the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> was completed, Solomon brought the things that his father David had consecrated—the silver, the gold, and the utensils—and deposited them in the treasury of the House of God.<verse eid="2CH 5:1" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 5:2" />Then Solomon convoked the elders of Israel—all the heads of the tribes and the ancestral chiefs of the Israelites—in Jerusalem, to bring up the Ark of the Covenant of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> from the City of David, that is, Zion.<verse eid="2CH 5:2" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 5:3" />Israel's entire delegation assembled before the king at the Feast [of Booths], in the seventh month. <verse eid="2CH 5:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 5:4" />When all the elders of Israel had come, the Levites carried the Ark. <verse eid="2CH 5:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 5:5" />They brought up the Ark and the Tent of Meeting and all the holy vessels that were in the Tent—the Levite priests brought them up. <verse eid="2CH 5:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 5:6" />Meanwhile, King Solomon and the whole community of Israel, who had gathered to him before the Ark, were sacrificing sheep and oxen in such abundance that they could not be numbered or counted.<verse eid="2CH 5:6" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 5:7" />The priests brought the Ark of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>'s Covenant to its place in the inner Sanctuary of the House, in the Holy of Holies, beneath the wings of the cherubim; <verse eid="2CH 5:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 5:8" />for the cherubim had their wings spread out over the place of the Ark so that the cherubim covered the Ark and its poles from above. <verse eid="2CH 5:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 5:9" />The poles projected beyond the Ark and the ends of the poles were visible from the front of the inner Sanctuary, but they could not be seen from the outside; and there they remain to this day. <verse eid="2CH 5:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 5:10" />There was nothing inside the Ark but the two tablets that Moses placed [there] at Horeb, when <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> made [a Covenant] with the Israelites after their departure from Egypt. <verse eid="2CH 5:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 5:11" />When the priests came out of the Sanctuary—all the priests present had sanctified themselves, without keeping to the set divisions— <verse eid="2CH 5:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 5:12" />all the Levite singers, Asaph, Heman, Jeduthun, their sons and their brothers, dressed in fine linen, holding cymbals, harps, and lyres, were standing to the east of the altar, and with them were 120 priests who blew trumpets. <verse eid="2CH 5:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 5:13" />The trumpeters and the singers joined in unison to praise and extol <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>; and as the sound of the trumpets, cymbals, and other musical instruments, and the praise of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>, “who is good—and whose steadfast love is eternal,” grew louder, the House, the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>, was filled with a cloud. <verse eid="2CH 5:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 5:14" />The priests could not stay and perform the service because of the cloud, for the glory of <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> filled the House of God.<verse eid="2CH 5:14" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 5" />
  <chapter number="6" style="c" sid="2CH 6" />
  <para style="po">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 6:1" />
    <note caller="a" style="f">
      <char style="fr" closed="false">6.1–42 </char>
      <char style="ft" closed="false">Cf. <char style="xt"><ref loc="1KI 8:12-53">1 Kings 8.12–53</ref></char>.</char>
    </note>Then Solomon declared:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2CH 6:1">“<char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> has chosen</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2CH 6:1">To abide in a thick cloud;<verse eid="2CH 6:1" /></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 6:2" />I have built for You</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2CH 6:2">A stately House,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2CH 6:2">And a place where You</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2CH 6:2">May dwell forever.”<verse eid="2CH 6:2" /></para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 6:3" />Then, as the whole congregation of Israel stood, the king turned and blessed the whole congregation of Israel. <verse eid="2CH 6:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 6:4" />He said, “Blessed is <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> God of Israel, who made a promise to my father David and fulfilled it<note caller="b" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6.4 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">who made a promise to my father David and fulfilled it </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Lit. “who spoke with His own mouth a promise to my father David and has fulfilled with His own hands.”</char></note>—after having said, <verse eid="2CH 6:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 6:5" />‘From the time I brought My people out of the land of Egypt, I never chose a city from among all the tribes of Israel to build a House where My name might abide; nor did I choose anyone to be the leader of My people Israel. <verse eid="2CH 6:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 6:6" />But then I chose Jerusalem for My name to abide there, and I chose David to rule My people Israel.’<verse eid="2CH 6:6" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 6:7" />“Now my father David had wanted to build a House for the name of <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> God of Israel. <verse eid="2CH 6:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 6:8" />But <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> said to my father David, ‘As for your wanting to build a House for My name, you do well to want that. <verse eid="2CH 6:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 6:9" />However, you shall not build the House; your son, the issue of your loins, he shall build the House for My name.’ <verse eid="2CH 6:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 6:10" />Now <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> has fulfilled the promise that was made. I have succeeded<note caller="c" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6.10 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">succeeded </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Lit. “risen in place of.”</char></note> my father David and have ascended the throne of Israel, as <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> promised. I have built the House for the name of <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> God of Israel, <verse eid="2CH 6:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 6:11" />and there I have set the Ark containing the Covenant that <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> made with the Israelites.”<verse eid="2CH 6:11" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 6:12" />Then, standing before the altar of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> in front of the whole congregation of Israel, he spread forth his hands. <verse eid="2CH 6:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 6:13" />Solomon had made a bronze platform<note caller="d" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6.13 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">platform </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Meaning of Heb. uncertain.</char></note> and placed it in the midst of the Great Court; it was 5 cubits long and 5 cubits wide and 3 cubits high. He stood on it; then, kneeling in front of the whole congregation of Israel, he spread forth his hands to heaven <verse eid="2CH 6:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 6:14" />and said, “O <char style="nd"><char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> God of Israel, there is no god like You in the heavens and on the earth, You who steadfastly maintain the Covenant with Your servants who walk before You with all their heart; <verse eid="2CH 6:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 6:15" />You who have kept the promises You made to Your servant, my father David; You made a promise and have fulfilled it—as is now the case. <verse eid="2CH 6:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 6:16" />And now, O <char style="nd"><char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> God of Israel, keep that promise that You made to Your servant, my father David, ‘You shall never lack a descendant<note caller="e" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6.16 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">You shall never lack a descendant </char><char style="ft" closed="false">See note at <char style="xt"><ref loc="1KI 2:4">1 Kings 2.4</ref></char>.</char></note> in My sight sitting on the throne of Israel if only your children will look to their way and walk in the [path] of My teachings as you have walked before Me.’ <verse eid="2CH 6:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 6:17" />Now, therefore, O God of Israel, let the promise that You made to Your servant, my father David, be confirmed.<verse eid="2CH 6:17" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 6:18" />“Does God really dwell with mortals on earth? Even the heavens to their uttermost reaches cannot contain You; how much less this House that I have built! <verse eid="2CH 6:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 6:19" />Yet turn, O <char style="nd"><char style="sc">Eternal</char> One</char> my God, to the prayer and supplication of Your servant, and hear the cry and the prayer that Your servant offers to You. <verse eid="2CH 6:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 6:20" />May Your eyes be open day and night toward this House, toward the place where You have resolved to make Your name abide; may You heed the prayers that Your servant offers toward this place. <verse eid="2CH 6:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 6:21" />And when You hear the supplications that Your servant and Your people Israel offer toward this place, give heed in Your heavenly abode—give heed and pardon.<verse eid="2CH 6:21" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 6:22" />“If one person commits an offense against another and is made to take an oath and utter a self-imprecation<note caller="f" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6.22 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">and is made to take an oath and utter a self-imprecation </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or “and the latter utters an imprecation to bring a curse upon the former.”</char></note> and, with that imprecation, comes before Your altar in this House, <verse eid="2CH 6:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="2CH 6:23" />may You hear in heaven and take action to judge Your servants, requiting the one who is in the wrong by bringing down the punishment of their conduct on their head—while vindicating the other, who is in the right, by rewarding them according to their righteousness.<verse eid="2CH 6:23" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="2CH 6:24" />“Should Your people Israel be defeated by an enemy because they have sinned against You, and then once again acknowledge Your name and offer prayer and supplication to You in this House, <verse eid="2CH 6:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="2CH 6:25" />may You hear in heaven and pardon the sin of Your people Israel, and restore them to the land that You gave to them and to their ancestors.<verse eid="2CH 6:25" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="2CH 6:26" />“Should the heavens be shut up and there be no rain because they have sinned against You, and then they pray toward this place and acknowledge Your name and repent of their sins, because You humbled them, <verse eid="2CH 6:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="2CH 6:27" />may You hear in heaven and pardon the sin of Your servants, Your people Israel, when You have shown them the proper way in which they are to walk, and send down rain upon the land that You gave to Your people as their heritage. <verse eid="2CH 6:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="2CH 6:28" />So, too, if there is a famine in the land, if there is pestilence, blight, mildew, locusts, or caterpillars, or if an enemy oppresses them in any of the settlements of their land.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2CH 6:28">“In any plague and in any disease, <verse eid="2CH 6:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="2CH 6:29" />any prayer or supplication offered by any person among all Your people Israel—each of whom knows their own affliction and pain—when they spread forth their hands toward this House, <verse eid="2CH 6:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="2CH 6:30" />may You hear in Your heavenly abode, and pardon. Deal with that individual according to their ways, as You know their heart to be—for You alone know every human heart. <verse eid="2CH 6:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="2CH 6:31" />Thus may Your people<note caller="g" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6.31 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">Your people </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Heb. “they.”</char></note> revere You all the days that they live on the land that You gave to our ancestors.<verse eid="2CH 6:31" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="2CH 6:32" />“Or if a foreigner who is not of Your people Israel comes from a distant land for the sake of Your great name, Your mighty hand, and Your outstretched arm—and if this person comes to pray toward this House, <verse eid="2CH 6:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="2CH 6:33" />may You hear in Your heavenly abode and grant whatever the foreigner appeals to You for. Thus all the peoples of the earth will know Your name and revere You, as does Your people Israel; and they will recognize that Your name is attached to this House that I have built.<verse eid="2CH 6:33" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="2CH 6:34" />“When Your people take the field against their enemies in a campaign on which You send them, and they pray to You in the direction of the city that You have chosen and the House that I have built to Your name, <verse eid="2CH 6:34" /><verse number="35" style="v" sid="2CH 6:35" />may You hear in heaven their prayer and supplication and uphold their cause.<verse eid="2CH 6:35" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="2CH 6:36" />“When they sin against You—for there is no mortal who does not sin—and You are angry with them and deliver them to the enemy, and their captors carry them off to an enemy land, near or far; <verse eid="2CH 6:36" /><verse number="37" style="v" sid="2CH 6:37" />and they take it to heart in the land to which they have been carried off, and repent and make supplication to You in the land of their captivity, saying, ‘We have sinned, we have acted perversely, we have acted wickedly,’ <verse eid="2CH 6:37" /><verse number="38" style="v" sid="2CH 6:38" />and they turn back to You with all their heart and soul, in the land of their captivity where they were carried off, and pray in the direction of their land that You gave to their ancestors and the city that You have chosen, and toward the House that I have built for Your name— <verse eid="2CH 6:38" /><verse number="39" style="v" sid="2CH 6:39" />may You hear their prayer and supplication in Your heavenly abode, uphold their cause, and pardon Your people who have sinned against You. <verse eid="2CH 6:39" /><verse number="40" style="v" sid="2CH 6:40" />Now My God, may Your eyes be open and Your ears attentive to prayer from this place, and now,<verse eid="2CH 6:40" /></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="2CH 6:41" />Advance, O <char style="nd"><char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> God, to your resting-place,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2CH 6:41">You and Your mighty Ark.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2CH 6:41">Your priests, O <char style="nd"><char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> God, are clothed in triumph;</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2CH 6:41">Your loyal ones will rejoice in [Your] goodness.<verse eid="2CH 6:41" /></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="42" style="v" sid="2CH 6:42" />O <char style="nd"><char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> God,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2CH 6:42">do not reject Your anointed one;</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2CH 6:42">remember the loyalty of Your servant David.”<verse eid="2CH 6:42" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 6" />
  <chapter number="7" style="c" sid="2CH 7" />
  <para style="po">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 7:1" />
    <note caller="a" style="f">
      <char style="fr" closed="false">7.1–22 </char>
      <char style="ft" closed="false">Cf. <char style="xt"><ref loc="1KI 8:54-9:9">1 Kings 8.54–9.9</ref></char>.</char>
    </note>When Solomon finished praying, fire descended from heaven and consumed the burnt offering and the sacrifices, and <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>'s glory filled the House. <verse eid="2CH 7:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 7:2" />The priests could not enter the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>, for <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>'s glory filled the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>. <verse eid="2CH 7:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 7:3" />All the Israelites witnessed the descent of the fire and <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>'s glory on the House; they knelt with their faces to the ground and prostrated themselves, praising <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>, “who is good—and whose steadfast love is eternal.”<verse eid="2CH 7:3" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 7:4" />Then the king and all the people offered sacrifices before <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>. <verse eid="2CH 7:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 7:5" />King Solomon offered as sacrifices 22,000 oxen and 120,000 sheep; thus the king and all the people dedicated the House of God. <verse eid="2CH 7:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 7:6" />The priests stood at their watches; the Levites with the instruments for <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>'s music that King David had made to praise <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>, “whose steadfast love is eternal,” by means of the psalms of David that they knew. The priests opposite them blew trumpets while all Israel were standing.<verse eid="2CH 7:6" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 7:7" />Solomon consecrated the center of the court in front of the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>, because he presented there the burnt offerings and the fat parts of the offerings of well-being, since the bronze altar that Solomon had made was not able to hold the burnt offerings, the grain offerings, and the fat parts. <verse eid="2CH 7:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 7:8" />At that time Solomon kept the Feast for seven days—all Israel with him—a great assemblage from Lebo-hamath to the Wadi of Egypt.<verse eid="2CH 7:8" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 7:9" />On the eighth day they held a solemn gathering; they observed the dedication of the altar seven days, and the Feast seven days. <verse eid="2CH 7:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 7:10" />On the twenty-third day of the seventh month he dismissed the people to their homes, rejoicing and in good spirits over the goodness that <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> had shown to David and Solomon and the people Israel.<verse eid="2CH 7:10" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 7:11" />Thus Solomon finished building the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> and the royal palace; Solomon succeeded in everything he had set his heart on accomplishing with regard to the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> and his palace. <verse eid="2CH 7:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 7:12" /><char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> appeared to<note caller="b" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">7.12 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">appeared to </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or “made contact with.”</char></note> Solomon at night and said to him, “I have heard your prayer and have chosen this site as My House of sacrifice. <verse eid="2CH 7:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 7:13" />If I shut up the heavens and there is no rain; if I command the locusts to ravage the land; or if I let loose pestilence against My people, <verse eid="2CH 7:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 7:14" />when My people, who bear My name, humble themselves, pray, and seek My favor and turn from their evil ways, I will hear in My heavenly abode and forgive their sins and heal their land. <verse eid="2CH 7:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 7:15" />Now My eyes will be open and My ears attentive to the prayers from this place. <verse eid="2CH 7:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 7:16" />And now I have chosen and consecrated this House that My name be there forever. My eyes and My heart shall always be there. <verse eid="2CH 7:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 7:17" />As for you, if you walk before Me as your father David walked before Me, doing all that I have commanded you, keeping My laws and rules, <verse eid="2CH 7:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 7:18" />then I will establish your royal throne over Israel forever, in accordance with the Covenant I made with your father David, saying, ‘You shall never lack a descendant<note caller="c" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">7.18 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">You shall never lack a descendant </char><char style="ft" closed="false">See note at <char style="xt"><ref loc="1KI 2:4">1 Kings 2.4</ref></char>.</char></note> ruling over Israel.’ <verse eid="2CH 7:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 7:19" />But if you turn away from Me and forsake My laws and commandments that I set before you, and go and serve other gods and worship them, <verse eid="2CH 7:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 7:20" />then I will uproot Israel<note caller="d" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">7.20 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">Israel </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Heb. “them”; cf. <char style="xt"><ref loc="1KI 9:7">1 Kings 9.7</ref></char>.</char></note> from My land that I gave them, and this House that I consecrated to My name I shall cast out of my sight, and make it a proverb and a byword among all peoples. <verse eid="2CH 7:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 7:21" />And as for this House, once so exalted, everyone passing by it shall be appalled and say, ‘Why did <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> do thus to this land and to this House?’ <verse eid="2CH 7:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 7:22" />And the reply will be, ‘It is because they forsook <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> God of their ancestors who freed them from the land of Egypt, and adopted other gods and worshiped them and served them; therefore all this calamity was brought upon them.’”<verse eid="2CH 7:22" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 7" />
  <chapter number="8" style="c" sid="2CH 8" />
  <para style="po">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 8:1" />
    <note caller="a" style="f">
      <char style="fr" closed="false">8.1–18 </char>
      <char style="ft" closed="false">Cf. <char style="xt"><ref loc="1KI 9:10-28">1 Kings 9.10–28</ref></char>.</char>
    </note>At the end of twenty years, during which Solomon constructed the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> and his palace— <verse eid="2CH 8:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 8:2" />Solomon also rebuilt the cities that Huram had given to him,<note caller="b" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8.2 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">him </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Heb. “Solomon.”</char></note> and settled Israelites in them— <verse eid="2CH 8:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 8:3" />Solomon marched against Hamath-zobah and overpowered it. <verse eid="2CH 8:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 8:4" />He built Tadmor in the desert and all the garrison towns that he built in Hamath. <verse eid="2CH 8:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 8:5" />He built Upper Beth-horon and Lower Beth-horon as fortified cities with walls, gates, and bars, <verse eid="2CH 8:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 8:6" />as well as Baalath and all of Solomon's garrison towns, chariot towns, and towns for his riders<note caller="c" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8.6 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">riders </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or “horses”; force of Heb. <char style="tl">parash(im)</char> uncertain.</char></note>—everything that Solomon desired to build in Jerusalem and in the Lebanon, and throughout the territory that he ruled. <verse eid="2CH 8:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 8:7" />All the people that were left of the Hittites, Amorites, Perizzites, Hivites, and Jebusites, none of whom were of Israelite stock— <verse eid="2CH 8:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 8:8" />those of their descendants who were left after them in the land, whom the Israelites had not annihilated—these Solomon subjected to forced labor, as is still the case. <verse eid="2CH 8:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 8:9" />But the Israelites, none of whom Solomon enslaved for his works, served as soldiers and as his chief officers, and as commanders of his chariots and riders. <verse eid="2CH 8:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 8:10" />These were King Solomon's prefects—250 supervisors over the people. <verse eid="2CH 8:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 8:11" />Solomon brought up Pharaoh's daughter from the City of David to the palace that he had built for her, for he said, “No wife of mine shall dwell in a palace of King David of Israel, for [the area] is sacred since the Ark of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> has entered it.”<verse eid="2CH 8:11" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 8:12" />At that time, Solomon offered burnt offerings on the altar that he had built in front of the porch. <verse eid="2CH 8:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 8:13" />What was due for each day he sacrificed according to the commandment of Moses for the sabbaths, the new moons, and the thrice-yearly festivals—the Feast of Unleavened Bread, the Feast of Weeks, and the Feast of Booths. <verse eid="2CH 8:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 8:14" />Following the prescription of his father David, he set up the divisions of the priests for their duties, and the Levites for their watches, to praise and to serve alongside the priests, according to each day's requirement, and the gatekeepers in their watches, gate by gate, for such was the commandment of David, the agent of God. <verse eid="2CH 8:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 8:15" />They did not depart from the commandment of the king relating to the priests and the Levites in all these matters and also relating to the treasuries. <verse eid="2CH 8:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 8:16" />And all of Solomon's work was well executed from the day the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> was founded until the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> was completed to perfection.<verse eid="2CH 8:16" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 8:17" />At that time Solomon went to Ezion-geber and to Eloth on the seacoast of the land of Edom. <verse eid="2CH 8:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 8:18" />Huram sent him, under the charge of servants, a fleet with a crew of expert seamen; they went with Solomon's men to Ophir, and obtained gold there in the amount of 450 talents, which they brought to King Solomon.<verse eid="2CH 8:18" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 8" />
  <chapter number="9" style="c" sid="2CH 9" />
  <para style="po">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 9:1" />
    <note caller="a" style="f">
      <char style="fr" closed="false">9.1–31 </char>
      <char style="ft" closed="false">Cf. <char style="xt"><ref loc="1KI 10">1 Kings 10</ref>; <ref loc="1KI 11:41-43">11.41–43</ref></char>.</char>
    </note>The queen of Sheba heard of Solomon's fame, and came to Jerusalem to test Solomon with hard questions, accompanied by a very large retinue, including camels bearing spices, a great quantity of gold, and precious stones. When she came to Solomon, she spoke to him of all that she had on her mind. <verse eid="2CH 9:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 9:2" />Solomon had answers for all her questions; there was nothing that Solomon did not know, nothing to which he could not give her an answer.<verse eid="2CH 9:2" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 9:3" />When the queen of Sheba saw how wise Solomon was and the palace he had built, <verse eid="2CH 9:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 9:4" />the fare of his table, the seating of his courtiers, the service and attire of his attendants, his butlers and their attire, and the procession with which he went up to the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>, it took her breath away. <verse eid="2CH 9:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 9:5" />She said to the king, “What I heard in my own land about you and your wisdom was true. <verse eid="2CH 9:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 9:6" />I did not believe what they said until I came and saw with my own eyes that not even the half of your great wisdom had been described to me; you surpass the report that I heard. <verse eid="2CH 9:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 9:7" />How fortunate are your people and how fortunate are these courtiers of yours who are always in attendance on you and can hear your wisdom! <verse eid="2CH 9:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 9:8" />Blessed is <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> your God, who favored you and set you on the throne as a king before <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char>. It is because of your God's love for Israel and in order to establish them forever that you were made king over them to execute righteous justice.”<verse eid="2CH 9:8" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 9:9" />She presented the king with 120 talents of gold, and a vast quantity of spices and precious stones. There were no such spices as those that the queen of Sheba gave to King Solomon— <verse eid="2CH 9:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 9:10" />also, the servants of Huram and Solomon who brought gold from Ophir brought <char style="tl">algum</char>-wood and precious stones. <verse eid="2CH 9:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 9:11" />The king made of the <char style="tl">algum</char>-wood ramps for the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> and for the royal palace, and lyres and harps for the musicians, whose like had never before been seen in the land of Judah— <verse eid="2CH 9:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 9:12" />King Solomon, in turn, gave the queen of Sheba everything she expressed a desire for, exceeding a return for what she had brought to the king. Then she and her courtiers left and returned to her own land.<verse eid="2CH 9:12" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 9:13" />The gold that Solomon received every year weighed 666 gold talents, <verse eid="2CH 9:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 9:14" />besides what traders<note caller="b" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9.14 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">traders </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or “traders' agents.”</char></note> and merchants brought, and the gold and silver that all the kings of Arabia and governors of the regions brought to Solomon. <verse eid="2CH 9:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 9:15" />King Solomon made 200 shields of beaten gold—600 shekels of beaten gold for each shield, <verse eid="2CH 9:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 9:16" />and 300 bucklers of beaten gold—300 [shekels] of gold for each buckler. The king placed them in the Lebanon Forest House. <verse eid="2CH 9:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 9:17" />The king also made a large throne of ivory, overlaid with pure gold. <verse eid="2CH 9:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 9:18" />Six steps led up to the throne; and the throne had a golden footstool attached to it, and arms on either side of the seat. Two lions stood beside the arms, <verse eid="2CH 9:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 9:19" />and twelve lions stood on the six steps, six on either side. None such was ever made for any other kingdom. <verse eid="2CH 9:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 9:20" />All of King Solomon's drinking vessels were of gold, and all the utensils of the Lebanon Forest House were of pure gold; silver counted for nothing in Solomon's days. <verse eid="2CH 9:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 9:21" />The king's fleet traveled to Tarshish with Huram's servants. Once every three years, the Tarshish fleet came in, bearing gold and silver, ivory, apes, and peacocks.<verse eid="2CH 9:21" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 9:22" />King Solomon surpassed all the royal rulers of the earth in wealth and wisdom. <verse eid="2CH 9:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="2CH 9:23" />Every one of them came to pay homage to Solomon and to listen to the wisdom with which God had endowed him. <verse eid="2CH 9:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="2CH 9:24" />Each brought tribute—silver and gold objects, robes, weapons, and spices, horses and mules—in the amount due each year. <verse eid="2CH 9:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="2CH 9:25" />Solomon had 4,000 stalls for horses and chariots, and 12,000 riders, which he stationed in the chariot towns and with the king in Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 9:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="2CH 9:26" />He ruled over all the kings from the Euphrates to the land of the Philistines and to the border of Egypt. <verse eid="2CH 9:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="2CH 9:27" />The king made silver as plentiful in Jerusalem as stones, and cedars as plentiful as sycamores in the Shephelah. <verse eid="2CH 9:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="2CH 9:28" />Horses were brought for Solomon from Egypt and all the lands. <verse eid="2CH 9:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="2CH 9:29" />The other events of Solomon's reign, early and late, are recorded in the chronicle of the prophet Nathan and in the prophecies of Ahijah the Shilonite and in the visions of Jedo the seer concerning Jeroboam son of Nebat. <verse eid="2CH 9:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="2CH 9:30" />Solomon reigned forty years over all Israel in Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 9:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="2CH 9:31" />Solomon rested with his ancestors and was buried in the city of his father David; his son Rehoboam succeeded him as king.<verse eid="2CH 9:31" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 9" />
  <chapter number="10" style="c" sid="2CH 10" />
  <para style="po">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 10:1" />
    <note caller="a" style="f">
      <char style="fr" closed="false">10.1–19 </char>
      <char style="ft" closed="false">Cf. <char style="xt"><ref loc="1KI 12:1-19">1 Kings 12.1–19</ref></char>.</char>
    </note>Rehoboam went to Shechem, for all Israel had come to Shechem to acclaim him king. <verse eid="2CH 10:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 10:2" />Jeroboam son of Nebat learned of it while he was in Egypt where he had fled from King Solomon, and Jeroboam returned from Egypt. <verse eid="2CH 10:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 10:3" />They sent for him; and Jeroboam and all Israel came and spoke to Rehoboam as follows: <verse eid="2CH 10:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 10:4" />“Your father made our yoke heavy. Now lighten the harsh labor and the heavy yoke that your father laid on us, and we will serve you.” <verse eid="2CH 10:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 10:5" />He answered them, “Come back to me in three days.” So the people went away.<verse eid="2CH 10:5" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 10:6" />King Rehoboam took counsel with the elders who had served during the lifetime of his father Solomon. He said, “What answer do you counsel to give these people?” <verse eid="2CH 10:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 10:7" />They answered him, “If you will be good to these people and appease them and speak to them with kind words, they will be your servants always.” <verse eid="2CH 10:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 10:8" />But he ignored the counsel that the elders gave him, and took counsel with the young men who had grown up with him and were serving him. <verse eid="2CH 10:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 10:9" />“What,” he asked, “do you counsel that we reply to these people who said to me, ‘Lighten the yoke that your father laid on us’?” <verse eid="2CH 10:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 10:10" />And the young men who had grown up with him answered, “Speak thus to the people who said to you, ‘Your father made our yoke heavy, now you make it lighter for us.’ Say to them, ‘My little finger is thicker than my father's loins. <verse eid="2CH 10:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 10:11" />My father imposed a heavy yoke on you, and I will add to your yoke; my father flogged you with whips, but I [will do so] with scorpions.’”<verse eid="2CH 10:11" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 10:12" />Jeroboam and all the people came to Rehoboam on the third day, since the king had told them, “Come back on the third day.” <verse eid="2CH 10:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 10:13" />The king answered them harshly; thus King Rehoboam ignored the elders' counsel. <verse eid="2CH 10:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 10:14" />He spoke to them in accordance with the counsel of the young men, and said, “I will make<note caller="b" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">10.14 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">I will make </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Some mss. and printed editions read “my father made”; cf. <char style="xt"><ref loc="1KI 12:14">1 Kings 12.14</ref></char>.</char></note> your yoke heavy, and I will add to it; my father flogged you with whips, but I [will do so] with scorpions.” <verse eid="2CH 10:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 10:15" />The king did not listen to the people, for God had brought it about—in order to fulfill the promise that <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> had made through Ahijah the Shilonite to Jeroboam son of Nebat. <verse eid="2CH 10:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 10:16" />When all Israel [saw] that the king had not listened to them, the people answered the king:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2CH 10:16">“We have no portion in David,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2CH 10:16">No share in Jesse's son!</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2CH 10:16">Everyone to your tents, O Israel!</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2CH 10:16">Now look to your own house, O David.”</para>
  <para style="m" vid="2CH 10:16">So all Israel returned to their homes.<note caller="c" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">10.16 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">homes </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Lit. “tents.”</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 10:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 10:17" />But Rehoboam continued to reign over the Israelites who lived in the towns of Judah. <verse eid="2CH 10:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 10:18" />King Rehoboam sent out Hadoram, who was in charge of the forced labor, but the Israelites pelted him to death with stones. Thereupon, King Rehoboam hurriedly mounted his chariot and fled to Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 10:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 10:19" />Israel has been in revolt against the house of David to this day.<verse eid="2CH 10:19" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 10" />
  <chapter number="11" style="c" sid="2CH 11" />
  <para style="po">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 11:1" />
    <note caller="a" style="f">
      <char style="fr" closed="false">11.1–4 </char>
      <char style="ft" closed="false">Cf. <char style="xt"><ref loc="1KI 12:21-24">1 Kings 12.21–24</ref></char>.</char>
    </note>When Rehoboam arrived in Jerusalem, he mustered the house of Judah and Benjamin, 180,000 of the best soldiers, to make war with Israel in order to restore the kingdom to Rehoboam. <verse eid="2CH 11:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 11:2" />But the word of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> came to Shemaiah, the agent of God: <verse eid="2CH 11:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 11:3" />“Say to Rehoboam son of Solomon king of Judah, and to all Israel in Judah and Benjamin: <verse eid="2CH 11:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 11:4" />Thus said <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>: You shall not set out to make war on your kin. Return to your homes, for this thing has been brought about by Me.” They heeded <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>'s words and refrained from marching against Jeroboam. <verse eid="2CH 11:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 11:5" />Rehoboam dwelt in Jerusalem and built fortified towns in Judah. <verse eid="2CH 11:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 11:6" />He built up Bethlehem, and Etam, and Tekoa, <verse eid="2CH 11:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 11:7" />and Beth-zur, and Soco, and Adullam, <verse eid="2CH 11:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 11:8" />and Gath, and Mareshah, and Ziph, <verse eid="2CH 11:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 11:9" />and Adoraim, and Lachish, and Azekah, <verse eid="2CH 11:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 11:10" />and Zorah, and Aijalon, and Hebron, which are in Judah and in Benjamin, as fortified towns. <verse eid="2CH 11:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 11:11" />He strengthened the fortified towns and put commanders in them, along with stores of food, oil, and wine, <verse eid="2CH 11:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 11:12" />and shields and spears in every town. He strengthened them exceedingly; thus Judah and Benjamin were his.<verse eid="2CH 11:12" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 11:13" />The priests and the Levites, from all their territories throughout Israel, presented themselves to him. <verse eid="2CH 11:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 11:14" />The Levites had left their pasturelands and their holdings and had set out for Judah and Jerusalem, for Jeroboam and his sons had prevented them from serving <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>, <verse eid="2CH 11:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 11:15" />having appointed his own priests for the shrines, goat-demons, and calves that he had made. <verse eid="2CH 11:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 11:16" />From all the tribes of Israel, those intent on seeking <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> God of Israel followed them to Jerusalem, to sacrifice to <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> God of their ancestors. <verse eid="2CH 11:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 11:17" />They strengthened the kingdom of Judah, and supported Rehoboam son of Solomon for three years, for they followed the ways of David and Solomon for three years.<verse eid="2CH 11:17" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 11:18" />Rehoboam married Mahalath daughter of Jerimoth son of David, and Abihail daughter of Eliab son of Jesse. <verse eid="2CH 11:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 11:19" />She bore him sons: Jeush, Shemariah, and Zaham. <verse eid="2CH 11:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 11:20" />He then took Maacah daughter of Absalom; she bore him Abijah, Attai, Ziza, and Shelomith. <verse eid="2CH 11:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 11:21" />Rehoboam loved Maacah daughter of Absalom more than his other wives and concubines—for he took eighteen wives and sixty concubines; he begot twenty-eight sons and sixty daughters. <verse eid="2CH 11:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 11:22" />Rehoboam designated Abijah son of Maacah as chief and leader among his brothers, for he intended him to be his successor. <verse eid="2CH 11:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="2CH 11:23" />He prudently distributed all his sons throughout the regions of Judah and Benjamin and throughout the fortified towns; he provided them with abundant food, and he sought many wives for them.<verse eid="2CH 11:23" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 11" />
  <chapter number="12" style="c" sid="2CH 12" />
  <para style="po">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 12:1" />When the kingship of Rehoboam was firmly established, and he grew strong, he abandoned the Teaching of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>, he and all Israel with him.<verse eid="2CH 12:1" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 12:2" />In the fifth year of King Rehoboam, King Shishak of Egypt marched against Jerusalem—for they had trespassed against <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>— <verse eid="2CH 12:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 12:3" />with 1,200 chariots, 60,000 riders<note caller="a" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12.3 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">riders </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or “horses”; see note at <char style="xt"><ref loc="2CH 8:6">8.6</ref></char>.</char></note> and innumerable troops who came with him from Egypt: Libyans, Sukkites, and Cushites. <verse eid="2CH 12:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 12:4" />He took the fortified towns of Judah and advanced on Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 12:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 12:5" />The prophet Shemaiah came to Rehoboam and the officers of Judah, who had assembled in Jerusalem because of Shishak, and said to them, “Thus said <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>: You have abandoned Me, so I am abandoning you to Shishak.” <verse eid="2CH 12:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 12:6" />Then the officers of Israel and the king humbled themselves and declared, “<char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> is in the right.” <verse eid="2CH 12:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 12:7" />When <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> saw that they had submitted, the word of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> came to Shemaiah, saying, “Since they have humbled themselves, I will not destroy them but will grant them some measure of deliverance, and My wrath will not be poured out on Jerusalem through Shishak. <verse eid="2CH 12:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 12:8" />They will be subject to him, and they will know the difference between serving Me and serving the kingdoms of the earth.” King Shishak of Egypt marched against Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 12:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 12:9" /><note caller="b" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12.9–16 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Cf. <char style="xt"><ref loc="1KI 14:26-31">1 Kings 14.26–31</ref></char>.</char></note>He took away the treasures of the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> and the treasures of the royal palace; he took away everything; he took away the golden shields that Solomon had made. <verse eid="2CH 12:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 12:10" />King Rehoboam had bronze shields made in their place, and entrusted them to the officers of the guard<note caller="c" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12.10 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">guard </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Lit. “runners.”</char></note> who guarded the entrance to the royal palace. <verse eid="2CH 12:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 12:11" />Whenever the king entered the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>, the guards would carry them and then bring them back to the armory of the guards. <verse eid="2CH 12:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 12:12" />After he had humbled himself, the anger of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> was averted and he was not destroyed entirely; in Judah, too, good things were found.<verse eid="2CH 12:12" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 12:13" />King Rehoboam grew strong in Jerusalem and exercised kingship. Rehoboam was forty-one years old when he became king, and he reigned seventeen years in Jerusalem—the city <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> had chosen out of all the tribes of Israel to establish a temple<note caller="d" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12.13 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">a temple </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Lit. “His name,” i.e., the temple bearing <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>'s name.</char></note> there. His mother's name was Naamah the Ammonitess. <verse eid="2CH 12:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 12:14" />He did what was wrong, for he had not set his heart to seek <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>. <verse eid="2CH 12:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 12:15" />The deeds of Rehoboam, early and late, are recorded in the chronicles of the prophet Shemaiah and Iddo the seer, in the manner of genealogy. There was continuous war between Rehoboam and Jeroboam. <verse eid="2CH 12:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 12:16" />Rehoboam rested with his ancestors and was buried in the City of David. His son Abijah succeeded him as king.<verse eid="2CH 12:16" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 12" />
  <chapter number="13" style="c" sid="2CH 13" />
  <para style="po">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 13:1" />In the eighteenth year of King Jeroboam, Abijah became king over Judah. <verse eid="2CH 13:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 13:2" />He reigned three years in Jerusalem; his mother's name was Micaiah daughter of Uriel of Gibeah. There was war between Abijah and Jeroboam. <verse eid="2CH 13:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 13:3" />Abijah joined battle with a force of warriors, 400,000 of the best troops. Jeroboam arrayed for battle against him 800,000 of the best troops, warriors. <verse eid="2CH 13:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 13:4" />Abijah stood on top of Mount Zemaraim in the hill country of Ephraim and said, “Listen to me, Jeroboam and all Israel. <verse eid="2CH 13:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 13:5" />Surely you know that <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> God of Israel gave David kingship over Israel forever—to him and his sons—by a covenant of salt. <verse eid="2CH 13:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 13:6" />Jeroboam son of Nebat had been in the service of Solomon son of David, but he rose up and rebelled against his master. <verse eid="2CH 13:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 13:7" />Riffraff and scoundrels gathered around him and pressed hard upon Rehoboam son of Solomon. Rehoboam was inexperienced and fainthearted and could not stand up to them. <verse eid="2CH 13:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 13:8" />Now you are bent on opposing <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>'s kingdom, which is in the charge of the sons of David, because you are a great multitude and possess the golden calves that Jeroboam made for you as gods. <verse eid="2CH 13:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 13:9" />Did you not banish <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>'s priests, the sons of Aaron and the Levites, and, like the peoples of the land, appoint your own priests? Anyone who offered himself for ordination with a young bull of the herd and seven rams became a priest of no-gods! <verse eid="2CH 13:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 13:10" />As for us, our God is <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char>, whom we have not forsaken. The priests who minister to <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> are the sons of Aaron, and the Levites are at their tasks. <verse eid="2CH 13:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 13:11" />They offer burnt offerings in smoke each morning and each evening, and the aromatic incense, the rows of bread on the pure table; they kindle the golden lampstand with its lamps burning each evening, for we keep the charge of <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> our God, while you have forsaken it. <verse eid="2CH 13:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 13:12" />See who is with us as our chief: God, whose priests have the trumpets for sounding blasts against you. O children of Israel, do not fight <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> God of your ancestors, because you will not succeed.” <verse eid="2CH 13:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 13:13" />Jeroboam, however, had directed the ambush to go around and come from the rear, thus the main body was<note caller="a" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">13.13 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">the main body was </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Lit. “they were.”</char></note> in front of Judah, while the ambush was behind them. <verse eid="2CH 13:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 13:14" />When Judah turned around and saw that the fighting was before and behind them, they cried out to <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>, and the priests blew the trumpets. <verse eid="2CH 13:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 13:15" />Judah's side raised a shout; and when Judah's side raised a shout, God routed Jeroboam and all Israel before Abijah and Judah. <verse eid="2CH 13:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 13:16" />The Israelites fled before Judah, and God delivered them into their hands. <verse eid="2CH 13:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 13:17" />Abijah and his army inflicted a severe defeat on them; 500,000 of Israel's best troops fell slain. <verse eid="2CH 13:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 13:18" />The Israelites were crushed at that time, while the people of Judah triumphed because they relied on <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> God of their ancestors. <verse eid="2CH 13:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 13:19" />Abijah pursued Jeroboam and captured some of his cities—Bethel with its dependencies, Jeshanah with its dependencies, and Ephrain with its dependencies. <verse eid="2CH 13:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 13:20" />Jeroboam could not muster strength again during the days of Abijah. <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> struck him down and he died. <verse eid="2CH 13:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 13:21" />But Abijah grew powerful; he married fourteen wives and begat twenty-two sons and sixteen daughters.<verse eid="2CH 13:21" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 13:22" />The other events of Abijah's reign, his conduct and his acts, are recorded in the story of the prophet Iddo. <verse eid="2CH 13:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="2CH 13:23" />Abijah rested with his ancestors and was buried in the City of David; his son Asa succeeded him as king. The land was untroubled for ten years.<verse eid="2CH 13:23" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 13" />
  <chapter number="14" style="c" sid="2CH 14" />
  <para style="po">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 14:1" />Asa did what was good and pleasing to <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> his God. <verse eid="2CH 14:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 14:2" />He abolished the alien altars and shrines; he smashed the pillars and cut down the sacred posts.<note caller="a" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">14.2 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">sacred posts </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Used in worship of the goddess Asherah.</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 14:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 14:3" />He ordered Judah to turn to <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> God of their ancestors and to observe the Teaching and the Commandment. <verse eid="2CH 14:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 14:4" />He abolished the shrines and the incense stands throughout the cities of Judah, and the kingdom was untroubled under him. <verse eid="2CH 14:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 14:5" />He built fortified towns in Judah, since the land was untroubled and he was not engaged in warfare during those years, for <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> had granted him respite. <verse eid="2CH 14:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 14:6" />He said to Judah, “Let us build up these cities and surround them with walls and towers, gates and bars, while the land is at our disposal because we turned to <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> our God—after we did so, we were given respite on all sides.” They were successful in their building.<verse eid="2CH 14:6" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 14:7" />Asa had an army of 300,000 men from Judah bearing shields and spears, and 280,000 from Benjamin bearing bucklers and drawing the bow; all these were valiant warriors. <verse eid="2CH 14:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 14:8" />Zerah the Cushite marched out against them with an army of a thousand thousand and 300 chariots. When he reached Mareshah <verse eid="2CH 14:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 14:9" />Asa confronted him, and the battle lines were drawn in the valley of Zephat by Mareshah. <verse eid="2CH 14:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 14:10" />Asa called to <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> his God, and said, “O <char style="nd"><char style="sc">Eternal</char> One</char>, it is all the same to You to help the numerous and the powerless. Help us, our <char style="nd"><char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> God, for we rely on You, and in Your name we have come against this great multitude. You are <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> our God. Let no mortal hinder You.” <verse eid="2CH 14:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 14:11" />So <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> routed the Cushites before Asa and Judah, and the Cushites fled. <verse eid="2CH 14:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 14:12" />Asa and the army with him pursued them as far as Gerar. Many of the Cushites fell wounded beyond recovery, for they broke before <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>'s camp.<note caller="b" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">14.12 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">before <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>'s camp </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Heb. “before <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> and before His camp.”</char></note> Very much spoil was taken. <verse eid="2CH 14:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 14:13" />All the cities in the vicinity of Gerar were ravaged, for a terror of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> seized them. All the cities were plundered, and they yielded much booty. <verse eid="2CH 14:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 14:14" />They also ravaged the encampment of herders, capturing much sheep, and camels. Then they returned to Jerusalem.<verse eid="2CH 14:14" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 14" />
  <chapter number="15" style="c" sid="2CH 15" />
  <para style="po">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 15:1" />The spirit of God came upon Azariah son of Oded. <verse eid="2CH 15:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 15:2" />He came to Asa and said to him, “Listen to me, Asa and all Judah and Benjamin; <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> is with you as long as you act faithfully.<note caller="a" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">15.2 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">act faithfully </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Lit. “are with Him.”</char></note> If it is [God] whom you seek, you will be answered, but if you forsake [God], you will be forsaken. <verse eid="2CH 15:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 15:3" />Israel has gone many days without the true God, without a priest to give instruction and without Teaching. <verse eid="2CH 15:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 15:4" />But in distress it returned to <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> God of Israel, whom it sought—and who, in turn, responded. <verse eid="2CH 15:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 15:5" />At those times, no wayfarer<note caller="b" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">15.5 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">wayfarer </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Lit. “one who goes out and one who comes in.”</char></note> was safe, for there was much tumult among all the inhabitants of the lands. <verse eid="2CH 15:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 15:6" />Nation was crushed by nation and city by city, for God threw them into panic with every kind of trouble. <verse eid="2CH 15:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 15:7" />As for you, be strong, do not be disheartened, for there is reward for your labor.”<verse eid="2CH 15:7" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 15:8" />When Asa heard these words, the prophecy of Oded the prophet, he took courage and removed the abominations from the entire land of Judah and Benjamin and from the cities that he had captured in the hill country of Ephraim. He restored the altar of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> in front of the porch of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>. <verse eid="2CH 15:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 15:9" />He assembled all the people of Judah and Benjamin and those people of Ephraim, Manasseh, and Simeon who sojourned among them, for many in Israel had thrown in their lot with him when they saw that <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> his God was with him. <verse eid="2CH 15:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 15:10" />They were assembled in Jerusalem in the third month of the fifteenth year of the reign of Asa. <verse eid="2CH 15:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 15:11" />They brought sacrifices to <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> on that day; they brought 700 oxen and 7,000 sheep of the spoil. <verse eid="2CH 15:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 15:12" />They entered into a covenant to worship <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> God of their ancestors with all their heart and with all their soul. <verse eid="2CH 15:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 15:13" />Whoever would not worship <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> God of Israel would be put to death, whether small or great, whether man or woman. <verse eid="2CH 15:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 15:14" />So they took an oath to <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> in a loud voice and with shouts, with trumpeting and blasts of the horn. <verse eid="2CH 15:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 15:15" />All Judah rejoiced over the oath, for they swore with all their heart and sought [God] with all their will. In response, they were given respite on every side.<verse eid="2CH 15:15" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 15:16" />
    <note caller="c" style="f">
      <char style="fr" closed="false">15.16–19 </char>
      <char style="ft" closed="false">Cf. <char style="xt"><ref loc="1KI 15:13-16">1 Kings 15.13–16</ref></char>.</char>
    </note>King Asa also deposed his mother Maacah from the rank of queen mother, because she had made an abominable thing for [the goddess] Asherah. Asa cut down her abominable thing, reduced it to dust, and burned it in the Wadi Kidron. <verse eid="2CH 15:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 15:17" />The shrines, indeed, were not abolished in Israel; however, Asa was wholehearted [with <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>] all his life. <verse eid="2CH 15:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 15:18" />He brought into the House of God the things that he and his father had consecrated—silver, gold, and utensils. <verse eid="2CH 15:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 15:19" />There was no war until the thirty-fifth year of the reign of Asa.<verse eid="2CH 15:19" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 15" />
  <chapter number="16" style="c" sid="2CH 16" />
  <para style="po">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 16:1" />
    <note caller="a" style="f">
      <char style="fr" closed="false">16.1–14 </char>
      <char style="ft" closed="false">Cf. <char style="xt"><ref loc="1KI 15:17-24">1 Kings 15.17–24</ref></char>.</char>
    </note>In the thirty-sixth year of the reign of Asa, King Baasha of Israel marched against Judah and built up Ramah to block all movement<note caller="b" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">16.1 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">all movement </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Lit. “one who goes out and one who comes in.”</char></note> on behalf of King Asa of Judah. <verse eid="2CH 16:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 16:2" />Asa took all the silver and gold from the treasuries of the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> and the royal palace, and sent them to King Ben-hadad of Aram, who resided in Damascus, with this message: <verse eid="2CH 16:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 16:3" />“There is a pact between me and you, as there was between my father and your father. I herewith send you silver and gold; go and break your pact with King Baasha of Israel so that he may withdraw from me.” <verse eid="2CH 16:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 16:4" />Ben-hadad acceded to King Asa's request; he sent his army officers against the towns of Israel and ravaged Ijon, Dan, Abel-maim, and all the garrison towns of Naphtali. <verse eid="2CH 16:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 16:5" />When Baasha heard about it, he stopped building up Ramah and put an end to the work on it. <verse eid="2CH 16:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 16:6" />Then King Asa mustered all Judah, and they carried away the stones and timber with which Baasha had built up Ramah; with these King Asa built up Geba and Mizpah.<verse eid="2CH 16:6" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 16:7" />At that time, Hanani the seer came to King Asa of Judah and said to him, “Because you relied on the king of Aram and did not rely on <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> your God, therefore the army of the king of Aram has slipped out of your hands. <verse eid="2CH 16:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 16:8" />The Cushites and Libyans were a mighty army with chariots and riders<note caller="c" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">16.8 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">riders </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or “horses”; see note at <char style="xt"><ref loc="2CH 8:6">8.6</ref></char>.</char></note> in very great numbers, yet because you relied on <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> they were delivered into your hands. <verse eid="2CH 16:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 16:9" />For <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>'s eyes range over the entire earth, to give support to those who are wholehearted. You have acted foolishly in this matter, and from now on you will be beset by wars.” <verse eid="2CH 16:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 16:10" />Asa was vexed at the seer and put him into the stocks,<note caller="d" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">16.10 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">stocks </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Meaning of Heb. uncertain.</char></note> for he was furious with him because of that. Asa inflicted cruelties on some of the people at that time.<verse eid="2CH 16:10" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 16:11" />The acts of Asa, early and late, are recorded in the annals of the kings of Judah and Israel. <verse eid="2CH 16:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 16:12" />In the thirty-ninth year of his reign, Asa suffered from an acute foot ailment; but ill as he was, he still did not turn to <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> but to physicians. <verse eid="2CH 16:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 16:13" />Asa rested with his ancestors. He died in the forty-first year of his reign <verse eid="2CH 16:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 16:14" />and was buried in the grave that he had made for himself in the City of David. He was laid in his resting-place, which was filled with spices of all kinds, expertly blended; a very great fire was made in his honor.<verse eid="2CH 16:14" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 16" />
  <chapter number="17" style="c" sid="2CH 17" />
  <para style="po">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 17:1" />His son Jehoshaphat succeeded him as king, and took firm hold of Israel. <verse eid="2CH 17:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 17:2" />He stationed troops in all the fortified towns of Judah, and stationed garrisons throughout the land of Judah and the cities of Ephraim that his father Asa had captured. <verse eid="2CH 17:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 17:3" /><char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> was with Jehoshaphat because he followed the earlier ways of his forefather David, and did not worship the Baalim, <verse eid="2CH 17:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 17:4" />but worshiped the God of his father and followed the commandments—unlike the behavior of Israel. <verse eid="2CH 17:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 17:5" />So <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> established the kingdom in his hands, and all Judah gave presents to Jehoshaphat. He had wealth and glory in abundance. <verse eid="2CH 17:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 17:6" />His mind was elevated in <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>'s ways. Moreover, he abolished the shrines and the sacred posts<note caller="a" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">17.6 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">sacred posts </char><char style="ft" closed="false">See note at <char style="xt"><ref loc="2CH 14:2">14.2</ref></char>.</char></note> from Judah.<verse eid="2CH 17:6" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 17:7" />In the third year of his reign he sent his officers Ben-hail, Obadiah, Zechariah, Nethanel, and Micaiah throughout the cities of Judah to offer instruction. <verse eid="2CH 17:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 17:8" />With them were the Levites, Shemaiah, Nethaniah, Zebadiah, Asahel, Shemiramoth, Jehonathan, Adonijah, Tobijah and Tob-adonijah the Levites; with them were Elishama and Jehoram the priests. <verse eid="2CH 17:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 17:9" />They offered instruction throughout Judah, having with them the Book of the Teaching of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>. They made the rounds of all the cities of Judah and instructed the people. <verse eid="2CH 17:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 17:10" />A terror of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> seized all the kingdoms of the lands around Judah, and they did not go to war with Jehoshaphat. <verse eid="2CH 17:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 17:11" />From Philistia a load of silver was brought to Jehoshaphat as tribute. The Arabs, too, brought him flocks: 7,700 rams and 7,700 he-goats. <verse eid="2CH 17:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 17:12" />Jehoshaphat grew greater and greater, and he built up fortresses and garrison towns in Judah. <verse eid="2CH 17:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 17:13" />He carried out extensive works in the towns of Judah, and had soldiers, valiant warriors, in Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 17:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 17:14" />They were enrolled according to their clans. Judah: chiefs of thousands, Adnah the chief, who had 300,000 valiant warriors; <verse eid="2CH 17:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 17:15" />next to him was Jehohanan the captain, who had 280,000; <verse eid="2CH 17:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 17:16" />next to him was Amasiah son of Zichri, who made a freewill offering to <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>. He had 200,000 valiant warriors. <verse eid="2CH 17:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 17:17" />Benjamin: Eliada, a valiant warrior, who had 200,000 men armed with bow and buckler; <verse eid="2CH 17:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 17:18" />next to him was Jehozabad, who had 180,000 armed men. <verse eid="2CH 17:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 17:19" />These served the king, besides those whom the king assigned to the fortified towns throughout Judah.<verse eid="2CH 17:19" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 17" />
  <chapter number="18" style="c" sid="2CH 18" />
  <para style="po">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 18:1" />
    <note caller="a" style="f">
      <char style="fr" closed="false">18.1–34 </char>
      <char style="ft" closed="false">Cf. <char style="xt"><ref loc="1KI 22">1 Kings 22</ref></char>.</char>
    </note>So Jehoshaphat had wealth and honor in abundance, and he allied himself by marriage to Ahab. <verse eid="2CH 18:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 18:2" />After some years had passed, he came to visit Ahab at Samaria. Ahab slaughtered sheep and oxen in abundance for him and for the people with him, and persuaded him to march against Ramoth-gilead. <verse eid="2CH 18:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 18:3" />King Ahab of Israel said to King Jehoshaphat of Judah, “Will you accompany me to Ramoth-gilead?” He answered him, “I will do what you do; my troops shall be your troops and shall accompany you in battle.” <verse eid="2CH 18:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 18:4" />Jehoshaphat then said to the king of Israel, “But first inquire for the word of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>.”<verse eid="2CH 18:4" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 18:5" />So the king of Israel gathered the prophets, four hundred of them, and asked them, “Shall I march upon Ramoth-gilead for battle, or shall I not?” “March,” they said, “and God will deliver it into the king's hands.” <verse eid="2CH 18:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 18:6" />Then Jehoshaphat asked, “Is there not another prophet of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> here through whom we can inquire?” <verse eid="2CH 18:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 18:7" />And the king of Israel answered Jehoshaphat, “There is one more through whom we can inquire of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>; but I hate him, because he never prophesies anything good for me but always misfortune. He is Micaiah son of Imlah.” Jehoshaphat replied, “Let the king not say such a thing.” <verse eid="2CH 18:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 18:8" />So the king of Israel summoned an officer and said, “Bring Micaiah son of Imlah at once.”<verse eid="2CH 18:8" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 18:9" />The king of Israel and King Jehoshaphat of Judah, wearing their robes, were seated on their thrones situated in the threshing floor at the entrance of the gate of Samaria; and all the prophets were prophesying before them. <verse eid="2CH 18:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 18:10" />Zedekiah son of Chenaanah had provided himself with iron horns; and he said, “Thus said <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>: With these you shall gore the Arameans till you make an end of them.” <verse eid="2CH 18:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 18:11" />All the other prophets were prophesying similarly, “March against Ramoth-gilead and be victorious! <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> will deliver it into Your Majesty's hands.”<verse eid="2CH 18:11" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 18:12" />The messenger who had gone to summon Micaiah said to him, “Look, the words of the prophets are unanimously favorable to the king. Let your word be like that of the rest of them; speak a favorable word.” <verse eid="2CH 18:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 18:13" />“By the life of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>,” Micaiah answered, “I will speak only what my God tells me.” <verse eid="2CH 18:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 18:14" />When he came before the king, the king said to him, “Micah,<note caller="b" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">18.14 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">Micah </char><char style="ft" closed="false">A shortened form of Micaiah.</char></note> shall we march against Ramoth-gilead for battle or shall we not?” He answered him, “March and be victorious! They will be delivered into your hands.” <verse eid="2CH 18:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 18:15" />The king said to him, “How many times must I adjure you to tell me nothing but the truth in the name of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>?” <verse eid="2CH 18:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 18:16" />Then he said, “I saw all Israel scattered over the hills like sheep without a shepherd; and <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> said, ‘These have no master; let everyone return home in safety.’” <verse eid="2CH 18:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 18:17" />The king of Israel said to Jehoshaphat, “Did I not tell you that he would not prophesy good fortune for me, but only misfortune?”<verse eid="2CH 18:17" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 18:18" />Then [Micaiah] said, “Indeed, hear now the word of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>! I saw <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> seated upon a throne, with all the host of heaven standing in attendance to the right and to the left. <verse eid="2CH 18:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 18:19" /><char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> asked, ‘Who will entice King Ahab of Israel so that he will march and fall at Ramoth-gilead?’ Then one said this and another said that, <verse eid="2CH 18:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 18:20" />until a certain spirit came forward and stood before <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> and said, ‘I will entice him.’ ‘How?’ said <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> to him. <verse eid="2CH 18:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 18:21" />And he replied, ‘I will go forth and become a lying spirit in the mouth of all his prophets.’ Then I heard, ‘You will entice with success. Go forth and do it.’ <verse eid="2CH 18:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 18:22" />Thus <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> has put a lying spirit in the mouth of all these prophets of yours; for <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> has decreed misfortune for you.”<verse eid="2CH 18:22" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="2CH 18:23" />Thereupon Zedekiah son of Chenaanah came up and struck Micaiah on the cheek, and exclaimed, “However did the spirit of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> pass from me to speak with you!” <verse eid="2CH 18:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="2CH 18:24" />Micaiah replied, “You will see on the day when you try to hide in the innermost room.” <verse eid="2CH 18:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="2CH 18:25" />Then the king of Israel said, “Take Micaiah and turn him over to Amon, the governor of the city, and to Prince Joash, <verse eid="2CH 18:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="2CH 18:26" />and say, ‘The king's orders are: Put this fellow in prison, and let his fare be scant bread and scant water until I come home safe.’” <verse eid="2CH 18:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="2CH 18:27" />To which Micaiah retorted, “If you ever come home safe, <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> has not spoken through me.” He said further, “Listen, all you peoples!”<note caller="c" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">18.27 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">Listen, all you peoples! </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Cf. <char style="xt"><ref loc="MIC 1:2">Mic. 1.2</ref></char>.</char></note><verse eid="2CH 18:27" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="2CH 18:28" />The king of Israel and King Jehoshaphat of Judah marched against Ramoth-gilead. <verse eid="2CH 18:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="2CH 18:29" />The king of Israel said to Jehoshaphat, “I will disguise myself and go<note caller="d" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">18.29 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">I will disguise myself and go </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Infinitives used for finite verbs; so Targum and Septuagint.</char></note> into the battle, but you, wear your robes.” So the king of Israel disguised himself, and they went into the battle. <verse eid="2CH 18:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="2CH 18:30" />The king of Aram had given these instructions to his chariot officers: “Do not attack anyone, small or great, except the king of Israel.” <verse eid="2CH 18:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="2CH 18:31" />When the chariot officers saw Jehoshaphat, whom they took for the king of Israel, they wheeled around to attack him, and Jehoshaphat cried out and <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> helped him, and God diverted them from him. <verse eid="2CH 18:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="2CH 18:32" />And when the chariot officers realized that he was not the king of Israel, they gave up the pursuit. <verse eid="2CH 18:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="2CH 18:33" />Then another man drew his bow at random and hit the king of Israel between the plates of the<note caller="e" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">18.33 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">plates of the </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Meaning of Heb. uncertain.</char></note> armor and he said to his charioteer, “Turn around and get me behind the lines; I am wounded.” <verse eid="2CH 18:33" /><verse number="34" style="v" sid="2CH 18:34" />The battle raged all day long,<note caller="f" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">18.34 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">raged all day long </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Meaning of Heb. uncertain.</char></note> and the king remained propped up in the chariot facing Aram until dusk; he died as the sun was setting.<verse eid="2CH 18:34" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 18" />
  <chapter number="19" style="c" sid="2CH 19" />
  <para style="po">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 19:1" />King Jehoshaphat of Judah returned safely to his palace, to Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 19:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 19:2" />Jehu son of Hanani the seer went out to meet King Jehoshaphat and said to him, “Should one give aid to the wicked and befriend those who hate <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>? For this, wrath is upon you from <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>. <verse eid="2CH 19:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 19:3" />However, there is some good in you, for you have purged the land of the sacred posts<note caller="a" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">19.3 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">sacred posts </char><char style="ft" closed="false">See note at <char style="xt"><ref loc="2CH 14:2">14.2</ref></char>.</char></note> and have dedicated yourself to worship God.”<verse eid="2CH 19:3" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 19:4" />Jehoshaphat remained in Jerusalem awhile and then went out among the people from Beer-sheba to the hill country of Ephraim; he brought them back to <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> God of their ancestors. <verse eid="2CH 19:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 19:5" />He appointed judges in the land in all the fortified towns of Judah, in each and every town. <verse eid="2CH 19:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 19:6" />He charged the judges: “Consider what you are doing, for you judge not on behalf of human beings, but on behalf of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>—who is with you when you pass judgment. <verse eid="2CH 19:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 19:7" />Now let the dread of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> be upon you; act with care, for there is no injustice or favoritism or bribe-taking with <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> our God.” <verse eid="2CH 19:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 19:8" />Jehoshaphat also appointed in Jerusalem some Levites and priests and heads of the clans of Israelites for rendering judgment in matters of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>, and for disputes. Then they returned to Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 19:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 19:9" />He charged them, “This is how you shall act: in fear of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>, with fidelity, and with whole heart. <verse eid="2CH 19:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 19:10" />When a dispute comes before you from your kindred living in their towns, whether about homicide, or about ritual, or laws or rules, you must instruct them so that they do not incur guilt before <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> and wrath be upon you and your kindred. Act so and you will not incur guilt. <verse eid="2CH 19:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 19:11" />See, Amariah the chief priest is over you in all cases concerning <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>, and Zebadiah son of Ishmael is the commander of the house of Judah in all cases concerning the king; the Levitical officials are at your disposal; act with resolve and <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> be with the good.”<verse eid="2CH 19:11" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 19" />
  <chapter number="20" style="c" sid="2CH 20" />
  <para style="po">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 20:1" />After that, Moabites, Ammonites, together with some Ammonim,<note caller="a" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">20.1 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">Ammonim </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Probably for <char style="tl">mʻnym</char> “Meunites” (<char style="xt"><ref loc="1CH 4:41">1 Chron. 4.41</ref></char>); cf. Kimhi.</char></note> came against Jehoshaphat to wage war. <verse eid="2CH 20:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 20:2" />The report was brought to Jehoshaphat: “A great multitude is coming against you from beyond the sea, from Aram, and is now in Hazazon-tamar”—that is, En-gedi. <verse eid="2CH 20:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 20:3" />Jehoshaphat was afraid; he decided to resort to <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> and proclaimed a fast for all Judah. <verse eid="2CH 20:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 20:4" />Judah assembled to plead before <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>. They also came from all the towns of Judah to seek <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>.<verse eid="2CH 20:4" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 20:5" />Jehoshaphat stood in the congregation of Judah and Jerusalem in the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> at the front of the new court. <verse eid="2CH 20:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 20:6" />He said, “<char style="nd"><char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> God of our ancestors, truly You are the God in heaven and You rule over the kingdoms of the nations; power and strength are Yours; none can oppose You. <verse eid="2CH 20:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 20:7" />O our God, you dispossessed the inhabitants of this land before Your people Israel, and You gave it to the descendants of Your friend Abraham forever. <verse eid="2CH 20:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 20:8" />They settled in it and in it built for You a House for Your name. They said, <verse eid="2CH 20:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 20:9" />‘Should misfortune befall us—the punishing sword, pestilence, or famine, we shall stand before this House and before You—for Your name is in this House—and we shall cry out to You in our distress, and You will listen and deliver us.’ <verse eid="2CH 20:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 20:10" />Now the people of Ammon, Moab, and the hill country of Seir, into whose [land] You did not let Israel come when they came from Egypt, but they turned aside from them and did not wipe them out, <verse eid="2CH 20:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 20:11" />these now repay us by coming to expel us from Your possession that You gave us as ours. <verse eid="2CH 20:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 20:12" />O our God, surely You will punish them, for we are powerless before this great multitude that has come against us, and do not know what to do, but our eyes are on You.” <verse eid="2CH 20:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 20:13" />All Judah<note caller="b" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">20.13 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">All Judah </char><char style="ft" closed="false">I.e., the militia that represents Judah on the battlefield.</char></note> stood before <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> with their dependents—their womenfolk and their children.<verse eid="2CH 20:13" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 20:14" />Then in the midst of the congregation the spirit of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> came upon Jahaziel son of Zechariah son of Benaiah son of Jeiel son of Mattaniah the Levite, of the sons of Asaph, <verse eid="2CH 20:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 20:15" />and he said, “Give heed, all Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem<note caller="c" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">20.15 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">inhabitants of Jerusalem </char><char style="ft" closed="false">I.e., the militia that represents the city's inhabitants on the battlefield.</char></note> and King Jehoshaphat; thus said <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> to you, ‘Do not fear or be dismayed by this great multitude, for the battle is God's, not yours. <verse eid="2CH 20:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 20:16" />March down against them tomorrow as they come up by the Ascent of Ziz; you will find them at the end of the wadi in the direction of the wilderness of Jeruel. <verse eid="2CH 20:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 20:17" />It is not for you to fight this battle; stand by, wait, and witness your deliverance by <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>, O Judah and Jerusalem; do not fear or be dismayed; go forth to meet them tomorrow and <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> will be with you.’” <verse eid="2CH 20:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 20:18" />Jehoshaphat bowed low with his face to the ground, and all Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem threw themselves down before <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> to worship <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>. <verse eid="2CH 20:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 20:19" />Levites of the sons of Kohath and of the sons of Korah got up to extol <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> God of Israel at the top of their voices.<verse eid="2CH 20:19" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 20:20" />Early the next morning they arose and went forth to the wilderness of Tekoa. As they went forth, Jehoshaphat stood and said, “Listen to me, O Judah and inhabitants of Jerusalem: Trust firmly in <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> your God and you will stand firm; trust firmly in God's prophets and you will succeed.” <verse eid="2CH 20:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 20:21" />After taking counsel with the people, he stationed singers to <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> extolling the One majestic in holiness as they went forth ahead of the vanguard, saying, “Praise <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>, whose steadfast love is eternal.” <verse eid="2CH 20:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 20:22" />As they began their joyous shouts and hymns, <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> set ambushes for the Ammonites, Moabites, and [the inhabitants of] the hill country of Seir, who were marching against Judah, and they were routed. <verse eid="2CH 20:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="2CH 20:23" />The Ammonites and Moabites turned against the inhabitants of the hill country of Seir to exterminate and annihilate them. When they had made an end of the inhabitants of Seir, each helped to destroy his fellow.<verse eid="2CH 20:23" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="2CH 20:24" />When Judah reached the lookout in the wilderness and looked for the multitude, they saw them lying on the ground as corpses; not one had survived. <verse eid="2CH 20:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="2CH 20:25" />Jehoshaphat and his army came to take the booty, and found an abundance of goods, corpses, and precious objects, which they pillaged, more than they could carry off. For three days they were taking booty, there was so much of it. <verse eid="2CH 20:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="2CH 20:26" />On the fourth day they assembled in the Valley of Blessing—for there they blessed <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>; that is why that place is called the Valley of Blessing to this day. <verse eid="2CH 20:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="2CH 20:27" />Judah and Jerusalem's entire force, with Jehoshaphat at their head, returned joyfully to Jerusalem, for <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> had given them cause for rejoicing over their enemies. <verse eid="2CH 20:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="2CH 20:28" />They came to Jerusalem to the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>, to the accompaniment of harps, lyres, and trumpets. <verse eid="2CH 20:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="2CH 20:29" />The terror of God seized all the kingdoms of the lands when they heard that <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> had fought the enemies of Israel. <verse eid="2CH 20:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="2CH 20:30" />The kingdom of Jehoshaphat was untroubled, and his God granted him respite on all sides.<verse eid="2CH 20:30" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="2CH 20:31" />
    <note caller="d" style="f">
      <char style="fr" closed="false">20.31–37 </char>
      <char style="ft" closed="false">Cf. <char style="xt"><ref loc="1KI 22:41-49">1 Kings 22.41–49</ref></char>.</char>
    </note>Jehoshaphat reigned over Judah. He was thirty-five years old when he became king, and he reigned in Jerusalem for twenty-five years. His mother's name was Azubah daughter of Shilhi. <verse eid="2CH 20:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="2CH 20:32" />He followed the course of his father Asa and did not deviate from it, doing what was pleasing to <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>. <verse eid="2CH 20:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="2CH 20:33" />However, the shrines did not cease; the people still did not direct their heart toward the God of their ancestors. <verse eid="2CH 20:33" /><verse number="34" style="v" sid="2CH 20:34" />As for the other events of Jehoshaphat's reign, early and late, they are recorded in the annals of Jehu son of Hanani, which were included in the book of the kings of Israel.<verse eid="2CH 20:34" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="2CH 20:35" />Afterward, King Jehoshaphat of Judah entered into a partnership with King Ahaziah of Israel, thereby acting wickedly. <verse eid="2CH 20:35" /><verse number="36" style="v" sid="2CH 20:36" />He joined with him in constructing ships to go to Tarshish; the ships were constructed in Ezion-geber. <verse eid="2CH 20:36" /><verse number="37" style="v" sid="2CH 20:37" />Eliezer son of Dodavahu of Mareshah prophesied against Jehoshaphat, “As you have made a partnership with Ahaziah, <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> will break up your work.” The ships were wrecked and were unable to go to Tarshish.<verse eid="2CH 20:37" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 20" />
  <chapter number="21" style="c" sid="2CH 21" />
  <para style="po">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 21:1" />
    <note caller="a" style="f">
      <char style="fr" closed="false">21.1–20 </char>
      <char style="ft" closed="false">Cf. <char style="xt"><ref loc="2KI 8:17-24">2 Kings 8.17–24</ref></char>.</char>
    </note>Jehoshaphat rested with his ancestors and was buried with his ancestors in the City of David; his son Jehoram succeeded him as king. <verse eid="2CH 21:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 21:2" />He had brothers, sons of Jehoshaphat: Azariah, Jehiel, Zechariah, Azariahu, Michael, and Shephatiah; all these were sons of King Jehoshaphat of Israel. <verse eid="2CH 21:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 21:3" />Their father gave them many gifts of silver, gold, and [other] presents, as well as fortified towns in Judah, but he gave the kingdom to Jehoram because he was the first-born.<verse eid="2CH 21:3" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 21:4" />Jehoram proceeded to take firm hold of his father's kingdom and put to the sword all his brothers, as well as some of the officers of Israel. <verse eid="2CH 21:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 21:5" />Jehoram was thirty-two years old when he became king, and he reigned in Jerusalem eight years. <verse eid="2CH 21:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 21:6" />He followed the practices of the kings of Israel doing what the House of Ahab had done, for he married a daughter of Ahab; he did what was displeasing to <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>. <verse eid="2CH 21:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 21:7" />However, <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> refrained from destroying the House of David for the sake of the covenant made with David, and in accordance with the promise to maintain a lamp for him and his descendants for all time. <verse eid="2CH 21:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 21:8" />During his reign, the Edomites rebelled against Judah's rule and set up a king of their own. <verse eid="2CH 21:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 21:9" />Jehoram advanced [against them] with his officers and all his chariotry. He arose by night and attacked the Edomites, who surrounded him and the chariot commanders. <verse eid="2CH 21:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 21:10" />Edom has been in rebellion against Judah, to this day; Libnah also rebelled against him at that time, because he had forsaken <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> God of his ancestors. <verse eid="2CH 21:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 21:11" />Moreover, he built shrines in the hill country of Judah; he led astray the inhabitants of Jerusalem and made Judah wayward.<verse eid="2CH 21:11" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 21:12" />A letter from Elijah the prophet came to him that read: “Thus says <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> God of your forefather David: Since you have not followed the practices of your father Jehoshaphat and the practices of King Asa of Judah, <verse eid="2CH 21:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 21:13" />but have followed the practices of the kings of Israel, leading astray Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem as the House of Ahab led them astray, and have also killed your brothers of your father's house, who were better than you, <verse eid="2CH 21:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 21:14" />therefore, <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> will inflict a great blow upon your people, your sons, and your wives and all your possessions. <verse eid="2CH 21:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 21:15" />As for you, you will be severely stricken with a disorder of the bowels year after year until your bowels drop out.”<verse eid="2CH 21:15" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 21:16" />
    <char style="nd">
      <char style="sc">God</char>
    </char> stirred up the spirit of the Philistines and the Arabs who were neighbors of the Cushites against Jehoram. <verse eid="2CH 21:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 21:17" />They marched against Judah, breached its defenses, and carried off all the property that was found in the king's palace, as well as his sons and his wives. The only son who remained was Jehoahaz, his youngest. <verse eid="2CH 21:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 21:18" />After this, <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> afflicted him with an incurable disease of the bowels. <verse eid="2CH 21:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 21:19" />Some years later, when a period of two years had elapsed, his bowels dropped out because of his disease, and he died a gruesome death. His people did not make a fire for him like the fire for his ancestors. <verse eid="2CH 21:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 21:20" />He was thirty-two years old when he became king, and he reigned in Jerusalem eight years. He departed unpraised,<note caller="b" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">21.20 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">unpraised </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Following Septuagint; cf. Arabic <char style="tl">ḥamada</char> “praise.”</char></note> and was buried in the City of David, but not in the tombs of the kings.<verse eid="2CH 21:20" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 21" />
  <chapter number="22" style="c" sid="2CH 22" />
  <para style="po">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 22:1" />
    <note caller="a" style="f">
      <char style="fr" closed="false">22.1–6 </char>
      <char style="ft" closed="false">Cf. <char style="xt"><ref loc="2KI 8:25-29">2 Kings 8.25–29</ref></char>.</char>
    </note>The inhabitants of Jerusalem made Ahaziah, his youngest son, king in his stead, because all the older ones had been killed by the troops that penetrated the camp with the Arabs. Ahaziah son of Jehoram reigned as king of Judah. <verse eid="2CH 22:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 22:2" />Ahaziah was forty-two years old when he became king, and he reigned in Jerusalem one year; his mother's name was Athaliah daughter of Omri. <verse eid="2CH 22:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 22:3" />He too followed the practices of the house of Ahab, for his mother counseled him to do evil. <verse eid="2CH 22:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 22:4" />He did what was displeasing to <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>, like the house of Ahab, for they became his counselors after his father's death, to his ruination. <verse eid="2CH 22:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 22:5" />Moreover, he followed their counsel and marched with Jehoram son of King Ahab of Israel to battle against King Hazael of Aram at Ramoth-gilead, where the Arameans wounded Joram. <verse eid="2CH 22:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 22:6" />He returned to Jezreel to recover from the wounds inflicted on him at Ramah when he fought against King Hazael of Aram. King Azariah son of Jehoram of Judah went down to Jezreel to visit Jehoram son of Ahab while he was ill. <verse eid="2CH 22:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 22:7" />God caused the downfall of Ahaziah because he visited Joram. During his visit he went out with Jehoram to Jehu son of Nimshi, whom <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> had anointed to cut off the house of Ahab. <verse eid="2CH 22:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 22:8" /><note caller="b" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">22.8–9 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Cf. <char style="xt"><ref loc="2KI 9:27-28">2 Kings 9.27–28</ref></char>.</char></note>In the course of bringing the house of Ahab to judgment, Jehu came upon the officers of Judah and the nephews of Ahaziah, ministers of Ahaziah, and killed them. <verse eid="2CH 22:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 22:9" />He sent in search of Ahaziah, who was caught hiding in Samaria, was brought to Jehu, and put to death. He was given a burial, because it was said, “He is the son of Jehoshaphat who worshiped <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> wholeheartedly.” So the house of Ahaziah could not muster the strength to rule.<verse eid="2CH 22:9" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 22:10" />
    <note caller="c" style="f">
      <char style="fr" closed="false">22.10–12 </char>
      <char style="ft" closed="false">Cf. <char style="xt"><ref loc="2KI 11:1-3">2 Kings 11.1–3</ref></char>.</char>
    </note>When Athaliah, Ahaziah's mother, learned that her son was dead, she promptly did away with all who were of the royal stock of the house of Judah. <verse eid="2CH 22:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 22:11" />But Jehoshabeath, daughter of the king, spirited away Ahaziah's son Joash from among the princes who were being slain, and put him and his nurse in a bedroom. Jehoshabeath, daughter of King Jehoram, wife of the priest Jehoiada—she was the sister of Ahaziah—kept him hidden from Athaliah so that he was not put to death. <verse eid="2CH 22:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 22:12" />He stayed with them for six years, hidden in the House of God, while Athaliah reigned over the land.<verse eid="2CH 22:12" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 22" />
  <chapter number="23" style="c" sid="2CH 23" />
  <para style="po">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 23:1" />
    <note caller="a" style="f">
      <char style="fr" closed="false">23.1–21 </char>
      <char style="ft" closed="false">Cf. <char style="xt"><ref loc="2KI 11:4-20">2 Kings 11.4–20</ref></char>.</char>
    </note>In the seventh year, Jehoiada took courage and brought the chiefs of the hundreds, Azariah son of Jeroham, Ishmael son of Jehohanan, Azariah son of Obed, Maaseiah son of Adaiah, and Elishaphat son of Zichri, into a compact with him. <verse eid="2CH 23:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 23:2" />They went through Judah and assembled the Levites from all the towns of Judah, and the chiefs of the clans of Israel. They came to Jerusalem <verse eid="2CH 23:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 23:3" />and the entire assembly made a covenant with the king in the House of God. [Jehoiada] said to them, “The son of the king shall be king according to the promise <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> made concerning the sons of David. <verse eid="2CH 23:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 23:4" />This is what you must do: One third of you, priests and Levites, who are on duty for the week, shall be gatekeepers at the thresholds; <verse eid="2CH 23:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 23:5" />another third shall be stationed in the royal palace, and the other third at the Foundation Gate. All the people shall be in the courts of the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>. <verse eid="2CH 23:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 23:6" />Let no one enter the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> except the priests and the ministering Levites. They may enter because they are sanctified, but all the people shall obey <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>'s proscription. <verse eid="2CH 23:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 23:7" />The Levites shall surround the king on every side, each with his arms at the ready; and whoever enters the House shall be killed. Stay close to the king in his comings and goings.” <verse eid="2CH 23:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 23:8" />The Levites and all Judah did just as Jehoiada the priest ordered: each took his men—those who were on duty that week and those who were off duty that week, for Jehoiada the priest had not dismissed the divisions. <verse eid="2CH 23:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 23:9" />Jehoiada the priest gave the chiefs of the hundreds King David's spears and shields and quivers that were kept in the House of God. <verse eid="2CH 23:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 23:10" />He stationed the entire force, each with his weapon at the ready, from the south end of the House to the north end of the House, at the altar and the House, to guard the king on every side. <verse eid="2CH 23:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 23:11" />Then they brought out the king's son, and placed upon him the crown and the insignia. They proclaimed him king, and Jehoiada and his sons anointed him and shouted, “Long live the king!”<verse eid="2CH 23:11" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 23:12" />When Athaliah heard the shouting of the people and the guards and the acclamation of the king, she came out to the people, to the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>. <verse eid="2CH 23:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 23:13" />She looked about and saw the king standing by his pillar at the entrance, the chiefs with their trumpets beside the king, and all the people of the land rejoicing and blowing trumpets, and the singers with musical instruments leading the hymns. Athaliah rent her garments and cried out, “Treason, treason!” <verse eid="2CH 23:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 23:14" />Then the priest Jehoiada ordered out the army officers, the chiefs of hundreds, and said to them, “Take her out between the ranks, and if anyone follows her, put him to the sword.” For the priest thought, “Let her not be put to death in the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>.” <verse eid="2CH 23:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 23:15" />They cleared a passage for her and she came to the entrance of the Horse Gate to the royal palace; there she was put to death.<verse eid="2CH 23:15" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 23:16" />Then Jehoiada solemnized a covenant between himself and the people and the king that they should be <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>'s people. <verse eid="2CH 23:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 23:17" />All the people then went to the temple of Baal; they tore it down and smashed its altars and images to bits, and they slew Mattan, the priest of Baal, in front of the altars. <verse eid="2CH 23:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 23:18" />Jehoiada put the officers of the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> in the charge of Levite priests whom David had assigned over the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> to offer up burnt offerings, as is prescribed in the Teaching of Moses, accompanied by joyful song as ordained by David. <verse eid="2CH 23:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 23:19" />He stationed the gatekeepers at the gates of the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> to prevent the entry of anyone impure for any reason. <verse eid="2CH 23:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 23:20" />He took the chiefs of hundreds, the nobles, and the rulers of the people and all the people of the land, and they escorted the king down from the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> into the royal palace by the upper gate, and seated the king on the royal throne. <verse eid="2CH 23:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 23:21" />All the people of the land rejoiced, and the city was quiet. As for Athaliah, she had been put to the sword.<verse eid="2CH 23:21" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 23" />
  <chapter number="24" style="c" sid="2CH 24" />
  <para style="po">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 24:1" />
    <note caller="a" style="f">
      <char style="fr" closed="false">24.1–27 </char>
      <char style="ft" closed="false">Cf. <char style="xt"><ref loc="2KI 12:1-22">2 Kings 12.1–22</ref></char>.</char>
    </note>Jehoash was seven years old when he became king, and he reigned in Jerusalem forty years. His mother's name was Zibiah of Beer-sheba. <verse eid="2CH 24:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 24:2" />All the days of the priest Jehoiada, Jehoash did what was pleasing to <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>. <verse eid="2CH 24:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 24:3" />Jehoiada took two wives for him, by whom he had sons and daughters.<verse eid="2CH 24:3" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 24:4" />Afterward, Joash decided to renovate the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>. <verse eid="2CH 24:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 24:5" />He assembled the priests and the Levites and charged them as follows: “Go out to the towns of Judah and collect money from all Israel for the annual repair of the House of your God. Do it quickly.” But the Levites did not act quickly. <verse eid="2CH 24:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 24:6" />The king summoned Jehoiada the chief and said to him, “Why have you not seen to it that the Levites brought the tax imposed by Moses, the servant of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>, and the congregation of Israel from Judah and Jerusalem to the Tent of the Pact?” <verse eid="2CH 24:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 24:7" />For the children of the wicked Athaliah had violated the House of God and had even used the sacred things of the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> for the Baals. <verse eid="2CH 24:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 24:8" />The king ordered that a chest be made and placed on the outside of the gate of the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>. <verse eid="2CH 24:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 24:9" />A proclamation was issued in Judah and Jerusalem to bring the tax imposed on Israel in the wilderness by Moses, the servant of God. <verse eid="2CH 24:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 24:10" />All the officers and all the people gladly brought it and threw it into the chest till it was full. <verse eid="2CH 24:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 24:11" />Whenever the chest was brought to the royal officers by the Levites, and they saw that it contained much money, the royal scribe and the agent of the chief priest came and emptied out the chest and carried it back to its place. They did this day by day, and much money was collected. <verse eid="2CH 24:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 24:12" />The king and Jehoiada delivered the money to those who oversaw the tasks connected with the work of the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>. They hired masons and carpenters to renovate the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>, as well as artisans in iron and bronze to repair the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>. <verse eid="2CH 24:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 24:13" />The overseers did their work; under them the work went well and they restored the House of God to its original form and repaired it. <verse eid="2CH 24:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 24:14" />When they had finished, they brought the money that was left over to the king and Jehoiada; it was made into utensils for the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>, service vessels: buckets and ladles, golden and silver vessels. Burnt offerings were offered up regularly in the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> all the days of Jehoiada. <verse eid="2CH 24:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 24:15" />Jehoiada reached a ripe old age and died; he was one hundred and thirty years old at his death. <verse eid="2CH 24:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 24:16" />They buried him in the City of David together with the kings, because he had done good in Israel, and on behalf of God and God's House.<verse eid="2CH 24:16" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 24:17" />But after the death of Jehoiada, the officers of Judah came, bowing low to the king; and the king listened to them. <verse eid="2CH 24:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 24:18" />They forsook the House of <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> God of their ancestors to serve the sacred posts<note caller="b" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">24.18 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">sacred posts </char><char style="ft" closed="false">See note at <char style="xt"><ref loc="2CH 14:2">14.2</ref></char>.</char></note> and idols; and there was wrath upon Judah and Jerusalem because of this guilt of theirs. <verse eid="2CH 24:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 24:19" /><char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> sent prophets among them to bring them back; they admonished them but they would not pay heed. <verse eid="2CH 24:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 24:20" />Then the spirit of God enveloped Zechariah son of Jehoiada the priest; he stood above the people and said to them, “Thus God said: Why do you transgress the commandments of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> when you cannot succeed? Since you have forsaken <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>, you yourselves have been forsaken.” <verse eid="2CH 24:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 24:21" />They conspired against him and pelted him with stones in the court of the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>, by order of the king. <verse eid="2CH 24:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 24:22" />King Joash disregarded the loyalty that his father Jehoiada had shown to him, and killed his son. As he was dying, he said, “May <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> see and requite it.”<verse eid="2CH 24:22" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="2CH 24:23" />At the turn of the year, the army of Aram marched against him; they invaded Judah and Jerusalem, and wiped out all the officers of the people from among the people, and sent all the booty they took to the king of Damascus. <verse eid="2CH 24:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="2CH 24:24" />The invading army of Aram had come with but a few men, but <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> delivered a very large army into their hands, because they had forsaken <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> God of their ancestors. They inflicted punishments on Joash. <verse eid="2CH 24:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="2CH 24:25" />When they withdrew, having left him with many wounds, his courtiers plotted against him because of the murder<note caller="c" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">24.25 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">murder </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Lit. “blood.”</char></note> of the sons of Jehoiada the priest, and they killed him in bed. He died and was buried in the City of David; he was not buried in the tombs of the kings. <verse eid="2CH 24:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="2CH 24:26" />Those who conspired against him were: Zabad son of Shimeath the Ammonitess, and Jehozabad son of Shimrith the Moabitess. <verse eid="2CH 24:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="2CH 24:27" />As to his sons, and the many pronouncements against him, and his rebuilding of the House of God, they are recorded in the story in the book of the kings. His son Amaziah succeeded him as king.<verse eid="2CH 24:27" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 24" />
  <chapter number="25" style="c" sid="2CH 25" />
  <para style="po">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 25:1" />
    <note caller="a" style="f">
      <char style="fr" closed="false">25.1–28 </char>
      <char style="ft" closed="false">Cf. <char style="xt"><ref loc="2KI 14">2 Kings 14</ref></char>.</char>
    </note>Amaziah was twenty-five years old when he became king, and he reigned twenty-nine years in Jerusalem; his mother's name was Jehoaddan of Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 25:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 25:2" />He did what was pleasing to <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>, but not with a whole heart. <verse eid="2CH 25:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 25:3" />Once he had the kingdom firmly under control, he executed the courtiers who had assassinated his father the king. <verse eid="2CH 25:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 25:4" />But he did not put their children to death for [he acted] in accordance with what is written in the Teaching, in the Book of Moses, where <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> commanded, “Parents shall not die for children, nor shall children die for parents, but each shall die only for their own crime.”<note caller="b" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">25.4 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">Parents shall … crime </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Cf. <char style="xt"><ref loc="DEU 24:16">Deut. 24.16</ref></char>.</char></note><verse eid="2CH 25:4" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 25:5" />Amaziah assembled the men of Judah, and he put all the men of Judah and Benjamin under officers of thousands and officers of hundreds, by clans. He mustered them from the age of twenty upward, and found that there were 300,000 fine soldiers fit for service, able to bear spear and shield. <verse eid="2CH 25:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 25:6" />He hired 100,000 warriors from Israel for 100 talents of silver. <verse eid="2CH 25:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 25:7" />Then an agent of God came to him and said, “O king! Do not let the army of Israel go with you, for <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> is not with Israel—all these Ephraimites. <verse eid="2CH 25:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 25:8" />But go by yourself and do it; take courage for battle, [else] God will make you fall before the enemy. For in God there is power to help one or make one fall!” <verse eid="2CH 25:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 25:9" />Amaziah said to the agent of God, “And what am I to do about the 100 talents I gave for the Israelite force?” The agent of God replied, “<char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> has the means to give you much more than that.” <verse eid="2CH 25:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 25:10" />So Amaziah detached the force that came to him from Ephraim, [ordering them] to go back to their place. They were greatly enraged against Judah and returned to their place in a rage.<verse eid="2CH 25:10" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 25:11" />Amaziah took courage and, leading his army, he marched to the Valley of Salt. He slew 10,000 men from Seir; <verse eid="2CH 25:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 25:12" />another 10,000 the Judahites captured alive and brought to the top of Sela. They threw them down from the top of Sela and every one of them was burst open. <verse eid="2CH 25:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 25:13" />The members of the force that Amaziah had sent back so they would not go with him into battle made forays against the towns of Judah from Samaria to Beth-horon. They slew 3,000 of them, and took much booty.<verse eid="2CH 25:13" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 25:14" />After Amaziah returned from defeating the Edomites, he had the gods of the people of Seir brought, and installed them as his gods; he prostrated himself before them, and to them he made sacrifice. <verse eid="2CH 25:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 25:15" /><char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> was enraged at Amaziah, and sent a prophet to him who said to him, “Why are you worshiping the gods of a people who could not save their people from you?” <verse eid="2CH 25:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 25:16" />As he spoke to him, [Amaziah] said to him, “Have we appointed you a counselor to the king? Stop, else you will be killed!” The prophet stopped, saying, “I see God has counseled that you be destroyed, since you act this way and disregard my counsel.”<verse eid="2CH 25:16" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 25:17" />Then King Amaziah of Judah took counsel and sent this message to Joash son of Jehoahaz son of Jehu, king of Israel, “Come, let us confront each other!” <verse eid="2CH 25:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 25:18" />King Joash of Israel sent back this message to King Amaziah of Judah, “The thistle in Lebanon sent this message to the cedar in Lebanon, ‘Give your daughter to my son in marriage.’ But a wild beast in Lebanon passed by and trampled the thistle. <verse eid="2CH 25:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 25:19" />You boast that you have defeated the Edomites and you are ambitious to get more glory. Now stay at home, lest, provoking disaster you fall, dragging Judah down with you.” <verse eid="2CH 25:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 25:20" />But Amaziah paid no heed—it was God's doing, in order to deliver them up because they worshiped the gods of Edom. <verse eid="2CH 25:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 25:21" />King Joash of Israel marched up, and he and King Amaziah of Judah confronted each other at Beth-shemesh in Judah. <verse eid="2CH 25:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 25:22" />Judah was routed by Israel, and [the Judahites] fled to their homes. <verse eid="2CH 25:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="2CH 25:23" />King Joash of Israel captured Amaziah son of Joash son of Jehoahaz, king of Judah, in Beth-shemesh. He brought him to Jerusalem and made a breach of 400 cubits in the wall of Jerusalem, from the Ephraim Gate to the Corner Gate. <verse eid="2CH 25:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="2CH 25:24" />Then, with all the gold and silver and all the utensils that were to be found in the House of God in the custody of Obed-edom, and with the treasuries of the royal palace, and with the hostages, he returned to Samaria.<verse eid="2CH 25:24" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="2CH 25:25" />King Amaziah son of Joash of Judah lived fifteen years after the death of King Joash son of Jehoahaz of Israel. <verse eid="2CH 25:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="2CH 25:26" />The other events of Amaziah's reign, early and late, are recorded in the book of the kings of Judah and Israel. <verse eid="2CH 25:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="2CH 25:27" />From the time that Amaziah turned from following <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>, a conspiracy was formed against him in Jerusalem, and he fled to Lachish; but they sent agents after him to Lachish and they put him to death there. <verse eid="2CH 25:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="2CH 25:28" />They brought his body back on horses and buried him with his ancestors in the city of Judah.<verse eid="2CH 25:28" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 25" />
  <chapter number="26" style="c" sid="2CH 26" />
  <para style="po">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 26:1" />Then all the people of Judah took Uzziah, who was sixteen years old, and proclaimed him king to succeed his father Amaziah. <verse eid="2CH 26:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 26:2" />It was he who rebuilt Eloth and restored it to Judah after King [Amaziah] rested with his ancestors.<verse eid="2CH 26:2" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 26:3" />Uzziah was sixteen years old when he became king, and he reigned fifty-two years in Jerusalem; his mother's name was Jecoliah of Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 26:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 26:4" />He did what was pleasing to <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> just as his father Amaziah had done. <verse eid="2CH 26:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 26:5" />He applied himself to the worship of God during the time of Zechariah, instructor in the visions<note caller="a" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">26.5 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">visions </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Some Heb. mss. read <char style="tl">byrʼt</char>; compare ancient versions, “fear.”</char></note> of God; during the time he worshiped <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char>, God made him prosper. <verse eid="2CH 26:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 26:6" />He went forth to fight the Philistines, and breached the wall of Gath and the wall of Jabneh and the wall of Ashdod; he built towns in [the region of] Ashdod and among the Philistines. <verse eid="2CH 26:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 26:7" />God helped him against the Philistines, against the Arabs who lived in Gur-baal, and the Meunites. <verse eid="2CH 26:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 26:8" />The Ammonites paid tribute to Uzziah, and his fame spread to the approaches of Egypt, for he grew exceedingly strong. <verse eid="2CH 26:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 26:9" />Uzziah built towers in Jerusalem on the Corner Gate and the Valley Gate and on the Angle, and fortified them. <verse eid="2CH 26:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 26:10" />He built towers in the wilderness and hewed out many cisterns, for he had much cattle, and farmers in the foothills and on the plain, and vine dressers in the mountains and on the fertile lands, for he loved the soil.<verse eid="2CH 26:10" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 26:11" />Uzziah had an army of warriors, a battle-ready force who were mustered by Jeiel the scribe and Maasseiah the adjutant under Hananiah, one of the king's officers. <verse eid="2CH 26:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 26:12" />The clan chiefs, valiants, totaled 2,600; <verse eid="2CH 26:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 26:13" />under them was the trained army of 307,500, who made war with might and power to aid the king against the enemy. <verse eid="2CH 26:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 26:14" />Uzziah provided them—the whole army—with shields and spears, and helmets and mail, and bows and slingstones. <verse eid="2CH 26:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 26:15" />He made clever devices in Jerusalem, set on the towers and the corners, for shooting arrows and large stones. His fame spread far, for he was helped wonderfully, and he became strong.<verse eid="2CH 26:15" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 26:16" />When he was strong, he grew so arrogant he acted corruptly: he trespassed against his God by entering the Temple of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> to offer incense on the incense altar. <verse eid="2CH 26:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 26:17" />The priest Azariah, with eighty other brave priests of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>, followed him in <verse eid="2CH 26:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 26:18" />and, confronting King Uzziah, said to him, “It is not for you, Uzziah, to offer incense to <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>, but for the Aaronite priests, who have been consecrated, to offer incense. Get out of the Sanctuary, for you have trespassed; there will be no glory in it for you from <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> God.” <verse eid="2CH 26:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 26:19" />Uzziah, holding the censer and ready to burn incense, got angry; but as he got angry with the priests, leprosy broke out on his forehead in front of the priests in the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> beside the incense altar. <verse eid="2CH 26:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 26:20" />When the chief priest Azariah and all the other priests looked at him, his forehead was leprous, so they rushed him out of there; he too made haste to get out, for <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> had struck him with a plague. <verse eid="2CH 26:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 26:21" />King Uzziah was a leper until the day of his death. He lived in isolated quarters<note caller="b" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">26.21 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">isolated quarters </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Meaning of Heb. uncertain.</char></note> as a leper, for he was cut off from the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>—while Jotham his son was in charge of the king's house and governed the people of the land.<verse eid="2CH 26:21" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 26:22" />The other events of Uzziah's reign, early and late, were recorded by the prophet Isaiah son of Amoz. <verse eid="2CH 26:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="2CH 26:23" />Uzziah rested with his ancestors in the burial field of the kings, because, they said, he was a leper; his son Jotham succeeded him as king.<verse eid="2CH 26:23" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 26" />
  <chapter number="27" style="c" sid="2CH 27" />
  <para style="po">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 27:1" />Jotham was twenty-five years old when he became king, and he reigned sixteen years in Jerusalem; his mother's name was Jerushah daughter of Zadok. <verse eid="2CH 27:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 27:2" />He did what was pleasing to <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> just as his father Uzziah had done, but he did not enter the Temple of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>; however, the people still acted corruptly. <verse eid="2CH 27:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 27:3" />It was he who built the Upper Gate of the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>; he also built extensively on the wall of Ophel. <verse eid="2CH 27:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 27:4" />He built towns in the hill country of Judah, and in the woods he built fortresses and towers. <verse eid="2CH 27:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 27:5" />Moreover, he fought with the king of the Ammonites and overcame them; the Ammonites gave him that year 100 talents of silver and 10,000 <char style="tl">kor</char>s of wheat and another 10,000 of barley; that is what the Ammonites paid him, and [likewise] in the second and third years. <verse eid="2CH 27:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 27:6" />Jotham was strong because he maintained a faithful course before <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> his God.<verse eid="2CH 27:6" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 27:7" />The other events of Jotham's reign, and all his battles and his conduct, are recorded in the book of the kings of Israel and Judah. <verse eid="2CH 27:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 27:8" />He was twenty-five years old when he became king, and he reigned sixteen years in Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 27:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 27:9" />Jotham rested with his ancestors, and was buried in the City of David; his son Ahaz succeeded him as king.<verse eid="2CH 27:9" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 27" />
  <chapter number="28" style="c" sid="2CH 28" />
  <para style="po">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 28:1" />Ahaz was twenty years old when he became king, and he reigned sixteen years in Jerusalem. He did not do what was pleasing to <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> as his forefather David had done, <verse eid="2CH 28:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 28:2" />but followed the ways of the kings of Israel; he even made molten images for the Baals. <verse eid="2CH 28:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 28:3" />He made offerings in the Valley of Ben-hinnom and burned his sons in fire, in the abhorrent fashion of the nations that <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> had dispossessed before the Israelites. <verse eid="2CH 28:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 28:4" />He sacrificed and made offerings at the shrines, on the hills, and under every leafy tree. <verse eid="2CH 28:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 28:5" /><char style="nd">The <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> his God delivered him over to the king of Aram, who defeated him and took many of his men captive, and brought them to Damascus. He was also delivered over to the king of Israel, who inflicted a great defeat on him. <verse eid="2CH 28:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 28:6" />Pekah son of Remaliah killed 120,000 in Judah—all brave fighters—in one day, because they had forsaken <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> God of their ancestors. <verse eid="2CH 28:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 28:7" />Zichri, the champion of Ephraim, killed Maaseiah the king's son, and Azrikam chief of the palace, and Elkanah, the second to the king. <verse eid="2CH 28:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 28:8" />The Israelites captured 200,000 of their kin—including women, boys, and girls; they also took a large amount of booty from them and brought the booty to Samaria.<verse eid="2CH 28:8" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 28:9" />A prophet of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> by the name of Oded was there, who went out to meet the army on its return to Samaria. He said to them, “Because of the fury of <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> God of your ancestors against Judah, they were delivered over to you, and you killed them in a rage that reached heaven. <verse eid="2CH 28:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 28:10" />Do you now intend to subjugate the men and women of Judah and Jerusalem to be your slaves? As it is, you have nothing but offenses against <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> your God. <verse eid="2CH 28:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 28:11" />Now then, listen to me, and send back the captives you have taken from your kin, for <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>'s wrath is upon you!” <verse eid="2CH 28:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 28:12" />Some of the Ephraimite chiefs—Azariah son of Jehohanan, Berechiah son of Meshillemoth, Jehizkiah son of Shallum, and Amasa son of Hadlai—confronted those returning from the campaign <verse eid="2CH 28:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 28:13" />and said to them, “Do not bring these captives here, for it would mean our offending <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>, adding to our sins and our offenses; for our offense is grave enough, and there is already wrath upon Israel.” <verse eid="2CH 28:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 28:14" />So the soldiers released the captives and the booty in the presence of the officers and all the congregation. <verse eid="2CH 28:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 28:15" />Then the men named above proceeded to take the captives in hand, and with the booty they clothed all the naked among them—they clothed them and shod them and gave them to eat and drink and anointed them and provided donkeys for all who were failing and brought them to Jericho, the city of palms, back to their kin. Then they returned to Samaria.<verse eid="2CH 28:15" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 28:16" />At that time, King Ahaz sent to the king of Assyria for help. <verse eid="2CH 28:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 28:17" />Again the Edomites came and inflicted a defeat on Judah and took captives. <verse eid="2CH 28:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 28:18" />And the Philistines made forays against the cities of the Shephelah and the Negeb of Judah; they seized Beth-shemesh and Aijalon and Gederoth, and Soco with its villages, and Timnah with its villages, and Gimzo with its villages; and they settled there. <verse eid="2CH 28:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 28:19" />Thus <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> brought Judah low on account of King Ahaz of Israel,<note caller="a" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">28.19 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">Israel </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Some mss. and ancient versions read “Judah.”</char></note> for he threw off restraint in Judah and trespassed against <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>. <verse eid="2CH 28:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 28:20" />Tillegath-pilneser, king of Assyria, marched against him and gave him trouble, instead of supporting him. <verse eid="2CH 28:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 28:21" />For Ahaz plundered the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> and the house of the king and the officers, and made a gift to the king of Assyria—to no avail.<verse eid="2CH 28:21" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 28:22" />In his time of trouble, this King Ahaz trespassed even more against <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>, <verse eid="2CH 28:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="2CH 28:23" />sacrificing to the gods of Damascus that had defeated him, for he thought, “The gods of the kings of Aram help them; I shall sacrifice to them and they will help me”; but they were his ruin and that of all Israel. <verse eid="2CH 28:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="2CH 28:24" />Ahaz collected the utensils of the House of God, and cut the utensils of the House of God to pieces. He shut the doors of the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> and made himself altars in every corner of Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 28:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="2CH 28:25" />In every town in Judah he set up shrines to make offerings to other gods, vexing <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> God of his ancestors.<verse eid="2CH 28:25" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="2CH 28:26" />The other events of his reign and all his conduct, early and late, are recorded in the book of the kings of Judah and Israel. <verse eid="2CH 28:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="2CH 28:27" />Ahaz rested with his ancestors and was buried in the city, in Jerusalem; his body was not brought to the tombs of the kings of Israel. His son Hezekiah succeeded him as king.<verse eid="2CH 28:27" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 28" />
  <chapter number="29" style="c" sid="2CH 29" />
  <para style="po">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 29:1" />Hezekiah became king at the age of twenty-five, and he reigned twenty-nine years in Jerusalem; his mother's name was Abijah daughter of Zechariah. <verse eid="2CH 29:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 29:2" />He did what was pleasing to <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>, just as his forefather David had done.<verse eid="2CH 29:2" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 29:3" />He, in the first month of the first year of his reign, opened the doors of the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> and repaired them. <verse eid="2CH 29:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 29:4" />He summoned the priests and the Levites and assembled them in the east square. <verse eid="2CH 29:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 29:5" />He said to them, “Listen to me, Levites! Sanctify yourselves and sanctify the House of <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> God of your ancestors, and take the abhorrent things out of the holy place. <verse eid="2CH 29:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 29:6" />For our ancestors trespassed and did what displeased <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> our God—whom they forsook as they turned their faces away from the dwelling-place of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>, turning their backs on it. <verse eid="2CH 29:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 29:7" />They also shut the doors of the porch and put out the lights; they did not offer incense and did not make burnt offerings in the holy place to the God of Israel. <verse eid="2CH 29:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 29:8" /><char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>'s wrath was upon Judah and Jerusalem; they were made to be an object of horror, amazement, and hissing<note caller="a" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">29.8 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">hissing </char><char style="ft" closed="false">See note at <char style="xt"><ref loc="JER 18:16">Jer. 18.16</ref></char>.</char></note>—as you see with your own eyes. <verse eid="2CH 29:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 29:9" />Our ancestors died by the sword, and our sons and daughters and wives are in captivity on account of this. <verse eid="2CH 29:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 29:10" />Now I wish to make a covenant with <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> God of Israel, whose rage may hopefully be withdrawn from us. <verse eid="2CH 29:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 29:11" />Now, my sons, do not be slack, for <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> chose you to be in attendance, to render service, to minister, and to make offerings.”<verse eid="2CH 29:11" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 29:12" />So the Levites set to—Mahath son of Amasai and Joel son of Azariah of the sons of Kohath; and of the sons of Merari, Kish son of Abdi and Azariah son of Jehallelel; and of the Gershonites, Joah son of Zimmah and Eden son of Joah; <verse eid="2CH 29:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 29:13" />and of the sons of Elizaphan, Shimri and Jeiel; and of the sons of Asaph, Zechariah and Mattaniah; <verse eid="2CH 29:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 29:14" />and of the sons of Heman, Jehiel and Shimei; and of the sons of Jeduthun, Shemaiah and Uzziel— <verse eid="2CH 29:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 29:15" />and, gathering their brothers, they sanctified themselves and came, by a command of the king concerning <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>'s ordinances, to purify the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>. <verse eid="2CH 29:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 29:16" />The priests went into the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> to purify it, and brought all the impure things they found in the Temple of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> out into the court of the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>; [there] the Levites received them, to take them outside to Wadi Kidron. <verse eid="2CH 29:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 29:17" />They began the sanctification on the first day of the first month; on the eighth day of the month they reached the porch of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>. They sanctified the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> for eight days, and on the sixteenth day of the first month they finished. <verse eid="2CH 29:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 29:18" />Then they went into the palace of King Hezekiah and said, “We have purified the whole House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> and the altar of burnt offering and all its utensils, and the table of the bread of display and all its utensils; <verse eid="2CH 29:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 29:19" />and all the utensils that King Ahaz had befouled during his reign, when he trespassed, we have made ready and sanctified. They are standing in front of the altar of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>.”<verse eid="2CH 29:19" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 29:20" />King Hezekiah rose early, gathered the officers of the city, and went up to the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>. <verse eid="2CH 29:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 29:21" />They brought seven bulls and seven rams and seven lambs and seven he-goats as a purgation offering for the kingdom and for the Sanctuary and for Judah. He ordered the Aaronite priests to offer them on the altar of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>. <verse eid="2CH 29:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 29:22" />The cattle were slaughtered, and the priests received the blood and dashed it against the altar; the rams were slaughtered and the blood was dashed against the altar; the lambs were slaughtered and the blood was dashed against the altar. <verse eid="2CH 29:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="2CH 29:23" />The he-goats for the purgation offering were presented to the king and the congregation, who laid their hands upon them. <verse eid="2CH 29:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="2CH 29:24" />The priests slaughtered them and performed the purgation rite with the blood against the altar, to expiate for all Israel, for the king had designated the burnt offering and the purgation offering to be for all Israel. <verse eid="2CH 29:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="2CH 29:25" />He stationed the Levites in the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> with cymbals and harps and lyres, as David and Gad the king's seer and Nathan the prophet had ordained, for the ordinance was by <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> through those prophets.<verse eid="2CH 29:25" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="2CH 29:26" />When the Levites were in place with the instruments of David, and the priests with their trumpets, <verse eid="2CH 29:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="2CH 29:27" />Hezekiah gave the order to offer the burnt offering on the altar. When the burnt offering began, the song of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> and the trumpets began also, together with the instruments of King David of Israel. <verse eid="2CH 29:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="2CH 29:28" />All the congregation prostrated themselves, the song was sung and the trumpets were blown—all this until the end of the burnt offering. <verse eid="2CH 29:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="2CH 29:29" />When the offering was finished, the king and all who were there with him knelt and prostrated themselves. <verse eid="2CH 29:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="2CH 29:30" />King Hezekiah and the officers ordered the Levites to praise <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> in the words of David and Asaph the seer; so they praised rapturously, and they bowed and prostrated themselves.<verse eid="2CH 29:30" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="2CH 29:31" />Then Hezekiah said, “Now you have consecrated yourselves to <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>; come, bring sacrifices of well-being and thanksgiving to the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>.” The congregation brought sacrifices of well-being and thanksgiving, and all who felt so moved brought burnt offerings. <verse eid="2CH 29:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="2CH 29:32" />The number of burnt offerings that the congregation brought was 70 cattle, 100 rams, 200 lambs—all these for burnt offerings to <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>. <verse eid="2CH 29:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="2CH 29:33" />The sacred offerings were 600 large cattle and 3,000 small cattle. <verse eid="2CH 29:33" /><verse number="34" style="v" sid="2CH 29:34" />The priests were too few to be able to flay all the burnt offerings, so their kindred, the Levites, reinforced them till the end of the work, and till the [rest of the] priests sanctified themselves. (The Levites were more conscientious about sanctifying themselves than the priests.) <verse eid="2CH 29:34" /><verse number="35" style="v" sid="2CH 29:35" />For beside the large number of burnt offerings, there were the fat parts of the sacrifices of well-being and the libations for the burnt offerings; so the service of the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> was properly accomplished. <verse eid="2CH 29:35" /><verse number="36" style="v" sid="2CH 29:36" />Hezekiah and all the people rejoiced over what God had enabled the people to accomplish, because it had happened so suddenly.<verse eid="2CH 29:36" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 29" />
  <chapter number="30" style="c" sid="2CH 30" />
  <para style="po">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 30:1" />Hezekiah sent word to all Israel and Judah; he also wrote letters to Ephraim and Manasseh to come to the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> in Jerusalem to keep the Passover for <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> God of Israel. <verse eid="2CH 30:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 30:2" />The king and his officers and the congregation in Jerusalem had agreed to keep the Passover in the second month, <verse eid="2CH 30:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 30:3" />for at the time, they were unable to keep it,<note caller="a" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">30.3 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">unable to keep it </char><char style="ft" closed="false">On its proper date; cf. <char style="xt"><ref loc="NUM 9:1-14">Num. 9.1–14</ref></char>.</char></note> for not enough priests had sanctified themselves, nor had the people assembled in Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 30:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 30:4" />The king and the whole congregation thought it proper <verse eid="2CH 30:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 30:5" />to issue a decree and proclaim throughout all Israel from Beer-sheba to Dan that they come and keep the Passover for <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> God of Israel in Jerusalem—not often did they act in accord with what was written. <verse eid="2CH 30:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 30:6" />The couriers went out with the letters from the king and his officers through all Israel and Judah, by order of the king, proclaiming, “O you Israelites! Return to <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> God of your fathers, Abraham, Isaac, and Israel, and [God] will return to the remnant of you who escaped from the hand of the kings of Assyria. <verse eid="2CH 30:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 30:7" />Do not be like your ancestors and kindred who trespassed against <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> God of their ancestors and were turned into a horror, as you see. <verse eid="2CH 30:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 30:8" />Now do not be stiffnecked like your ancestors; submit yourselves to <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> and come to the sanctuary that has been consecrated forever, and serve <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> your God, whose anger may hopefully turn back from you. <verse eid="2CH 30:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 30:9" />If you return to <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>, your brothers and children will be regarded with compassion by their captors, and will return to this land; <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> your God, being gracious and merciful, will not turn away from you if you return.”<verse eid="2CH 30:9" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 30:10" />As the couriers passed from town to town in the land of Ephraim and Manasseh till they reached Zebulun, they were laughed at and mocked. <verse eid="2CH 30:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 30:11" />Some of the people of Asher and Manasseh and Zebulun, however, were contrite, and came to Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 30:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 30:12" />The hand of God was on Judah, too, making them of a single mind to carry out the command of the king and officers concerning the ordinance of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>. <verse eid="2CH 30:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 30:13" />A great crowd assembled at Jerusalem to keep the Feast of Unleavened Bread in the second month, a very great congregation. <verse eid="2CH 30:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 30:14" />They set to and removed the altars that were in Jerusalem, and they removed all the incense stands and threw them into Wadi Kidron. <verse eid="2CH 30:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 30:15" />They slaughtered the passover sacrifice on the fourteenth of the second month. The priests and Levites were ashamed, and they sanctified themselves and brought burnt offerings to the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>. <verse eid="2CH 30:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 30:16" />They took their stations, as was their rule according to the Teaching of Moses, agent of God. The priests dashed the blood [that they received] from the Levites. <verse eid="2CH 30:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 30:17" />Since many in the congregation had not sanctified themselves, the Levites were in charge of slaughtering the passover sacrifice for everyone who was not pure, so as to consecrate them to <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>. <verse eid="2CH 30:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 30:18" />For most of the people—many from Ephraim and Manasseh, Issachar and Zebulun—had not purified themselves, yet they ate the passover sacrifice in violation of what was written. Hezekiah prayed for them, saying, “The good <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> will provide atonement for <verse eid="2CH 30:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 30:19" />all who set their mind on worshiping God—<char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> God of their ancestors—even if they are not purified for the sanctuary.” <verse eid="2CH 30:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 30:20" /><char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> heard Hezekiah and healed the people.<verse eid="2CH 30:20" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 30:21" />The Israelites who were in Jerusalem kept the Feast of Unleavened Bread seven days, with great rejoicing, the Levites and the priests praising <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> daily with powerful instruments for <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>. <verse eid="2CH 30:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 30:22" />Hezekiah persuaded all the Levites who performed skillfully for <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> to spend the seven days of the festival making offerings of well-being, and confessing to <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> God of their ancestors. <verse eid="2CH 30:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="2CH 30:23" />All the congregation resolved to keep seven more days, so they kept seven more days of rejoicing. <verse eid="2CH 30:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="2CH 30:24" />King Hezekiah of Judah contributed to the congregation 1,000 bulls and 7,000 sheep. And the officers contributed to the congregation 1,000 bulls and 10,000 sheep. And the priests sanctified themselves in large numbers. <verse eid="2CH 30:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="2CH 30:25" />All the congregation of Judah and the priests and the Levites and all the congregation that came from Israel, and the resident aliens who came from the land of Israel and who lived in Judah, rejoiced. <verse eid="2CH 30:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="2CH 30:26" />There was great rejoicing in Jerusalem, for since the time of King Solomon son of David of Israel nothing like it had happened in Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 30:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="2CH 30:27" />The Levite priests rose and blessed the people, and their voice was heard, and their prayer went up to God's holy abode, to heaven.<verse eid="2CH 30:27" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 30" />
  <chapter number="31" style="c" sid="2CH 31" />
  <para style="po">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 31:1" />When all this was finished, all Israel who were present went out into the towns of Judah and smashed the pillars, cut down the sacred posts,<note caller="a" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">31.1 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">sacred posts </char><char style="ft" closed="false">See note at <char style="xt"><ref loc="2CH 14:2">14.2</ref></char>.</char></note> demolished the shrines and altars throughout Judah and Benjamin, and throughout Ephraim and Manasseh, to the very last one. Then all the Israelites returned to their towns, each to their homestead.<verse eid="2CH 31:1" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 31:2" />Hezekiah reconstituted the divisions of the priests and Levites, each of the priests and Levites according to his office, for the burnt offerings, the offerings of well-being, to minister, and to sing hymns and praises in the gates of the courts of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>; <verse eid="2CH 31:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 31:3" />also the king's portion, from his property, for the burnt offerings—the morning and evening burnt offering, and the burnt offerings for sabbaths, and new moons, and festivals, as prescribed in the Teaching of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>.<verse eid="2CH 31:3" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 31:4" />He ordered the people, the inhabitants of Jerusalem, to deliver the portions of the priests and the Levites, so that they might devote themselves to the Teaching of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>. <verse eid="2CH 31:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 31:5" />When the word spread, the Israelites brought large quantities of grain, wine, oil, honey, and all kinds of agricultural produce, and tithes of all, in large amounts. <verse eid="2CH 31:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 31:6" />The people of Israel and Judah living in the towns of Judah—they too brought tithes of cattle and sheep and tithes of sacred things consecrated to <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> their God, piling them in heaps. <verse eid="2CH 31:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 31:7" />In the third month the heaps began to accumulate, and were finished in the seventh month. <verse eid="2CH 31:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 31:8" />When Hezekiah and the officers came and saw the heaps, they blessed <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> and the people Israel. <verse eid="2CH 31:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 31:9" />Hezekiah asked the priests and Levites about the heaps. <verse eid="2CH 31:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 31:10" />The chief priest Azariah, of the house of Zadok, replied to him, saying, “Ever since the gifts began to be brought to the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>, people have been eating to satiety and leaving over in great amounts, for <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> has blessed the people; this huge amount is left over!” <verse eid="2CH 31:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 31:11" />Hezekiah then gave orders to prepare store-chambers in the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>; and they were prepared. <verse eid="2CH 31:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 31:12" />They brought in the gifts and the tithes and the sacred things faithfully. Their supervisor was Conaniah the Levite, and Shimei his brother was second in rank. <verse eid="2CH 31:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 31:13" />Jehiel and Azaziah and Nahath and Asahel and Jerimoth and Jozabad and Eliel and Ismachiah and Mahath and Benaiah were commissioners under Conaniah and Shimei his brother by appointment of King Hezekiah; Azariah was supervisor of the House of God. <verse eid="2CH 31:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 31:14" />Kore son of Imnah the Levite, the keeper of the East Gate, was in charge of the freewill offerings to God, of the allocation of gifts to <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>, and the most sacred things. <verse eid="2CH 31:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 31:15" />Under him were Eden, Miniamin, Jeshua, Shemaiah, Amariah, and Shecaniah, in offices of trust in the priestly towns, making allocation to their brothers by divisions, to great and small alike; <verse eid="2CH 31:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 31:16" />besides allocating their daily rations to those males registered by families from three years old and up, all who entered the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> according to their service and their shift by division; <verse eid="2CH 31:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 31:17" />and in charge of the registry of priests by clans, and of the Levites, from twenty years old and up, by shifts, in their divisions; <verse eid="2CH 31:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 31:18" />and the registry of the dependents of their whole company—wives, sons, and daughters—for, relying upon them, they sanctified themselves in holiness. <verse eid="2CH 31:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 31:19" />And for the Aaronite priests, in each and every one of their towns with adjoining fields, those named above were to allocate portions to every male of the priests and to every registered Levite. <verse eid="2CH 31:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 31:20" />Hezekiah did this throughout Judah. He acted in a way that was good, upright, and faithful before <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> his God. <verse eid="2CH 31:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 31:21" />Every work he undertook in the service of the House of God or in the Teaching and the Commandment, to worship his God, he did with all his heart; and he prospered.<verse eid="2CH 31:21" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 31" />
  <chapter number="32" style="c" sid="2CH 32" />
  <para style="po">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 32:1" />
    <note caller="a" style="f">
      <char style="fr" closed="false">32.1–33 </char>
      <char style="ft" closed="false">Cf. <char style="xt"><ref loc="2KI 18">2 Kings 18</ref></char>–<char style="xt" link-href="2KI 20:0"><ref loc="2KI 20">20</ref></char>; <char style="xt"><ref loc="ISA 36">Isa. 36</ref></char>–<char style="xt" link-href="ISA 39:0"><ref loc="ISA 39">39</ref></char>.</char>
    </note>After these faithful deeds, King Sennacherib of Assyria invaded Judah and encamped against its fortified towns with the aim of taking them over. <verse eid="2CH 32:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 32:2" />When Hezekiah saw that Sennacherib had come, intent on making war against Jerusalem, <verse eid="2CH 32:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 32:3" />he consulted with his officers and warriors about stopping the flow of the springs outside the city, and they supported him. <verse eid="2CH 32:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 32:4" />A large force was assembled to stop up all the springs and the wadi that flowed through the land, for otherwise, they thought, the king of Assyria would come and find water in abundance. <verse eid="2CH 32:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 32:5" />He acted with vigor, rebuilding the whole breached wall, raising towers on it, and building another wall outside it. He fortified the Millo of the City of David, and made a great quantity of arms and shields. <verse eid="2CH 32:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 32:6" />He appointed battle officers over the people; then, gathering them to him in the square of the city gate, he rallied them, saying, <verse eid="2CH 32:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 32:7" />“Be strong and of good courage; do not be frightened or dismayed by the king of Assyria or by the horde that is with him, for we have more with us than he has with him. <verse eid="2CH 32:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 32:8" />With him is an arm of flesh, but with us is <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> our God, to help us and to fight our battles.” The people were encouraged by the speech of King Hezekiah of Judah.<verse eid="2CH 32:8" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 32:9" />Afterward, King Sennacherib of Assyria sent his officers to Jerusalem—he and all his staff being at Lachish—with this message to King Hezekiah of Judah and to all the people of Judah who were in Jerusalem: <verse eid="2CH 32:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 32:10" />“Thus said King Sennacherib of Assyria: On what do you trust to enable you to endure a siege in Jerusalem? <verse eid="2CH 32:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 32:11" />Hezekiah is seducing you to a death of hunger and thirst, saying, ‘<char style="nd">The <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> our God will save us from the king of Assyria.’ <verse eid="2CH 32:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 32:12" />But is not Hezekiah the one who removed your God's<note caller="b" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">32.12 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">your God's </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Lit. “His.”</char></note> shrines and altars and commanded the people of Judah and Jerusalem saying, ‘Before this one altar you shall prostrate yourselves, and upon it make your burnt offerings’? <verse eid="2CH 32:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 32:13" />Surely you know what I and my ancestors have done to the peoples of the lands? Were the gods of the nations of the lands able to save their lands from me? <verse eid="2CH 32:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 32:14" />Which of all the gods of any of those nations whom my ancestors destroyed was able to save their people from me, that your God should be able to save you from me? <verse eid="2CH 32:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 32:15" />Now then, do not let Hezekiah delude you; do not let him seduce you in this way; do not believe him. For no god of any nation or kingdom has been able to save their people from me or from my ancestors—much less your God, to save you from me!” <verse eid="2CH 32:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 32:16" />His officers said still more things against <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> God and against Hezekiah—God's servant. <verse eid="2CH 32:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 32:17" />He also wrote letters reviling <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> God of Israel, saying, “Just as the gods of the other nations of the earth did not save their people from me, so the God of Hezekiah will not save this people from me.” <verse eid="2CH 32:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 32:18" />They called loudly in the language of Judah to the people of Jerusalem who were on the wall, to frighten them into panic, so as to capture the city. <verse eid="2CH 32:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 32:19" />They spoke of the God of Jerusalem like they spoke of the gods of the other peoples of the earth, made by human hands. <verse eid="2CH 32:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 32:20" />Then King Hezekiah and the prophet Isaiah son of Amoz prayed about this, and cried out to heaven.<verse eid="2CH 32:20" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 32:21" />
    <char style="nd">
      <char style="sc">God</char>
    </char> sent an angel who annihilated every mighty warrior, commander, and officer in the army of the king of Assyria, and he returned in disgrace to his land. He entered the house of his god, and there some of his own offspring struck him down by the sword. <verse eid="2CH 32:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 32:22" />Thus <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> delivered Hezekiah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem from King Sennacherib of Assyria, and from everyone—providing for them on all sides. <verse eid="2CH 32:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="2CH 32:23" />Many brought tribute to <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> to Jerusalem, and gifts to King Hezekiah of Judah; thereafter he was exalted in the eyes of all the nations.<verse eid="2CH 32:23" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="2CH 32:24" />At that time, Hezekiah fell deathly sick. He prayed to <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>, who responded to him and gave him a sign. <verse eid="2CH 32:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="2CH 32:25" />Hezekiah made no return for what had been bestowed upon him, for he grew arrogant; so wrath was decreed for him and for Judah and Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 32:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="2CH 32:26" />Then Hezekiah humbled himself where he had been arrogant, he and the inhabitants of Jerusalem, and no wrath of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> came on them during the reign of Hezekiah. <verse eid="2CH 32:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="2CH 32:27" />Hezekiah enjoyed riches and glory in abundance; he filled treasuries with silver and gold, precious stones, spices, shields, and all lovely objects; <verse eid="2CH 32:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="2CH 32:28" />and store-cities with the produce of grain, wine, and oil, and stalls for all kinds of beasts, and flocks for sheepfolds. <verse eid="2CH 32:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="2CH 32:29" />And he acquired towns, and flocks of small and large cattle in great number, for God endowed him with very many possessions. <verse eid="2CH 32:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="2CH 32:30" />It was Hezekiah who stopped up the spring of water of Upper Gihon, leading it downward west of the City of David; Hezekiah prospered in all that he did. <verse eid="2CH 32:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="2CH 32:31" />So too in the matter of the ambassadors of the princes of Babylon, who were sent to him to inquire about the sign that was in the land, when God forsook him in order to test him, to learn all that was in his mind.<verse eid="2CH 32:31" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="2CH 32:32" />The other events of Hezekiah's reign, and his faithful acts, are recorded in the visions of the prophet Isaiah son of Amoz and in the book of the kings of Judah and Israel. <verse eid="2CH 32:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="2CH 32:33" />Hezekiah rested with his ancestors, and was buried on the upper part of the tombs of the sons of David. When he died, all the people of Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem accorded him much honor. Manasseh, his son, succeeded him.<verse eid="2CH 32:33" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 32" />
  <chapter number="33" style="c" sid="2CH 33" />
  <para style="po">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 33:1" />
    <note caller="a" style="f">
      <char style="fr" closed="false">33.1–25 </char>
      <char style="ft" closed="false">Cf. <char style="xt"><ref loc="2KI 21">2 Kings 21</ref></char>.</char>
    </note>Manasseh was twelve years old when he became king, and he reigned fifty-five years in Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 33:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 33:2" />He did what was displeasing to <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>, following the abhorrent practices of the nations that <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> had dispossessed before the Israelites. <verse eid="2CH 33:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 33:3" />He rebuilt the shrines that his father Hezekiah had demolished; he erected altars for the Baals and made sacred posts.<note caller="b" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">33.3 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">sacred posts </char><char style="ft" closed="false">See note at <char style="xt"><ref loc="2CH 14:2">14.2</ref></char>.</char></note> He bowed down to all the host of heaven and worshiped them, <verse eid="2CH 33:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 33:4" />and he built altars [to them] in the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>, of which <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> had said, “My name will be in Jerusalem forever.” <verse eid="2CH 33:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 33:5" />He built altars for all the host of heaven in the two courts of the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>. <verse eid="2CH 33:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 33:6" />He consigned his sons to the fire in the Valley of Ben-hinnom, and he practiced soothsaying, divination, and sorcery, and consulted ghosts and familiar spirits; he did much that was displeasing to <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> in order to provoke anger. <verse eid="2CH 33:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 33:7" />He placed a sculptured image that he made in the House of God, of which God had said to David and to his son Solomon, “In this House and in Jerusalem, which I chose out of all the tribes of Israel, I will establish My name forever. <verse eid="2CH 33:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 33:8" />And I will never again remove the feet of Israel from the land that I assigned to their ancestors, if only they observe faithfully all that I have commanded them—all the teaching and the laws and the rules given by Moses.” <verse eid="2CH 33:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 33:9" />Manasseh led Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem astray into evil greater than that done by the nations that <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> had destroyed before the Israelites.<verse eid="2CH 33:9" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 33:10" />
    <char style="nd">
      <char style="sc">God</char>
    </char> spoke to Manasseh and his people, but they would not pay heed, <verse eid="2CH 33:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 33:11" />so <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> brought against them the officers of the army of the king of Assyria, who took Manasseh captive in manacles, bound him in fetters, and led him off to Babylon. <verse eid="2CH 33:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 33:12" />In his distress, he entreated <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> his God and humbled himself greatly before the God of his ancestors. <verse eid="2CH 33:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 33:13" />He prayed to [God], who granted his prayer, heard his plea, and returned him to Jerusalem to his kingdom. Then Manasseh knew that <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> alone was God. <verse eid="2CH 33:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 33:14" />Afterward he built the outer wall of the City of David west of Gihon in the wadi on the way to the Fish Gate, and it encircled Ophel; he raised it very high. He also placed army officers in all the fortified towns of Judah. <verse eid="2CH 33:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 33:15" />He removed the foreign gods and the image from the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>, as well as all the altars that he had built on the Mount of the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> and in Jerusalem, and dumped them outside the city. <verse eid="2CH 33:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 33:16" />He rebuilt the altar of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> and offered on it sacrifices of well-being and thanksgiving, and commanded the people of Judah to worship <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> God of Israel. <verse eid="2CH 33:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 33:17" />To be sure, the people continued sacrificing at the shrines, but only to <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> their God.<verse eid="2CH 33:17" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 33:18" />The other events of Manasseh's reign, and his prayer to his God, and the words of the seers who spoke to him in the name of <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> God of Israel are found in the chronicles of the kings of Israel. <verse eid="2CH 33:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 33:19" />His prayer and how it was granted to him, the whole account of his sin and trespass, and the places in which he built shrines and installed sacred posts<note caller="c" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">33.19 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">sacred posts </char><char style="ft" closed="false">See note at <char style="xt"><ref loc="2CH 14:2">14.2</ref></char>.</char></note> and images before he humbled himself are recorded in the words of Hozai.<note caller="d" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">33.19 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">Hozai </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or “seers.”</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 33:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 33:20" />Manasseh rested with his ancestors and was buried on his palace grounds; his son Amon succeeded him as king.<verse eid="2CH 33:20" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 33:21" />Amon was twenty-two years old when he became king, and he reigned two years in Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 33:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 33:22" />He did what was displeasing to <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>, as his father Manasseh had done. Amon sacrificed to all the idols that his father Manasseh had made and worshiped them. <verse eid="2CH 33:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="2CH 33:23" />He did not humble himself before <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>, as his father Manasseh had humbled himself; instead, Amon incurred much guilt. <verse eid="2CH 33:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="2CH 33:24" />His courtiers conspired against him and killed him in his palace. <verse eid="2CH 33:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="2CH 33:25" />But the people of the land struck down all who had conspired against King Amon; and the people of the land made his son Josiah king in his stead.<verse eid="2CH 33:25" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 33" />
  <chapter number="34" style="c" sid="2CH 34" />
  <para style="po">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 34:1" />
    <note caller="a" style="f">
      <char style="fr" closed="false">34.1–33 </char>
      <char style="ft" closed="false">Cf. <char style="xt"><ref loc="2KI 22">2 Kings 22</ref>; <ref loc="2KI 23:1-20">23.1–20</ref></char>.</char>
    </note>Josiah was eight years old when he became king, and he reigned thirty-one years in Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 34:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 34:2" />He did what was pleasing to <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>, following the ways of his forefather David without deviating to the right or to the left. <verse eid="2CH 34:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 34:3" />In the eighth year of his reign, while he was still young, he began to seek the God of his forefather David, and in the twelfth year he began to purge Judah and Jerusalem of the shrines, the sacred posts,<note caller="b" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">34.3 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">sacred posts </char><char style="ft" closed="false">See note at <char style="xt"><ref loc="2CH 14:2">14.2</ref></char>.</char></note> the idols, and the molten images. <verse eid="2CH 34:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 34:4" />At his bidding, they demolished the altars of the Baals, and he had the incense stands above them cut down; he smashed the sacred posts, the idols, and the images, ground them into dust, and strewed it onto the graves of those who had sacrificed to them. <verse eid="2CH 34:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 34:5" />He burned the bones of priests on their altars and purged Judah and Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 34:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 34:6" />In the towns of Manasseh and Ephraim and Simeon, as far as Naphtali, [lying] in ruins on every side, <verse eid="2CH 34:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 34:7" />he demolished the altars and the sacred posts and smashed the idols and ground them into dust; and he hewed down all the incense stands throughout the land of Israel. Then he returned to Jerusalem.<verse eid="2CH 34:7" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 34:8" />In the eighteenth year of his reign, after purging the land and the House, he commissioned Shaphan son of Azaliah, Maaseiah the governor of the city, and Joah son of Joahaz the recorder to repair the House of <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> his God. <verse eid="2CH 34:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 34:9" />They came to the high priest Hilkiah and delivered to him the silver brought to the House of God, which the Levites, the guards of the threshold, had collected from Manasseh and Ephraim and from all the remnant of Israel and from all Judah and Benjamin and the inhabitants of Jerusalem.<note caller="c" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">34.9 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">the inhabitants of Jerusalem </char><char style="ft" closed="false">With <char style="tl">kethib</char> and ancient versions; <char style="tl">qere</char>, “they returned to Jerusalem.”</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 34:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 34:10" />They delivered it into the custody of the overseers who were in charge at the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>, and the overseers who worked in the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> spent it on examining and repairing the House. <verse eid="2CH 34:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 34:11" />They paid it out to the artisans and the masons to buy quarried stone and wood for the couplings and for making roof-beams for the buildings that the kings of Judah had allowed to fall into ruin. <verse eid="2CH 34:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 34:12" />Those involved did the work honestly; over them were appointed the Levites Jahath and Obadiah, of the sons of Merari, and Zechariah and Meshullam, of the sons of Kohath, to supervise; while other Levites, all the master musicians, <verse eid="2CH 34:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 34:13" />were over the porters, supervising all who worked at each and every task; some of the Levites were scribes and officials and gatekeepers.<verse eid="2CH 34:13" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 34:14" />As they took out the silver that had been brought to the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>, the priest Hilkiah found a scroll of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>'s Teaching given by Moses. <verse eid="2CH 34:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 34:15" />Hilkiah spoke up and said to the scribe Shaphan, “I have found a scroll of the Teaching in the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>”; and Hilkiah gave the scroll to Shaphan. <verse eid="2CH 34:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 34:16" />Shaphan brought the scroll to the king and also reported to the king, “All that was entrusted to your servants is being done; <verse eid="2CH 34:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 34:17" />they have melted down the silver that was found in the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> and delivered it to those who were in charge, to the overseers.” <verse eid="2CH 34:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 34:18" />The scribe Shaphan also told the king, “The priest Hilkiah has given me a scroll”; and Shaphan read from it to the king. <verse eid="2CH 34:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 34:19" />When the king heard the words of the Teaching, he tore his clothes. <verse eid="2CH 34:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 34:20" />The king gave orders to Hilkiah, and Ahikam son of Shaphan, and Abdon son of Micah, and the scribe Shaphan, and Asaiah the king's minister, saying, <verse eid="2CH 34:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 34:21" />“Go, inquire of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> on my behalf and on behalf of those who remain in Israel and Judah concerning the words of the scroll that has been found, for great indeed must be <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>'s wrath that has been poured down upon us because our ancestors did not obey the word of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> and do all that is written in this scroll.”<verse eid="2CH 34:21" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 34:22" />Hilkiah and those whom the king [had ordered] went to the prophetess Huldah, wife of Shallum son of Tokhath son of Hasrah, keeper of the wardrobe, who was living in Jerusalem in the Mishneh,<note caller="d" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">34.22 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">Mishneh </char><char style="ft" closed="false">A quarter in Jerusalem; cf. <char style="xt"><ref loc="ZEP 1:10">Zeph. 1.10</ref></char>.</char></note> and spoke to her accordingly. <verse eid="2CH 34:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="2CH 34:23" />She responded to them: “Thus said <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> God of Israel: Say to the one who sent you to Me, <verse eid="2CH 34:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="2CH 34:24" />‘Thus said <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>: I am going to bring disaster upon this place and its inhabitants—all the curses that are written in the scroll that was read to the king of Judah— <verse eid="2CH 34:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="2CH 34:25" />because they forsook Me and made offerings to other gods in order to vex Me with all the works of their hands; My wrath shall be poured out against this place and not be quenched.’ <verse eid="2CH 34:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="2CH 34:26" />But say this to the king of Judah who sent you to inquire of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>: ‘Thus said <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> God of Israel: As for the words that you have heard, <verse eid="2CH 34:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="2CH 34:27" />since your heart was softened and you humbled yourself before God when you heard My<note caller="e" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">34.27 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">My </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Heb. 3rd person.</char></note> words concerning this place and its inhabitants, and you humbled yourself before Me and tore your clothes and wept before Me, I for My part have listened, declares <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>. <verse eid="2CH 34:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="2CH 34:28" />Assuredly, I will gather you to your ancestors, and you will be laid in your grave in peace; your eyes shall see nothing of the disaster that I will bring upon this place and its inhabitants.’” They reported this back to the king.<verse eid="2CH 34:28" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="2CH 34:29" />Then the king sent word and assembled all the elders of Judah and Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 34:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="2CH 34:30" />The king went up to the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> with the entire citizenry of Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem and the priests and the Levites—all the people, young and old—and he read to them the entire text of the covenant scroll that was found in the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>. <verse eid="2CH 34:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="2CH 34:31" />The king stood in his place and solemnized the covenant before <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>: to follow <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> and to observe God's commandments, injunctions, and laws with all his heart and soul, to fulfill all the terms of the covenant written in this scroll. <verse eid="2CH 34:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="2CH 34:32" />He obligated all the people of Jerusalem and Benjamin who were present; and the inhabitants of Jerusalem acted in accord with the Covenant of God, God of their ancestors. <verse eid="2CH 34:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="2CH 34:33" />Josiah removed all the abominations from the whole territory of the Israelites and obliged all who were in Israel to worship <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> their God. Throughout his reign they did not deviate from following <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> God of their ancestors.<verse eid="2CH 34:33" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 34" />
  <chapter number="35" style="c" sid="2CH 35" />
  <para style="po">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 35:1" />
    <note caller="a" style="f">
      <char style="fr" closed="false">35.1–27 </char>
      <char style="ft" closed="false">Cf. <char style="xt"><ref loc="2KI 23:21-30">2 Kings 23.21–30</ref></char>.</char>
    </note>Josiah kept the Passover for <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> in Jerusalem; the passover sacrifice was slaughtered on the fourteenth day of the first month. <verse eid="2CH 35:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 35:2" />He reinstated the priests in their shifts and rallied them to the service of the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>. <verse eid="2CH 35:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 35:3" />He said to the Levites, consecrated to <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>, who taught all Israel, “Put the Holy Ark in the House that Solomon son of David, king of Israel, built; as you no longer carry it on your shoulders, see now to the service of <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> your God and Israel—God's people, <verse eid="2CH 35:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 35:4" />and dispose yourselves by clans according to your divisions, as prescribed in the writing of King David of Israel and in the document of his son Solomon, <verse eid="2CH 35:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 35:5" />and attend in the Sanctuary, by clan divisions, on your kindred, the people—by clan divisions of the Levites. <verse eid="2CH 35:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 35:6" />Having sanctified yourselves, slaughter the passover sacrifice and prepare it for your kindred, according to the word of God given by Moses.” <verse eid="2CH 35:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 35:7" />Josiah donated to the people small cattle—lambs and goats, all for passover sacrifices for all present—to the sum of 30,000, and large cattle, 3,000—these from the property of the king. <verse eid="2CH 35:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 35:8" />His officers gave a freewill offering to the people, to the priests, and to the Levites. Hilkiah and Zechariah and Jehiel, the chiefs of the House of God, donated to the priests for passover sacrifices 2,600 [small cattle] and 300 large cattle. <verse eid="2CH 35:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 35:9" />Conaniah, Shemaiah, and Nethanel, his brothers, and Hashabiah and Jeiel and Jozabad, officers of the Levites, donated 5,000 [small cattle] and 500 large cattle to the Levites for passover sacrifices.<verse eid="2CH 35:9" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 35:10" />The service was arranged well: the priests stood at their posts and the Levites in their divisions, by the king's command. <verse eid="2CH 35:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 35:11" />They slaughtered the passover sacrifice and the priests [received its blood] from them and dashed it, while the Levites flayed the animals. <verse eid="2CH 35:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 35:12" />They removed the parts to be burnt, distributing them to divisions of the people by clans, and making the sacrifices to <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>, as prescribed in the scroll of Moses; they did the same for the cattle. <verse eid="2CH 35:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 35:13" />They roasted the passover sacrifice in fire, as prescribed, while the sacred offerings they cooked in pots, cauldrons, and pans, and conveyed them with dispatch to all the people. <verse eid="2CH 35:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 35:14" />Afterward they provided for themselves and the priests, for the Aaronite priests were busy offering the burnt offerings and the fatty parts until nightfall, so the Levites provided both for themselves and for the Aaronite priests. <verse eid="2CH 35:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 35:15" />The Asaphite singers were at their stations, by command of David and Asaph and Heman and Jeduthun, the seer of the king; and the gatekeepers were at each and every gate. They did not have to leave their tasks, because their Levite brothers provided for them. <verse eid="2CH 35:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 35:16" />The entire service of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> was arranged well that day, to keep the Passover and to make the burnt offerings on the altar of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>, according to the command of King Josiah. <verse eid="2CH 35:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 35:17" />All the Israelites present kept the Passover at that time, and the Feast of Unleavened Bread for seven days. <verse eid="2CH 35:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 35:18" />Since the time of the prophet Samuel, no Passover like that one had ever been kept in Israel; none of the kings of Israel had kept a Passover like the one kept by Josiah and the priests and the Levites and all Judah and Israel there present and the inhabitants of Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 35:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 35:19" />That Passover was kept in the eighteenth year of the reign of Josiah.<verse eid="2CH 35:19" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 35:20" />After all this furbishing of the temple by Josiah, King Necho of Egypt came up to fight at Carchemish on the Euphrates, and Josiah went out against him. <verse eid="2CH 35:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 35:21" />[Necho] sent messengers to him, saying, “What have I to do with you, king of Judah? I do not march against you this day but against the kingdom that wars with me, and it is God's will that I hurry. Refrain, then, from interfering with God—who is with me—that you not be destroyed.” <verse eid="2CH 35:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 35:22" />But Josiah would not let him alone; instead, he donned [his armor]<note caller="b" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">35.22 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">he donned [his armor] </char><char style="ft" closed="false">With Targum.</char></note> to fight him, heedless of Necho's words from the mouth of God; and he came to fight in the plain of Megiddo. <verse eid="2CH 35:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="2CH 35:23" />Archers shot King Josiah, and the king said to his servants, “Get me away from here, for I am badly wounded.” <verse eid="2CH 35:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="2CH 35:24" />His servants carried him out of his chariot and put him in the wagon of his second-in-command, and conveyed him to Jerusalem. There he died, and was buried in the grave of his ancestors, and all Judah and Jerusalem went into mourning over Josiah. <verse eid="2CH 35:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="2CH 35:25" />Jeremiah composed laments for Josiah that all the singers, male and female, recited in their laments for Josiah, as is done to this day; they became customary in Israel and were incorporated into the laments. <verse eid="2CH 35:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="2CH 35:26" />The other events of Josiah's reign and his faithful deeds, in accord with the Teaching of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>, <verse eid="2CH 35:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="2CH 35:27" />and his acts, early and late, are recorded in the book of the kings of Israel and Judah.<verse eid="2CH 35:27" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 35" />
  <chapter number="36" style="c" sid="2CH 36" />
  <para style="po">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 36:1" />
    <note caller="a" style="f">
      <char style="fr" closed="false">36.1–13 </char>
      <char style="ft" closed="false">Cf. <char style="xt"><ref loc="2KI 23:28-37">2 Kings 23.28–37</ref>; <ref loc="2KI 24:1-20">24.1–20</ref></char>.</char>
    </note>The people of the land took Jehoahaz son of Josiah and made him king instead of his father in Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 36:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 36:2" />Jehoahaz was twenty-three years old when he became king and he reigned three months in Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 36:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 36:3" />The king of Egypt deposed him in Jerusalem and laid a fine on the land of 100 silver talents and one gold talent. <verse eid="2CH 36:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 36:4" />The king of Egypt made his brother Eliakim king over Judah and Jerusalem, and changed his name to Jehoiakim; Necho took his brother Joahaz and brought him to Egypt.<verse eid="2CH 36:4" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 36:5" />Jehoiakim was twenty-five years old when he became king, and he reigned eleven years in Jerusalem; he did what was displeasing to <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> his God. <verse eid="2CH 36:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 36:6" />King Nebuchadnezzar of Babylon marched against him; he bound him in fetters to convey him to Babylon. <verse eid="2CH 36:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 36:7" />Nebuchadnezzar also brought some vessels of the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> to Babylon, and set them in his palace in Babylon. <verse eid="2CH 36:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 36:8" />The other events of Jehoiakim's reign, and the abominable things he did, and what was found against him, are recorded in the book of the kings of Israel and Judah. His son Jehoiachin succeeded him as king.<verse eid="2CH 36:8" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 36:9" />Jehoiachin was eight years old when he became king, and he reigned three months and ten days in Jerusalem; he did what was displeasing to <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>. <verse eid="2CH 36:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 36:10" />At the turn of the year, King Nebuchadnezzar sent to have him brought to Babylon with the precious vessels of the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>, and he made his kinsman Zedekiah king over Judah and Jerusalem.<verse eid="2CH 36:10" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 36:11" />Zedekiah was twenty-one years old when he became king, and he reigned eleven years in Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 36:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 36:12" />He did what was displeasing to <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> his God; he did not humble himself before the prophet Jeremiah, who spoke for <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>. <verse eid="2CH 36:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 36:13" />He also rebelled against Nebuchadnezzar, who made him take an oath<note caller="b" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">36.13 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">an oath </char><char style="ft" closed="false">A vassal oath; cf. <char style="xt"><ref loc="EZK 17:11-21">Ezek. 17.11–21</ref></char>.</char></note> by God; he stiffened his neck and hardened his heart so as not to turn to <char style="nd">the <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> God of Israel. <verse eid="2CH 36:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 36:14" />All the officers of the priests and the people committed many trespasses, following all the abominable practices of the nations. They polluted the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> that had been consecrated in Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 36:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 36:15" /><char style="nd">The <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> God of their ancestors had sent word to them through messengers daily without fail, having taken pity on the people and on the temple.<note caller="c" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">36.15 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">the temple </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Lit. “His habitation.”</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 36:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 36:16" />But they mocked the messengers of God and disdained those words and taunted those prophets until <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char>'s wrath against this people grew beyond remedy. <verse eid="2CH 36:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 36:17" />[God] therefore brought the king of the Chaldeans upon them, who killed their youths by the sword in their sanctuary; neither youth nor maiden, elder, or graybeard were spared—all were delivered into his hands. <verse eid="2CH 36:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 36:18" />All the vessels of the House of God, large and small, and the treasures of the House of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> and the treasures of the king and his officers were all brought to Babylon. <verse eid="2CH 36:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 36:19" />They burned the House of God and tore down the wall of Jerusalem, burned down all its mansions, and consigned all its precious objects to destruction. <verse eid="2CH 36:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 36:20" />Those who survived the sword he exiled to Babylon, and they became his and his sons' servants till the rise of the Persian kingdom, <verse eid="2CH 36:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 36:21" />in fulfillment of the word of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> spoken by Jeremiah, until the land paid back its sabbaths; as long as it lay desolate it kept sabbath, till seventy years were completed.<verse eid="2CH 36:21" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 36:22" />And in the first year of King Cyrus of Persia, when the word of <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> spoken by Jeremiah was fulfilled, <char style="nd"><char style="sc">God</char></char> roused the spirit of King Cyrus of Persia to issue a proclamation throughout his realm by word of mouth and in writing, as follows: <verse eid="2CH 36:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="2CH 36:23" />“Thus said King Cyrus of Persia: <char style="nd">The <char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> God of Heaven has given me all the kingdoms of the earth, and has charged me with building a house [of God] in Jerusalem, which is in Judah. May the <char style="nd"><char style="sc">Eternal</char></char> God be with those of you among this people who wish to go up.”<verse eid="2CH 36:23" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 36" />
</usx>