<book>
<appendix>
<p><bold>[[1]] Who shall go up for us against the Canaanites?</bold> To the territories for which lots were cast<sup><xref rid="fn1">1</xref></sup> but are as yet unconquered.</p>
<p><bold>[[2]] Let Yehudah go up.</bold> Let the tribe of Yehudah go up first<sup><xref rid="fn2">2</xref></sup> to conquer their alloted territory.</p>
<p><bold>[[3]] To his brother Shimon.</bold> To the tribe of Shimon.</p>
<p><bold>Go up with me</bold> and assist me in conquering my alloted portion. Some interpret &#x201C;Let Yehudah go up&#x201D; as a reference to Asniel,<sup><xref rid="fn3">3</xref></sup> also known as Ya&#x2019;avetz;<sup><xref rid="fn4">4</xref></sup> for it is remarked, in tractate Temurah,<sup><xref rid="fn5">5</xref></sup> &#x201C;What was his name? His name was Yehudah, brother of Shimon.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn6">6</xref></sup> He<sup><xref rid="fn7">7</xref></sup> told his brother Shimon<sup><xref rid="fn8">8</xref></sup> to accompany him.</p>
<p><bold>[[4]] At Bezek.</bold> The name of a place.<sup><xref rid="fn9">9</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[7]] Seventy kings.</bold> From here we learn of the eminence and affluence of the Canaanite potentates, for Adoni-bezek was not worthy of being listed among the Canaanite monarchs<sup><xref rid="fn10">10</xref></sup> by the title &#x201C;king&#x201D;, yet this is written of him.<sup><xref rid="fn11">11</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>They brought him to Yerushalayim.</bold> They proceeded from there to do battle at Yerushalayim.</p>
<p><bold>[[8]] They set [literally &#x2018;sent&#x2019;] fire.</bold> They sent the fire<sup><xref rid="fn12">12</xref></sup> throughout it.</p>
<p><bold>[[13]] Coleiv&#x2019;s &#x2026;brother.</bold> Maternally.<sup><xref rid="fn13">13</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[14]] She cajoled him.</bold> She advised him, as in &#x201C;he took counsel&#x201D;;<sup><xref rid="fn14">14</xref></sup> one counsels a person, and directs his thinking to an alternative. This is my opinion.</p>
<p><bold>She lowered herself.</bold> &#x201C;She lowered herself&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn15">15</xref></sup> as if falling at her father&#x2019;s feet.</p>
<p><bold>[[15]] Arid land.</bold> A man barren of anything gainful, as he contains nothing but Torah.<sup><xref rid="fn16">16</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>Streams of water.</bold> Wetland, &#x201C;territory supplied abundantly with water.&#x201D;</p>
<p><bold>[[16]] From the city of dates.</bold> This refers to Yericho, as the fertile tract of Yericho<sup><xref rid="fn17">17</xref></sup> was given to them for their consumption until the Beis HaMikdosh would be built. The one in whose portion the Beis HaMikdosh would be built<sup><xref rid="fn18">18</xref></sup> would then receive it,<sup><xref rid="fn19">19</xref></sup> so that all of Yisroel could share in the Beis HaMikdosh. It was given to the descendants of Yisro for four hundred and forty years.<sup><xref rid="fn20">20</xref></sup> The scholars among them departed, and went to Asniel, the son of Kenaz, also known as Ya&#x2019;avetz, to the wilderness of Yehudah south of Arad to study Torah.<sup><xref rid="fn21">21</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>He settled with the people.</bold> With the disciples who sat before him. He requested of the Holy One, blessed is He, that He furnish him with suitable disciples, as it said, &#x201C;Ya&#x2019;avetz cried out to Elohim&#x2026;etc.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn22">22</xref></sup> He furnished him with these pious men.<sup><xref rid="fn23">23</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[19]] However, he could not oust.</bold> [Targum] Yonasan interprets: Afterward, as they had sinned, they could not oust the valley dwellers.</p>
<p><bold>[[21]] But the Yevusi dwellers of Yerushalayim.</bold> There was a section of Yerushalayim<sup><xref rid="fn24">24</xref></sup> entitled Yevusi. They were descendants of Avimelech,<sup><xref rid="fn25">25</xref></sup> and they could not oust them because of the oath&#x2014;until the arrival of Dovid<sup><xref rid="fn26">26</xref></sup>&#x2014;as his<sup><xref rid="fn27">27</xref></sup> grandson still lived, and he<sup><xref rid="fn28">28</xref></sup> had sworn to him, his son, and his grandson.</p>
<p><bold>[[22]] Beis El</bold> which was part of their ancestral allotment. Although Michah&#x2019;s idol<sup><xref rid="fn29">29</xref></sup> was in their possession&#x2014;for Michah was from the tribe of Ephraim&#x2014;it is said here, &#x201C;and Adonoy was with them.&#x201D; Concerning this, Daniel said, &#x201C;Yours, O Adonoy, is benevolence&#x2014;ours is the face of humiliation.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn30">30</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[23]] Sent spies.</bold> Through others, they sent spies.<sup><xref rid="fn31">31</xref></sup> &#x201C;They spied the land&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn32">32</xref></sup> is said concerning the spies themselves. However, concerning these who sent spies it is said, &#x201C;they sent spies.&#x201D;</p>
<p><bold>[[24]] The entrance to the city.</bold> It was entered through a cave. A hazelnut tree stood at the mouth of the cave, and they passed through the tree<sup><xref rid="fn33">33</xref></sup> into the cave.</p>
<p><bold>Luz.</bold> Small nuts grow on this. &#x201C;Coudre&#x201D; in old French.</p>
<p><bold>[[25]] He showed them</bold> with his finger.<sup><xref rid="fn34">34</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[26]] It is so entitled to this day.</bold> Sancheriv did not &#x201C;jumble&#x201D; it,<sup><xref rid="fn35">35</xref></sup> and Nevuchadnetzar did not devastate it.<sup><xref rid="fn36">36</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[27]] Menashe did not oust.</bold> Scripture censures them, as they began betraying the Holy One, blessed is He, Who commanded them: &#x201C;Oust all those dwelling in the land, etc.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn37">37</xref></sup></p>
<ftnote id="fn1"><sup>1</sup>By Yehoshua, Elazar, and the tribal chieftains (Yehoshua, 14:1,2). Chapters 14&#x2013;19 (there) list in detail the territories alloted to the various tribes when the lots were cast.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn2"><sup>2</sup>The tribesmen of Yehudah were first in many instances; they entered the water first at the splitting of the sea, their banner was the first to proceed when the Yisroelites journeyed in the wilderness, they went up first in the Book of Shoftim. Indeed, at the coming redemption, their tribesman Dovid will reign as the first of his countrymen. (Yalkut, 37:a. See Yalkut to Beshalach, 234)</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn3"><sup>3</sup>Asniel ben Kenaz, the first of the Shoftim to lead Yisroel after the death of Yehoshua. (Below, 3:9&#x2013;11)</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn4"><sup>4</sup>Ya&#x2019;avetz is listed among the tribesmen of Yehudah, and described as &#x201C;revered over his brethren.&#x201D; (Divrei Hayamim 1, 4:9)</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn5"><sup>5</sup>16:a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn6"><sup>6</sup>This was his true name. His surnames were Asniel and Ya&#x2019;avetz. Asniel is a contraction of &#x2018;anah El&#x2019;, &#x2018;Adonoy answered&#x2019; [Divrei Hayamim 1, 4:10, relates that Adonoy answered his prayer]. Ya&#x2019;avetz is a contraction of &#x2018;ya&#x2019;atz v&#x2019;herebetz&#x2019;, &#x2018;he counseled and disseminated [Torah]&#x2019;. (Temurah, 16:a)</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn7"><sup>7</sup>Not the tribe of Yehudah, but the individual Yehudah, otherwise known as Asniel or Ya&#x2019;avetz.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn8"><sup>8</sup>The individual Shimon, brother of Yehudah / Asniel. Accordingly, the inquiry &#x201C;Who shall go up first?&#x201D; [v.1] did not concern the tribe which would engage in battle first, but the individual who would lead the people into battle. Adonoy answered [v.2] that Yehudah, also known as Asniel or Ya&#x2019;avetz, would lead.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn9"><sup>9</sup>&#x2018;Bezek&#x2019; may also be translated as &#x2018;shard&#x2019;, meaning a broken piece of pottery. Here, however, the reference is to a place named &#x2018;Bezek&#x2019;. (Yoma, 22:b)</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn10"><sup>10</sup>Yehoshua 12: 7&#x2013;24 lists the thirty one Canaanite kings. Adoni bezek is not among them.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn11"><sup>11</sup>Yalkut, 37:a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn12"><sup>12</sup>By igniting it. This follows the literal meaning of <span dir="rtl">&#x05E9;&#x05C7;&#x05DC;&#x05B0;&#x05D7;&#xFB35;</span>, &#x2018;thy sent&#x2019;. (Metzudas Tzion) Afterward, the B&#x2019;nei Yehudah went down to wage war with the Canaanites dwelling in the hills, the Negev, and the lowlands.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn13"><sup>13</sup>Coleiv is referred to as &#x201C;the Kenizite&#x201D; (Yehoshua, 14:6), rather than &#x2018;son of Kenaz&#x2019;. This indicates that he was not Kenaz&#x2019; biological son, but his stepson. (Sotah, 11:b, 12:a).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn14"><sup>14</sup>Rather than &#x2018;she tempted him&#x2019;, as in Devarim, 13:7.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn15"><sup>15</sup>This is a quotation from Targum Yonasan.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn16"><sup>16</sup>Temurah, 16:a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn17"><sup>17</sup>An area outside the city, measuring five hundred <italic>amohs</italic> by five hundred <italic>amohs</italic>. (Yalkut, 38.)</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn18"><sup>18</sup>The tribe of Binyomin. (Ibid).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn19"><sup>19</sup>In return for the Beis Hamikdosh territory, which would become the property of all the tribes.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn20"><sup>20</sup>From the conquest of Eretz Yisroel by Yehoshua, until the construction of the Beis Hamikdosh by King Solomon. (See Melachim 1,6:1.)</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn21"><sup>21</sup>Yalkut, ibid.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn22"><sup>22</sup>&#x201C;&#x2026;of Yisroel, saying: If You bless me by broadening my boundary, and Your hand shall be with me&#x2026;&#x201D;. (Divrei Hayamim 1, 4:10. See fn.6)</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn23"><sup>23</sup>Yalkut, ibid.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn24"><sup>24</sup>The reference here is not to members of the Yevusite nation, as Rashi explains that they were descendants of the Pelishte king Avimelech. Cf.Rashi to Yehoshua, 16:63, and Shmuel 2, 5:6.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn25"><sup>25</sup>The Pelishite king (Bereishis, 21:32, 26:8). The patriarch Avrohom swore that he would deal kindly with him and his children and grandchildren. (Ibd, 21:23). Avrohom&#x2019;s descendants were obligated by the oath as well. Cf.Midrash Rabah, Bereishis, 54:2.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn26"><sup>26</sup>When Avimelech&#x2019;s grandchildren no longer survived. (Rashi to Shmueil 2, 5:8)</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn27"><sup>27</sup>Avimelech&#x2019;s grandson.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn28"><sup>28</sup>Avrohom had sworn.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn29"><sup>29</sup>Chapter 17, v.4 [below] relates that Michah of Mount Ephraim made a graven image and kept it at his home, where it was worshiped. Although the incident is not mentioned earlier in the text, Rashi asserts that the idol was already in existence during the conquest of Eretz Yisroel. See Rasi to 17:1.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn30"><sup>30</sup>Daniel, 9:7.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn31"><sup>31</sup>This is Targum Yonasan&#x2019;s translation.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn32"><sup>32</sup> Bamidbar, 13:21. This refers to the spies sent by Moshe in the wilderness.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn33"><sup>33</sup>The tree was hollow. They passed through the hollow section into the cave, then through the cave into the city. (Bereishis Rabah, 69:8)</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn34"><sup>34</sup>If this heathen, by the mere flick of a finger, saved himself and his progeny, then certainly one who actively escorts others. (Sotah, 46:b)</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn35"><sup>35</sup>Sancheriv &#x201C;jumbled&#x201D; all the nations of the world by transporting the inhabitants of one country to another. (Yadayim, 4:3, Yeshaya, 10:13). He did the same to the inhabitants of Eretz Yisroel (Melachim 2, 17:6, 23, 24) but not to the inhabitants of Luz.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn36"><sup>36</sup>Sotah, 46:b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn37"><sup>37</sup>Bemidbar, 33:52.</ftnote>
</appendix>
<appendix>
<p><bold>[[1]] Adonoy&#x2019;s emissary went up.</bold> We learn in Seder Olam that this was Pinchos.<sup><xref rid="fn38">1</xref>&#160;<xref rid="fn39">2</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>To Bochim.</bold> The name of a place.<sup><xref rid="fn40">3</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>I took you up.</bold> This was My original intent,<sup><xref rid="fn41">4</xref></sup> to take you up from Mitzrayim&#x2014;and I did so&#x2014;with the stipulation that My enemies be ousted.<sup><xref rid="fn42">5</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[3]] Now I have also declared.</bold> At present I have declared, in My fury.<sup><xref rid="fn43">6</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>At your flanks.</bold> They will harass your flanks with bandits and troops, pillaging and plundering.</p>
<p><bold>[[6]] Yehoshua dismissed, etc.</bold> This incident had taken place previously, but, as Scripture intends to relate that they acted wickedly [v.11], it begins with the following statement: at Yehoshua&#x2019;s death, when they resolved, in his presence, to serve Adonoy, he dismissed them, each man to his ancestral property. They served Adonoy throughout his days and the days of the elders. Afterward, &#x201C;The Bnei Yisroel acted wickedly.&#x201D;</p>
<p><bold>[[7]] Whose days extended.</bold> Their &#x2018;days&#x2019; extended<sup><xref rid="fn44">7</xref></sup> but not their &#x2018;years&#x2019;, as they neglected to eulogize him.<sup><xref rid="fn45">8</xref></sup> Thus it is said, &#x201C;&#x2026;of Mount Ga&#x2019;ash&#x201D;&#x2014;<sup><xref rid="fn46">9</xref></sup> the mountain stormed at them<sup><xref rid="fn47">10</xref></sup> to slaughter them.</p>
<p><bold>[[9]] At Timnas Cheres.</bold> So entitled because a likeness of the sun<sup><xref rid="fn48">11</xref></sup> was placed over his grave, as if to say, &#x201C;Alas, that a man who halted the sun<sup><xref rid="fn49">12</xref></sup> lies in the grave.&#x201D;</p>
<p><bold>[[15]] Wherever they went, the hand of Adonoy was destructive to them.</bold> This refers to Elimelech, Machlon, and Chilyon&#x2014;<sup><xref rid="fn50">13</xref></sup> Seder Olam.</p>
<p><bold>[[16]] Adonoy established judges.</bold> Continuously, in successive generations, as enumerated in this book, judge succeeding judge.</p>
<p><bold>[[18]] When He would establish</bold>&#x2014;This describes an ongoing process&#x2014;&#x2018;When He would establish judges for them, and Adonoy would visit with the judge, etc.&#x2019;</p>
<p><bold>For He would recant.</bold> He would recant, concerning them, from the destruction.<sup><xref rid="fn51">14</xref></sup> This is Yonasan&#x2019;s rendition.</p>
<p><bold>From the outcry</bold>&#x2014;As a result of their cry that went up to Him because of their tormentors</p>
<p><bold>[[19]] They fell nothing short.</bold> They omitted nothing deserving of the reproach inherent in everything that befell them.</p>
<p><bold>[[22]] Whether they observe.</bold> The letter <span dir="rtl">&#x05D4;</span> is vocalized with the abridged <italic>pasach</italic>,<sup><xref rid="fn52">15</xref></sup> as it expresses the inquiry involved in testing.</p>
<ftnote id="fn38"><sup>1</sup> Son of Elazar, grandson of Aharon Hakohen. (Bemidbar, 25:11.)</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn39"><sup>2</sup> Why is Pinchas entitled <span dir="rtl">&#x05DE;&#x05B7;&#x05DC;&#x05B0;&#xFB2E;&#x05DA;&#x05B0; &#x05D4;&#x05F3;</span>, lit. &#x201C;an angel of Adonoy&#x201D;? Because, when visited by the sacred spirit, he was enflamed with radiance. (Vayikra Rabah, A. See Rashi to Yehoshua, 2:4).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn40"><sup>3</sup>Not literally &#x201C;weeping&#x201D;. See vs.4,5.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn41"><sup>4</sup>The future tense, <span dir="rtl">&#xFB2E;&#x05E2;&#x05B2;&#x05DC;&#x05B6;&#x05D4;</span>, literally &#x201C;I shall take&#x201D;, indicates the intent which preceded the actual taking. See Rashi to Shemos, 15:1.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn42"><sup>5</sup> As indicated by the warning against covenants [v.2].</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn43"><sup>6</sup>This is not part of the original intent stated in vs.1,2, but is a new declaration, made now because they sinned.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn44"><sup>7</sup>In contentment. However, their lives were short. (Shabbos, 105:b.-See Rashi there).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn45"><sup>8</sup>Scripture omits any mention of a mourning period for Yehoshua, as with Aharon (Bemidbar 20:29) and Moshe (Devarim 34:8). This indicates that they were remiss in eulogizing him and mourning for him. (Tosafos to Shabbos, 105:b).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn46"><sup>9</sup>&#x201C;They buried him (Yehoshua)&#x2026;at Mount Ephraim, north of Ga&#x2019;ash.&#x201D; [v.9] Mount Ephraim was better known than G&#x2019;ash. Why, then, does Scripture identify the famous Mountain by its proximity to the obscure Ga&#x2019;ash? Evidently, &#x201C;Ga&#x2019;ash&#x201D; is not an identifying landmark, but is intended as a homiletical allusion to &#x201C;ra&#x2019;ash&#x201D;, &#x201C;storm&#x201D;, teaching that the mountain stormed against them. (Maharsha to Shabbos, ibid.).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn47"><sup>10</sup>Shabbos, ibid.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn48"><sup>11</sup>&#x2018;Timnas Serach&#x2019; is literally translated as &#x2018;The likeness of the sun&#x2019;.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn49"><sup>12</sup>Yehoshua ordered the sun to stand still, and the sun obeyed. (Yehoshua, 10:12,13.)</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn50"><sup>13</sup>Naomi&#x2019;s husband and two sons, mentioned in the opening passages of the Book of Rus. They were punished with poverty and then death. See Rashi to Megilas Rus, ch.1.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn51"><sup>14</sup>Which He had intended to rain upon them. Accordingly, <span dir="rtl">&#x05D9;&#x05B0;&#x05E0;&#x05B7;&#x05D7;&#x05B5;&#x05DD;</span> is not understood as &#x2018;would find comfort,&#x2019; but as &#x2018;would recant.&#x2019; See Rashi to Bereishis, 6:6, second interpretation.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn52"><sup>15</sup>This vocalization is used to express inquiry.</ftnote>
</appendix>
<appendix>
<p><bold>[[1]] So that Yisroel would be tested through them.</bold> This was a different generation, ignorant of the miracles of the Canaanite wars, and not having witnessed the great deeds, they rebelled, and betrayed the Omnipresent.</p>
<p><bold>[[2]] Only so that they should know.</bold> For this alone, He permitted these nations to remain, so that future generations of the Bnei Yisroel might grasp the consequence of iniquity&#x2014;for it was now necessary for them to undergo martial training.</p>
<p><bold>Whereas earlier</bold> when they stood worshiping Adonoy.</p>
<p><bold>This was unknown.</bold> These wars and the art of battle. It was unnecessary.</p>
<p><bold>[[3]] Five Pelishtite sovereignties.</bold> These were the nations whom He permited to remain as a test.</p>
<p><bold>[[10]] The Divine spirit visited him.</bold> R&#x2019; Tanchuma expounded: He studied the statement of the Holy One, blessed is He, to Moshe in Mitzrayim, &#x201C;I have surely seen (lit. &#x2018;seeing, I have seen&#x2019;) the tribulation of my people.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn53">1</xref></sup> What are the two sights?<sup><xref rid="fn54">2</xref></sup> He said to him, &#x201C;I see that they are destined to err with the golden calf&#x2014;nevertheless, &#x2018;I have seen the tribulation of my people.&#x2019;&#x201D; Asniel expounded upon this, saying, whether innocent or guilty, He is obliged to save them.<sup><xref rid="fn55">3</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[13]] The city of dates.</bold> Yericho.</p>
<p><bold>[[15]] Whose right arm was immobile.</bold> Yonasan renders &#x201C;A man whose right arm was shrunken.&#x201D; &#x201C;Gamid&#x201D; in the Aramaic always indicates something shrunken by disease, &#x201C;retrait&#x201D;, &#x201C;shrunk&#x201D; in old French. He could not utilize his right arm. In Hebrew, &#x201C;closed&#x201D;, as in &#x201C;Let not the well close its mouth over me.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn56">4</xref></sup> His right arm was &#x201C;closed&#x201D;&#x2014;he could not utilize it.</p>
<p><bold>[[16]] One <italic>gomed</italic> long.</bold> An abridged amoh.<sup><xref rid="fn57">5</xref></sup> In German, &#x2018;daumen lang&#x2019;. In old French, &#x2018;espan courte&#x2019;.</p>
<p><bold>Over his right thigh.</bold> Since he was able to utilize his left hand, he would grasp it with the left hand.</p>
<p><bold>[[17]] Obese.</bold> Fat.</p>
<p><bold>[[18]] He escorted the people.</bold> He turned back to accompany the delegation of Yisroelites who came with him to bear the gift. He escorted them until Gilgal.</p>
<p><bold>He then returned</bold> alone.</p>
<p><bold>From the quarries.</bold> An area where stones were excavated from the mountain. Similarly, Yonasan renders &#x201C;from the quarries.&#x201D; Then he went to Eglon,<sup><xref rid="fn58">6</xref></sup> and declared to him.<sup><xref rid="fn59">7</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>He said, &#x201C;Hsst.&#x201D;</bold> Eglon said, &#x201C;Silence everyone near me&#x0021;&#x201D; Yonasan renders, &#x201C;Leave&#x0021;&#x201D;&#x2014;remove everyone. Still, the term connotes silence.<sup><xref rid="fn60">8</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[20]] In his penthouse veranda.</bold> In the summer penthouse which was airy and cool.</p>
<p><bold>I have a Divine message for you&#x0021;</bold> Thus, you are required to rise.</p>
<p><bold>He rose from the throne.</bold> He therefore merited that Rus was descended from him.</p>
<p><bold>[[22]] The hilt.</bold> The iron into which the blade is inserted, called &#x2018;hulot&#x2019; in old French. This balances the sword in its scabbard.</p>
<p><bold>The blade.</bold> The sharpened section, called &#x201C;brant&#x201D; and &#x201C;lama&#x201D; in old French.</p>
<p><bold>The fat closed.</bold> His fat. He was extremely corpulent, so that he enclosed the entire length of the dagger.</p>
<p><bold>Waste matter oozed.</bold> Yonasan renders, &#x201C;Spilled waste matter oozed.&#x201D; He reads this as a contraction of two words with the &#x2018;shin&#x2019; serving both.<sup><xref rid="fn61">9</xref></sup> &#x201C;spilled waste matter&#x201D; [oozed].<sup><xref rid="fn62">10</xref></sup>&#160;<span dir="rtl">&#xFB2A;&#x05B0;&#x05E4;&#x05B7;&#x05DA;&#x05B0;</span>, &#x201C;spilled&#x201D;, is the translation of <span dir="ltr">&#xFB2A;&#x05B0;&#x05D3;&#x05B8;&#x05D0;</span><sup><xref rid="fn63">11</xref></sup> according to Yonasan.</p>
<p><bold>[[23]] And Ehud went out to the hallway.</bold> From the penthouse to the <span dir="rtl">&#x05DE;&#x05E1;&#x05D3;&#x05E8;&#x05D5;&#x05E0;&#x05D4;</span>, translated by Targum Yonasan as &#x2018;hallway&#x2019;.</p>
<p><bold>And locked</bold> With the key.</p>
<p><bold>[[24]] As he left.</bold> Ehud left, and Eglon&#x2019;s servants came.</p>
<p><bold>Relieving himself [lit. &#x2018;covering his legs&#x2019;].</bold> Performing his necessary bodily functions. This refers to a bowel movement.<sup><xref rid="fn64">12</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[25]] A considerable time.</bold> [lit.] Until [it constituted] delay, as if to say, a considerable time.</p>
<p><bold>[[26]] Escaped.</bold> Fled, &#x201C;eschamocier&#x201D; in old French.</p>
<p><bold>While [lit. until] they tarried.</bold> As in,<sup><xref rid="fn65">13</xref></sup> &#x201C;While the king lounged,&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn66">14</xref></sup> &#x201C;Affection, while still desired&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn67">15</xref></sup>&#x2014;while we both desire it.</p>
<p><bold>In the underbrush.</bold> A thin-branched, heavily wooded forest, called &#x201C;brousaille&#x201D;, brush, in old French, excellent for concealment. Frequently, in the order of Zeraim, thin branches are called &#x201C;sa&#x2019;ar&#x201D;&#x2014;&#x201C;[He] overturned the branches,&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn68">16</xref></sup> &#x201C;If the branches meshed.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn69">17</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[27]] It happened that, when he arrived.</bold> He crossed the Yardein, and arrived at his place in the land of Canaan.<sup><xref rid="fn70">18</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>At Mount Ephrayim.</bold> Which was in the land of Canaan, on the western side of the Yardein. The land of Moav was on the eastern side of the Yardein, but as they had subdued Yisroel and crossed the Yardein, they occupied Yericho as stated above, and installed their princes and governors over Yisroel.</p>
<p><bold>[[28]] Charge behind me</bold> to wipe out all the Moabites on our side of the Yardein.</p>
<p><bold>Took control of the Yardein passes</bold> so that the Moabites could not cross to escape and return to their country.</p>
<p><bold>[[29]] All horrific [lit. corpulent].</bold> Every man awe inspiring.</p>
<p><bold>[[31]] With a goad.</bold> A saddle spur, &#x201C;aiguillon&#x201D; in old French.</p>
<ftnote id="fn53"><sup>1</sup> Shemos, 3:7.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn54"><sup>2</sup>&#x2018;Seeing&#x2019; I have &#x2018;seen&#x2019;.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn55"><sup>3</sup>Shemos Rabah, 3:2. Accordingly, &#x201C;He judged Yisroel&#x201D; in our passage does not refer to Asniel&#x2019;s adjudication of litigation in the courtroom, but to his exposition of &#x201C;I have seen&#x201D; in his prayer before Adonoy. In his &#x201C;judgement&#x201D;, Yisroel was to be saved. (Radal there, 5)</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn56"><sup>4</sup>Tehilim, 69:16.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn57"><sup>5</sup>The length of the forearm. (Rashbam to Bava Basra, 100:a).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn58"><sup>6</sup>Ehud&#x2019;s return to Eglon is not actually discussed in the text. Rashi mentions the return for the sake of clarification.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn59"><sup>7</sup>&#x201C;&#x2026;I have a matter, etc.&#x201D;.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn60"><sup>8</sup>Silence them by removing them.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn61"><sup>9</sup>&#160;<span dir="rtl">&#xFB44;&#x05B7;&#x05E8;&#x05B0;&#xFB2A;&#x05B0;&#x05D3;&#x05B9;&#x05BD;&#x05E0;&#x05C7;&#x05D4;</span> is read as <span dir="rtl">&#xFB44;&#x05B6;&#x05E8;&#x05B6;&#xFB2A;&#x05BE;&#xFB2A;&#x05B0;&#x05D3;&#xFB4B;&#x05E0;&#x05C7;&#x05D0;</span>, &#x201C;spilled waste matter&#x201D;, with the middle <span dir="rtl">&#x05E9;</span> serving as the last letter of <span dir="rtl">&#xFB44;&#x05B6;&#x05E8;&#x05B6;&#xFB2A;</span> and the first letter of <span dir="rtl">&#xFB2A;&#x05B0;&#x05D3;&#xFB4B;&#x05E0;&#x05C7;&#x05D0;</span>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn62"><sup>10</sup>The waste matter first spilled from the abdomen into the body, then it oozed from the wound. (Ralbag).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn63"><sup>11</sup>Or <span dir="rtl">&#xFB2A;&#x05B0;&#x05D3;&#xFB4B;&#x05E0;&#x05C7;&#x05D0;</span>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn64"><sup>12</sup>When the legs are covered as a matter of modesty. (Metzudas).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn65"><sup>13</sup>Rashi cites these quotations to demonstrate that <span dir="rtl">&#x05E2;&#x05B7;&#x05D3;</span>, lit. &#x201C;until&#x201D;, may be translated as while&#x201D;.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn66"><sup>14</sup>Shir Hashirim, 1:12.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn67"><sup>15</sup>Ibid, 2:7.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn68"><sup>16</sup>Kilayim, 4:9.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn69"><sup>17</sup>Peah, 2:3.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn70"><sup>18</sup>The text omits Ehud&#x2019;s crossing of the Yardein andhis arrival in Canaan. Rashi mentions these events for clarification.</ftnote>
</appendix>
<appendix>
<p><bold>[[2]] Charoshes Hogoyim.</bold> The name of a city, so entitled because it was a stronghold, and the seat of authority.<sup><xref rid="fn71">1</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[3]] Oppressed the Bnei Yisroel intensely.</bold> R&#x2019; Tanchuma expounded, through ridicule. Similarly, it is said, &#x201C;Your remarks offend me intensely.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn72">2</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[4]] The wife of Lapidos.</bold> She fashioned wicks for the sanctuary.<sup><xref rid="fn73">3</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[5]] Under [Devorah&#x2019;s] date tree.</bold> She owned date trees in Yericho.</p>
<p><bold>Between Ramah and Beis El, on Mount Ephrayim.</bold> From Yonasan&#x2019;s translation<sup><xref rid="fn74">4</xref></sup> we infer that this passage is not meant literally&#x2014;that these are not intended to identify her dwelling place. Rather, we learn that she was an affluent woman, with financial interests in these places. She lived in a city named Ataros.</p>
<p><bold>Under [Devorah&#x2019;s] date tree.</bold> She owned date trees in Yericho, vineyards in Rama, olive trees in the Bethel plateau, a fertile area, and white soil in Mount Ephrayim, at Tur Malka. In my opinion, this was sold for ceramic use. Some interpret &#x201C;white soil&#x201D; as grain fields, as in &#x201C;the grain [lit. &#x201C;white&#x201D;] field.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn75">5</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[6]] Has not&#x2026;.commanded?</bold> Through Moshe, &#x201C;For you shall totally annihilate them.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn76">6</xref></sup> Mechilta teaches this.<sup><xref rid="fn77">7</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[10]] At his heels.</bold> With him.</p>
<p><bold>[[11]] Elon Betza&#x2019;anayim.</bold> The marshland plain.<sup><xref rid="fn78">8</xref></sup> A plateau area with marshes, &#x201C;mariscum&#x201D;, &#x201C;morass&#x201D; in old French. This is called <span dir="rtl">&#x05D0;&#x05B7;&#x05D2;&#x05B8;&#x05E0;&#x05B7;&#x05D9;&#x05B8;&#x05D0;</span>&#x2014;pools, similar to ditches where water settles, &#x201C;entitled &#x2018;the earth&#x2019;s flasks.&#x2019;&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn79">9</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[13]] From Charoshes Hagoyim to Kishon stream.</bold> He mobilized them to proceed to the stream of Kishon from Charoshes Hagoyim where he was stationed.</p>
<p><bold>[[18]] With a cloak.</bold> Yonasan renders <span dir="rtl">&#x05D2;&#xFB4B;&#x05E0;&#x05B0;&#x05DB;&#x05C7;&#x05D0;</span>. R&#x2019; Hai translates <span dir="rtl">&#x05D2;&#xFB4B;&#x05E0;&#x05B0;&#x05DB;&#x05C7;&#x05D0;</span> as cloak, &#x201C;Coate&#x201D; in old French.</p>
<p><bold>[[19]] The milk pouch.</bold> Since milk induces drowsiness, then slumber.<sup><xref rid="fn80">10</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[20]] Stand at the entrance to the tent.</bold> Be zealous about it. Some interpret <span dir="rtl">&#x05E2;&#x05B2;&#x05DE;&#x05B9;&#x05D3;</span> [lit. &#x201C;stand&#x201D;] as <span dir="rtl">&#x05DC;&#x05B7;&#x05E2;&#x05B2;&#x05DE;&#xFB4B;&#x05D3;</span>, &#x201C;to stand&#x201D;.<sup><xref rid="fn81">11</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[21]] A tent peg.</bold> &#x201C;Chevilles&#x201D; in old French. This is embedded in the ground with the lower flap of the tent in order to extend it fully.</p>
<p><bold>A hammer.</bold> Hammer, &#x201C;martel&#x201D; in old French.</p>
<p><bold>Furtively.</bold> Stealthily, in secret.</p>
<p><bold>And impaled it into the ground.</bold>&#160;<span dir="ltr">&#xFB35;&#x05E0;&#x05B0;&#x05E2;&#x05B7;&#x05E6;&#x05B7;&#xFB4A;&#x05B0; &#xFB31;&#x05B0;&#xFB2E;&#x05E8;&#x05B0;&#x05E2;&#x05B8;&#x05D0;</span>,<sup><xref rid="fn82">12</xref></sup> and impaled it into the ground.</p>
<p><bold>[[22]] In his forehead.</bold>&#160;<span dir="rtl">&#xFB31;&#x05B0;&#x05E6;&#x05B4;&#x05D9;&#x05D3;&#x05BD;&#x05E2;&#x05B5;&#x05D9;&#x05D4;</span>, &#x201C;tenplia&#x201D; in old French. She had penetrated his forehead and the ground.</p>
<ftnote id="fn71"><sup>1</sup>This is based on Targum Yonasan, who translates <span dir="rtl">&#x05D7;&#x05B2;&#x05E8;&#x05B9;&#xFB2A;&#x05B6;&#x05EA; &#x05D4;&#x05B7;&#xFB32;&#xFB4B;&#x05D9;&#x05C5;&#x05DD;</span> as &#x201C;the stronghold, metropolis of nations&#x201D;.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn72"><sup>2</sup>Malachi, 3:13. Vs. 14, 15 there define the offensive remarks as ridicule of the worship of Adonoy.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn73"><sup>3</sup>Megilah, 14:a. <span dir="rtl">&#x05DC;&#x05B7;&#xFB44;&#x05C5;&#x05D9;&#x05D3;</span> is translated as &#x201C;torch&#x201D;.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn74"><sup>4</sup>Targum Yonasan renders, &#x201C;She lived in the city of Ataros. Devorah was financially independent. She owned date trees in Yericho, orchards in Ramah, oil producing olive trees in the wetlands of the Beis Eil plateau, white soil in Tur Malka.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn75"><sup>5</sup>The Talmud [Moed Katan, 6:b, etc.] refers to the grain field as <span dir="rtl">&#xFB2B;&#x05BD;&#x05D3;&#x05B5;&#x05D4; &#x05DC;&#x05C7;&#x05DB;&#x05C7;&#x05DF;</span>, literally &#x201C;white field.&#x201D; Rashi [Pe&#x2019;ah, 3:1] explains that this is because grain whitens when ripe for harvesting. Or, to distinguish between the grain field, which is subject to the sun&#x2019;s white glare, and the orchard, which is darkened by the shade of the trees.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn76"><sup>6</sup>Devarim, 20:17</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn77"><sup>7</sup>Yalkut, 4:43.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn78"><sup>8</sup>This is Targum Yonasan&#x2019;s rendition.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn79"><sup>9</sup>Kiddushin, 61:a, notes that water filed ditches are entitled <span dir="rtl">&#x05D0;&#x05B7;&#xFB32;&#x05C7;&#x05E0;&#x05B5;&#x05D9; &#xFB33;&#x05BD;&#x05D0;&#x05B7;&#x05E8;&#x05B0;&#x05E2;&#x05B8;&#x05D0;</span>, &#x201C;the earth&#x2019;s flasks.&#x201D; Thus, <span dir="rtl">&#x05D0;&#x05B7;&#x05D2;&#x05B8;&#x05E0;&#x05B7;&#x05D9;&#x05C7;&#x05D0;</span>, &#x201C;flasks,&#x201D; refer to the marshland pools.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn80"><sup>10</sup>He requested water. Why did she give him milk? To make him drowsy.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn81"><sup>11</sup>This interpretation adds the <span dir="rtl">&#x05DC;</span>, which does not actually appear in the text, so that the reading is &#x201C;He told her to stand at the entrance.&#x201D; According to the literal textual interpretation, the reading is, &#x201C;He told her, stand at the entrance.&#x201D; This is problematic, as the masculine <span dir="rtl">&#x05E2;&#x05B2;&#x05DE;&#xFB4B;&#x05D3;</span>, rather than <span dir="rtl">&#x05E2;&#x05B4;&#x05DE;&#x05BD;&#x05D3;&#x05B4;&#x05D9;</span>, is inappropriate in addressing a woman. The additional <span dir="rtl">&#x05DC;</span> solves this difficulty by transforming the command, <span dir="rtl">&#x05E2;&#x05B2;&#x05DE;&#xFB4B;&#x05D3;</span>, &#x201C;stand&#x201D;, into the infinitive <span dir="rtl">&#x05DC;&#x05B7;&#x05E2;&#x05B2;&#x05DE;&#xFB4B;&#x05D3;</span>, &#x201C;to stand.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn82"><sup>12</sup>This is Targum Yonasan&#x2019;s rendition.</ftnote>
</appendix>
<appendix>
<p><bold>[[2]] When Yisroel was inundated with breaches.</bold> When breaches befell Yisroel; when their enemies invaded them because they deserted Adonoy, and yet the people volunteered to repent&#x2014;at this point, bless Adonoy for bringing deliverance.</p>
<p><bold>[[3]] I&#x2026;I.</bold> The word is doubled. I have heard in the name of Midrash Agaddah: the Holy One blessed is He did not deny a reward for [Mount] Tovor and [Mount] Carmel, who came to the giving of Torah so that it might be given on them, and turned away in humiliation. The Holy One, blessed is He told them, &#x201C;Eventually, I shall reward you doubly. At Sinai it is said, &#x2018;I am the Lord your God;&#x2019;<sup><xref rid="fn83">1</xref></sup> at Tovor it shall be said, &#x2018;I&#x2026;I.&#x2019;<sup><xref rid="fn84">2</xref></sup> At Sinai it is said, &#x2018;I am the Lord your God;&#x2019; At Carmel it shall be said doubly, &#x2018;Adonoy is God,&#x2019; &#x2018;Adonoy is God&#x0021;&#x2019;<sup><xref rid="fn85">3</xref></sup> in Eliyahu&#x2019;s days.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn86">4</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[4]] Adonoy, when You went forth from Seir,</bold> This refers to the giving of Torah, as it is said, &#x201C;&#x2026;and shone forth from Seir to them.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn87">5</xref></sup> Why is this relevant here? This is what Devorah said: &#x201C;The Torah is severe when forsaken, but rewarding when adhered to, as it was given in awesomeness and power.<sup><xref rid="fn88">6</xref></sup> Thus, the Yisroelites were handed over to their enemies for forsaking it; and, when they offered to engross themselves in it, they were saved.&#x201D; All this we learn from Targum Yonasan&#x2019;s rendition.<sup><xref rid="fn89">7</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>Dripped.</bold> They dripped dew of revival.<sup><xref rid="fn90">8</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[5]] Mountains streamed.</bold> Like streaming water&#x2014;they dissolved.</p>
<p><bold>This Sinai&#x2026;.</bold> Scripture has already recounted the visions there&#x2014;covered by mist, thunder, flashes of light, flame.<sup><xref rid="fn91">9</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>Because of the presence of Adonoy</bold> This is an shortened passage: &#x201C;This Sinai&#x2014;what took place there occured because the mountain was visited by Adonoy.&#x201D;</p>
<p><bold>[[6]] In the days of Shamgar ben Anas, in the days of Yael.</bold> This teaches that Yael, too, judged Yisroel in her days.</p>
<p><bold>Thoroughfares came to a halt.</bold> The Yisroelites were afraid to undertake normal travel, because of their enemies. They would proceed along round about pathways, clandestinely.</p>
<p><bold>[[7]] Exposure was discontinued.</bold> Exposed, unwalled cities were discontinued as dwelling places, because of the enemies, and they flocked to the fortified cities.</p>
<p><bold>Until I rose.</bold> This<sup><xref rid="fn92">10</xref></sup> is the same as <span dir="rtl">&#xFB2A;&#x05B6;&#x05E7;&#x05B7;&#x05DE;&#x05B0;&#xFB4A;&#x05B4;&#x05D9;</span> Similarly, &#x2018;That you are speaking to me&#x2019;</p>
<p><bold>[[8]] When they chose new gods&#x2014;there was war in the cities.</bold> When the Yisroelites preferred modern Deities, then they needed to engage in battle in their cities. But, take note, now, when they volunteered, was a shield or battle ax in sight among the Yisroelites when they needed to do battle with the forty thousand field marshals the idolators flung against them? The Omnipresent overwhelmed them all with celestial warfare, and the Kishon stream swept them away.</p>
<p><bold>Cities.</bold> As in, &#x201C;If there should be found in your midst, in one of your cities&#x201D;.<sup><xref rid="fn93">11</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[9]] My heart.</bold> I, Devorah, [my heart is out] to the legislators of Yisroel&#x2014;with affection for the sages of Yisroel who volunteered, among the people, saying, &#x201C;Bless Adonoy, return to Him&#x201D;.</p>
<p><bold>[[10]] Riders of white donkeys.</bold> Merchants and gentry who may now ride elegant, white donkeys without intimidation or concern about their enemies. And jurists&#x2014;this refers to the magistrates who were afraid to deliver judgement publicly, as Targum Yonasan&#x2019;s translates, &#x201C;Those who assembled to sit in judgement&#x201D;. And wayfarers on foot. Speak up&#x0021; Recount this salvation, when, in place of the clamor of the formations battling you&#x2014;marauders, thieves, tax processors, who station themselves in battle formations organized to waylay those crossing to watering places&#x2014;there, the donkey riders and wayfarers will retell Adonoy&#x2019;s charity. What is this charity? The charity of His restoration of exposure in Yisroel, when He brought tranquility to Yisroel, allowing them to dwell in exposed cities, and to venture forth when dipersed,<sup><xref rid="fn94">12</xref></sup> singly, without grouping together. Then, they went down to the cities, returning to the cities they had inhabited when they fled to congregate in the fortified cities.</p>
<p><bold>[[11]] Battle formations.</bold> Menachen interprets &#x201C;strategists, military tactitians.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn95">13</xref></sup> He relates this to &#x201C;The locust has no king, yet he advances entirely &#x2018;in formation&#x2019;.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn96">14</xref></sup> The meaning is &#x2018;battle formations.&#x201D; Another interpretation,<sup><xref rid="fn97">15</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>Concerning the clatter of pebbles amidst the watering places.</bold> When you would walk amidst the watering places to draw water, you were terrified by the clatter of the pebbles smoothed by the stream, &#x201C;cailloux&#x201D; in old French. When stepped on, they emit a noise, and you were afraid that your presence would be sensed by your enemies. Now, however, such fears are baseless, and this is why you are commanded to offer thanks to His Name.</p>
<p><bold>Pebbles.</bold> This refers to pebbles smoothed by a stream, as in &#x201C;He ground with pebbles.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn98">16</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[12]] Awaken, awaken.</bold> The inference is, &#x201C;awaken to praise,&#x201D; as plainly indicated. &#x201C;Intensify your singing.&#x201D; However, the Rabbis remark,<sup><xref rid="fn99">17</xref></sup> because she was self lauditory and said, &#x201C;Until I rose, Devorah,&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn100">18</xref></sup> the Divine spirit departed from her.<sup><xref rid="fn101">19</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[13]] Dominated.</bold>&#160;<span dir="rtl">&#x05D9;&#x05B0;&#x05E8;&#x05B7;&#x05D3;</span> is similar to <span dir="rtl">&#x05D9;&#x05B4;&#x05E8;&#x05B0;&#x05D3;&#x05B6;&#x05D4;</span>, &#x201C;dominated,&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn102">20</xref></sup> as in &#x201C;to prostrate nations before him.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn103">21</xref></sup> The surviving Yisroelites dominated the mighty among the idolators.</p>
<p><bold>Adonoy empowered me over the mighty.</bold> Gave me dominion<sup><xref rid="fn104">22</xref></sup> over the mighty warriors among the nations.</p>
<p><bold>[[14]] In Ephraim.</bold> From Ephraim emerged the root of Yehoshua bin Nun&#x2019;s dominance over Amaleik<sup><xref rid="fn105">23</xref></sup> when he debilitated them with the sword.<sup><xref rid="fn106">24</xref></sup> This passage is related to the preceding one, as it explains &#x201C;Adonoy empowered me over the mighty&#x201D; by establishing Yehoshua&#x2019;s dominance over Amaleik.</p>
<p><bold>Your successor</bold> shall arise from the tribe of Binyomin.<sup><xref rid="fn107">25</xref></sup> Shaul ben Kish, who will batter them<sup><xref rid="fn108">26</xref></sup> and extinguish them like flickering embers. Another interpretation: &#x201C;with your people,<sup><xref rid="fn109">27</xref></sup> referring to the army of two hundred thousand infantrymen which Shaul mobilized against them.<sup><xref rid="fn110">28</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>From Mochir descended warlords.</bold> Great lords who vanquished the Emorites. They captured sixty cities&#x2014;the entire imperial zone conquered by Yair.<sup><xref rid="fn111">29</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[15]] Yesochar&#x2019;s nobles.</bold> The noblemen of Yesochar. This refers to members of the Sanhedrin who were engrossed in Torah study, and who knew and understood the times.<sup><xref rid="fn112">30</xref></sup> They constantly accompanied Devorah, teaching the Yisroelites the laws and precepts.</p>
<p><bold>Yesochar&#x2019;s nobles.</bold> The &#x201C;<span dir="rtl">&#x05D9;</span>&#x201D; in <span dir="rtl">&#xFB2B;&#x05C7;&#x05E8;&#x05B7;&#x05D9;</span> [lit. &#x201C;my&#x201D; nobles] is ancillary, fulfilling no grammatic function. It is similar to the &#x201C;<span dir="rtl">&#x05D9;</span>&#x201D; in &#x201C;the animals in the field,&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn113">31</xref></sup> or &#x201C;he cut open, for himself, a window.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn114">32</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>Yesochar with Barak.</bold> The remainder of Yesochar&#x2019;s constituency were likewise at Barak&#x2019;s disposal whenever he issued orders.</p>
<p><bold>Dispatched to the valley at his heels.</bold> He dispatched them on all of his missions&#x2014;to mobilize the people, and for all military needs.</p>
<p><bold>However, in Reuven&#x2019;s equivocation.</bold> However, in Reuven&#x2019;s ambiguity was great cunning. &#x201C;Craftiness of heart,&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn115">33</xref></sup> cunning. In what way was he cunning? He straddled the battle lines to learn who would emerge the victor so that he could join them.</p>
<p><bold>[[16]] The shrieking companies.</bold> Listening to the sounds emitted by the companies engaged in battle, to determine which was the cry of triumph, and which the cry of defeat.</p>
<p><bold>[[17]] Is ensconced beyond the Yardein</bold> and never arrived at the battle front. Similarly, Dan hoarded his money into sea vessels, poised to escape.</p>
<p><bold>At his exposures.</bold> To defend his exposed territory.</p>
<p><bold>[[18]] Zevulun; a people who disdained, etc.</bold> They were contemptuous of their lives, and subjected themselves to death in battle with Barak. Likewise, Naftoli at the highland field on Mount Tovor.</p>
<p><bold>[[19]] At Ta&#x2019;anach to the waters of Megiddo.</bold> Targum Yonasan renders, &#x201C;They were encamped at Ta&#x2019;anach, and reached the waters of Megiddo.&#x201D; The upper section of the camp was at Ta&#x2019;anach, and it extended to the waters of Megiddo.</p>
<p><bold>Deigning no mercenary reward.</bold> They came to Sisera&#x2019;s assistance gratuitously&#x2014;without requesting payment.</p>
<p><bold>[[20]] War was waged from heaven.</bold> The Holy One blessed is He, as well, dispatched His hosts against them. They, too, have no desire for any payment.</p>
<p><bold>In their pathways.</bold> The upper tip of the star was in heaven, the bottom on earth. This teaches that the width of the firmament is equivalent to the distance between heaven and earth. For the star is suspended across the firmament like a sort of bolt across a door, its length measuring the same as the width of the firmament. From this passage, which attests that they waged war in their pathways, we learn that the width of the firmament is the same as the elevation of heaven from earth.<sup><xref rid="fn116">34</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[21]] Swept them away.</bold> It brushed them from the world like a broom which brushes ashes from an oven.</p>
<p><bold>The stream of antiquity.</bold> It guaranteed the obligation to the sea concerning this, from the days of Egypt,<sup><xref rid="fn117">35</xref></sup> as stated in Pesachim.<sup><xref rid="fn118">36</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>My soul trampled underfoot</bold> the power of the mighty Canaanite warriors.</p>
<p><bold>[[22]] Horses&#x2019; legs were battered.</bold> Their horses&#x2019; hooves were severed. The heat of the star brought the mud to a boil, severing the hooves, as when legs are scalded in boiling water to detach the hooves. Once the hooves were severed, the legs were battered.</p>
<p><bold>By the prancing, the prancing of their mighty.</bold> They pranced their horses in battle, as in &#x201C;a prancing horse.<sup><xref rid="fn119">37</xref></sup> The word connotes the dancing of a horse.</p>
<p><bold>[[23]] Curse Meroz&#x0021;</bold> One opinion is that this was a star.<sup><xref rid="fn120">38</xref></sup> According to others, this was a distinguished person who was near the battle field but failed to appear.<sup><xref rid="fn121">39</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>Declares Adonoy&#x2019;s emissary.</bold> Barak made this declaration, as the emissary of the Holy One, blessed is He.</p>
<p><bold>Those who dwell in it.</bold> Those who remain within his four <italic>amohs.</italic> With four hundred shofar blasts, Barak excommunicated Meroz.<sup><xref rid="fn122">40</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>To assist Adonoy.</bold> As if it were possible,<sup><xref rid="fn123">41</xref></sup> if anyone comes to Yisroel&#x2019;s assistance, it is as if he were assisting the Divine Presence.<sup><xref rid="fn124">42</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[24]] By the women of the tent.</bold> Sarah, of whom it is said, &#x201C;Here she is, in the tent.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn125">43</xref></sup> Rivkah, of whom it is said, &#x201C;Yitzchak brought her to the tent.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn126">44</xref></sup> Rachel and Leah, of whom it is said, &#x201C;He left Leah&#x2019;s tent and entered Rachel&#x2019;s tent.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn127">45</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>Blessed by the women of the tent.</bold> Yael was blessed. Why? They bore and raised children. Were it not for Yael, this scoundrel would have annihilated them. This is taught in Breishis Rabbah.<sup><xref rid="fn128">46</xref></sup> Another interpretation: Yael, as well, remained in the tent,<sup><xref rid="fn129">47</xref></sup> and she is therefore, mentioned in the blessing of the women of the tents.</p>
<p><bold>[[25]] But she gave milk</bold> to ascertain whether he was alert enough to differentiate between the taste of water and the taste of milk. This is Yonasan&#x2019;s rendition.</p>
<p><bold>In a cup of the mighty.</bold> In a cup used for drinking water, for waters are described as &#x201C;mighty&#x201D;, as it is said, &#x201C;in mighty waters.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn130">48</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[26]] To batter the exhausted</bold> Sisera, who was exhausted, totally fatigued.</p>
<p><bold>Penetrated.</bold> From <span dir="rtl">&#x05D7;&#x05B4;&#x05D9;&#xFB47;&#xFB35;&#x05D9;</span>, &#x201C;penetration&#x201D;.</p>
<p><bold>Inflicted grievous injury.</bold> From <span dir="rtl">&#x05DE;&#x05B7;&#x05D7;&#x05B7;&#x05E5;</span>, &#x201C;injury&#x201D;.</p>
<p><bold>Impaled.</bold> It emerged from the other side.</p>
<p><bold>[[28]] Moaning.</bold> The word refers to expressing speech, as in &#x201C;the expression of the lips.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn131">49</xref></sup> However, the Rabbis<sup><xref rid="fn132">50</xref></sup> interpret this as referring to moaning, as in the shofar&#x2019;s <italic>&#x201C;teruah&#x201D;</italic> sound, translated <span dir="rtl">&#x05D9;&#x05B7;&#xFB31;&#x05B8;&#x05D1;&#x05B8;&#x05D0;</span>, &#x201C;moan&#x201D;.<sup><xref rid="fn133">51</xref></sup> In my opinion, the reference is to seeing, as in &#x201C;the pupil of his eye.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn134">52</xref></sup> This is Menachem&#x2019;s interpretation. A window.</p>
<p><bold>[[29]] The wise among her ladies responded to her.</bold> The wise ones<sup><xref rid="fn135">53</xref></sup> among her ladies. This is why the &#x201C;<span dir="rtl">&#x05D7;</span>&#x201D; is vocalized with a <italic>&#x201C;pasach&#x201D;.</italic> The plural noun, lit. &#x201C;wisdoms&#x201D; is vocalized with the half-<italic>kametz</italic>, as in &#x201C;Wisdoms are remote gems to the foolish.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn136">54</xref></sup> Here, the vocalization is <span dir="rtl">&#x05D7;&#x05B7;&#x05DB;&#x05B0;&#x05DE;&#xFB4B;&#x05EA;</span>. Similarly, &#x201C;The wise among women has constructed her home.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn137">55</xref></sup> The wise one among the women.</p>
<p><bold>Responded.</bold> The period punctuating the <span dir="rtl">&#x05E0;</span> serves as a substitute for a third <span dir="ltr">&#x05E0;</span>.<sup><xref rid="fn138">56</xref></sup> Hence, the translation is &#x201C;[the wise ones] responded &#x2018;to her.&#x2019;&#x201D; The period punctuating <span dir="rtl">&#x05E0;</span> serves as a substitute for &#x201C;her&#x201D;,<sup><xref rid="fn139">57</xref></sup> as in &#x201C;you shall bring &#x2018;her&#x2019; scalded.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn140">58</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>Indeed, she stated in reply.</bold> She consoled herself. Why should I keep wondering about my son&#x2019;s delay?</p>
<p><bold>[[30]] Are they not finding</bold> and dividing the pillage? That is the cause of the delay.</p>
<p><bold>Or two [wombs] for each man.</bold> They are ravishing the attractive Yisroelite women, and each of them has, in his bed, two or three women.</p>
<p><bold>[[31]] So may perish</bold>. Devorah declared,<sup><xref rid="fn141">59</xref></sup> her consolation is hollow&#x2014;may all your enemies perish, Adonoy, as he perished.</p>
<p><bold>But those who love him</bold>&#x2014;as the sun emerging in its full power in the world to come, sevenfold over the light of the seven days of creation, or three hundred forty three to one. This equals forty nine times seven.<sup><xref rid="fn142">60</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>The land was tranquil for forty years.</bold> These words are not Devorah&#x2019;s, but the author&#x2019;s.</p>
<ftnote id="fn83"><sup>1</sup>Shemos, 20:2.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn84"><sup>2</sup>The word &#x201C;I&#x201D; is doubled.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn85"><sup>3</sup>Melachim 1, 18:39.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn86"><sup>4</sup>Yalkut, 47.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn87"><sup>5</sup>Devarim, 33:2. Adonoy first offered the Torah to Eisov&#x2019;s descendants at Seir. When they refused, He shone forth from there to Yisroel at Sinai. (Rashi to Devarim, there).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn88"><sup>6</sup>As indicated by the quaking of the earth and the dripping of heaven in v.4, and the dissolving of the mountain in v.5.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn89"><sup>7</sup>&#x201C;Adonoy, the Torah which you have given to Yisroel: When they violate it, their enemies dominate them, and when they return to it, they are empowered over their antagonists&#x201D;. (Targum Yonasan)</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn90"><sup>8</sup>As the Yisroelites glowed with a heavenly fire, Adonoy instructed the clouds of glory to drip dew of revival to restore them. (Yalkut, 48)</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn91"><sup>9</sup>Shemos, 19:18, 20:15, etc. Our passage, therefore, omits this, leaving it to the reader&#x2019;s understanding. See the following Rashi.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn92"><sup>10</sup>Scripture substitutes the <italic>&#x201C;pasach&#x201D;</italic> vowelization for the <italic>&#x201C;segol&#x201D;</italic> in the opening &#x2018;<span dir="rtl">&#x05E9;</span>&#x2019; of <span dir="rtl">&#x05E9;&#x05E7;&#x05DE;&#x05EA;&#x05D9;</span>. The <italic>&#x201C;kametz&#x201D;</italic> vowelization of the opening &#x2018;<span dir="rtl">&#x05E9;</span>&#x2019; is substituted for the <italic>&#x201C;segol&#x201D;.</italic></ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn93"><sup>11</sup>Devarim, 17:2. Although generally translated as &#x201C;gates&#x201D;, <span dir="rtl">&#xFB2A;&#x05B0;&#x05E2;&#x05B8;&#x05E8;&#x05B4;&#x05D9;&#x05DD;</span> is translated here as &#x201C;cities&#x201D;.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn94"><sup>12</sup>The Talmud (Pesachim, 87:b) reads <span dir="rtl">&#xFB44;&#x05BD;&#x05E8;&#x05B8;&#x05D6;&#xFB4B;&#x05DF;</span>, lit. &#x201C;exposure&#x201D;, as <span dir="rtl">&#xFB44;&#x05B4;&#x05D6;&#x05B0;&#x05E8;&#xFB4B;&#x05DF;</span>, &#x201C;dispersion&#x201D;. Rashi follows this interpretation.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn95"><sup>13</sup>Meaning &#x201C;the battle formations organized by strategists and tactitians.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn96"><sup>14</sup>Mishlei, 30:27.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn97"><sup>15</sup>Both interpretations appear in Targum Yonasan.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn98"><sup>16</sup>Eichah, 3:16.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn99"><sup>17</sup>Pesachim, 66:b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn100"><sup>18</sup>Thereby favoring herself over the leaders who preceded her. (Rashi to Pesachim, ibid.)</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn101"><sup>19</sup>Silencing her song (Rashi to Pesachim, ibid). It was now necessary for her to reinvoke the prophetic spirit by saying, &#x201C;Awake, awake.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn102"><sup>20</sup><span dir="rtl">&#x05D9;&#x05B8;&#x05E8;&#x05B7;&#x05D3;</span> is translated as descended. <span dir="rtl">&#x05D9;&#x05B0;&#x05E8;&#x05B7;&#x05D3;</span>, however, means dominated.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn103"><sup>21</sup>To give him dominion over them. (Yeshayah, 45:1.)</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn104"><sup>22</sup>See fn.19.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn105"><sup>23</sup> Yehoshua was descended from Ephraim, son of Yoseif, and Amaleik was a descendant of Eisov. Scripture states, &#x201C;The house of Yaakov shall be fire, the house of Yoseif flame, the house of Eisov chaff&#x201D; [Ovadiah, 18], teaching that the descendants of Yoseif shall devour the descendants of Eisov as flame consumes chaff. (Yalkut, 51. Cf. Rashi to Bereishis, 30:25)</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn106"><sup>24</sup>Shemos, 17:13.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn107"><sup>25</sup>Like Yoseif, Binyomin was a child of Rochel, and Eisov is destined to fall by the power of Rochel&#x2019;s descendants. (Yalkut, ibid.)</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn108"><sup>26</sup>Shmuel 1, 15:7. This took place during the time of the prophet Shmuel, after the days of Devorah and the Shoftim. Her remarks here are prophetic. (Radak)</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn109"><sup>27</sup>&#x201C;Your succesor, with your people.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn110"><sup>28</sup> I Shmuel 15:4.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn111"><sup>29</sup>Ben Menashe. (Bemidbar, 32:41, Devarim, 3:14).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn112"><sup>30</sup>Divrei Hayamim (1, 12:32) lists, among King Davids followers, &#x201C;Of the sons of Yesachar, who knew and understood the times.&#x201D; They understood the nature of the events taking place in their times, and were, therefore, qualified to serve as King David&#x2019;s advisors. (Rashi to Divrei Hayamim, there). Or, they were expertly versed in the calculations used in fixing the months and years of the Jewish calendar. They knew and understood the determination of the times of the calendar. (Yalkut, here, 52. See Rashi to Bereishis, 49:15)</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn113"><sup>31</sup>Tehilim, 8:8. <span dir="rtl">&#xFB2B;&#x05C7;&#x05D3;&#x05B7;&#x05D9;</span>, lit. &#x201C;my&#x201D; field, is translated as <span dir="rtl">&#xFB2B;&#x05C7;&#x05D3;&#x05B6;&#x05D4;</span>, &#x201C;the field.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn114"><sup>32</sup>Yermiyahu, 22:14. <span dir="rtl">&#x05D7;&#x05B7;&#xFB3C;&#xFB4B;&#x05E0;&#x05B7;&#x05D9;</span>, lit. &#x201C;my windows,&#x201D; is translated as <span dir="rtl">&#x05D7;&#x05B7;&#xFB3C;&#xFB4B;&#x05DF;</span>, &#x201C;the window.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn115"><sup>33</sup> This is Targum Yonasan&#x2019;s translation.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn116"><sup>34</sup>&#x201C;In their pathways&#x201D; indicates that the star remained in its celestial path during the battle on earth. Evidently, the tip of the star remained fixed in heaven, while the remainder swung downward so that the lower edge reached the earth and destroyed Sisera&#x2019;s forces. Since the star now extended from heaven to earth normally reached across the firmament, we learn that the distance between the two areas is the same.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn117"><sup>35</sup>In the days of antiquity, during the exodus from Egypt.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn118"><sup>36</sup> 118:b. When the Egyptians drowned at the splitting of the Reed Sea, Adonoy ordered the sea to cast their bodies onto the shore, to prove to the Yisroelites that they had perished. The sea objected, claiming the bodies as its due, and consented only when Kishon stream guaranteed repayment of the obligation. Kishon now fulfilled the guarantee, by sweeping Sisera&#x2019;s forces into the sea.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn119"><sup>37</sup>Nachum, 3:2.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn120"><sup>38</sup>Sisera&#x2019;s protective star. (Rashi to Moed Katan, 16:a).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn121"><sup>39</sup>Moed Katan ibid.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn122"><sup>40</sup>Ibid.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn123"><sup>41</sup>&#160;<span dir="rtl">&#x05DB;&#x05D1;&#x05D9;&#x05DB;&#x05D5;&#x05DC;</span>, &#x201C;as if it were possible,&#x201D; is used as a caveat when human qualities seem to be attributed to Adonoy.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn124"><sup>42</sup>Yalkut, 55.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn125"><sup>43</sup>Bereishis, 18:9.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn126"><sup>44</sup>Ibid, 24:67.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn127"><sup>45</sup>Ibid, 31:33.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn128"><sup>46</sup>48:15.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn129"><sup>47</sup>4:17.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn130"><sup>48</sup>Shemos, 15:10.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn131"><sup>49</sup>Yeshaya, 57:19.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn132"><sup>50</sup>Rosh Hashona 33:b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn133"><sup>51</sup>Bemidbar, 29:1.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn134"><sup>52</sup>Zechariah, 2:12.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn135"><sup>53</sup>Not &#x201C;the wisdoms of her ladies.&#x201D; The vocalization indicates that the proper translation is &#x201C;the wise ones,&#x201D; rather than &#x201C;the wisdoms,&#x201D; as Rashi explains.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn136"><sup>54</sup>Mishlei, 24:7.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn137"><sup>55</sup>Mishlei, 14:1.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn138"><sup>56</sup>The third person feminine plural for &#x201C;response&#x201D; is <span dir="rtl">&#xFB4A;&#x05B7;&#x05E2;&#x05B2;&#x05E0;&#x05C7;&#x05E0;&#x05C7;&#x05D4;</span>, &#x201C;they responded&#x201D;. Also, as a general rule, the suffix <span dir="rtl">&#x05E0;&#x05D4;</span> is added as a contraction of <span dir="rtl">&#x05D0;&#xFB4B;&#x05EA;&#x05C7;&#xFB34;</span>, &#x201C;to her.&#x201D; Thus, &#x201C;they responded to her&#x201D; should actually read <span dir="rtl">&#x05D5;&#x05B7;&#xFB4A;&#x05B7;&#x05E2;&#x05B2;&#x05E0;&#x05C7;&#x05E0;&#x05C7;&#x05D4;</span>, with the <span dir="rtl">&#x05E0;</span> tripled. However, Rashi notes, Scripture drops the third <span dir="rtl">&#x05E0;</span>, and punctuates the second <span dir="rtl">&#x05E0;</span> with a period to represent the missing letter.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn139"><sup>57</sup> A punctuated <span dir="rtl">&#x05E0;</span> may appear where no letter has been dropped. Then, its purpose is to represent a contraction of <span dir="rtl">&#x05D0;&#xFB4B;&#x05EA;&#xFB34;</span>, &#x201C;her&#x201D;.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn140"><sup>58</sup>Vayikra, 6:14. This refers to the feminine <span dir="rtl">&#x05DE;&#x05B4;&#x05E0;&#x05B0;&#x05D7;&#x05B8;&#x05D4;</span>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn141"><sup>59</sup>Our verse was not recited by Sisera&#x2019;s mother, but by Devorah. (Yalkut, 58.)</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn142"><sup>60</sup>Sevenfold over the light of all seven days of creation is equivalent to forty nine-fold over the original light of creation. (Rashi to Zechariah, 4:3). The light of creation was sevenfold over our present light. (Tosafos to Bava Basra, 8:b). Hence, the light of the world to come will be one hundred forty three times as great as our present light.</ftnote>
</appendix>
<appendix>
<p><bold>[[1]] Acted wickedly.</bold> Until this period, Scripture states, &#x201C;They resumed [acting wickedly]&#x201D; since their iniquities accumulated. However, through this hymn<sup><xref rid="fn143">1</xref></sup> they were granted forgiveness for all that they had perpetrated.<sup><xref rid="fn144">2</xref></sup> But now they began sinning anew. This interpretation is in Agadas Tehilim.</p>
<p><bold>[[2]] Retreats.</bold> Hidden places.<sup><xref rid="fn145">3</xref></sup> In old French, &#x201C;voutes&#x201D;. Because a slight bit of illumination is positioned in them in some inconspicuous spot, they are referred to as <span dir="rtl">&#x05DE;&#x05B4;&#x05E0;&#x05B0;&#x05D4;&#x05C7;&#x05E8;&#xFB4B;&#x05EA;</span>, lit. &#x201C;glimmerings&#x201D;, &#x201C;lucerno&#x201D; in old French.</p>
<p><bold>Caves.</bold> &#x201C;Grotte&#x201D; in old French</p>
<p><bold>Stockades.</bold> &#x201C;Palliser&#x201D; in old French, &#x201C;pales&#x201D;, as it is constructed in the forest by felling trees around its perimeter.<sup><xref rid="fn146">4</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[5]] With their cattle</bold> to graze on the produce.</p>
<p><bold>[[8]] A prophet.</bold> This prophet was Pinchas.<sup><xref rid="fn147">5</xref></sup> Taken from Seder Olam.</p>
<p><bold>[[11]] The Aviezrite.</bold> One of the sons of Aviezer ben Gilod ben Menasheh.</p>
<p><bold>His son Gidon.</bold> His father had been threshing, while he sifted. He told him, &#x201C;Father, you are elderly. If the enemies come, you will never be able to escape. You leave, and I will thresh.&#x201D;</p>
<p><bold>In the wine press.</bold> With beams of an olive press.</p>
<p><bold>[[12]] Adonoy is with you, man of supreme power.</bold> Since He infused you with such power.</p>
<p><bold>[[13]] If [lit. and] Adonoy is with us.<sup><xref rid="fn148">6</xref></sup></bold> If Adonoy is with us, why has [all this] occurred, etc.</p>
<p><bold>Which our forefathers recounted to us.</bold> It was Pesach, and he told him, &#x201C;Last night father recited the Hallel for me, and I heard him read, &#x201C;When Yisroel departed from Egypt&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn149">7</xref></sup>&#x2014;but now He has abandoned us. If our forefathers were saintly, let Him act in our behalf in their merit; and if they were wicked, then, just as He worked His wonders for them gratuitously, so, let Him act in our behalf. Where are all His marvels?&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn150">8</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[14]] Turned to him.</bold> The Holy One, blessed is He, Himself.<sup><xref rid="fn151">9</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>By this power of yours.</bold> By the power of the merit of your advocacy of my children.<sup><xref rid="fn152">10</xref></sup> This is R&#x2019; Tanchuma&#x2019;s explanation.</p>
<p><bold>Behold, my unit [lit. thousand].</bold> The thousand member unit of which I am a constituent, under the command of its captain, is the most inadequate unit among all the units in Menasheh.</p>
<p><bold>[[17]] That you.</bold> The same as <span dir="rtl">&#xFB2A;&#x05B6;&#x05D0;&#x05B7;&#xFB4A;&#x05C7;&#x05D4;</span>, with the <italic>segol</italic> vocalization.<sup><xref rid="fn153">11</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[19]] Matzos containing flour.</bold> We learn that it was Pesach, the day the Omer offering was waved.<sup><xref rid="fn154">12</xref></sup> This is why it is said,<sup><xref rid="fn155">13</xref></sup> &#x201C;Behold, a toasted barley bread was careening,<sup><xref rid="fn156">14</xref></sup> etc.&#x201D;</p>
<p><bold>Soup.</bold> Broth.</p>
<p><bold>[[22]] Aahha.</bold> This denotes apprehension, as if to say, &#x201C;What will become of me?&#x201D;</p>
<p><bold>This, because I have seen.</bold> Because I have seen an angel of Adonoy&#x2014;this is why I am apprehensive and exclaim &#x201C;Aahha&#x0021;&#x201D;</p>
<p><bold>[[24]] Entitled it.</bold> Gidon named the altar.<sup><xref rid="fn157">15</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>Adonoy is peace.</bold> Adonoy is our peace.</p>
<p><bold>[[25]] Bullock [lit. bull ox].</bold> The young bull, as even a day old ox is called an &#x201C;ox&#x201D;.<sup><xref rid="fn158">16</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>A second bull.</bold>&#160;<span dir="rtl">&#x05D5;&#x05B0;&#x05EA;&#xFB4B;&#x05E8;&#x05B8;&#x05D0; &#xFB4A;&#x05B4;&#x05E0;&#x05B0;&#x05D9;&#x05C7;&#x05E0;&#x05C7;&#x05D0;</span>, &#x201C;A second bull&#x201D;.<sup><xref rid="fn159">17</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>Seven year.</bold> Which had been fattened for seven years to be brought as an idolatrous sacrifice. Eight prohibitions were suspended<sup><xref rid="fn160">18</xref></sup> that night; &#x2018;designated&#x2019;, <italic>&#x2018;asheirah&#x2019;,</italic> &#x2018;night&#x2019;, &#x2018;altar&#x2019;, etc., as enumerated in Temurah.<sup><xref rid="fn161">19</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[26]] Top of the bulwark.</bold> Top of the rock.</p>
<p><bold>[[31]] You want to fight for [lit. &#x201C;to&#x201D;] the baal?</bold> For the sake of the baal.</p>
<p><bold>To avenge [lit. rescue] him.</bold> To exact vengeance for him.<sup><xref rid="fn162">20</xref></sup> Similarly, &#x201C;by my own hand exacting my vengeance,&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn163">21</xref></sup> by David concerning Novol.</p>
<p><bold>Whoever fights for [lit. &#x201C;to&#x201D;] him.</bold> For his sake.</p>
<p><bold>Wait until morning.</bold> Until morning, wait.</p>
<p><bold>If he is a god</bold> let him fight his own battle and exact his own vengeance. To rebuff them until Gidon could escape, he said this.</p>
<p><bold>[[32]] Fight against him.</bold> Against Gidon. In relation to <span dir="rtl">&#x05E8;&#x05B7;&#x05D9;&#x05D1;</span>, &#x201C;fight&#x201D;, the proper term is <span dir="rtl">&#x05E2;&#x05B4;&#x05DD;</span>, or <span dir="rtl">&#x05D0;&#x05B6;&#x05EA;</span>, or <span dir="rtl">&#xFB31;&#xFB4B;</span>, &#x201C;with&#x201D; [him], as in &#x201C;he fought with Lavan&#x201D;.<sup><xref rid="fn164">22</xref></sup> However, <span dir="rtl">&#x05DC;&#xFB4B;</span>, lit. &#x201C;to&#x201D;, is not the proper term. Every <span dir="rtl">&#x05DC;&#xFB4B;</span> mentioned here is interpreted as &#x201C;for his sake.&#x201D;</p>
<p><bold>[[34]] The Divine spirit.</bold> The spirit of valor.</p>
<p><bold>Aviezer gathered.</bold> The entire clan.</p>
<p><bold>[[38]] That is what occurred.</bold> The dew condensed on the fleece alone more than everywhere else, as it is said, &#x201C;a full bowl of water.&#x201D; However, &#x201C;while all of the ground is dry&#x201D; did not materialize, as a Divine covenant assures perpetual dew fall.</p>
<p><bold>He squeezed.</bold> The word connotes pressure. Similarly, &#x201C;They were neither pressed nor bandaged.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn165">23</xref></sup> They were not strapped in bandages to draw out the discharge.</p>
<ftnote id="fn143"><sup>1</sup>Sung by Devorah and Barak [ch.5].</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn144"><sup>2</sup>Anyone rescued miraculously who then sings a hymn of praise forgiven all his sins, as if he had been newly created. (Yalkut, 60)</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn145"><sup>3</sup>This is Targum Yonasan&#x2019;s translation.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn146"><sup>4</sup>The trees serve as the pales or stakes forming the stockade.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn147"><sup>5</sup> See above, 2:1.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn148"><sup>6</sup>Not &#x201C;And Adonoy is with us,&#x201D; as the literal reading would indicate, but &#x201C;If Adonoy is with us,&#x201D; as demonstrated by the following phrase cited by Rashi, &#x201C;why has [all this] occurred, etc.&#x201D;.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn149"><sup>7</sup> &#x201C;&#x2026;the sea observed and fled, the Yardein turned back, etc.&#x201D; (Tehilim, 114)</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn150"><sup>8</sup>Yalkut, 62.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn151"><sup>9</sup>Gidon was visited by Adonoy himself in the merit of his advocacy of Yisroel. (Yalkut, ibid)</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn152"><sup>10</sup>Ibid.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn153"><sup>11</sup>&#160;<span dir="rtl">&#xFB2A;&#x05B6;&#x05D0;&#x05B7;&#xFB4A;&#x05C7;&#x05D4;</span>, with the <italic>&#x201C;kamatz&#x201D;</italic> vocalization, which appears in the text, is the same as <span dir="rtl">&#xFB2A;&#x05B6;&#x05D0;&#x05B7;&#xFB4A;&#x05C7;&#x05D4;</span> &#x201C;that you.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn154"><sup>12</sup>On the second day of Pesach. (Vayikra, 23:11)</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn155"><sup>13</sup>Below, 7:13.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn156"><sup>14</sup> &#x201C;&#x2026; into the camp of Midyon. It reached the tent and struck it down.&#x201D; This was in the merit of the Omer offering (Rashi, there, Yalkut, 62), which was made of barley.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn157"><sup>15</sup>The reading is, &#x201C;[He] entitled it, &#x2018;Adonoy is peace,&#x2019;&#x201D; not &#x201C;Adonoy entitled it, &#x2018;Peace.&#x2019;&#x201D;.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn158"><sup>16</sup>The inference of &#x201C;Bull ox&#x201D; is a bull that qualifies as an ox. Since even a day old bull qualifies, the reference is to a young bull.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn159"><sup>17</sup>This is Targum Yonasan&#x2019;s rendition.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn160"><sup>18</sup> 1. The second bull, which had been designated as an idolatrous sacrifice, was now brought as an offering. 2. Utensils used previously for the <italic>Asheirah</italic> sacrifices were now used. 3. The wood of the <italic>Asheirah</italic> tree was used as fuel. 4. The offering was brought at night. 5. It was brought on a personal altar outside the Mishkon at Shiloh. 6. The second bull had been actually worshipped as a deity. 7. Gidon was not a Kohein. 8. He did not use the required sacred utensils.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn161"><sup>19</sup>28:b, 29:a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn162"><sup>20</sup>The literal translation of <span dir="rtl">&#xFB4A;&#xFB4B;&#xFB2A;&#x05B4;&#x05D9;&#x05E2;&#xFB35;&#x05DF;</span>, &#x201C;to rescue,&#x201D; does not apply, since the idol was no longer endangered. The alternate interpretation, &#x201C;to avenge,&#x201D; is correct here.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn163"><sup>21</sup>Shmuel 1, 25:33. <span dir="rtl">&#x05D4;&#xFB4B;&#xFB2A;&#x05B4;&#x05D9;&#x05E2;&#x05B8;&#x05D4;</span> is interpreted as &#x201C;avenge.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn164"><sup>22</sup>Bereishis, 31:36.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn165"><sup>23</sup>Yeshaya, 1:6.</ftnote>
</appendix>
<appendix>
<p><bold>[[1]] Of signal valley ridge.</bold> Overlooking the plain<sup><xref rid="fn166">1</xref></sup>. <span dir="rtl">&#x05D4;&#x05B7;&#xFB3E;&#xFB4B;&#x05E8;&#x05B6;&#x05D4;</span> connotes instruction, observation, as in &#x201C;instructs by gesturing.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn167">2</xref></sup> From there they would observe, and then signal instructions to the valley.</p>
<p><bold>[[2]] Glorify.</bold> &#x201C;Vanter&#x201D; in old French.</p>
<p><bold>[[3]] In the morning.</bold> In the morning is <span dir="rtl">&#x05E6;&#x05B7;&#x05E4;&#x05B0;&#x05D3;&#x05C7;&#x05D0;</span> in Aramaic.</p>
<p><bold>[[5]] Anyone who laps with his tongue, etc.</bold> Anyone who bends forward while on his knees to drink, set them aside, out of your retinue. They shall not accompany you, since they are practiced in kneeling before idols.<sup><xref rid="fn168">3</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[6]] Who lapped from hand.</bold> This is not the kind of bending forward as when lapping up with the tongue.<sup><xref rid="fn169">4</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[12]] Lay in the valley.</bold> Were stationed in the valley.</p>
<p><bold>[[13]] Toasted.</bold> The written text is <span dir="rtl">&#x05E6;&#x05C7;&#x05DC;&#xFB35;&#x05DC;</span>, &#x201C;clear&#x201D;.<sup><xref rid="fn170">5</xref></sup> The generation was cleared of righteous men.</p>
<p><bold>A toasted barley bread.</bold> A loaf of barley bread. A loaf toasted over coals.</p>
<p><bold>Barley bread.</bold> This represents the merit of the Omer offering, which was brought on Pesach.<sup><xref rid="fn171">6</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>And hit it, and it collapsed</bold> (the tent), <bold>then it overturned</bold> the tent, completely overturned, and the tent collapsed.</p>
<p><bold>[[15]] The recounting of the dream.</bold> The story of the dream.<sup><xref rid="fn172">7</xref></sup> &#x201C;The retelling of the dream and its interpretation.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn173">8</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>And its interpretation [lit. &#x201C;its sale&#x201D;].</bold> The goods exchanged for it,<sup><xref rid="fn174">9</xref></sup> or its interpretation.</p>
<p><bold>[[16]] Shofars and torches</bold> to invoke the merit of the giving of the Torah.<sup><xref rid="fn175">10</xref></sup> According to the plain explanation: this took place at night, as it is written,<sup><xref rid="fn176">11</xref></sup> and it was dark. They therefore carried torches to provide them with light. They placed them in pitchers so that the torches would remain undetected.</p>
<p><bold>[[17]] Watch me.</bold> Watch my actions, and follow suit.</p>
<p><bold>[[18]] I, and everyone with me.</bold> One of the divisions and one hundred men accompanied him.</p>
<p><bold>For Adonoy, and for Gidon.</bold> The sword that executes is from Adonoy, so that victory is Gidon&#x2019;s.<sup><xref rid="fn177">12</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[19]] Had posted.</bold> The soldiers had already posted the sentries who were assigned to the middle watch. Members of the military usually assign sentry duty so that some serve during the first third of the night, some during the second third, and some during the final third.<sup><xref rid="fn178">13</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>And smashed the pitchers.</bold> And broke<sup><xref rid="fn179">14</xref></sup> the pitchers which were in their hands.</p>
<p><bold>[[21]] They sounded the alarm.</bold> The signal to withdraw and flee.</p>
<p><bold>[[24]] Capture the waters</bold> which intervene between Aram and Canaanite territory.</p>
<p><bold>And the Yardein</bold> which also intervened.</p>
<p><bold>[[25]] They brought to Gidon, across the Yardein.</bold> In the morning, when Gidon crossed the Yardein pursuing Zevach and Tzalmona.<sup><xref rid="fn180">15</xref></sup></p>
<ftnote id="fn166"><sup>1</sup>This is Targum Yonasan&#x2019;s interpretation. The ridge overlooked the plain, and was thus suitable as an observation post.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn167"><sup>2</sup>Mishlei, 6:13.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn168"><sup>3</sup>Both phrases of this passage&#x2014;&#x201C;Anyone who laps, etc.&#x201D; and &#x201C;anyone who bends forward, etc.&#x201D;&#x2014;refer to the same drinkers. Those who bend forward while on their knees, bringing their faces down to the water in order to lap it up, are practiced in prostrating themselves before idols.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn169"><sup>4</sup>Lapping from hand to mouth does not involve prostrating oneself.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn170"><sup>5</sup>Occasionally, the written Scriptural text, <span dir="rtl">&#x05DB;&#x05B0;&#x05EA;&#x05B7;&#x05D1;</span>, differs from the the spoken text, <span dir="rtl">&#x05E7;&#x05BD;&#x05E8;&#x05B4;&#x05D9;</span>. Rashi notes that this is the case here, where the written text is <span dir="rtl">&#x05E6;&#x05C7;&#x05DC;&#xFB35;&#x05DC;</span>, while the spoken text is <span dir="rtl">&#x05E6;&#x05B0;&#x05DC;&#x05B4;&#x05D9;&#x05DC;</span>, &#x201C;toasted&#x201D;.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn171"><sup>6</sup> On the second day of Pesach. The offering consisted of barley meal. (Vayikra, 23:11,16. See Rashi there. Cf. Rashi above, 6:19).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn172"><sup>7</sup>&#160;<span dir="rtl">&#x05DE;&#x05B4;&#x05E1;&#x05B0;&#x05E4;&#x05B7;&#x05E8;</span>, generally translated as &#x201C;number&#x201D;, is interpreted here as &#x201C;story&#x201D;.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn173"><sup>8</sup>This is Targum Yonasan&#x2019;s translation.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn174"><sup>9</sup>According to the literal interpretation, &#x201C;sale&#x201D;.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn175"><sup>10</sup> At Mount Sinai, when the shofar sounded, and fire descended on the mountain. (Shemos, 19:16&#x2013;19).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn176"><sup>11</sup>V. 9.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn177"><sup>12</sup>This is Targum Yonasan&#x2019;s interpretation, following v. 20, &#x201C;Adonoy&#x2019;s sword, and for Gidon!&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn178"><sup>13</sup>See Yalkut, 63.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn179"><sup>14</sup>&#160;<span dir="rtl">&#x05E0;&#x05C7;&#x05E4;&#xFB4B;&#x05E5;</span> is sometimes translated as &#x201C;dispersed&#x201D;. Here, however, the translation is <span dir="rtl">&#x05E9;&#x05B8;&#x05D1;&#xFB4B;&#x05E8;</span>, &#x201C;broke&#x201D;, as stated clearly in v.20.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn180"><sup>15</sup>8:4,5.</ftnote>
</appendix>
<appendix>
<p><bold>[[2]] Can any action of mine compare with yours?</bold> How significant were my actions at the beginning in comparison with yours at the end?</p>
<p><bold>Do not Ephraim&#x2019;s underripened gleanings surpass.</bold> The gleanings<sup><xref rid="fn181">1</xref></sup> which you acquired at the end surpass the early harvest which my family and I gathered, for Adonoy delivered the kings into your hands.</p>
<p><bold>[[3]] What could I have</bold> done that would have been as significant as your accomplishments?</p>
<p><bold>[[4]] He crossed with the three hundred men.</bold> They crossed the Yardein after Zevach and Tzalmuna, who had crossed previously and wreaked destruction across the Yardein, in the territory of Reuven, Gad, and Menashe. He crossed to take revenge against them as well.</p>
<p><bold>[[5]] To the people of Succos.</bold> They were Yisroelites.</p>
<p><bold>[[6]] Are the palms of Zevach and Tzalmuna</bold> in your hands that you pride yourself in having rescued us from the hand of Midyon.</p>
<p><bold>[[7]] Thorns.</bold> &#x201C;Ronzes&#x201D; in old French.</p>
<p><bold>[[10]] At Karkor.</bold> The name of a place.</p>
<p><bold>[[11]] By way of the tent dwellers.</bold> By way of the lands of Kedar and Arabia, whose inhabitants were wilderness tent dwellers. Since they were occupied exclusively as shepherds, they could not dwell in houses.</p>
<p><bold>East of Novach and Yagbeha.</bold> These were Yisroelite cities. He chose not to pass through them, but rather travelled roundabout, so that they would remain undetected, and could overwhelm them by surprise.</p>
<p><bold>[[13]] With the sun high.</bold> Before sunset, with the sun still visible high above the horizon.</p>
<p><bold>[[16]] Tore with them.</bold> &#x201C;Broke apart&#x201D; with them.<sup><xref rid="fn182">2</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[18]] Singular, of princely appearance.</bold> Yonasan explains that one of them was of princely appearance.<sup><xref rid="fn183">3</xref></sup> However, this may be interpreted as, &#x201C;They were exactly like you, all of singular appearance, for they were of princely appearance.&#x201D;</p>
<p><bold>[[20]] But the boy would not draw his sword</bold> to execute them, for he was afraid of them.</p>
<p><bold>[[21]] Crescent chains.</bold> Lunettes in old French, moonshaped, made of gold.</p>
<p><bold>[[26]] The crescent chains and crowns.</bold> The neckbands and crowns.<sup><xref rid="fn184">4</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[27]] Gidon fashioned it into an apron</bold> as a memorial to the the great salvation, demonstrating how enormous their forces were, as the nose rings of their eminent men contained so much gold.</p>
<p><bold>All of Yisroel were perverted towards it</bold> after Gidon&#x2019;s demise.<sup><xref rid="fn185">5</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[33]] Baal beris.</bold> This was his name.</p>
<p><bold>[[35]] They did not act benevolently.</bold> They murdered his children, as stated in the narrative.<sup><xref rid="fn186">6</xref></sup></p>
<ftnote id="fn181"><sup>1</sup>&#160;<span dir="rtl">&#x05E2;&#xFB4B;&#x05DC;&#x05B0;&#x05DC;&#xFB4B;&#x05EA;</span> are underripened grapes which may not be harvested, but must be left to be gleaned afterward by the poor. (Vayikra, 19:10) Gidon compared his original battle with the Midyonites to the harvest, and the ensuing execution of Orev and Z&#x2019;ev to the gleaning of the <span dir="rtl">&#x05E2;&#xFB4B;&#x05DC;&#x05B0;&#x05DC;&#xFB4B;&#x05EA;</span>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn182"><sup>2</sup>This is Targum Yonasan&#x2019;s translation.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn183"><sup>3</sup>Yonasan&#x2019;s reading is: &#x201C;One was exactly like you, of princely appearance.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn184"><sup>4</sup>This is Targum Yonasan&#x2019;s rendition.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn185"><sup>5</sup>But not during his lifetime. Gidon&#x2019;s intentions were pure. (See Yalkut, 64.)</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn186"><sup>6</sup>Ch. 9.</ftnote>
</appendix>
<appendix>
<p><bold>[[4]] Headstrong.</bold> They acted impetuously, thoughtlessly.</p>
<p><bold>[[6]] Near the plain of the pillar.</bold> &#x201C;The plain of monuments&#x201C;&#x2014;<sup><xref rid="fn187">1</xref></sup> A plain in which monuments stood.</p>
<p><bold>[[8]] The trees went about resolutely.</bold> This is a parable.<sup><xref rid="fn188">2</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>The olive tree.</bold> Asniel ben Kenaz,<sup><xref rid="fn189">3</xref></sup> a tribesman of Judah, who are entitled &#x201C;olive&#x201D;, as it is said, &#x201C;Refreshed olive tree, with fruit beautiful in appearance, etc.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn190">4</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[9]] The richness of my oil.</bold> The connotation here is fattiness.</p>
<p><bold>[[10]] To the fig tree.</bold> This refers to Devorah.<sup><xref rid="fn191">5</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[11]] My sweetness.</bold> the honey of dates.</p>
<p><bold>[[12]] To the grapevine.</bold> This refers to Gidon,<sup><xref rid="fn192">6</xref></sup> a descendant of Yoseif, of whom it is said, &#x201C;A flourishing son&#x201D;&#x2014;&#x201C;like a grapevine positioned, etc.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn193">7</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[13]] Which brings joy to God.</bold> As the Levi&#x2019;im chant the hymns of glory only during the wine libation ceremony.<sup><xref rid="fn194">8</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[14]] The thornbush.</bold> &#x201C;epine&#x201D; in old French.</p>
<p><bold>[[15]] If you genuinely.</bold> Because I qualify as a sovereign.</p>
<p><bold>[[22]] Ruled.</bold> He wielded his authority through repression, and conducted himself arrogantly.</p>
<p><bold>[[23]] A malicious sentiment.</bold> Hatred. &#x201C;Talent&#x201D; in old French.</p>
<p><bold>[[26]] Ga&#x2019;al ben Eved.</bold> He was from another nation.</p>
<p><bold>[[27]] Indulged in carousals.</bold> Performed dances.<sup><xref rid="fn195">9</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[28]] Who is Avimelech, and who is Shechem.</bold> Who is Avimelech to control Shechem, and who is Shechem to be subjugated to Avimelech? Is not Avimelech Yerubaal&#x2019;s son, from Ofros, of the Aviezrites?<sup><xref rid="fn196">10</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>And his henchman Zevul?</bold> The city superintendent, named Zevul, is Avimelech&#x2019;s henchman. His master cannot justify his authority over the city; thus his appointee, as well, is a non-entity.</p>
<p><bold>Serve the people of Chamor.</bold> If you want to get yourselves leaders, come serve the men of Chamor, who ruled the land in early times.<sup><xref rid="fn197">11</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>But why must we serve him?</bold> Avimelech.</p>
<p><bold>[[29]] He said: For Avimelech.</bold> Ga&#x2019;al declared in the presence of Zevul, &#x201C;Tell Avimelech.&#x201D;</p>
<p><bold>Beef up your army and come on out</bold> from your place, and let us see how grand you are&#x0021;</p>
<p><bold>[[31]] Clandestinely.</bold> As in &#x201C;cunningly,&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn198">12</xref></sup> &#x201C;in deceit,&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn199">13</xref></sup> meaning secretively, stealthily.</p>
<p><bold>[[34]] Four divisions.</bold> Four companies.</p>
<p><bold>[[37]] From the promontory of the land.</bold> &#x201C;From the pre-eminence of the land.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn200">14</xref></sup> From the highest summit of all.</p>
<p><bold>Elon Meonenim.</bold> The plain of Meonenim</p>
<p><bold>[[42]] The people went out to the fields.</bold> The people of Shechem.</p>
<p><bold>They informed.</bold> Those who gave the information to Avimelech, that the townspeople had gone to the fields to attend to their wants.</p>
<p><bold>[[44]] At the entrance to the gateway of the city</bold> to block their entry.</p>
<p><bold>[[46]] Forest stockade.</bold> A forest encircled by twisted trees and branches, called &#x201C;plisse&#x201D; in old French.</p>
<p><bold>Of the temple of the god Beris.</bold> The stockade belonged to Baal Beris, the name of their deity. Tzalmon<sup><xref rid="fn201">15</xref></sup>, too, owned a forest there. Others interpret <span dir="rtl"><bold>&#x05E6;&#x05BD;&#x05E8;&#x05B4;&#x05D9;&#x05D7;&#x05B7;</bold></span> as &#x201C;voutes&#x201D; in old French, &#x201C;bunker,&#x201D; dug into the ground.</p>
<p><bold>[[48]] The overhang of a tree.</bold> The branch of a tree.</p>
<p><bold>[[53]] A pestle shard.</bold> A fragment of upper grinding stone called &#x201C;pestle&#x201D; [lit. &#x201C;rider.<sup><xref rid="fn202">16</xref></sup>].</p>
<p><bold>And smashed.</bold> Crushed.<sup><xref rid="fn203">17</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[54]] Lest it be said of me.</bold> Lest it be said concerning me.<sup><xref rid="fn204">18</xref></sup></p>
<ftnote id="fn187"><sup>1</sup>This is Targum Yonasan&#x2019;s translation.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn188"><sup>2</sup>Yalkut, 65.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn189"><sup>3</sup>Above, 3; 9&#x2013;11. (Yalkut, ibid)</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn190"><sup>4</sup>Yirmiyahu, 11:16. The chapter is addressed to &#x201C;the men of Yehudah&#x201D; (v.1).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn191"><sup>5</sup> Above, 4:4. (Yalkut, ibid.)</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn192"><sup>6</sup>Yalkut, ibid.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn193"><sup>7</sup>&#x201C;A flourishing son over a wellspring&#x201D;. (Bereishis, 49:22). Targum Onkelos there interprets, &#x201C;like a grapevine positioned over a wellspring.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn194"><sup>8</sup>Berachos, 35:b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn195"><sup>9</sup>This is Targum Yonasan&#x2019;s translation.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn196"><sup>10</sup>6:11.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn197"><sup>11</sup>Bereishis, 34:2.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn198"><sup>12</sup>Bereishis, 27:35.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn199"><sup>13</sup>Yirmiyahu, 8:5.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn200"><sup>14</sup>This is Targum Yonasan&#x2019;s translation.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn201"><sup>15</sup>Mentioned in v. 48.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn202"><sup>16</sup>As the upper pestle stone &#x201C;rides&#x201D; the lower mortar stone. (Metzudos).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn203"><sup>17</sup><span dir="rtl"><bold>&#x05EA;&#x05BC;&#x05B8;&#x05E8;&#x05B8;&#x05E5;</bold></span> is usually translated as &#x201C;ran&#x201D;. Here, however, the translation is &#x201C;crushed&#x201D;, or &#x201C;smashed&#x201D;.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn204"><sup>18</sup><span dir="rtl"><bold>&#x05DC;&#x05D9;</bold></span> is not translated as &#x201C;to me,&#x201D; but as &#x201C;concerning me.&#x201D;</ftnote>
</appendix>
<appendix>
<p><bold>[[1]] Ben Dodo.</bold> This was his name.</p>
<p><bold>[[4]] Thoroughbreds.</bold>&#160;<span dir="ltr"><bold>&#x05E2;&#x05D5;&#x05BC;&#x05DC;&#x05B4;&#x05D9;&#x05DF;</bold></span>,<sup><xref rid="fn205">1</xref></sup> the choicest horses.</p>
<p><bold>They owned thirty towns.</bold> They owned thirty unwalled municipalities. This is why they are described as <span dir="rtl"><bold>&#x05E2;&#x05B7;&#x05D9;&#x05B8;&#x05E8;&#x05B4;&#x05D9;&#x05DD;</bold></span>, &#x201C;towns&#x201D;, meaning the same as <span dir="ltr"><bold>&#x05E2;&#x05B7;&#x05D9;&#x05B8;&#x05D9;&#x05E8;&#x05B8;&#x05D5;&#x05B9;&#x05EA;</bold></span>.<sup><xref rid="fn206">2</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[6]] The Baals.</bold> Seven pagan gods are enumerated here.<sup><xref rid="fn207">3</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>They abandoned Adonoy,</bold> and did not worship Him. Not even concurrently with these.<sup><xref rid="fn208">4</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[8]] That year</bold> when Yair died.</p>
<p><bold>Across the Yardein.</bold> The territory of Reuven, Gad, and half of Menasheh; they were neighbors.<sup><xref rid="fn209">5</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[11]] Was it not from Mitzrayim.</bold> There are seven salvations here, corresponding with the seven pagan gods they worshiped.<sup><xref rid="fn210">6</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[12]] And Maon.</bold> The name of a nation.<sup><xref rid="fn211">7</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[16]] Could not contain Himself at [Yisroel&#x2019;s] anguish.</bold> As if one could depict God as lacking the space to bear and encompass His pain at Yisroel&#x2019;s anguish.</p>
<p><bold>[[17]] Were called together.</bold> They were assembled by proclamation.</p>
<ftnote id="fn205"><sup>1</sup>This is Targum Yonasan&#x2019;s translation.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn206"><sup>2</sup>Rather than <span dir="rtl"><bold>&#x05E2;&#x05B8;&#x05E8;&#x05B4;&#x05D9;&#x05DD;</bold></span> meaning walled cities.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn207"><sup>3</sup>Beitzah, 25:b. &#x201C;The deities of Aram, Tzidon, etc.&#x201D; does not explain where the Baals and Ashteros were worshiped, but lists deities in addition to them. Hence, the total is seven.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn208"><sup>4</sup>Otherwise, &#x201C;and did not worship Him&#x201D; is redundant. (Beitzah, ibid).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn209"><sup>5</sup>Of the Ammonites. See below, ch.11.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn210"><sup>6</sup>V. 6. See Rashi there.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn211"><sup>7</sup>But not, as generally translated, &#x201C;a dwelling place.&#x201D;</ftnote>
</appendix>
<appendix>
<p><bold>[[4]] The Bnei Ammon waged war.</bold> As mentioned above.<sup><xref rid="fn212">1</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[11]] All his stipulations.</bold> The conditions between them.</p>
<p><bold>Before Adonoy, at Mitzpah.</bold> Where everyone was assembled, as the Divine Presence rests upon multitudes.</p>
<p><bold>[[16]] Until the Reed Sea.</bold> South of the land of Edom, while the land of Edom is south of the land of Canaan.</p>
<p><bold>[[17]] Please allow me to traverse your country.</bold> From south to north, in order to enter the land of Canaan.</p>
<p><bold>To the king of Moav as well.</bold> Whose country bordered the extremity of the land of Edom, east of Edom, and south of Eretz Yisroel.</p>
<p><bold>And he refused.</bold> Moshe alludes to this in the Torah, &#x201C;As perpetrated against me by the Bnei Eisov residing at Sair, and the Moavites residing at Ar.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn213">2</xref></sup> Just as Edom refused them permission to pass, so did Moav refuse them permission to pass.</p>
<p><bold>[[18]] They then continued through the wilderness</bold> from west to east, along the southern borders of Edom and Moav.</p>
<p><bold>Circumvented the land of Edom.</bold> All of its southern border.</p>
<p><bold>And the land of Moav.</bold> All of its southern border. When they reached the southeastern corner, they angled northward along the periphery of the eastern border.</p>
<p><bold>Arrived at the east of the land of Moav, and camped opposite Arnon.</bold> At the end of the eastern border of the land of Moav. This was the starting point of the lands of Sichon and Og. They conquered the trans-Yardeinian territory east of the land of Canaan, crossed the Yardein, and invaded the land of Canaan by the eastern route.</p>
<p><bold>[[22]] They took possession, etc., from Arnon to the Yabok.</bold> Which you claim as yours, they annexed from Sichon.</p>
<p><bold>From the wilderness to the Yardein.</bold> There was a wilderness area adjoining the Yardein.</p>
<p><bold>[[26]] Adjoining [lit. by the hands of] Arnon.</bold> Near Arnon. These cities had belonged to Moav, but they recognized that they could not lay claim to them, since they were confiscated from Sichon, who had annexed them from the king of Moav.</p>
<p><bold>Three centuries</bold> from the conquest of the land in the days of Yehoshua, until Yiftoch. This teaches us concerning the years of the Judges mentioned until now&#x2014;whether the years of subjugation by the nations are included in the reckoning of the days of the Judge, or not.<sup><xref rid="fn214">3</xref></sup> We learn in Seder Olam:<sup><xref rid="fn215">4</xref></sup> Yehoshua directed Yisroel for twenty eight years&#x2014;I am not aware of any Scriptural derivation for this. Asniel for forty years,<sup><xref rid="fn216">5</xref></sup> the years of subjugation by Cushan Rishasaim are included.<sup><xref rid="fn217">6</xref></sup> Afterward, Ehud for eighty years,<sup><xref rid="fn218">7</xref></sup> with the eighteen years of subjugation by Eglon<sup><xref rid="fn219">8</xref></sup> included. This totals one hundred forty eight years. Devorah for forty years,<sup><xref rid="fn220">9</xref></sup> with the years of subjugation by Yavin<sup><xref rid="fn221">10</xref></sup> included, totaling one hundred eighty eight years. Afterward, seven years of subjugation by Midyon,<sup><xref rid="fn222">11</xref></sup> forty years of Gidon,<sup><xref rid="fn223">12</xref></sup> and<sup><xref rid="fn224">13</xref></sup> three of Avimelech, totaling two hundred thirty eight years. Afterward, twenty three years of Tola<sup><xref rid="fn225">14</xref></sup> and twenty two of Yair,<sup><xref rid="fn226">15</xref></sup> with one year overlapping both, and eighteen years of the Bnei Ammon<sup><xref rid="fn227">16</xref></sup> until Yiftoch&#x2019;s appearance. This totals three hundred.</p>
<p><bold>[[29]] He crossed to the Bnei Ammon.</bold> &#x201C;To&#x201D; the Bnei Ammon.</p>
<p><bold>[[33]] The Vineyard plains.</bold> The plain of the vineyards.<sup><xref rid="fn228">17</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>You are among those who ruined me.</bold> This is the feminine usage.<sup><xref rid="fn229">18</xref></sup> Similarly, &#x201C;You captured my heart, my sister bride.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn230">19</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[35]] You have surely brought me to my knees</bold> All my blood is in turmoil, You have taken away my feet.</p>
<p><bold>[[37]] To grieve on the hills.</bold> This word refers to bewailing. <sup><xref rid="fn231">20</xref></sup> Similarly, &#x201C;On its roofs and thoroughfares, total wailing, weeping grief.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn232">21</xref></sup> Weeping so intense that it causes a physical breakdown.<sup><xref rid="fn233">22</xref></sup> Midrash Agada: R&#x2019; Tanchuma expounded, On the hills; before the Sanhedrin&#x2014;perhaps they may find a loophole in your vow.<sup><xref rid="fn234">23</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[38]] Wept over her maidenhood.</bold> Since it is not written &#x201C;over her maidens,&#x201D; the inference is, over her actual maidenhood.</p>
<p><bold>[[39]] She became the subject of a law.</bold> Legislation was enacted prohibiting any repetition of this, for, had he approached Pinchos, or had Pinchos approached him, he would have released him from his vow.<sup><xref rid="fn235">24</xref></sup> But they refused to humble themselves,<sup><xref rid="fn236">25</xref></sup> and were, thus, both responsible for her ruin. They were punished. The Divine Presence departed from Pinchos, as it is said in Divrei Hayamim,<sup><xref rid="fn237">26</xref></sup> &#x201C;Adonoy was with him previously.&#x201D; We learn that he was not with him later. And Yiftoch was afflicted with ulcerations and the loss of his limbs, as it is said,<sup><xref rid="fn238">27</xref></sup> &#x201C;He was buried in the cities of Gilod.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn239">28</xref></sup> Another interpretation: &#x201C;She became the subject of a law in Yisroel&#x201D; relates to the following passage.<sup><xref rid="fn240">29</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[40]] Journeyed annually.</bold> This was established as a law.<sup><xref rid="fn241">30</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>To grieve.</bold> To weep.</p>
<ftnote id="fn212"><sup>1</sup>10:8,9.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn213"><sup>2</sup>Devarim, 2:29.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn214"><sup>3</sup>The three hundred year total is only accurate if certain of the years of subjugation are included in the years of the judge, and certain years are not, as Rashi explains below.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn215"><sup>4</sup>Ch. 12.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn216"><sup>5</sup>3:11</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn217"><sup>6</sup>Eight years. (3:8).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn218"><sup>7</sup>3:30.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn219"><sup>8</sup>3:14</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn220"><sup>9</sup>5:31.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn221"><sup>10</sup>Twenty years. (4:3.)</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn222"><sup>11</sup>6:1.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn223"><sup>12</sup>8:28.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn224"><sup>13</sup>9:22.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn225"><sup>14</sup>10:2</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn226"><sup>15</sup>10:3.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn227"><sup>16</sup>10:8.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn228"><sup>17</sup>This is Targum Yonasan&#x2019;s translation.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn229"><sup>18</sup><span dir="rtl"><bold>&#x05D4;&#x05B4;&#x05DB;&#x05B0;&#x05E8;&#x05B7;&#x05E2;&#x05B0;&#x05EA;&#x05BC;&#x05B4;&#x05E0;&#x05B4;&#x05D9;</bold></span>, with the &#x201C;<italic>cherik</italic>&#x201D; vocalization under the <span dir="rtl"><bold>&#x05EA;</bold></span>, is generally translated as referring to the first person neuter, &#x201C;I brought to the knees.&#x201D; Here, however, the translation is the feminine &#x201C;you brought to the knees.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn230"><sup>19</sup>Shir Hashirim, 4:9. Here, too, <span dir="rtl"><bold>&#x05DC;&#x05B4;&#x05D1;&#x05BC;&#x05B7;&#x05D1;&#x05BD;&#x05EA;&#x05BC;&#x05B4;&#x05E0;&#x05B4;&#x05D9;</bold></span>, with the &#x201C;<italic>cherik</italic>&#x201D; vocalization under the the <span dir="rtl"><bold>&#x05EA;</bold></span>, is translated as the feminine &#x201C;you captured my heart.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn231"><sup>20</sup>Not, as translated elsewhere, &#x201C;To descend,&#x201D; but &#x201C;To grieve.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn232"><sup>21</sup>Yeshaya, 15:3.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn233"><sup>22</sup><span dir="rtl"><bold>&#x05E8;&#x05D3;</bold></span> may also be translated as &#x201C;crushing.&#x201D; See Yeshaya, 45:1.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn234"><sup>23</sup>Yalkut, 67.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn235"><sup>24</sup>By informing him that a human being cannot be designated as an offering.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn236"><sup>25</sup>Pinchas, because it was Yiftoch who required his services; Yiftoch, because he was the supreme commander. (Yalkut, 68)</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn237"><sup>26</sup>Divrei Hayamim 1, 9:20.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn238"><sup>27</sup>Below, 12:7.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn239"><sup>28</sup>Individual limbs, like the entire body, require burial. The plural usage, &#x201C;cities&#x201D;, teaches that his burial took place in a number of cities&#x2014;wherever his limbs fell. (Yalkut, ibid.)</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn240"><sup>29</sup>She was the subject of a law requiring the daughters of Yisroel to visit her yearly.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn241"><sup>30</sup>This follows Rashi&#x2019;s second interpretation of v. 39. See fn.29.</ftnote>
</appendix>
<appendix>
<p><bold>[[1]] And crossed northward.</bold> They crossed the Yardein and travelled north in trans-Yardein to Gilod.</p>
<p><bold>[[4]] Since the contemptibles of Ephraim had said,</bold> &#x201C;What are you ,Gilod?&#x201D; The lowliest in Ephraim would mock Gilod, saying, &#x201C;Of what significance are you, Gilod, among Ephraim and among Menasheh?&#x201D; This is Targum Yonasan&#x2019;s interpretation.</p>
<p><bold>[[5]] The Gilodites captured the Yardein crossings.</bold> They posted sentries at the crossing areas.</p>
<p><bold>[[6]] Say Shiboles please.</bold> May I cross this river flow?<sup><xref rid="fn242">1</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>They were not proficient in proper pronunciation.</bold> They were speech deficient.</p>
<p><bold>[[8]] Ivtzan.</bold> Boaz.<sup><xref rid="fn243">2</xref></sup></p>
<ftnote id="fn242"><sup>1</sup>Shiboles&#x201D; is translated as &#x201C;flow&#x201D;.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn243"><sup>2</sup>The husband of Rus, ancestor of King David. (Bava Basra, 91:a)</ftnote>
</appendix>
<appendix>
<p><bold>[[4]] Freshly pressed or intoxicating wine</bold> Freshly pressed or aged wine.<sup><xref rid="fn244">1</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[5]] The razor [lit. flinger].</bold> The razor, as it flings off and casts away the hair.</p>
<p><bold>[[7]] Do not consume anything ritually defiled.</bold> Anything prohibited to the Nazirite.<sup><xref rid="fn245">2</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[8]] With the boy who will be [lit. who was] born.</bold> Who is destined to be born.</p>
<p><bold>[[11]] Behind his wife.</bold> Following her advice.</p>
<p><bold>[[12]] What regulations must we follow</bold> with the boy?</p>
<p><bold>How shall we treat him?</bold> What should appropriately be done with the boy, what must we do with him?<sup><xref rid="fn246">3</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[15]] Allow us to detain you</bold> as our house guest.</p>
<p><bold>[[17]] When your instructions reach us.</bold> If we are contacted with instructions to fulfill a mission for you, and we know and recognize your name,</p>
<p><bold>We shall honor you</bold> by fulfilling the mission.</p>
<p><bold>[[18]] When it is mystical.</bold> It is concealed. It changes constantly,<sup><xref rid="fn247">4</xref></sup> so that its identity remains unknown on any given day.</p>
<p><bold>[[23]] At this time [lit. at the time].</bold> At this time.</p>
<p><bold>He would not have apprised us in this way.</bold> He would not have apprised us of these tidings<sup><xref rid="fn248">5</xref></sup> if we deserved to die.</p>
<p><bold>[[25]] Pulsating within him.</bold> Visiting him intermittently.</p>
<ftnote id="fn244"><sup>1</sup>This is Targum Yonasan&#x2019;s translation.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn245"><sup>2</sup>Sotah, 9:b. This includes grape extract, in addition to wine. (Rashi, there).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn246"><sup>3</sup>Targum Yonasan. The question was not what must the boy do, but what must we do with him.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn247"><sup>4</sup>According to the angel&#x2019;s mission at that particular time. Cf. Rashi to Bereishis, 32:30.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn248"><sup>5</sup>Concerning the birth of a son.</ftnote>
</appendix>
<appendix>
<p><bold>[[4]] As He sought a pretext.</bold> An accusation with which to provoke a confrontation against them.</p>
<p><bold>[[7]] And discussed [lit. spoke with] the woman.</bold> He spoke of the woman<sup><xref rid="fn249">1</xref></sup> with her relatives. This is Targum Yonasan&#x2019;s rendition.</p>
<p><bold>[[8]] A colony of bees.</bold> A beehive&#x2014;a swarm of bees.</p>
<p><bold>[[9]] He dislodged it.</bold> This connotes the separation of an attached object. Similarly, with regard to a loaf attached to an oven, separation is described as &#x201C;dislodging&#x201D;&#x2014;<sup><xref rid="fn250">2</xref></sup> &#x201C;If one dislodges a loaf from the oven,&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn251">3</xref></sup> &#x201C;If one dislodges his hive,&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn252">4</xref></sup> as the honey is produced in wax combs attached to the walls of the hive in every area, extending from wall to wall along its circumference. Similarly, Targum Yonasan translates &#x201C;He removed it.&#x201D;</p>
<p><bold>[[10]] His father descended to discuss the woman.</bold> With regard to the woman.</p>
<p><bold>[[11]] Friends.</bold> Companions who formed the retinue of wedding attendants.</p>
<p><bold>[[15]] It was on the seventh day</bold> of the week, but not the seventh of the feast. It was, rather, the fourth of the feast days.</p>
<p><bold>Was it to impoverish us that you invited us here.</bold> Targum Yonasan renders: Was it to make us poor<sup><xref rid="fn253">5</xref></sup> that you called us here?<sup><xref rid="fn254">6</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[17]] The seven days.</bold> What remained of the seven days, after the fourth day.</p>
<p><bold>[[18]] Before sunset.</bold> Before the sun descended, as they still had time until nightfall.</p>
<p><bold>Plowed with my calf.</bold> This is allegorical&#x2014;if you had not questioned my wife.<sup><xref rid="fn255">7</xref>&#160;<xref rid="fn256">8</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[19]] The Divine spirit.</bold> A spirit of power, Divinely inspired.<sup><xref rid="fn257">9</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>Their garments.</bold> The garments which he had stripped from them.</p>
<p><bold>[[20]] To a Friend.</bold> To one of the wedding attendants.</p>
<ftnote id="fn249"><sup>1</sup>Not &#x201C;with&#x201D; the woman.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn250"><sup>2</sup>Shabbos, 117:b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn251"><sup>3</sup>Shabbos, 95:a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn252"><sup>4</sup>The honeycomb from the hive.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn253"><sup>5</sup><span dir="rtl"><bold>&#x05DC;&#x05B0;&#x05D9;&#x05B8;&#x05E8;&#x05B0;&#x05E9;&#x05C1;&#x05B5;&#x05E0;&#x05D5;&#x05BC;</bold></span> is not interpreted as &#x201C;to inherit us,&#x201D; but as &#x201C;to make us poor.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn254"><sup>6</sup><span dir="rtl"><bold>&#x05D4;&#x05B2;&#x05DC;&#x05B9;&#x05D0;</bold></span> is not interpreted as &#x201C;Did you not? but as &#x201C;here.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn255"><sup>7</sup>This is Targum Yonasan&#x2019;s translation.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn256"><sup>8</sup>Who is cherished as a young calf is cherished. (Sanhedrin, 21:a.)</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn257"><sup>9</sup>This is Targum Yonasan&#x2019;s translation.</ftnote>
</appendix>
<appendix>
<p><bold>[[3]] At this time I am innocent.</bold> I shall be justified in inflicting injury upon them.</p>
<p><bold>[[4]] Twisted.</bold> The tails, each into the next. <span dir="rtl"><bold>&#x05D5;&#x05B7;&#x05D9;&#x05B4;&#x05E4;&#x05B6;&#x05DF;</bold></span> implies that he himself turned, <span dir="rtl"><bold>&#x05D5;&#x05B7;&#x05D9;&#x05B6;&#x05E4;&#x05B6;&#x05DF;</bold></span> that he turned, or twisted, others. This usage applies with every word whose verbal root ends with <span dir="ltr"><bold>&#x05D4;</bold></span>.<sup><xref rid="fn258">1</xref></sup> &#x201C;The people increased;&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn259">2</xref></sup> &#x201C;He increased, in the people of Yehudah, lamentation&#x2026;.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn260">3</xref></sup> &#x201C;Yehudah went into exile from his homeland&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn261">4</xref></sup>&#x2014;went into exile. &#x201C;The king [of Ashur] exiled Yisroel to Ashur&#x201D; <sup><xref rid="fn262">5</xref></sup>&#x2014;exiled others.</p>
<p><bold>[[6]] The son-in-law of the Timnite.</bold> The son-in-law of the Pelishtite from Timnah.</p>
<p><bold>[[7]] Is this the way you behave.</bold> Perhaps you are accustomed to this&#x2014;shifting wives from one to another.</p>
<p><bold>[[8]] Cavalry and infantry [lit. calf and thigh].</bold> &#x201C;Horsemen and foot soldiers.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn263">6</xref></sup> The horseman is not supported by the thigh, but by the calf of the foot inserted into the metal stirrup hanging from the saddle.</p>
<p><bold>On the promontory</bold> of a crevice of the Eitam cliff. Similarly, &#x201C;The promontories of the cliffs,&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn264">7</xref></sup> &#x201C;[He] shall remove its branches.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn265">8</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[9]] They fanned out.</bold> They dispersed.</p>
<p><bold>At Lechi.</bold> The name of a place<sup><xref rid="fn266">9</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[10]] Why have you ascended against us.</bold> Are we not enslaved by you?</p>
<p><bold>To tie down Shimshon.</bold> In order that you tie him down and deliver him to us.</p>
<p><bold>[[13]] No&#x0021; We shall merely tie you down.</bold> We shall not execute you, but merely tie you down.</p>
<p><bold>[[14]] The spirit of Adonoy.</bold> A spirit of power, emanating from Adonoy.<sup><xref rid="fn267">10</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>His bonds</bold> which tied him down.</p>
<p><bold>[[15]] Moist.</bold> Wet. I saw a medical lexicon which refers to pus oozing from a wound as <span dir="rtl"><bold>&#x05D8;&#x05B0;&#x05E8;&#x05B4;&#x05D9;&#x05B8;&#x05D4;</bold></span>.</p>
<p><bold>[[16]] I amassed mounds</bold> with the jawbone of a donkey, amassing numerous mounds. &#x201C;With the jawbone of a donkey I hurled them into mounds.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn268">11</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[19]] The socket [lit. &#x201C;the mortar&#x201D;].</bold> The socket where the tooth is set is shaped like a mortar.</p>
<p><bold>Ein Hakorei.</bold> &#x201C;The wellspring which materialized through the cry of the one who called out to Adonoy.&#x201D;</p>
<ftnote id="fn258"><sup>1</sup>Such as <span dir="rtl"><bold>&#x05D2;&#x05B8;&#x05DC;&#x05B8;&#x05D4; ,&#x05E8;&#x05B8;&#x05D1;&#x05B8;&#x05D4; ,&#x05E4;&#x05B8;&#x05E0;&#x05B8;&#x05D4;</bold></span>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn259"><sup>2</sup>Shemos, 1:20.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn260"><sup>3</sup>Eichah, 2:5. Cf. Rashi there.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn261"><sup>4</sup>Melachim 2, 25:21.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn262"><sup>5</sup>Melachim 2, 17:6.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn263"><sup>6</sup>This is Targum Yonasan&#x2019;s translation. &#x201C;Calf&#x201D; refers to the horseman, supported by the calf, as Rashi explains, and &#x201C;thigh&#x201D; refers to the footsoldier, whose weight is supported by the thigh.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn264"><sup>7</sup>Yeshaya, 2:21</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn265"><sup>8</sup>Ibid, 10:33.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn266"><sup>9</sup>Not literally &#x201C;cheek&#x201D;.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn267"><sup>10</sup>This is Targum Yonasan&#x2019;s translation.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn268"><sup>11</sup>This is Targum Yonasan&#x2019;s translation.</ftnote>
</appendix>
<appendix>
<p><bold>[[2]] The Azites were informed.</bold> It was said to the people of Aza.</p>
<p><bold>They were silent [lit. &#x201C;They were muted&#x201D;].</bold> They acted in silence.</p>
<p><bold>[[3]] Uprooted them [lit. &#x201C;moved them&#x201D;].</bold> He uprooted them from their places.</p>
<p><bold>[[7]] Cords.</bold> Thin strings.</p>
<p><bold>[[9]] The source of his strength was not revealed.</bold> It was not necessary for him to exert himself when he snapped them.</p>
<p><bold>[[11]] With ropes.</bold> Thick rope.<sup><xref rid="fn269">1</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[13]] Tresses</bold> Locks. &#x201C;Pelous&#x201D; in old French.</p>
<p><bold>With the mounting pin.</bold> A wooden rod which the weaver uses to mount the threads of the warp. The name of the wood is &#x201C;ensouple&#x201D;, of the pin, &#x201C;ourdissuire&#x201D;.</p>
<p><bold>[[16]] And goaded him.</bold> She oppressed him. There is no similar word.</p>
<p><bold>[[18]] Delilah saw that he had confided to her.</bold> One instinctively recognizes the truth.<sup><xref rid="fn270">2</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[19]] [She] summoned the man.</bold> The nobles&#x2019; agent.</p>
<p><bold>[[21]] They brought him down to Aza.</bold> The location where his ruin began<sup><xref rid="fn271">3</xref>&#160;<xref rid="fn272">4</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>He became the miller. With grinding stones&#x2014;</bold>arduous labor. The Rabbis interpret this after their fashion.<sup><xref rid="fn273">5</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[25]] Between the pillars</bold> which supported the building.</p>
<p><bold>[[26]] And give me a hold.</bold> &#x201C;Palpare&#x201D; in old French, as in, &#x201C;Perhaps my father will touch me.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn274">6</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[28]] Please remember me.</bold> Remember the twenty years that I judged Yisroel without asking any of them to carry a staff from place to place.<sup><xref rid="fn275">7</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>Avenge one of my two eyes.</bold> The reward for my second eye reserve for me in the World to Come. At present, grant me the reward for one of them.<sup><xref rid="fn276">8</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[29]] Shimshon embraced.</bold> He grasped, &#x201C;embrasser&#x201D; in old French, as in &#x201C;The man trembled, and was embraced&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn277">9</xref></sup>&#x2014;he was embraced in a woman&#x2019;s arms.</p>
<ftnote id="fn269"><sup>1</sup>Unlike the thin string specified in v. 7.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn270"><sup>2</sup>Sotah, 9:b</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn271"><sup>3</sup>V.l.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn272"><sup>4</sup>Sotah, 9:b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn273"><sup>5</sup>According to their interpretation, the Pelishtites brought their wives to the prison to be impregnated by Shimshon, (Sotah, 10:a)</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn274"><sup>6</sup>Bereishis, 27:12.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn275"><sup>7</sup>Sotah, 10:a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn276"><sup>8</sup>Yalkut, 71.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn277"><sup>9</sup>Rus, 3:8.</ftnote>
</appendix>
<appendix>
<p><bold>[[1]] There was a man from Mount Ephraim.</bold> Although both incidents are recorded at the conclusion of this book, the episodes of Michah and the concubine at Givoh took place at the beginning of the period of Judges, during the days of Asniel ben Kenaz,<sup><xref rid="fn278">1</xref></sup> as it is said, &#x201C;They appointed, for themselves, the figure of Michah, etc., during the entire period of the <italic>Mishkon</italic> at Shiloh.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn279">2</xref></sup> We learn that, throughout the period of Shiloh, the graven figure of Michah was in existence.<sup><xref rid="fn280">3</xref></sup> Concerning the concubine at Givoh, it is said, about Yevus of Jerusalem, &#x201C;Let us not turn to an alien city&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn281">4</xref></sup> we learn that Jerusalem had not yet been conquered.<sup><xref rid="fn282">5</xref>&#160;<xref rid="fn283">6</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[2]] Stolen from you [lit. &#x201C;to you&#x201D;].</bold> Stolen from you.<sup><xref rid="fn284">7</xref></sup> Similarly,<sup><xref rid="fn285">8</xref></sup> &#x201C;For women were withheld &#x2018;to&#x2019; us,&#x201D;&#x2014;&#x2018;from&#x2019; us.</p>
<p><bold>When you cursed.</bold> You cursed whoever stole it, and even uttered the curse in my ear.</p>
<p><bold>Look, the silver.</bold> I confess to you, concerning it, that it is in my possession, as I stole it.</p>
<p><bold>[[3]] He returned the eleven hundred silver pieces to his mother.</bold> He verbalized his intent to return it to her, hence, wherever it was, it reverted to her possession.</p>
<p><bold>I expressly consecrated the silver, from my hand to my son&#x2019;s.</bold> I resolved to deliver it from my hand to yours for the purpose of making an image and a molten figure. Give it to me now, so that I may return it from my hand to you. Some say that this woman was Delilah, since Scripture specifies eleven hundred pieces of silver<sup><xref rid="fn286">9</xref></sup>. However, they are in error, as Michah preceded Shimshon by many years.<sup><xref rid="fn287">10</xref></sup> But the episodes are juxtaposed because of the corrupt silver, which was of equal value in each of the incidents. The silver inflicted injury in both cases.</p>
<p><bold>[[5]] An idolatrous temple</bold> [lit. &#x201C;temple of Elohim&#x201D;]. A temple of idol worship. Similarly, &#x201C;god&#x201D; throughout this chapter is profane, except for the following: &#x201C;Throughout the time that the Sanctuary of God was at Shiloh.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn288">11</xref>&#160;<xref rid="fn289">12</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>And inducted [lit. &#x201C;filled the hands of&#x201D;] one.</bold> He inducted him into the service of the image, to serve as its priest. Any induction process which a person enters for the purpose of achieving a position of prominence is described as &#x201C;filling the hands,&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn290">13</xref></sup> &#x201C;revetir&#x201D; in old French. When a person is charged with a position, it is described as &#x201C;reveture&#x201D; in old French.</p>
<p><bold>[[7]] Of the klan of Yehudah.</bold> He was a Leivi maternally.<sup><xref rid="fn291">14</xref></sup> However, the Rabbis<sup><xref rid="fn292">15</xref></sup> interpret that, because he behaved like Menasheh,<sup><xref rid="fn293">16</xref></sup> who was descended from Yehudah, he is described as &#x201C;of the klan of Yehudah.&#x201D; He was actually a Leivi, the son of Gershom, son of our master Moshe, as stated explicitly below, &#x201C;Yehonasan, son of Gershom, etc.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn294">17</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[8]] To make his way.</bold> The way by which he would journey.</p>
<p><bold>[[9]] Anywhere I will find</bold> a profitable livelihood.</p>
<p><bold>[[10]] Per year</bold> At the year&#x2019;s end.</p>
<p><bold>An appropriate wardrobe</bold> A pair of outfits appropriate for everyone&#x2019;s yearly requirements.</p>
<p><bold>An appropriate wardrobe.</bold> &#x201C;Appareillement&#x201D; in old French.</p>
<p><bold>And your board</bold> Your meals.</p>
<p><bold>The Levi acquiesced [lit. went]</bold> Followed his advice.</p>
<ftnote id="fn278"><sup>1</sup>3:9. Asniel was the first of the judges.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn279"><sup>2</sup>18:31.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn280"><sup>3</sup>Thus encompassing the period of Asniel, as his tenure began after the death of Yehoshua, when the Mishkon had already been established at Shiloh.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn281"><sup>4</sup>19:12.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn282"><sup>5</sup>It was later conquered by the tribe of Judah (1:8), during the time of Asniel (there, v.13).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn283"><sup>6</sup>Seder Olam, 12.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn284"><sup>7</sup><span dir="rtl"><bold>&#x05DC;&#x05DA;</bold></span>, lit. &#x201C;to you&#x201D;, may also be interpreted as &#x201C;from you&#x201D;.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn285"><sup>8</sup>Shmuel 1, 21:6</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn286"><sup>9</sup>See above 16:5.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn287"><sup>10</sup>See Rashi, v.l.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn288"><sup>11</sup>18:31.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn289"><sup>12</sup>Shevuos, 35:b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn290"><sup>13</sup>See Shemos, 28:41.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn291"><sup>14</sup>Paternally, he was descended from Yehudah. This explains why he was both &#x201C;of the klan of Yehudah&#x201D;, and a Levi.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn292"><sup>15</sup>Bava Basra, 109:b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn293"><sup>16</sup>The king who instituted idol worship throughout Eretz Yisroel. (Melachim 2, 21).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn294"><sup>17</sup>18:30.</ftnote>
</appendix>
<appendix>
<p><bold>[[1]] As there had not fallen to their lot.</bold> A suitable inheritance for them in the conquered territory, as it is said in Yehoshua, &#x201C;The boundry of Bnei Don extended from them.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn295">1</xref>&#160;<xref rid="fn296">2</xref></sup> This, too, teaches us that this episode took place at the very beginning of the period of the judges.<sup><xref rid="fn297">3</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[3]] Who brought you here.</bold> There are numerous questions here. Are you not descended from our teacher Moshe,  to whom it was said, &#x201C;Do not come close here,&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn298">4</xref></sup> &#x201C;Who provided mankind with the mouth?&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn299">5</xref></sup> and &#x201C;What is this in your hand?&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn300">6</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[5]] Please inquire of God</bold> through the figurines, which communicate by sorcery.</p>
<p><bold>[[6]] The route you will follow is before Adonoy</bold> It is revealed before the Holy One, blessed is He, but these [figurines] are worthless.</p>
<p><bold>[[7]] With nothing to put them to shame.</bold> No one ever needed anothers&#x2019; help, who might have rebuffed him empty handedly, thus humiliating him, as stated below, &#x201C;Nothing is lacking.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn301">7</xref></sup> So I have heard.</p>
<p><bold>There is a dearth of heirs.</bold> There are few heirs, so that if they should be killed, no other claimants will wage war against those who occupy the territory.</p>
<p><bold>They were distant.</bold> From the support of the Tzidonians.</p>
<p><bold>And they were not allied with anyone.</bold> They had not entered into any treaty requiring others to come to their assistance in times of need.</p>
<p><bold>[[8]] What is your response?</bold> As if to say, &#x201C;what is your response?&#x201D; What have you found, in the territory apportioned to us? Are the people strong or weak?&#x2019;</p>
<p><bold>[[9]] You are apathetic</bold> Lazy.</p>
<p><bold>[[21]] The bulky cargo.</bold> The loads. Anything which moved ponderously, thus making it impossible to move quickly should the local inhabitants pursue them.</p>
<p><bold>The bulky cargo.</bold> &#x201C;Pezantume&#x201D; in old French.</p>
<p><bold>[[23]] They turned their faces.</bold> The sons of Don turned towards those who shouted at them.</p>
<p><bold>[[24]] What else do I have.</bold> What else remains for me?</p>
<p><bold>[[25]] Bitter tempered men.</bold> There are angry men in our company.</p>
<p><bold>[[27]] Laish.</bold> The city&#x2019;s name. The book of Yehoshua entitles it &#x201C;Leshem,&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn302">8</xref></sup> because they discovered, there, a precious gem called &#x201C;leshem.&#x201D; This was inlaid in the Choshen plate,<sup><xref rid="fn303">9</xref></sup> and symbolized the tribe of Don, whose name was inscribed on it. Thus, they were certain that this was actually their ancestral property.</p>
<p><bold>[[30]] Ben Menasheh.</bold> In deference to Moshe, the letter &#x201C;nun&#x201D; was included, thus altering the name. It is scripturally suspended to indicate that he was actually not Menasheh, but Moshe.<sup><xref rid="fn304">10</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>Until the day of the exile from the land.</bold> During the time of Sancheriv, at the first exile.</p>
<ftnote id="fn295"><sup>1</sup>Yehoshua, 19:47. See Rashi there.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn296"><sup>2</sup>When the apportioning of the land among the tribes was completed.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn297"><sup>3</sup>In addition to the evidence presented by Rashi above, 17:1.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn298"><sup>4</sup>Shemos, 3:5.<span dir="rtl"><bold>&#x05D4;&#x05B2;&#x05DC;&#xFB4B;&#x05DD;</bold></span>, &#x201C;here&#x201D;, in our passage corresponds with <span dir="rtl"><bold>&#x05D4;&#x05B2;&#x05DC;&#xFB4B;&#x05DD;</bold></span>, &#x201C;here&#x201D;, in the statement to Moshe.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn299"><sup>5</sup>Ibid, 4:11. <span dir="rtl"><bold>&#x05E4;&#x05B6;&#x05D6;</bold></span> in our passage coresponds with <span dir="rtl"><bold>&#x05E4;&#x05B6;&#x05D4;</bold></span> &#x201C;mouth&#x201D;, there.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn300"><sup>6</sup>Ibid, 4:2. <span dir="rtl"><bold>&#x05DE;&#x05B8;&#x05D4;&#x2026;&#x05D1;&#x05BC;&#x05B8;&#x05D6;&#x05B6;&#x05D4;</bold></span> corresponds with <span dir="rtl"><bold>&#x05DE;&#x05B7;&#x05D4; &#x05D6;&#x05B6;&#x05D4;</bold></span> there.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn301"><sup>7</sup>Below v.10.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn302"><sup>8</sup>Yehoshua 19:47.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn303"><sup>9</sup>The sacred Urim Vetumim oracles, which spelled out the Divine message for those inquirii of Adonoy. (Yoma, 73:b).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn304"><sup>10</sup>Bava Basra 109b.</ftnote>
</appendix>
<appendix>
<p><bold>[[2]] His concubine strayed away from him</bold> She strayed away from his home to the outside. The word <span dir="rtl"><bold>&#x05D6;&#x05B0;&#x05E0;&#x05D5;&#x05BC;&#x05EA;</bold></span>, &#x201C;promiscuity,&#x201D; always denotes departure&#x2014;&#x201C;One who departs to the outside,&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn305">1</xref></sup> who leaves her husband and loves another.</p>
<p><bold>[[6]] Give your assent, and remain overnight.</bold> Tonight.</p>
<p><bold>[[9]] Has waned.</bold> The sun [has waned] from full strength, and has begun setting.</p>
<p><bold>It is the time of day for encamping.</bold> The time when all travellers turn in to encamp indoors.</p>
<p><bold>[[12]] To Giv&#x2019;oh.</bold> Giv&#x2019;oh of Binyomin.</p>
<p><bold>[[13]] We will spend the night.</bold> As in <span dir="rtl"><bold>&#x05D5;&#x05B0;&#x05DC;&#x05B7;&#x05E0;&#x05B0;&#x05E0;&#x05D5;&#x05BC;</bold></span>. The period punctuating the <span dir="rtl"><bold>&#x05E0;</bold></span> serves as a replacement for a second <span dir="ltr"><bold>&#x05E0;</bold></span>.<sup><xref rid="fn306">2</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[18]] To the Sanctuary of Adonoy.</bold> I am going to Shiloh.<sup><xref rid="fn307">3</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[21]] And fed produce to the donkeys.</bold> He gave produce to the donkeys. He fed produce, &#x201C;aprovender&#x201D; in old French.</p>
<p><bold>[[22]] We want to have relations with him</bold> to sodomize him.</p>
<p><bold>[[28]] There was no answer,</bold> for she was dead.</p>
<ftnote id="fn305"><sup>1</sup>This is Targum Yonasan&#x2019;s rendition of <span dir="rtl"><bold>&#x05D6;&#x05D5;&#x05B9;&#x05E0;&#x05B8;&#x05D4;</bold></span>, &#x201C;promiscuous woman.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn306"><sup>2</sup>The suffix <span dir="rtl"><bold>&#x05E0;&#x05D5;</bold></span> denotes the plural usage. When the letter <span dir="rtl"><bold>&#x05E0;</bold></span> appears in the root, as in <span dir="rtl"><bold>&#x05DC;&#x05D9;&#x05DF;</bold></span>, the additional <span dir="rtl"><bold>&#x05E0;</bold></span> is dropped, and is replaced by a period in the original <span dir="rtl"><bold>&#x05E0;</bold></span>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn307"><sup>3</sup>The Mishkon was at Shiloh. (Yehosnua, 18:1).</ftnote>
</appendix>
<appendix>
<p><bold>[[2]] The leaders of the entire people.</bold> The heads of the entire people.<sup><xref rid="fn308">1</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[5]] They thought they would murder me.</bold> They intended to murder me. &#x201C;Apesment&#x201D; in old French.</p>
<p><bold>[[10]] When taking action in their engagement</bold> in this engagement with Givas Binyomin, as befits their entirely loathsome, etc.</p>
<p><bold>[[11]] Comrades.</bold> In unified counsel.</p>
<p><bold>[[12]] To all the tribes of Binyomin.</bold> Their ten clans were considered ten families, so that twelve tribes would emanate from Rochel.<sup><xref rid="fn309">2</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[16]] With shriveled right arms.</bold> Their right arms were shrunken. They could not utilize them, as if they were closed, as in &#x201C;Let not the well close its mouth over me.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn310">3</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>Each of them</bold> These seven hundred men.</p>
<p><bold>At a hair.</bold> A strand of hair.</p>
<p><bold>And not miss.</bold> And not err.</p>
<p><bold>[[18]] Yehudah first.</bold> But they did not try to inquire whether they would be victorious or vanquished. When they ultimately tried, He replied, &#x201C;Go up, for tomorrow I shall deliver them into your hand.&#x201D; They were consistent, and fulfilled their promise.<sup><xref rid="fn311">4</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[21]] They crushed.</bold> They were punished because they were not equally vengeful over the incident of the figure of Michah,<sup><xref rid="fn312">5</xref></sup> which had already taken place.<sup><xref rid="fn313">6</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[33]] Baal Tamar.</bold> The plain of Yericho.<sup><xref rid="fn314">7</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>Poured.</bold> Extended themselves, as in &#x201C;He shall draw the Yardein into his mouth,&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn315">8</xref></sup> &#x201C;You drew me from the womb.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn316">9</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>Maareh Gev&#x2019;ah.</bold> From a narrow pass, the &#x201C;nakedness,&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn317">10</xref></sup> or exposed overlook of Givas Binyomin; its uncovered part from which it was defenseless against conquest, as in, &#x201C;You have come to gaze at the nakedness of the land.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn318">11</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[36]] The Yisroelite troops gave.</bold> Those in the field gave ground to Binyomin to escape to Givoh, since the Yisroelites depended on the ambushers to advance toward them.</p>
<p><bold>[[37]] The ambushers sounded the signal.</bold> The shofar blast. Another interpretation: With the shofar, they drew the people with them to the city.</p>
<p><bold>[[38]] A time frame was pre-arranged</bold> At the outset, a signal was arranged between the Yisroelites and the ambushers, whereby the ambushers would raise continuous smoke from the city. The Yisroelites would thus understand that the ambushers had conquered Givoh.</p>
<p><bold>Clouds of smoke.</bold> High hanging smoke.</p>
<p><bold>[[39]] The Yisroelite troops retreated.</bold> Scripture now returns to the beginning of the narrative, reviewing and explaining how the twenty five thousand mentioned above<sup><xref rid="fn319">12</xref></sup> fell, and where they fell.</p>
<p><bold>[[42]] While those in the city.</bold> The ambushers who had penetrated the city demolished the tribe from within the city.</p>
<p><bold>[[43]] The [lit. crowned] Binyomin.</bold> They encircled Binyomin the way a crown encircles the head. Similarly, &#x201C;The mighty of Bashan encircled me,&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn320">13</xref></sup> and, &#x201C;For the villain encircles the saint.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn321">14</xref></sup> Also, the word &#x201C;wreath&#x201D; connotes encirclement, as in, &#x201C;Shaul and his troops encircled [lit. wreathed] David and his troops in order to seize them&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn322">15</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>Called for their pursuit.</bold> They called for pursuit behind them&#x2014;they shouted to each other to pursue.</p>
<p><bold>And intercepted them at rest.</bold> At the cities, where they generally rested, they intercepted them.</p>
<p><bold>Intercepted them.</bold> Caught them. There is a similar term in the Talmud, &#x201C;He pursued him a parsa in the sand, but did not catch him.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn323">16</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>Up to the area facing Givoh.</bold> East of Givoh.</p>
<p><bold>[[44]] There fell, from Binyomin,</bold> eighteen thousand troops In the field, in the thick of battle.</p>
<p><bold>[[45]] They gleaned them.</bold> Killing constantly, like plucking gleanings after reaping.</p>
<p><bold>Five thousand troops.</bold> Thus totaling twenty three thousand.</p>
<p><bold>Until Gid&#x2019;om.</bold> The name of a place.</p>
<p><bold>Striking down, of them, two thousand troops.</bold> Thus totaling twenty-five thousand mentioned above.<sup><xref rid="fn324">17</xref></sup> The remaining one hundred recorded above<sup><xref rid="fn325">18</xref></sup> fell at unnamed locations.</p>
<p><bold>[[48]] Turned to the sons of Binyomin</bold> in all the cities.</p>
<p><bold>Completely annihilating the cities.</bold> They annihilated all the inhabitants of the cities,</p>
<p><bold>Including the cattle&#x2014;</bold>the people are included in &#x201C;completely annihilating,&#x201D; since <span dir="rtl"><bold>&#x05DE;&#x05BC;&#x05B0;&#x05EA;&#x05B9;&#x05DD;</bold></span> denotes absolute annihilation. There is a problem with the location of one thousand, as twenty-six thousand were counted in the cities, and seven hundred at Givoh;<sup><xref rid="fn326">19</xref></sup> here, those who fell totaled twenty-five thousand, one hundred troops,<sup><xref rid="fn327">20</xref></sup> and six hundred escaped to Rimon cliff.<sup><xref rid="fn328">21</xref></sup> Evidently, one thousand fled to the cities, and fell the following day when the Bnei Yisroel turned to the cities of Binyomin to annihilate the women and children.</p>
<ftnote id="fn308"><sup>1</sup>This is Targum Yonasan&#x2019;s translation.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn309"><sup>2</sup>The ten clans and the tribes of Menashe and Efraim.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn310"><sup>3</sup>Tehilim, 69:16.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn311"><sup>4</sup>V.28.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn312"><sup>5</sup>Chapters 17, 18.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn313"><sup>6</sup>Sanhedrin, 103:b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn314"><sup>7</sup>&#x201C;Tamar&#x201D;, lit. &#x201C;date&#x201D;, alludes to Yericho, &#x201C;The city of dates.&#x201D; Devarim, 34:3.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn315"><sup>8</sup>Eyov, 40:23.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn316"><sup>9</sup>Tehilim, 22:10.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn317"><sup>10</sup>&#x201C;Maareh&#x201D; is from <italic>&#x201C;Ervah,&#x201D;</italic> nakedness.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn318"><sup>11</sup>Beraishis, 42:9. Yoseif accused his brothers of spying, claiming. that they were seeking Egypt&#x2019;s &#x201C;nakedness,&#x201D; or exposed, defenseless areas.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn319"><sup>12</sup>V.35.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn320"><sup>13</sup>Tehilim, 22:13.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn321"><sup>14</sup>Chabakuk, 1:4.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn322"><sup>15</sup>Shmuel 1, 23:26.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn323"><sup>16</sup>Kesubos, 60:b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn324"><sup>17</sup>V.35.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn325"><sup>18</sup>Ibid.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn326"><sup>19</sup>V.15.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn327"><sup>20</sup>V. 46.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn328"><sup>21</sup>V. 47. This totals 25,700, whereas the total in v. 15 was 26,700.</ftnote>
</appendix>
<appendix>
<p><bold>[[3]] Will be eliminated</bold> Removed.<sup><xref rid="fn329">1</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[6]] Were regretful</bold> They reversed themselves,<sup><xref rid="fn330">2</xref></sup> and contemplated escape for them.</p>
<p><bold>[[12]] Four hundred virgin maids</bold> They placed them over the openings of wine barrels. Those with carnal knowledge emitted an aroma, the virgins did not.<sup><xref rid="fn331">3</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[14]] This did not satisfy</bold> They were insufficient for them.</p>
<p><bold>[[17]] The survivors must inherit the ancestral property</bold> The tribe&#x2019;s ancestral property remains unclaimed; let us devise a plan whereby they may father children, so that the property will fall into the possession of the remaining survivors, and a tribe will not be obliterated from Yisroel.</p>
<p><bold>[[19]] East [lit. &#x201C;sunrise&#x201D;] of the road.</bold> To the east of the road. Shiloh was north of Beis El, south of Levonah, and east of the road ascending from Beis El to Shechem.</p>
<p><bold>[[22]] To fight us</bold> To go to war against us.</p>
<p><bold>We shall tell them we were merciful with them.</bold> We were merciful with them because they did not know what to do, as we could not provide each of these men with a wife at the time of the war with Yoveish Gilod, except for four hundred of them. And if it is your oath that disturbs you, there is nothing sinful here on your part, since you were not the ones who provided them with your daughters, so that you would now be blameworthy. Peaceful salutations, have no fear&#x0021;</p>
<ftnote id="fn329"><sup>1</sup><span dir="rtl"><bold>&#x05E4;&#x05E7;&#x05D3;</bold></span> is sometimes translated as &#x201C;remembered&#x201D; (Bereishis, 50:25). Here, however, the translation is &#x201C;removed,&#x201D; or &#x201C;eliminated.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn330"><sup>2</sup><span dir="rtl"><bold>&#x05D5;&#x05B7;&#x05D9;&#x05B4;&#x05E0;&#x05BC;&#x05B8;&#x05D7;&#x05B2;&#x05DE;&#x05D5;&#x05BC;</bold></span> is translated as &#x201C;they regretted,&#x201D; rather than &#x201C;they were comforted.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn331"><sup>3</sup>Yevamos, 60:b.</ftnote>
</appendix>
</book>
