<book>
<chapter>
<title><bold>SECTION ON CHARITY<br/><small>FROM THE</small><br/>SHULHAN ARUKH</bold></title>
<p><italic>Article 247.</italic></p>
<p>1.&#x2014;It is a positive Biblical command to give Charity according to one&#x2019;s means. There are numerous positive commands as to Charity; and also a negative command not to close one&#x2019;s eyes to charity, for it is written, &#x201C;Thou shalt not harden thy heart nor shut thy hand [from thy poor brother].&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn1">1</xref></sup> And he who closes his eyes to it is called &#x201C;wicked&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn2">2</xref></sup> and is regarded as if he worships idols. One should take great heed in giving alms that he be not the cause of bloodshed, for the poor man in need may die before help reaches him if it is not offered quickly, as in the story of Nahum of Gimzo.<sup><xref rid="fn3">3</xref></sup></p>
<p>2.&#x2014;No man is ever impoverished from giving alms, nor is evil or harm ever caused by it; as it is written, &#x201C;And the work of righteousness shall be peace.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn4">4</xref></sup></p>
<p>3.&#x2014;Whosoever has compassion on the poor, the Holy One, blessed be He, has compassion on him.</p>
<p align="blockquote">RMI.<sup><xref rid="fn5">5</xref></sup>&#x2014;Let man realize that he himself is forever seeking sustenance at the hand of God, and just as God answers his prayer, so should he answer the prayer of the poor. Let him also realize that the world is a revolving sphere, and that eventually he or his son or his grandson may be reduced to such circumstances.</p>
<p>4.&#x2014;Charity prevents threatened punishment from Heaven, and in famine it delivereth from death, as in the story of the widow of Zarephath.<sup><xref rid="fn6">1</xref></sup></p>
<p><italic>Article 248.</italic></p>
<p>1.&#x2014;Everyone is obliged to contribute to charity. Even a poor man who is himself [partly] maintained by Charity should give a portion of what he receives. If one would give less than his due, the Court used to bring pressure to bear and punish him for contempt of court until he would give the amount assessed; and if he persisted in his refusal, they would seize his goods to that amount [in his presence].</p>
<p>2.&#x2014;A pledge may be taken as security for the Charity tax even on Friday afternoon.<sup><xref rid="fn7">2</xref></sup></p>
<p>3. Orphans are not assessed even for ransoming captives (not even wealthy orphans) unless the assessment is made for their glory, to maintain their reputation.</p>
<p>4.&#x2014;Gabba&#x00EF;m,<sup><xref rid="fn8">3</xref></sup> in collecting charity, should accept only small values from women, slaves, or children, because in case of valuables we fear they were obtained by theft or robbery. As to what is to be considered of small value, that depends upon the wealth or poverty of the master. This applies to cases in general; but where the master objects, Gabba&#x00EF;m are forbidden to receive anything from them.</p>
<p>5. If the wife engages a teacher for her son and the husband is aware of it and is silent, we assume he is pleased with it; but if he objects immediately upon hearing of it, her transaction is nullified (even though she manage affairs in the house).</p>
<p>6.&#x2014;A son who eats at his father&#x2019;s table, or a servant who eats at his master&#x2019;s table, may give a piece of bread to a pauper or to a friend&#x2019;s child without fear of being accused of robbery; for such is the way of householders.</p>
<p>7.&#x2014;A well-to-do man who gives more than his share to Charity, or who straitens himself to pay the collector in order not to be embarrassed,&#x2014;from such a man it is forbidden to demand or claim his dues; and the Gabbai who humiliates him by asking for it, will be called to account in the future by the Holy One, blessed be He.</p>
<p>8. He who wishes to be deserving of divine reward, shall conquer his evil inclinations and open wide his hand, and everything [done or given] in the name of Heaven shall be of the best and the finest. If he build a house of worship, let it be more beautiful than his dwelling; if he feed a hungry one, let him give him to eat of the best and the sweetest on his table; if he clothe one naked, let him clothe him with one of his finest garments; if he consecrate anything, let him consecrate from the best of his property; and so, too, the Bible says: &#x201C;All the fat is Jehovah&#x2019;s.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn9">1</xref></sup></p>
<p><italic>Article 249.</italic></p>
<p>1.&#x2014;The amount of charity one should give is as follows: if one can but afford, let him give as much as is needed. Under ordinary circumstances, a fifth of one&#x2019;s property is most laudable. To give one-tenth is the average disposition. But to give less than one-tenth is niggardly. When the Rabbis said a &#x201C;fifth&#x201D; they meant a fifth of the property the first year only and a fifth of the profits in succeeding years.</p>
<p align="blockquote">RMI.&#x2014;But a man should not squander more than one-fifth to charity, so that he might not himself become a public charge. This refers only to his lifetime. Of course, at the time of death one may leave for charity as much as he pleases.</p>
<p>2.&#x2014;One should never give less than one-third of a Shekel a year and if he gives less than this, he does not fulfil the command to be charitable.</p>
<p>3.&#x2014;Charity should be given with a friendly countenance, with joy, and with a good heart; the giver should, sympathize with the poor man, and should speak words of comfort to him. If he gives with a displeased countenance he loses his reward.</p>
<p>4.&#x2014;If the poor man stretches out his hand and he has nothing to give him, he should not scold and raise his voice to him, but should speak gently to him and show him his goodness of heart; namely, that he wishes to give him something but cannot.</p>
<p align="blockquote">RMI.&#x2014;It is forbidden to turn away a poor man entirely empty-handed. Let him give something, if only a fig, for it is written, &#x201C;Oh, let not the oppressed return ashamed.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn10">1</xref></sup></p>
<p>5.&#x2014;If he can induce others to give, his reward is greater than the reward of the one who gives.</p>
<p>6.&#x2014;The following are eight grades of charity work, arranged in a descending scale. The noblest form is to strengthen the hand of an Israelite in need, to give him a gift or a loan, or to join him in partnership, or to find him work, that he may not become a public charge and beggar; and it is with reference to such a mode of charity that the Bible says, &#x201C;&#x2026; thou shalt uphold him.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn11">1</xref></sup></p>
<p>7.&#x2014;The next highest form of doing charity is to give in such a way that the giver should not know to whom he gives; nor should the receiver know from whom he receives. Contributing to a charity fund is a close analogy; but one should not contribute to a fund unless he knows that the official in charge of it is trustworthy and knows how to manage it properly.</p>
<p>8.&#x2014;A somewhat lower form than that is when the giver knows to whom he gives but the receiver knows not from whom he receives; as the greatest of our sages used to do when they would secretly throw money into the doorways of the poor. This method is especially recommended where those appointed over the charities do not manage them properly.</p>
<p>9.&#x2014;It is a still lower form when the poor man knows from whom he takes, but the giver knows not to whom he gives; as when the sages would tie money in a corner of a sheet and throw it over the shoulder, so that the poor might come and take it without humiliation.</p>
<p>10.&#x2014;A still lower form&#x2014;to give before being asked.</p>
<p>11.&#x2014;Next,&#x2014;to give a sufficient sum after the asking.</p>
<p>12.&#x2014;To give, even what is insufficient, but with a pleasing countenance.</p>
<p align="blockquote">RMI.&#x2014;On the other hand a man should not pride himself on the charity he gives; for if he does, he not only receives no reward but there is punishment in store for him. However one may have his name inscribed on anything he donates, as a. remembrance,&#x2014;in fact, it is the proper thing to do.</p>
<p>13.&#x2014;The lowest form of charity is to give grudgingly.</p>
<p>14.&#x2014;It is well to give a coin to some poor man before every prayer, as it is written, &#x201C;As for me, I will behold thy face in righteousness&#x201D; [or, <italic>&#x201C;</italic>&#x2026; with charity&#x201D;].<sup><xref rid="fn12">1</xref></sup></p>
<p>15.&#x2014;The Gabba&#x00EF;m may use charity funds in their possession as dowries for poor virgins, for there is no greater charity than this.</p>
<p>16.&#x2014;There is an authority that holds that Synagogue is more important than charity, but that maintaining poor boys in the study of the Law or supporting sick poor people is more important than the maintenance of a Synagogue.</p>
<p><italic>Article 250.</italic></p>
<p>1.&#x2014;How much is to be given to a poor man? Sufficient for his need in that which he wanteth.<sup><xref rid="fn13">2</xref></sup> Thus, if he is hungry, he should be fed; if he needs clothing, he should be clothed; if he lacks household utensils, they should be purchased for him; and even if he had been accustomed before he was impoverished to ride on horseback with a slave running before him, he should be furnished with a horse and a slave. And so each and every one should be supplied with what he needs.<sup><xref rid="fn14">3</xref></sup> If it is fit to give him [merely] a slice of bread, give him a slice; if it is proper to give him dough, give him dough; if he ought to be provided with lodging, too, provide a bed for him. If it is fit to give him a warm meal, give him warm food; if cold lunch, then cold lunch. If he has to be fed [like an infant] then he must be fed. If he is unmarried and he comes to take a wife, the community should find him a mate; but first they should rent him a home, prepare him a bed and furnish him with necessary household utensils, and then marry him off.</p>
<p align="blockquote">RMI.&#x2014;It appears that all this applies to Gabba&#x00EF;m over public funds or to many doing charitable work together, but every individual is not bound to satisfy all the needs of a poor man who may chance to come his way. What he ought to do is to arouse public interest in a worthy case; but if he lives far from men, he should give what he can afford.</p>
<p>2.&#x2014;A poor woman who has an opportunity of marrying, shall receive not less than fifty Zuz; and if there is enough in the treasury, she should be maintained as honorably as is befitting her.</p>
<p>3.&#x2014;A pauper who begs from house to house should be given only a small sum from the Kuphah.<sup><xref rid="fn15">1</xref></sup></p>
<p>4.&#x2014;A poor man, who goes from place to place, shall receive not less than a loaf of bread costing a dupondium, when four S&#x2019;ah of wheat are worth one Sela. If he remains over night, he should be given a couch to sleep upon and a bolster under his head, and oil and small fruit; and if it is Sabbath, he should be provided with food for three meals, and oil, small fruit, fish and herbs; and if he is known [to be worthy], he should be given as much as is befitting his honor.</p>
<p>5.&#x2014;If the poor in a city are numerous, and the rich say they should go and beg, and the middle classes say they should not beg but be supported by the members of the community in proportion to their wealth, the law is as the latter say.</p>
<p><italic>Article 251.</italic></p>
<p>1.&#x2014;If one wilfully and repeatedly transgresses even one of the Biblical commands and does not repent, we are not obliged to support him or to lend him money; (but we should support the heathen poor<sup><xref rid="fn16">1</xref></sup> with the Jewish poor for the sake of peace).<sup><xref rid="fn17">2</xref></sup></p>
<p>2.&#x2014;One who transgresses even one command in a sheer spirit of defiance; as, for example, when he eats the flesh of an animal not slaughtered according to the ritual rules in a place where kosher meat is available,&#x2014;such a person it is forbidden to ransom if made captive. (But when one is a transgressor on account of an irresistible appetite, they may ransom him if they wish, but they are not obliged to.)</p>
<p>3.&#x2014;Helping one&#x2019;s grown up sons or daughters in need when he is not obliged to&#x2014;in order to give his sons an opportunity of studying the Law, or to keep his daughters in the right path&#x2014;and presenting gifts to one&#x2019;s father in need,&#x2014;all this comes under the general head of Charity. In fact, such charity is to be preferred to other forms. Not only a father or child, but any relative should be given preference to a stranger; a brother of one&#x2019;s father, to a brother of one&#x2019;s mother; the poor of his own house to the poor of the city at large; the poor of his own city to the poor of other cities; and the poor that dwell in the Holy Land to those that dwell in other lands.</p>
<p>4.&#x2014;The community can compel a father to support an impoverished son, and even where the son is an adult, the father is taxed more than the other wealthy men. (And so with other relatives).</p>
<p>5.&#x2014;Once a man has contributed a sum of money to the Gabba&#x00EF;m, neither he nor his heirs have any power over it, but the community can do with it what is pleasing in the eyes of God and man.</p>
<p align="blockquote">RMI.&#x2014;But if he made the donation without specification, before the money reaches the Gabbai, we give it to his poor relatives, because we presume that he meant it for his poor relatives. And this, only if he had poor relatives at the time of the donation. But if they were rich at the time and then became poor, we do not give it to them. All this applies to one making an individual donation; but if he donates in connection with other members of the community, we presume that he leaves it to the judgment of the community to dispose of it in any manner deemed fit.</p>
<p>6.&#x2014;Let the poor be members of thy household.<sup><xref rid="fn18">1</xref></sup></p>
<p>7.&#x2014;Feeding the hungry should precede clothing the naked.</p>
<p>8.&#x2014;If a man and a woman ask for food, the woman is given the preference; and so, too, if they ask for clothing. So also, if two orphans, a man and a woman, come to be married off, the woman is given the precedence.</p>
<p>9.&#x2014;If many poor seek help and there is not enough money in the treasury to help them all, a priest is given preference before a Levite; a Levite before an ordinary Israelite; an Israelite before a Halal;<sup><xref rid="fn19">2</xref></sup> a Halal before a child of unknown fatherhood; such a one before a foundling; a foundling before a bastard; a bastard before a Nathin;<sup><xref rid="fn20">3</xref></sup> a Nathin before a proselyte; a proselyte before an emancipated slave. This applies only in case they are equal in learning. But between a bastard a scholar and a high priest an ignoramus, the scholarly bastard is given the preference; and so whosoever is greater in learning is preferred. However, if the father or teacher of the charity distributor is among the poor seeking aid, the teacher, or the father (provided he too is a scholar) is given the preference, even if there is a far greater scholar among them.</p>
<p>10.&#x2014;If one comes and says, &#x201C;Give me food,&#x201D; no investigation is made to see that he is not an impostor, but he is given food at once. If he is destitute and asks for clothing, the case is investigated, and if he is found worthy, he is immediately furnished with raiment.</p>
<p>11.&#x2014;Rabbi [Judah the Prince] grieved that he had given his bread to an illiterate,<sup><xref rid="fn21">1</xref></sup> because those years were years of dearth and what the illiterate ate might have been given to a scholar. But if it had not been a time of scarcity, he would have been obliged to sustain him. However, if one is on the point of starvation, he must be given food, even though there is a possibility that a scholar will later be in need on account of it.</p>
<p>12.&#x2014;Two poor men who are required to give to charity, may pay their obligations by giving alms to one another.</p>
<p align="blockquote">RMI.&#x2014;This refers to Charity in the ordinary sense. But if the community imposes it as a fine upon them for some misdemeanor that they give a certain sum to Charity, they can not give it to one another; for that would not be paying a fine.</p>
<p>13.&#x2014;A congregation in need of a Rabbi and a Public Reader, but unable to engage both, should give the preference to the former, provided he is a distinguished rabbi well versed in the Teachings and Laws; otherwise, a Reader should be engaged.</p>
<p align="blockquote">RMI.&#x2014;The Rabbi should not be maintained out of the charity fund, as it is a disgrace both for him and for the city; but the community should provide him another source of income. However, gifts of individuals are perfectly honorable.</p>
<p>14.&#x2014;The community authorities may use even school-funds if necessary, for the payment of the annual per-capita tax of thirty Peshitim<sup><xref rid="fn22">1</xref></sup> to the commander of the city&#x2019;s troops, because it is a matter of life and death; for if they will not come to terms with him now, many poor people, not having the wherewithal to pay, will be beaten and stripped naked.</p>
<p><italic>Article 252.</italic></p>
<p>1.&#x2014;Ransoming captives comes before feeding or clothing the poor. There is no act of charity more meritorious than ransoming captives; therefore, money collected for any worthy purpose whatsoever may be used as ransom, even if originally collected for the erection of a Synagogue. And further: even if the building materials have already been bought and the beams squared (which makes it a grave offense to sell them for any other purpose) nevertheless, it is permitted to sell them to raise a ransom. However, if the structure is already erected it should not be sold. (Still, if one donates a Sela to Charity without specification, ransoming is not to be understood in the general term of charity, and the Sela should not be used for this purpose without the knowledge of the members of the community.)</p>
<p>2.&#x2014;He who shuts his eyes against the ransoming of captives transgresses the negative precepts, &#x201C;Thou shalt not harden thy heart&#x201D;,<sup><xref rid="fn23">2</xref></sup> and, &#x201C;[Thou shalt not] shut thy hand&#x201D;;<sup><xref rid="fn23">2</xref></sup> also this, &#x201C;Neither shalt thou stand against the blood of thy neighbor&#x201D;,<sup><xref rid="fn24">3</xref></sup> and this, &#x201C;He shall not rule with rigor over him in thy sight&#x201D;;<sup><xref rid="fn25">1</xref></sup> and he neglects the positive precepts, &#x201C;Thou shalt surely open thy hand unto him&#x201D;,<sup><xref rid="fn26">2</xref></sup> and, &#x201C;that thy brother may live with thee,&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn27">3</xref></sup> and, &#x201C;Thou shalt love thy neighbor as thyself&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn28">4</xref></sup> and, &#x201C;Deliver them that are carried away unto death.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn29">5</xref></sup></p>
<p>3.&#x2014;Every moment that one delays unnecessarily the ransoming of a captive, it is as if he were to shed blood.</p>
<p>4.&#x2014;Captives are not to be ransomed at an unreasonable cost, for the safety of society; otherwise, the enemies would exert every effort to capture victims. But a man may ransom himself at any price. So also, a scholar should be ransomed at a greater price, or even a student who gives promise of becoming a great scholar. (As to whether one&#x2019;s wife is considered &#x201C;another&#x201D; or &#x201C;one&#x2019;s self,&#x201D; see Eben Ha-Ezer,<sup><xref rid="fn30">6</xref></sup> 78.)</p>
<p>5.&#x2014;Captives should not be aided to escape, for the sake of public safety; lest the enemies treat the captives with greater severity and confine them under closer custody.</p>
<p>6.&#x2014;He who sells himself to heathens, or who borrowed from them and is held by them for non-payment, should be ransomed the first time and the second time, but not if it happens a third time. But his children should be ransomed after the father&#x2019;s death. However, if his life is in danger, he must be ransomed immediately, no matter how many times it has happened before. (But one who is an apostate with regard to even one precept, as, for instance, if he eats meat not slaughtered according to ritual in a spirit of defiance, it is forbidden to ransom him.) (See Art. 251.)</p>
<p>7.&#x2014;A slave who is made captive, is ransomed like a captive Israelite, since he is regarded as a free-man after he takes the required ritual bath and assumes the obligations of certain Jewish laws.</p>
<p>8.&#x2014;A woman is redeemed before a man; but where pederasty is common, the man is given precedence. (If both are willing to drown, the man is rescued first.)</p>
<p>9.&#x2014;If he and his father and his teacher are captives, he himself comes before his teacher; and his teacher before his father; but his mother comes before all.</p>
<p>10.&#x2014;If a man and his wife are captured, the wife is ransomed first, and Court may seize his property to ransom her; and even if he protests, &#x201C;Do not ransom her with my property,&#x201D; no attention is paid to him.</p>
<p>11.&#x2014;If a captive has property but does not wish to ransom himself, his ransom is paid against his will.</p>
<p>12.&#x2014;A father is obliged to ransom his son, if the father has the means and the son has not.</p>
<p><italic>Article 253.</italic></p>
<p>1.&#x2014;One who has food to suffice for two meals must not take any from the Tamhuy.<sup><xref rid="fn31">1</xref></sup> One who has enough for fourteen meals must not take anything from the Kuphah.<sup><xref rid="fn32">2</xref></sup> And if he has two hundred Zuz uninvested or fifty Zuz invested, he should receive no charity. But if he has two hundred Zuz minus one denar uninvested, he may accept charity, even if the sum of a thousand Zuz be given him at one time. And if he has much money in his possession, but is indebted to others, or the money is the security of his wife&#x2019;s widowhood-endowment, he is entitled to charity. If one possesses a house and many household utensils but no two hundred Zuz, he may accept charity; and he does not have to sell his household goods, even if they be vessels of gold and silver. This applies only to eating and drinking utensils, articles of clothing, bedclothes and the like; but if he has a silver strigil or pestle, he should sell it and not depend on charity. Further, this law that he is not required to sell his gold and silver utensils applies only where he does not have to touch the public charity-fund but depends upon secret private assistance. But where he asks to be maintained out of the Kuphah, he should be refused until he sell the utensils.</p>
<p align="blockquote">RMI.&#x2014;And so, in communities where it is a rule not to give charity to anyone having a definite capital, the dwelling and the necessary household utensils are not reckoned as &#x201C;definite capital.&#x201D;</p>
<p>2.&#x2014;Some authorities hold that the limits<sup><xref rid="fn33">1</xref></sup> spoken of here, were meant only for their days,<sup><xref rid="fn34">2</xref></sup> but that to-day one may depend on charity until he possesses a large enough principal to yield a sufficient income with which to support himself and family&#x2014;and there is sound reason in this view.</p>
<p>3.&#x2014;If a poor man possesses a piece of land which he would have to sell cheaply if he sold it in the winter time, but which he could sell at full value if he waited till the summer, then he is not obliged to sell at a loss: he should be maintained by the tithes-of-the-poor to the extent of half the value of the property, so that he should not be driven to sell out of season. (But some hold that he is to be supported until he is able to sell at half-price.) If others are buying at a high price, but he is unable to find a purchaser except at a low price, because he is occupied, he is not compelled to sell but may live on the tithes-of-the-poor until he can sell at a fair price; so that all may know that he is not pressed to sell.</p>
<p>4.&#x2014;If, while journeying from place to place, one&#x2019;s funds give out, he may resort to charity, and on returning home he is not compelled to refund (for the law in this case is like that of a poor man who later grows rich,&#x2014;he does not have to repay).</p>
<p>5.&#x2014;If one who supported an orphan and intended it as an act of kindness, demands repayment when the orphan reaches majority, the orphan is not obliged to pay him.</p>
<p align="blockquote">RMI.&#x2014;Even if he now has the means, he is not obliged to pay; since his patron did not specify at the time that it was in the nature of a loan. This applies only to an orphan. But another must pay, even if nothing was specified, for we assume it was meant as a loan; inasmuch as he now possesses the means.</p>
<p>6.&#x2014;If, in collecting for a poor man, more was collected than is necessary for the satisfaction of his wants, the excess belongs to him as well. But if they collected for &#x201C;the poor&#x201D; in general, and something remained, it should be kept for other poor. So, too, the excess of a ransom belongs to the ransomed one; but if they collected for &#x201C;ransoming captives,&#x201D; what is left should be kept for future captives. So, too, what remains after burying a dead person belongs to the heirs, but the remainder of the &#x201C;fund for burying the dead&#x201D; should be kept for other dead. But if the heads of the community see fit to devote it to some immediate need, they may do so.</p>
<p>7.&#x2014;If money was collected to ransom a captive, and the captive in question died before he could be ransomed, some hold that the money should go to the heirs, and others say it should not.<sup><xref rid="fn35">1</xref></sup> To-day we incline towards this latter view, for we presume the donors did not intend that their money should thus be disposed of. The same law holds in case one captured by heathens becomes thoroughly assimilated and lost among them before ransoming is attempted.</p>
<p>8.&#x2014;If a poor man contributes a coin to charity, the money is accepted; but if he does not give, he is not compelled to. If he was given new garments and he returns his old ones, they are accepted; but if he does not return them, he is not compelled to.</p>
<p>9.&#x2014;If a needy poor man does not wish to be an object of charity, cunning may be resorted to; <italic>i. e.</italic>, the money should be given him in the form of a gift or a loan.</p>
<p>10.&#x2014;A rich man who starves himself because of parsimony, need not be looked after.</p>
<p>11.&#x2014;A scholar in need should be helped in a manner befitting his station. If he does not wish to accept their help as charity, they should buy goods for him cheaply and buy them from him at a higher price. If he really understands business, then they should lend him money with which to engage in traffic.</p>
<p>12.&#x2014;If one depending upon charity roams about for a livelihood and succeeds in collecting alms, his creditors cannot take what he collected as charity, in payment of debts due them.</p>
<p align="blockquote">RMI.&#x2014;Unless it is noted in the charity records that he is indebted to others, for in that case the money was given him presumably to pay his debts.</p>
<p><italic>Article 254.</italic></p>
<p>1.&#x2014;An Israelite is forbidden to accept charity from heathens in public. But if he cannot subsist on Jewish charity alone and he is unable to receive it from heathens without public notice,&#x2014;in that case it is permitted.</p>
<p>2.&#x2014;If a heathen prince donates money for Jewish Charities, the money should be accepted for the sake of peace; but it should be distributed among non-Jewish poor secretly so that the prince might not hear of it.</p>
<p align="blockquote">RMI.&#x2014;Some hold that if he specified the purpose, the money should be devoted to that purpose. But donations towards the erection of a synagogue are always accepted.<sup><xref rid="fn36">1</xref></sup></p>
<p><italic>Article 255.</italic></p>
<p>1.&#x2014;One should always avoid charity and rather roll in misery than to depend upon the help of man. And thus our Sages commanded, &#x201C;Rather make thy Sabbath a week-day<sup><xref rid="fn37">2</xref></sup> than be dependent on men.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn38">3</xref></sup> And even though he be scholarly and respectable, let him engage in some occupation, even an unpleasant occupation, so as not to need the help of man.</p>
<p>2.&#x2014;Whosoever is not in need of charity but deceives the public and takes it, will be in actual need before his days are ended. And whosoever is so much in need of charity that he cannot live unless he receive it&#x2014;as, for instance, a man who is old or sick or in constant pain,&#x2014;but takes none out of pride, is guilty of blood-shed and is responsible for his own life; so that he has nothing for his suffering, save punishment and sin. But, whosoever is in need of charity and suffers patiently and leads a pinched and humble life, so as not to become a burden to society, will live to help others some day; and it is with reference to such a person that the Bible says, &#x201C;Blessed is the man that trusteth in the Lord.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn39">1</xref></sup></p>
<p><italic>Article 256.</italic></p>
<p>1.&#x2014;Every city in which Israelites dwell must appoint charity Gabba&#x00EF;m,&#x2014;well-known and trustworthy men who should go about and collect from each one what he ought to give and what he has been taxed. This money they should divide among the poor once a week before the Sabbath, giving each one enough to suffice him for seven days. This fund is called Kuphah. The community should also appoint other Gabba&#x00EF;m to collect, day by day from every household, donations of bread and other victuals, or fruit, or money. This should be distributed among the poor daily towards evening, to each one enough food for the day. And this is what is called Tamhuy.<sup><xref rid="fn40">2</xref></sup> We have never seen or heard of a Jewish community that has no Kuphah, but in some places it is not customary to maintain a Tamhuy.</p>
<p>2.&#x2014;On the night of a fast day food should be distributed among the poor. If, at the close of a fast, the people eat and retire without giving charity to the poor, they are regarded as if they had shed blood. This is so only when the distribution is made of bread or fruit; but if they fail to distribute money or wheat,<sup><xref rid="fn41">3</xref></sup> they are not regarded as shedders of blood.</p>
<p>3.&#x2014;Collections for the Kuphah must never be made by less than two, because no office for communal money-affairs can be created with less than two officers; but after collection one can be trusted with it as treasurer. Therefore, two brothers may be appointed as treasurers. The distribution of charity, however, must be made by no less than three (as in all civil cases) because every poor man must be judged as to the amount he needs. But the Tamhuy is not only distributed by three but also collected by three, because it is not a fixed matter, but each person approached must be judged every day as to the amount he is to give that day. The Tamhuy is collected every day, and the Kuphah, once a week. The Tamhuy is meant for any poor people who may apply, while the Kuphah is intended for the poor of that particular city. The community may convert a Kuphah into a Tamhuy, or vice versa; or it may use both for any other communal purpose, although such a condition was not specifically made at the time of collection. If there is in the city a distinguished wise man who enjoys the confidence of the community and who has charge of the distribution of charity, he alone may devote the charity funds to any other communal purpose.</p>
<p align="blockquote">RMI.&#x2014;And the same applies to a duly elected Gabbai. And even when an individual donates a sum of money<sup><xref rid="fn42">1</xref></sup> and gives it to the Gabbai [the Gabbai may use it as he sees fit]; but if that individual appoints his own trustees, the members of the community have no right to change its purpose; because the money is not donated to be disposed of at their discretion. Nor have they the right of change when the donor specifies that the money be given to the poor of the city, or to a certain poor man,&#x2014;not even for school purposes. If a controversy arises between the Gabbai and the community, resulting in an irreparable breach, and the funds are still in the hands of the Gabbai,&#x2014;then, if he possessed the right originally to dispose of the money as seemed best to him, he may exercise that right now; but if he always had to take counsel with the leaders of the community, he should likewise do so now. If, however, it is impossible to bring them together, or they cannot come to an agreement, the Gabbai should do with the money what he deems proper,&#x2014;only he should spend it for some worthy purpose.</p>
<p>4.&#x2014;After dwelling in a place thirty days, one can be compelled to contribute towards the Kuphah; after three months, to the Tamhuy; after six months, he can be compelled to contribute to the Clothing-Fund for the poor; after nine months to the Burial Fund with which to make interment of the poor and perform all funeral rites. This applies to one who comes to dwell in a place temporarily; but if he settles there permanently, he must become a contributor at once.</p>
<p>5.&#x2014;If one comes to a strange city on business, and that city assesses him with an amount for charity, he must pay that for the poor of that city. But if a number of merchants come in a body and they are assessed, they must deposit the amount; but, when they are ready to return home, they take back the total amount of their contributions and bring it to their home city, to be devoted to the poor of their own city. And if there is a universally recognized scholar there, they should give it to him for distribution.</p>
<p align="blockquote">RMI.&#x2014;They have to pay immediately in order to avoid suspicion, but it is afterwards returned to them. And this refers to a kind of charity to which they would not have been obliged to contribute had they remained at home; but to the usual charities they do not have to contribute in the strange city, for we assume that they are taxed in their home town.</p>
<p><italic>Article 257.</italic></p>
<p>1.&#x2014;Charity collectors must not separate from one another in the market-place, but they must be within sight of one another; as, when one is in the gateway collecting, and the other in the store. If the collector finds money in the street, he shall not put it into his pocket, but into the charity bag&#x2014;until he reaches home, when he may take it. If the collector collects a personal debt from a friend in the street, he shall not put the money into his pocket, but into the charity bag and take it when he reaches home. He shall not count the coins of the Kuphah two at a time, but one by one, to avoid suspicion; as it is written &#x201C;And ye shall be guiltless before the Lord and before Israel.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn43">1</xref></sup></p>
<p>2.&#x2014;If the Gabba&#x00EF;m have no poor among whom to distribute the money, they may exchange it for Denarii,<sup><xref rid="fn44">2</xref></sup> but not from their own pockets. So, too, if anything is left from the Tamhuy, they should sell it&#x2014;to others, not to themselves, in order to avoid suspicion. No accounts should be required of Gabba&#x00EF;m of charity, nor of treasurers of sacred funds, for it is written, &#x201C;Moreover, they reckoned not with the men, into whose hand they delivered the money to be bestowed on workmen: for they dealt faithfully.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn45">3</xref></sup></p>
<p align="blockquote">RMI.&#x2014;Still, in order to be &#x201C;guiltless before the Lord and before Israel,&#x201D; it is better for them to submit accounts. And besides, the text refers to men whose honesty and capacity were undisputed; but wherever there is the slightest suspicion or where the official obtained his position through force, an account must be submitted. And so with all public financial institutions. The community at the expiration of the term has the right to elect another official and cannot on that account be accused of suspecting the former official.</p>
<p>3.&#x2014;Charity comes within the general class of vows. Therefore, if one says, &#x201C;I vow a Sela<sup><xref rid="fn46">4</xref></sup> to charity,&#x201D; or, &#x201C;I vow <italic>this</italic> Sela to charity,&#x201D; he must give it to the poor immediately; and, if he delays, he is guilty of transgressing the precept, &#x201C;Thou shalt not slack to pay it,&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn47">1</xref></sup> since he has the money and poor people are a-plenty. But if no poor are available, he should separate the money and lay it aside until he meet one.</p>
<p align="blockquote">RMI.&#x2014;He transgresses a law in delaying payment, only when he vows to give charity which he himself must distribute. But if he vows to contribute to the general charity fund in the synagogue and the like, which must go through the hands of the Gabbai, he does not transgress the precept, although poor are a-plenty, until the Gabbai asks for it; and then, if he delays, he is a transgressor. And if the Gabbai does not know of the vow, he must inform him how much he vowed, so that he might come to collect.</p>
<p>That he must not delay in paying his vows to charity refers to vows as ordinarily made; but, of course, a man is permitted to separate a sum of money which he himself is to distribute a little at a time as he may see fit. And so also, if he stipulates a condition in making the vow, that the Gabba&#x00EF;m should be permitted to exchange the money for gold, then they are permitted to do so.</p>
<p>4.&#x2014;One should avoid vows. If people are being taxed for charity and one feels obliged to fix an amount for himself, let him say, &#x201C;Without vowing, I promise,&#x201D; etc.</p>
<p>5.&#x2014;If the charity treasury lacks funds, let the Gabbai make a loan to the fund out of his private purse; and when conditions improve, he may draw that amount without permission from the contributors.</p>
<p>6.&#x2014;If the Gabbai, while still in office, says, &#x201C;I have loaned so much and so much to the fund,&#x201D; he is believed without taking an oath; but not after he is discharged.</p>
<p>7.&#x2014;A Gabbai should not take to heart the insults which the poor may heap upon him: his reward will be the greater for it.</p>
<p>8.&#x2014;A poor man who has wealthy relatives does not have to be supported by the Gabba&#x00EF;m, even though the relatives are contributors to the fund.</p>
<p>9.&#x2014;One should not center all his charities in one poor man.</p>
<p>10.&#x2014;He who distributes the charities should guard himself against being partial to his relatives.</p>
<p align="blockquote">RMI.&#x2014;That is to say, a public Gabbai. But a private individual may give charity or his tithes to whichever relative he chooses,&#x2014;in fact, his relatives come first, as already explained in Art. 251.</p>
<p>11.&#x2014;If one invests a sum of money the income of which is to be devoted to religious education and he appoints his wife to give it to whomsoever she wishes, she has no right to deposit the money with another, even though that other be as honorable a man as Rabbi Hananiah ben Tradion. But if the donor appoints a prominent scholar over the funds, he has the right to deposit them with his wife.</p>
<p><italic>Article 258.</italic></p>
<p>1.&#x2014;One may consecrate something to charity by &#x201C;comparing&#x201D; it to something already sacred, just as in vows. For example; if a Sela belonging to charity lies before him and he says with reference to another Sela, &#x201C;Let that one be like this one,&#x201D; that one becomes a contribution to charity.</p>
<p>2.&#x2014;If he separates a Sela and says, &#x201C;Let this become charity,&#x201D; and then adds, referring to another, &#x201C;and this,&#x201D; the second likewise becomes charity.<sup><xref rid="fn48">1</xref></sup></p>
<p>3.&#x2014;He who vowed to give charity but does not know how much he vowed, should give and give until he feels certain that he did not intend to give that much.</p>
<p>4.&#x2014;If one says, &#x201C;Give two hundred Zuz, or a Scroll of the Law, to the Synagogue [on my account],&#x201D; they should give it to the synagogue in which he usually worships in the city in which he dwells.</p>
<p align="blockquote">RMI.&#x2014;And if he frequents two, the money should be divided between them. If one donates illuminating oil [without specifying] it should go to the synagogue rather than the House of Study.</p>
<p>5.&#x2014;If one says, &#x201C;Give [these] two hundred Zuz to the poor,&#x201D; the money should be given to the poor of the city in which he dwells.</p>
<p align="blockquote">RMI.&#x2014;Only when there is no reason to assume otherwise. But where we know that he did not intend it for the poor of that city only, as in places where wealthy people leave vast sums at the time of death to be distributed among various Charities, we follow the custom of the place even when it is not so specified in the will; and the heirs distribute the money as they deem best, even to charities of other cities. And even if the money is deposited with another at the time of the donor&#x2019;s death, it is returned to the heirs and they are informed of the manner of the bequest.</p>
<p>6.&#x2014;He who makes a vow to give charity cannot retract, unless he turns to a Rabbi and obtains a release; but, after the money reaches the Gabbai, he cannot apply for a release.</p>
<p>7.&#x2014;A man cannot hallow<sup><xref rid="fn49">1</xref></sup> anything not in his possession. For example: If A deposited something with B, and B denies that it belongs to A, then A cannot hallow it. But if B does not deny it, then it is considered in A&#x2019;s possession, no matter where A may be. This refers only to chattel property. But if B robs A of a piece of land and denies that it belongs to A, then if A can recover it by law, he may hallow it even before it is recovered; for the principle is that real estate always continues in the possession of the true owner. If one robs another of some object and the owner does not yet despair of recovering it, neither can hallow it,&#x2014;the one because it is not his, and the other because it is not in his possession. And so on.</p>
<p>8.&#x2014;If A owes B a debt, and B says, &#x201C;Let it become hallowed,&#x201D; or, &#x201C;Let it go to charity,&#x201D; it does not take effect. But if he says, &#x201C;When I shall get the money which A owes me, I shall hallow it or give it to charity,&#x201D; he must fulfil his promise when the money reaches him. Even if he says, &#x201C;Let the debt which A owes me go to charity,&#x201D; if only the debtor and the Gabbai are present, or the leaders of the community (or a highly respected scholar in the community), the Gabbai comes into possession of it by virtue of the fact that three are present, and he cannot retract or change his word.</p>
<p>9.&#x2014;If A strikes B or insults him (for which according to the community ordinances A must pay five gold-pieces) and he says, in the presence of the Gabbai or the leading members of the community, &#x201C;I want my fine to go to charity,&#x201D; and then they make peace, so that B forgives A, this does not affect what preceded, and the poor are not deprived of A&#x2019;s fine.</p>
<p>10.&#x2014;If one makes his vow to charity depend upon a condition, as, for example, &#x201C;If I do this and that, I shall give so and so much to charity,&#x201D; he must pay it, if he fulfils the condition.</p>
<p>11.&#x2014;If a man and his wife solemnly vow to divorce and fix a fine upon themselves, and finally they decide not to divorce, some are of the opinion that they are exempt from paying the fine.</p>
<p>12.&#x2014;If one promises to give another a gift, and that other happens to be a dependent poor man, it is as if he had made a vow to charity which he cannot retract.</p>
<p>13.&#x2014;If one says, &#x201C;I give this object to charity at such and such a value,&#x201D; and it is found to be worth more, he cannot retract (for whenever charity can be the gainer because of a word, we say &#x201C;a word&#x201D; is as binding in sacred matters as actual transfer in lay matters). But if the object was not worth more at the time and later increased in value, he may retract as long as the money is not yet transferred.</p>
<p align="blockquote">RMI.&#x2014;If he promises in his mind to give anything to charity, he is obliged to fulfil his thought and no speech is necessary, except that when he expresses it verbally we can compe him to fulfil his promise.</p>
<p><italic>Article 259.</italic></p>
<p>1.&#x2014;If one says, &#x201C;Let this Sela go to charity,&#x201D; or if he says, &#x201C;I vow to give a Sela to charity,&#x201D; and separates the coin, he may still change the coin as long as the Gabbai does not come to collect it; <italic>i. e</italic>., he may borrow it himself or lend it to another, but he must pay another instead.</p>
<p align="blockquote">RMI.&#x2014;So, too, if vessels or utensils have been hallowed, they may be sold according to the appraisal of three experts, and the proceeds given to charity.</p>
<p>But after the money reaches the Gabbai it must not be loaned to anyone, neither to the donor, nor to another, nor even to the Gabbai. But if the poor can benefit by the fact that the Gabbai retains the money for a time; as, for example, thereby to induce others to pay, he may borrow it and then pay it back.</p>
<p align="blockquote">RMI.&#x2014;Because charity is not exactly like Temple funds, as it is permitted to derive benefit from the former.<sup><xref rid="fn50">1</xref></sup> But funds ready for distribution should not be tied up in business, only money-changing and the like being permitted where the cash is always on hand, because the poor may come and there would be no ready money to give them. However, funds not meant for immediate distribution may be invested, so that the principal should remain intact and only the income thereof be distributed. And this, in fact, is the custom in vogue.</p>
<p>2.&#x2014;Moneys donated for purposes of the synagogue or of the cemetery, may, if the community sees fit to do so, be diverted to the use of the House of Study or to the maintenance of a Religious School,<sup><xref rid="fn51">2</xref></sup> even against the will of the donors; but moneys collected for the support of a school cannot be commuted to the synagogue.</p>
<p align="blockquote">RMI.&#x2014;Only where there is ground for apprehension that there will not be sufficient money for school purposes [if this money were to be diverted to the synagogue]; but where the members of the community support the schools generously (so that if this money is spent for a synagogue they will surely furnish more money for the schools); in such a case, it is permitted, even in a place where it is [usually] forbidden to change the will of the donor. If one donates a sum of money for a purpose for which there is no need [at present]; as, for example, he donates a site for a House of Study and for certain reasons the building cannot be erected immediately, the donor cannot retract, but the site remains until the House of Study is eventually erected. All this applies in places where there is no established custom. But where it is established that the Gabbai or the assembled community has the right to commute the funds from one charitable purpose to another, we follow the usual custom; for we presume that the donor makes his donation subject to custom and that the authorities accept it with this condition at heart [that they may dispose of it at their discretion]. Of course, where the donor expressly stipulates that his donation shall not be subject to change, naturally it cannot be commuted.</p>
<p>3.&#x2014;If a Jew had donated a lamp or a candelabrum to the synagogue, and the name of the donor is not associated with the object, the community<sup><xref rid="fn52">1</xref></sup> may devote it to another purpose, even a non-religious purpose<sup><xref rid="fn53">2</xref></sup> (even against the donor&#x2019;s protests). But if the donor&#x2019;s name is associated with the gift, it cannot be commuted for a non-religious purpose, but it may, for a religious purpose. If the donor is a heathen, the gift cannot be commuted even for some other religious purpose, as long as his name is associated with the gift. (And as long as the name of the donor is engraved on the vessels donated, the name is said to be &#x201C;associated&#x201D; with the gift.)</p>
<p>4.&#x2014;If a heathen donates a candelabrum or other object to the synagogue, we accept it, if he says, &#x201C;I have consecrated this according to the intentions of the Israelites&#x201D;; but if he does not say this, it must be put away.<sup><xref rid="fn54">3</xref></sup> (See Art. 254.)</p>
<p>5.&#x2014;If a person has money in his possession and he is in doubt whether it belongs to charity or not, he must give it to charity.</p>
<p align="blockquote">RMI.&#x2014;If one consecrated something with an ambiguous expression and died, the property continues in the possession of the rightful heirs, since it is impossible to know the intention of the deceased. For the burden of proof rests with the Charity officials who are interested in changing the present status of the property; and as long as they cannot bring proof, the property in question continues in the possession of the heirs.</p>
<p>6.&#x2014;The community has no right to assess or tax charity funds.</p>
<p align="blockquote">RMI.&#x2014;If one finds a purse in his chest with the word &#x201C;charity&#x201D; written over it, we depend upon the written word and it is Charity. So, too, if one said to his children, &#x201C;This is Charity,&#x201D; and it seems to them now that he said this to inform them of a fact, the money is Charity. But if it seems to them that he told them this so that they should not take any, or so that they should not consider him wealthy, then we put no stock in his words. So also, if one is informed in a dream that his father concealed money in a certain place<sup><xref rid="fn55">1</xref></sup> and that the money is Charity, we put no trust in these words, because the words of dreams are of no account either one way or the other.</p>
<p align="blockquote">&#x2026; If one handles a box of charity funds and one of other funds, and money is later found on the floor, we say it belongs to the chest he used last. If he used both simultaneously, we say it belongs to the larger sum. But if he finds it in a crevice or hole, where, we might say, it has been lying for a long time without being noticed, then we give it to the larger fund even if he handled them successively.</p>
<ftnote id="fn1"><sup>1</sup> Deut. 15:7.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn2"><sup>2</sup> The word is Beliya&#x2019;al, which occurs in Deut. 15:9.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn3"><sup>3</sup> Ta&#x2019;anith 21. (A treatise of the Talmud.)</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn4"><sup>4</sup> Isaiah 32:17. A play on the word Tsedakah meaning &#x201C;righteousness&#x201D; and also &#x201C;charity.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn5"><sup>5</sup> Rabbi Moses Isserles, died in Cracow 1572, annotator of the Shulhan Arukh.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn6"><sup>1</sup> I Kings 17.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn7"><sup>2</sup> When the delinquent can plead for delay on the ground that he is occupied with preparations for the Sabbath.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn8"><sup>3</sup> The term Gabbai (pl. Gabba&#x00EF;m) means &#x201C;collector,&#x201D; but since the collector was usually also the &#x201C;charities manager,&#x201D; the same word is used for both.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn9"><sup>1</sup> Levit. 3:16.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn10"><sup>1</sup> Psalms 74:21.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn11"><sup>1</sup> Leviticus 25:35.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn12"><sup>1</sup> Psalms 17:15.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn13"><sup>2</sup> Deut. 15:8.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn14"><sup>3</sup> Deut. 15: 8 &#x201C;&#x2026; sufficient for his need in that which he wanteth,&#x201D; with emphasis on <italic>his</italic> and <italic>he</italic>. But see Ketub. 67b (a treatise of the Talmud), story of Rabbi Nehemiah.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn15"><sup>1</sup> See Article 256, Sec. 1.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn16"><sup>1</sup> Although they transgress many Biblical laws.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn17"><sup>2</sup> Gittin 61<sup>a</sup>. (A treatise of the Talmud.)</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn18"><sup>1</sup> Aboth 5, 1. It means: employ them as your servants whenever possible (Maimonides).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn19"><sup>2</sup> The issue of a marriage forbidden to priests. See Levit. 21 : 7, 14.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn20"><sup>3</sup> A descendant of the Gibeonites. Joshua 9:27; Zebahim 78b. (A treatise of the Talmud.)</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn21"><sup>1</sup> Baba Bathra 8<sup>a</sup>. (A treatise of the Talmud.)</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn22"><sup>1</sup> Small coins.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn23"><sup>2</sup> Deut. 15:7.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn24"><sup>3</sup> Lev. 19:16.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn25"><sup>1</sup> Lev. 25:53.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn26"><sup>2</sup> Dent. 15:8.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn27"><sup>3</sup> Lev. 25:36. The Hebrew text permits the rendition &#x201C;Let thy brother live,&#x201D; etc.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn28"><sup>4</sup> Lev. 19:18.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn29"><sup>5</sup> Prov. 24:11.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn30"><sup>6</sup> Eben Ha-Ezer is the fourth part of this code of Shulhan Arukh, and deals with laws pertaining to woman.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn31"><sup>1</sup> Alms-basket or soup-kitchen, from which provisions are distributed daily.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn32"><sup>2</sup> Charity-fund, distributed weekly. See Article 256.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn33"><sup>1</sup> 206 Zuz, 50 Zuz.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn34"><sup>2</sup> Talmudic times.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn35"><sup>1</sup> But should be returned to the contributors.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn36"><sup>1</sup> As they are not worse than Temple offerings, which heathens also were permitted to donate.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn37"><sup>2</sup> As regards festive meals.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn38"><sup>3</sup> Pesahim 112<sup>a</sup>. (A treatise of the Talmud.)</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn39"><sup>1</sup> Jeremiah 17:7.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn40"><sup>2</sup> See notes on Article 253, Sec. 1.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn41"><sup>3</sup> I. e., they postpone distribution until the morrow.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn42"><sup>1</sup> Without stating explicitly that it is to be given to the poor.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn43"><sup>1</sup> Numbers 32:22.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn44"><sup>2</sup> Coins of a higher denomination.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn45"><sup>3</sup> II Kings, 12:15.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn46"><sup>4</sup> A coin worth two common Shekels.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn47"><sup>1</sup> Deut. 23:21.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn48"><sup>1</sup> Although he is not explicit with the second.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn49"><sup>1</sup> Donate for some holy purpose.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn50"><sup>1</sup> Provided it be used for some sacred purpose.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn51"><sup>1</sup> If the enjoyment of its benefits does not use up the article or depreciate it.</ftnote>
<p>Because they are more important than synagogues.</p>
<ftnote id="fn52"><sup>1</sup> But not the Gabbai.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn53"><sup>2</sup> If the lamp or candlestick has not yet been used.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn54"><sup>3</sup> For we fear he might have consecrated it for idol-worship.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn55"><sup>1</sup> And it is actually found in the place designated.</ftnote>
</chapter>
</book>
