<book>
<chapter>
<title>Preface and Dedication</title>
<p>The texts included in this volume were selected by Seth Brody, late Assistant Professor of Religious Studies at Haverford College. Brody translated and annotated most of the texts, leaving perhaps less than a quarter of the work to be completed at the time of his tragic final illness and untimely death on the Intermediate Sabbath of Passover, 5556 (April 1996). It has been my sad task and great privilege, as Seth&#x2019;s teacher and mentor, to do for his work what I might have hoped he one day would have done for mine. As my work here is merely a completion of his, I did not deem it necessary to distinguish our efforts from one another. I am, however, responsible for all introductory materials with the exception of the introduction to the Zohar on Lamentations, which I was able to edit from Brody&#x2019;s notes.</p>
<p>I do not know to whom Brody had planned to dedicate this volume; no such indication was found in his notes. All I can do is offer it in his own memory, that of a young rabbi and scholar filled with love of Torah and overflowing with excitement about the work he still planned to do, both in the realm of historical scholarship on Kabbalah and in the creation of a contemporary Jewish mystical theology. The loss of this great voice to the worlds of Jewish scholarship and theology is dwarfed only by the personal loss suffered by his parents, friends, and students. May his memory serve as a source of blessing to us all.</p>
<p><small>ARTHUR GREEN</small></p>
<p><small>BRANDEIS UNIVERSITY</small></p>
<p>O<small>CTOBER</small> 1997</p>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>A Note on Sources</title>
<p>Like most medieval Hebrew writings, the texts translated here are replete with quotations from Scripture as well as from the classic compilations of early rabbinic literature. Biblical books are referenced by standard abbreviations. References to rabbinic texts use generally accepted form and refer to standard editions. Mishnah references are to tractate, chapter, and pericope, e.g., <italic>Berakhot</italic> 4:11. Talmudic references, marked b. for Babylonian Talmud and y. for Yerushalmi or Jerusalem Talmud, are then listed by folio in the standard editions, e.g. b. <italic>Sanhedrin</italic> 21b. Referencing styles to Midrashic works vary considerably, but the chapter indications here should provide the reader with sufficient guidance for use of the various modern or critical editions.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>On Reading Kabbalistic Texts</title>
<p>The traditions of mystical theosophy elucidated and taught by Jews in Provence, Catalonia, and Castile in the twelfth-thirteenth centuries have come to be identified as the intellectual Kabbalah.<sup><xref rid="fn1">1</xref></sup> The present volume contains one of the most important and earliest texts composed in this tradition, along with two briefer late thirteenth-century examples of its use. In order to appreciate these texts as they were intended to be understood, some brief introduction to Kabbalistic use of language is required.</p>
<p>The most important creation of the Kabbalists lies in the realm of mystical symbolism and the daring reincorporation of myth into Judaism. When reading some of their writings, most particularly the Zohar, considered the crowning achievement of medieval Kabbalah, one can easily gain the impression that it is more the mythical than the mystical that lies at the heart of the Kabbalistic enterprise. The essential myth of a divine/cosmic unity rent asunder and in search of reunion is told through a vast array of symbols. These are arranged in a tenfold grid of associative clusters called the ten <italic>sefirot</italic>. The <italic>sefirot</italic> (literally &#x201C;numbers&#x201D;) are presented as a series of primal divine emanations, stages in the advancing flow (both premundane and constant) of divinity toward the lower world and the mystic&#x2019;s mind. Simultaneously these <italic>sefirot</italic> also serve as stages in the mystic&#x2019;s ascent and the ascent of the worlds and rungs themselves as they seek reinclusion within the undifferentiated Godhead.</p>
<p>But seen functionally rather than hypostatically, each of these ten <italic>sefirot</italic> is in effect a group of terms or verbal pictures (they are indeed the richest &#x201C;iconography&#x201D; of medieval Judaism), each member of the cluster identified with all the others. Thus the Kabbalist might speak of the &#x201C;right hand&#x201D; of God, or of silver, milk, morning, south, the myrtle-branch, or the love of Abraham. One who knows the Kabbalistic system understands that all of these are symbol-terms of the fourth cluster, usually designated by the lead-term <italic>&#x1E25;esed</italic> or compassion. In the course of his discourse, especially if it comes (as so often) in the form of commentary on Biblical or early rabbinic sources, the author will switch from one of these symbols to another without missing a beat, at each step reinforcing the cluster of associations in the reader&#x2019;s mind. While talking about the same <italic>sefirah</italic> or pair of <italic>sefirot</italic> in union, the writer may with utmost symbolic grace let his thought flow from water imagery to that of light, from sexual metaphors to those of one or another of the commandments, and thence on to beasts and birds or Jerusalem and the history of the Jews. Significantly, each cluster contains both terms derived from nature (sun and moon, heaven and earth, trees, wells, streams, and oceans) and figures from the Jewish cult. Within a given cluster, all terms bear the same valence and are interchangeable with one another.</p>
<p>In this way the Kabbalists created a symbolically enriched language, a linguistic entity given a new profundity by this network of associations reaching across bounds of nature, Scriptural text, and Jewish religious tradition. This language was seen as the appropriate one for speaking of the inner life of God, a matter too elevated and glorious to be conveyed by the ordinary linguistic vehicle. Since for the Kabbalist, as Elliot Wolfson has aptly noted,<sup><xref rid="fn2">2</xref></sup> hermeneutics and experience are fully united, we may say that to speak sefirotic language is itself to enter the world of the <italic>sefirot</italic> and to live on that intensified plane of being.</p>
<p>The works presented in this volume represent two stages in the unfolding of Kabbalistic language. Rabbi Ezra ben Solomon&#x2019;s <italic>Commentary on the Song of Songs</italic> belongs to the Geronese School, which may be designated as the &#x201C;second generation,&#x201D; but the first full flowering of writing in the Kabbalistic mode. The Zohar to Lamentations and R. Bahya&#x2019;s Commentary to the Torah were both written about fifty years after R. Ezra&#x2019;s work, in Castile and Catalonia respectively. The following brief conspectus of symbolic associations, intended specifically for use in connection with the texts translated here, necessarily includes terms used in both periods and must therefore be used with some caution. A much fuller Kabbalistic symbolary is Rabbi Joseph Gikatilla&#x2019;s <italic>Gates of Light</italic>, written by an important Kabbalist close to the circle of the Zohar and now available in English translation.<sup><xref rid="fn3">3</xref></sup> Nevertheless, for the reader&#x2019;s convenience the following brief list may be helpful.</p>
<p>1. <italic>KETER</italic></p>
<p>Highest Crown. Nothing. The Nothingness of Thought. Intellect.</p>
<p>2. <italic>&#x1E24;OKHMAH</italic></p>
<p>Wisdom. Lebanon. Wine. Primordial Torah.</p>
<p>3. <italic>BINAH</italic></p>
<p>Understanding. Mother. Repentance. Jubilee. Fiftieth Gate.</p>
<p>4. <italic>&#x1E24;ESED</italic></p>
<p>Compassion. Abraham. South. White. Morning. Silver. Milk.</p>
<p>5. <italic>DIN; GEVURAH</italic></p>
<p>Judgment. Isaac. North. Red. Dusk. Gold. Blood.</p>
<p>6. <italic>TIFERET</italic></p>
<p>Glory. Jacob. The Blessed Holy One. Solomon. Peace. Truth. East. Bridegroom. Sun. Heaven. Written Torah.</p>
<p>7. <italic>NETZA&#x1E24;</italic></p>
<p>Eternity. Victory. Cherub.</p>
<p>8. <italic>HOD</italic></p>
<p>Beauty. Cherub.</p>
<p>9. <italic>YESOD</italic></p>
<p>Foundation. Joseph. Phallus. Sign of the Covenant. Righteous One.</p>
<p>10. <italic>MALKHUT; SHEKHINAH</italic></p>
<p>Kingdom. Indwelling Presence. Jerusalem. King David. Rachel. Bride. Temple. Tent of Meeting. Moon. Ocean. Earth. Vagina. Oral Torah.</p>
<p>For a fuller introduction to exegesis in the Kabbalistic mode, including some comparison of Kabbalistic symbolism and medieval Christian allegory, see Frank Talmage&#x2019;s &#x201C;Apples of Gold: The Inner Meaning of Sacred Texts in Medieval Judaism&#x201D; in <italic>Jewish Spirituality I</italic>, ed. A. Green (New York: Crossroad, 1987).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<h2><bold>Editor&#x2019;s Note</bold></h2>
<p>The commentary of Rabbi Ezra ben Solomon of Gerona (d. ca. 1245) on the Song of Songs is one of the most important texts of the first clearly identified circle of Kabbalists, those operating in the Catalonian town of Gerona at the middle of the thirteenth century. This group, the best-known members of whom are R. Ezra and R. Azriel, claimed to have been initiated into the Kabbalistic mysteries through the teachings of R. Isaac the Blind, son of the well-known legal as well as mystical authority R. Abraham ben David of Posquieres, the earliest historical figure linked by tradition to Kabbalistic teaching.</p>
<p>As the earliest Kabbalistic commentary to the Song of Songs, R. Ezra&#x2019;s work may be seen as one that had a truly pivotal influence on the future development of Jewish mysticism. While the origins of Kabbalistic symbolism as a whole are complex and recondite, among its clearly distinguishing characteristics is the large scale reappropriation of natural and erotic symbols into the language of Jewish theology. Both of these are grounded largely in the exegetical traditions surrounding the Canticle, and the commentary of R. Ezra must be seen as a primary channel through which they came to be accepted. Kabbalah in its most classic manifestations, the Zohar and related works of the late thirteenth and early fourteenth centuries, would be unthinkable without the great infusion of Song of Songs interpretation offered by R. Ezra and his successors, including R. Moshe of Burgos and R. Isaac Ibn Sahola.<sup><xref rid="fn4">4</xref></sup></p>
<p>The Zohar, composed in Castile some forty to fifty years after this work, is replete on nearly every page with allusions to the Canticle. The great lushness of natural imagery, so central and striking a characteristic of the Kabbalistic imagination, is nourished in large measure by constant reference to the Song&#x2019;s gardens, mountains, flocks, and flowing springs as well as its lovers themselves. It is fully taken for granted by the Zohar and its circle that all of these allude to the upper realms, the symbolically described universe of the <italic>sefirot</italic>, chief object of the Kabbalists&#x2019; attention. This transition from the very earthly setting of the Canticle itself to the realm of sublime symbolism was brought about largely through the influence of R. Ezra&#x2019;s work.</p>
<p>There is much to be learned from R. Ezra&#x2019;s commentary about the way Kabbalistic authors inserted themselves into the rabbinic tradition. While critical of those philosophical interpreters who possess &#x201C;neither wisdom nor insight&#x201D; and &#x201C;turn words of holiness into profanity,&#x201D; the highly radical character of the Kabbalist&#x2019;s own reading of the text is slipped unstatedly into the classic garb of the rabbinic reading, in which the Song of Songs is a dialogue, spread over Jewish history, between the Holy One and the Jewish people, personified in the figure of &#x201C;Community of Israel.&#x201D; Some of this reading is preserved in R. Ezra&#x2019;s commentary, and he surely takes no pains to deny it. But as the text unfolds it is clear that the chief focus here is that of union <italic>within</italic> the Godhead, rather than between God and His people Israel. It is <italic>shekhinah</italic> or <italic>malkhut</italic>, the feminine tenth <italic>sefirah</italic>, who unites with Solomon or the Glory, or who ascends with Him to their shared source in the font of <italic>&#x1E25;okhmah</italic>, which makes this work truly a Kabbalistic one.</p>
<p>The <italic>Commentary on the Song of Songs</italic> is the major extant work of Rabbi Ezra ben Solomon of Gerona. He also authored commentaries on <italic>Sefer Yetzirah</italic> (no longer extant) and on sections of the Talmudic <italic>Aggadah</italic>. Several epistles and smaller fragments are also attributed to him, including an important discussion of &#x201C;The Secret of the Tree of Knowledge.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn5">5</xref></sup></p>
<p>The present work, long attributed to R. Ezra&#x2019;s better-known contemporary Moses Nahmanides, was first published in Altona in 1764. That poor edition, copied many times over by various printers, has been included in Charles Chavel&#x2019;s edition of Nahmanides&#x2019; writings, Kitvey RaMBaN, published by the Rabbi Kook Institute of Jerusalem in 1963. Fortunately, better manuscript versions of the text abound, though a critical edition of this important text is still a desideratum of Kabbalistic scholarship. The present translation has been undertaken in consultation with the Jewish Theological Seminary&#x2019;s manuscript designated Lutzki 1059. In all but a few cases the manuscript reading was preferred over that of the printed text.</p>
<p>In the course of commenting on the Song of Songs, R. Ezra allows himself several digressions, typical of Hebrew exegetical literature in his day. The largest of these is a treatise on the six hundred thirteen commandments and the way each is derived from its root in the decalogue. Chavel treats this text as a separate work, published following the <italic>Commentary</italic>. We have followed the lead of Georges Vajda, French translator of the <italic>Commentary</italic>,<sup><xref rid="fn6">6</xref></sup> in eliminating this lengthy and somewhat technical digression. We have, however, retained its introduction and conclusion, which are of more general interest. Several shorter digressions from the text, including a commentary on Job 28 in the context of a discussion of Wisdom, an important treatise on creation via a commentary on Psalm 104, and various historical/eschatological discussions, are retained.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<h1><bold>Introduction</bold></h1>
<p>Praise to the Lord, the God of Israel, for all eternity.</p>
<p align="blockquote">At the dawning of His Kingdom,</p>
<p align="blockquote">God founded a throne for His dwelling,</p>
<p align="blockquote">establishing it through His spirit,</p>
<p align="blockquote">making it through His mighty arm.</p>
<p align="blockquote">He brought forth wisdom and understanding,</p>
<p align="blockquote">treasure without limits.</p>
<p align="blockquote">From there flow the lives of souls;</p>
<p align="blockquote">all the worlds draw their existence.</p>
<p align="blockquote">Who can comprehend God&#x2019;s comings and goings,</p>
<p align="blockquote">His intentions,</p>
<p align="blockquote">save Moses who held fast to His presence,</p>
<p align="blockquote">who attained a firm stance upon His foundations,</p>
<p align="blockquote">as it is written:</p>
<p align="blockquote">&#x201C;He grasps hold of His throne, He spreads His cloud over him&#x201D; [Job 26:9].</p>
<p align="blockquote">When God established His throne during creation&#x2019;s six days,</p>
<p align="blockquote">he formed two fawns,<sup><xref rid="fn7">7</xref></sup></p>
<p align="blockquote">twins of a gazelle,</p>
<p align="blockquote">placing them in a domicile of delight,</p>
<p align="blockquote">a chamber with figures inlaid.</p>
<p align="blockquote">Nothing was denied them,</p>
<p align="blockquote">no false divinity</p>
<p align="blockquote">nor anything of evil</p>
<p align="blockquote">was in their midst.</p>
<p align="blockquote">The intent of their creation</p>
<p align="blockquote">was that they would be a seed of truth,</p>
<p align="blockquote">&#x201C;holy seed their stock&#x201D; [Isa. 6:21],</p>
<p align="blockquote">so that they might stroll among stones of fire,<sup><xref rid="fn8">8</xref></sup></p>
<p align="blockquote">among the angelic watches,</p>
<p align="blockquote">while the <italic>shekhinah</italic> herself would walk in the lower worlds.</p>
<p align="blockquote">So it was until a crafty man arose.</p>
<p align="blockquote">Iniquitous, endowed with jealous plots,</p>
<p align="blockquote">he devised deeds of wickedness,</p>
<p align="blockquote">enticing and misleading the gracious lady</p>
<p align="blockquote">with his blandishments.</p>
<p align="blockquote">Eschewing aforethought,</p>
<p align="blockquote">she observed not her commandment</p>
<p align="blockquote">but followed his counsel.</p>
<p align="blockquote">Swayed by her eloquence,</p>
<p align="blockquote">by the sweetness of her lips,</p>
<p align="blockquote">her husband followed her lead.</p>
<p align="blockquote">Thus a spirit of impurity</p>
<p align="blockquote">descended upon them,</p>
<p align="blockquote">transformed them,</p>
<p align="blockquote">bound itself to them and to all of their descendants,</p>
<p align="blockquote">as it is written:</p>
<p align="blockquote">&#x201C;But see, this did I find: God made men righteous but they invent</p>
<p align="blockquote">multitudinous contrivances&#x201D; [Eccles. 7:29].</p>
<p align="blockquote">Seeing his molten image having proved deceitful,</p>
<p align="blockquote">the human repented,</p>
<p align="blockquote">and conceived Seth in his image and likeness.</p>
<p align="blockquote">Seth conceived Enosh;</p>
<p align="blockquote">from them came Enoch who walked before God,</p>
<p align="blockquote">knowing and cognizing Him in truth.</p>
<p align="blockquote">As it says:</p>
<p align="blockquote">&#x201C;And Enoch walked with God&#x201D; [Gen. 5:22].</p>
<p align="blockquote">Generations passed until Noah&#x2019;s arose,</p>
<p align="blockquote">the tenth in count since Adam&#x2019;s.</p>
<p align="blockquote">He too knew God with a perfect knowledge,</p>
<p align="blockquote">prudence dwelling with Wisdom.</p>
<p align="blockquote">Thus Noah found favor in God&#x2019;s eyes,</p>
<p align="blockquote">as it is written:</p>
<p align="blockquote">&#x201C;And Noah found favor&#x201D; [Gen. 6:8].</p>
<p align="blockquote">Among Noah&#x2019;s three sons,</p>
<p align="blockquote">Shem was chosen, for he was the first born,</p>
<p align="blockquote">recognizing his Creator,</p>
<p align="blockquote">knowing and cognizing Him in faith.</p>
<p align="blockquote">His descendent Ever grasped hold of God&#x2019;s path,</p>
<p align="blockquote">upheld its steps,</p>
<p align="blockquote">was chosen from his entire generation</p>
<p align="blockquote">to be singled out for fame and praise.</p>
<p align="blockquote">By means of a knowledge</p>
<p align="blockquote">complete, lucid and pure,</p>
<p align="blockquote">Shem and Ever comprehended the rational commandments</p>
<p align="blockquote">and statutes divine,</p>
<p align="blockquote">setting right the branches on high.</p>
<p align="blockquote">And they charged the multitudes</p>
<p align="blockquote">to walk in God&#x2019;s paths.</p>
<p align="blockquote">The generations progressed.</p>
<p align="blockquote">The tenth after Noah&#x2019;s</p>
<p align="blockquote">was distinguished by the man</p>
<p align="blockquote">chosen from the womb since the dawn,</p>
<p align="blockquote">our father Abraham.</p>
<p align="blockquote">He perceived a knowledge of his Creator</p>
<p align="blockquote">transcending his predecessors&#x2019;,</p>
<p align="blockquote">comprehending God&#x2019;s reality</p>
<p align="blockquote">in a manner formerly unknown.</p>
<p align="blockquote">He began to call upon God&#x2019;s name</p>
<p align="blockquote">among all of the nations and kingdoms,</p>
<p align="blockquote">as it is written:</p>
<p align="blockquote">&#x201C;And there he built an altar to the Lord</p>
<p align="blockquote">and called upon God&#x2019;s name&#x201D; [Gen. 12:8].</p>
<p align="blockquote">And it says:</p>
<p align="blockquote">&#x201C;He planted an oak in Be&#x2018;er Sheva</p>
<p align="blockquote">and invoked the name of the Lord, the God of the world&#x201D; [Gen. 21:33].</p>
<p align="blockquote">Since he took possession of the attribute of divine love,</p>
<p align="blockquote">his son Isaac was chosen from among all of his sons and offspring.</p>
<p align="blockquote">As it is written:</p>
<p align="blockquote">&#x201C;God said to Abraham:</p>
<p align="blockquote">&#x2018;Do not be distressed over the boy or your handmaid;</p>
<p align="blockquote">whatever Sarah tells you, do as she says,</p>
<p align="blockquote">for it is through Isaac that your offspring will be continued&#x2019;&#x201D; [Gen. 21:12].</p>
<p align="blockquote">Isaac attained knowledge of his Creator,</p>
<p align="blockquote">he too exhorting his sons to walk in God&#x2019;s ways,</p>
<p align="blockquote">as it is written:</p>
<p align="blockquote">&#x201C;he built an altar there and invoked the Lord by name,</p>
<p align="blockquote">pitching there his tent&#x201D; [Gen. 26:25].</p>
<p align="blockquote">He took divine justice as his portion.</p>
<p align="blockquote">When his son Jacob was born,</p>
<p align="blockquote">the image of the likeness of the blessed Holy One,</p>
<p align="blockquote">engraved on the Throne of Glory,</p>
<p align="blockquote">manifested itself in the world.</p>
<p align="blockquote">For Jacob grasped the attributes of justice and mercy</p>
<p align="blockquote">a path equalized and balanced,</p>
<p align="blockquote">so that his ways were imbued with truth</p>
<p align="blockquote">and the paths of peace.</p>
<p align="blockquote">For fourteen years</p>
<p align="blockquote">he studied in Ever&#x2019;s school</p>
<p align="blockquote">and from his father Isaac</p>
<p align="blockquote">and his grandfather Abraham,</p>
<p align="blockquote">he received the knowledge of God.</p>
<p align="blockquote">Thus, <italic>shekhinah</italic>&#x2019;s glory was revealed to him.</p>
<p align="blockquote">Then the three patriarchs formed a chariot-throne</p>
<p align="blockquote">for Him who rides the ancient highest heavens [Ps. 68:34].</p>
<p align="blockquote">They fulfilled the Teaching and commandment,</p>
<p align="blockquote">serving their Creator by knowing Him;</p>
<p align="blockquote">their worship lacking nothing.</p>
<p align="blockquote">&#x201C;For Abraham obeyed Me and kept My charge:</p>
<p align="blockquote">My commandments, My laws and My teachings&#x201D; [Gen. 26:5].</p>
<p align="blockquote">Twelve sons were engendered by Jacob,</p>
<p align="blockquote">righteous and good,</p>
<p align="blockquote">who recognized the Creator, be He blessed,</p>
<p align="blockquote">and knew Him as they had learned</p>
<p align="blockquote">from their father Jacob.</p>
<p align="blockquote">From their knowledge and perceptions of the Creator,</p>
<p align="blockquote">they too observed the commandments:</p>
<p align="blockquote">&#x201C;Judah said to Onan:</p>
<p align="blockquote">&#x2018;Join with your brother&#x2019;s wife</p>
<p align="blockquote">and perform your levirate duty with her,</p>
<p align="blockquote">and provide offspring for your brother&#x2019;&#x201D; [Gen. 38:8].</p>
<p align="blockquote">So matters unfolded</p>
<p align="blockquote">until our father Jacob&#x2019;s descent to Egypt,</p>
<p align="blockquote">engendering offspring,</p>
<p align="blockquote">twelve tribes in the likeness of that which is on high,</p>
<p align="blockquote">the tribes of Yah,</p>
<p align="blockquote">the community of Israel,</p>
<p align="blockquote">whose numbers came to fulfillment at seventy.</p>
<p align="blockquote">After that generation,</p>
<p align="blockquote">they were immersed in Egypt,</p>
<p align="blockquote">among a people lacking comprehension,</p>
<p align="blockquote">whose speech was subtle and obscure</p>
<p align="blockquote">whose languages were different from their own.</p>
<p align="blockquote">Israel adopted their ways and abominations,</p>
<p align="blockquote">learnt their customs,</p>
<p align="blockquote">grew ignorant of the knowledge of God</p>
<p align="blockquote">inherited from their ancestors, elders, and primal progenitors.</p>
<p align="blockquote">Then God in His compassion,</p>
<p align="blockquote">sent them His beloved prophet, Moses,</p>
<p align="blockquote">faithful of His household.</p>
<p align="blockquote">He called to Moses, revealing Himself in a bush,</p>
<p align="blockquote">the angel Michael with <italic>shekhinah</italic>&#x2019;s glory.</p>
<p align="blockquote">God charged Moses</p>
<p align="blockquote">to inform the people that the time had come;</p>
<p align="blockquote">having seen their oppression,</p>
<p align="blockquote">their merciful father</p>
<p align="blockquote">would extricate them from their imprisonment and captivity.</p>
<p align="blockquote">With Moses&#x2019; own words did the process commence:</p>
<p align="blockquote">&#x201C;Moses said to God:</p>
<p align="blockquote">&#x2018;When I come to the Israelites and say to them</p>
<p align="blockquote">&#x201C;The God of your fathers has sent me to you,&#x201D;</p>
<p align="blockquote">and they ask me &#x201C;What is His name?&#x201D;</p>
<p align="blockquote">what shall I say to them?&#x2019;&#x201D; [Exod. 3:13].</p>
<p align="blockquote">Israel&#x2019;s fundamental question,</p>
<p align="blockquote">the essence of all mystical intentionality</p>
<p align="blockquote">and the mystery of faith,</p>
<p align="blockquote">is this very query:</p>
<p align="blockquote">&#x201C;What is His Name?&#x201D;</p>
<p align="blockquote">It is the desire to know its origin,</p>
<p align="blockquote">the manner in which the name</p>
<p align="blockquote">is bound to the Primal Cause.</p>
<p align="blockquote">In that holy place,</p>
<p align="blockquote">Moses received the knowledge of God,</p>
<p align="blockquote">learning that the divine possesses three names</p>
<p align="blockquote">composed of twelve letters,</p>
<p align="blockquote">faces within faces, ten <italic>sefirot</italic>,</p>
<p align="blockquote">existence within existences.</p>
<p align="blockquote">In verification of his mission,</p>
<p align="blockquote">God explained:</p>
<p align="blockquote">&#x201C;Thus shall you say to the Israelites,</p>
<p align="blockquote">&#x2018;EHeYeH sent me to you.&#x2019;&#x201D;</p>
<p align="blockquote">Scripture further states:</p>
<p align="blockquote">&#x201C;And God further said to Moses:</p>
<p align="blockquote">&#x2018;Thus shall you speak to the Israelites:</p>
<p align="blockquote">&#x201C;YHVH, the God of your fathers,</p>
<p align="blockquote">the God of Abraham, the God of Isaac,</p>
<p align="blockquote">and the God of Jacob has sent me to you,&#x201D;&#x2019;&#x201D;</p>
<p align="blockquote">placing the name EHeYeH aside</p>
<p align="blockquote">and commencing with YHVH,</p>
<p align="blockquote">adding and explicating:</p>
<p align="blockquote">&#x201C;This shall be My name forever,</p>
<p align="blockquote">This is my appellation for all eternity&#x201D; [Exod. 3:15].</p>
<p align="blockquote">And in that conversation God said:</p>
<p align="blockquote">&#x201C;And when you have freed the people,</p>
<p align="blockquote">they shall worship God on this very mountain&#x201D; [Exod. 3:12],</p>
<p align="blockquote">promising them that God would appear to them face to face,</p>
<p align="blockquote">and that they would see God&#x2019;s glory with their very eyes.</p>
<p align="blockquote">To extricate some of the populace</p>
<p align="blockquote">from their darkness and doubt</p>
<p align="blockquote">concerning the veracity of Moses&#x2019; prophecy,</p>
<p align="blockquote">God said:</p>
<p align="blockquote">&#x201C;Behold I will come to you in a thick cloud,</p>
<p align="blockquote">in order that the people might hear</p>
<p align="blockquote">when I speak with you</p>
<p align="blockquote">and so trust you ever after&#x201D; [Exod. 19:9].</p>
<p align="blockquote">In that holy convocation</p>
<p align="blockquote">the people directly saw <italic>shekhinah</italic>&#x2019;s glory,</p>
<p align="blockquote">viewing seven partitions of fire,</p>
<p align="blockquote">moving them to the fear of God and faith in His</p>
<p align="blockquote">goodness.</p>
<p align="blockquote">As soon as they heard that voice,</p>
<p align="blockquote">their souls almost departed from their bodies,</p>
<p align="blockquote">just as occurred among the nations,</p>
<p align="blockquote">as it says:</p>
<p align="blockquote">&#x201C;Has any people heard the voice of God</p>
<p align="blockquote">speaking from amidst the fire</p>
<p align="blockquote">as you have and lived?&#x201D; [Deut. 4:33].</p>
<p align="blockquote">And as it says:</p>
<p align="blockquote">&#x201C;All the world&#x2019;s kings acknowledged you,</p>
<p align="blockquote">for they heard the words of Your mouth&#x201D; [Ps. 138:4].</p>
<p align="blockquote">During that holy convocation,</p>
<p align="blockquote">Moses and Aaron, Nadav and Avihu,</p>
<p align="blockquote">seventy of Israel&#x2019;s elders and all of Israel</p>
<p align="blockquote">attained an illumination concerning God&#x2019;s reality</p>
<p align="blockquote">and the essence of God&#x2019;s glory,</p>
<p align="blockquote">each and every one in accord</p>
<p align="blockquote">with his perfection, ability, and power.</p>
<p align="blockquote">There were varied rungs among them,</p>
<p align="blockquote">some more inward, some outward,</p>
<p align="blockquote">some higher, some lower.</p>
<p align="blockquote">From this true knowing</p>
<p align="blockquote">the holy Torah was revealed,</p>
<p align="blockquote">coming forth from an inner voice,</p>
<p align="blockquote">spreading forth into seventy branches,</p>
<p align="blockquote">the seventy &#x201C;faces&#x201D; of the Torah.</p>
<p align="blockquote">These are the multiple meanings of its verses,</p>
<p align="blockquote">ever changing and transmuting in every direction:</p>
<p align="blockquote">from pure to impure,</p>
<p align="blockquote">forbidden to permitted,</p>
<p align="blockquote">ritually fit to ritually disqualified,</p>
<p align="blockquote">each parallel to its opposite</p>
<p align="blockquote">containing within themselves the ability</p>
<p align="blockquote">to declare a given reptile both pure and impure.</p>
<p align="blockquote">From that moment the prophets</p>
<p align="blockquote">who would arise in every generation</p>
<p align="blockquote">received their prophecies,</p>
<p align="blockquote">and the sages who in the future</p>
<p align="blockquote">would ascend to greatness</p>
<p align="blockquote">received the fundamentals</p>
<p align="blockquote">of their teachings, rulings, and debates.</p>
<p align="blockquote">As it is written:</p>
<p align="blockquote">&#x201C;From the beginning, I did not speak in secret;</p>
<p align="blockquote">From the time anything existed, I was there.</p>
<p align="blockquote">And now the Lord God has sent me,</p>
<p align="blockquote">endowed with His spirit&#x201D; [Isa. 48:16].</p>
<p align="blockquote">And it is also said:</p>
<p align="blockquote">&#x201C;The Lord spoke all these words</p>
<p align="blockquote">to your entire congregation</p>
<p align="blockquote">on the mountain, from amid the fire, cloud, and mist,</p>
<p align="blockquote">a great voice that did not cease&#x201D; [Deut. 5:19].</p>
<p align="blockquote">From that period until now,</p>
<p align="blockquote">there never ceased to be a generation of Israel</p>
<p align="blockquote">to which the heritage of Wisdom,</p>
<p align="blockquote">that is the knowledge of the divine Name,</p>
<p align="blockquote">was transmitted through the tradition of Oral Torah.</p>
<p align="blockquote">For our master Moses,</p>
<p align="blockquote">when death drew near</p>
<p align="blockquote">and the transmission of Wisdom was concealed from him,</p>
<p align="blockquote">handed this wisdom to Joshua,</p>
<p align="blockquote">as it is written:</p>
<p align="blockquote">&#x201C;Joshua the son of Nun was filled with the spirit of wisdom,</p>
<p align="blockquote">for Moses had placed his hands upon him&#x201D; [Deut. 34:9].</p>
<p align="blockquote">And Joshua transmitted it to the elders,</p>
<p align="blockquote">who sustained their generation</p>
<p align="blockquote">and were Israel&#x2019;s leaders,</p>
<p align="blockquote">praying for them during periods of trouble.</p>
<p align="blockquote">All Israel obeyed them</p>
<p align="blockquote">and were directed by their instruction,</p>
<p align="blockquote">as it is written:</p>
<p align="blockquote">&#x201C;Israel served the Lord during the lifetime of Joshua</p>
<p align="blockquote">and the lifetime of the elders who lived on after Joshua&#x201D; [Josh. 24:31].</p>
<p align="blockquote">And the elders transmitted to the prophets.</p>
<p align="blockquote">From the prophets it was given to the Men of the Great Assembly:</p>
<p align="blockquote">Daniel, Hananiah, Mishael and Azariah, Mordecai, Zerubavel and Ezra,</p>
<p align="blockquote">the last among them being Simon the Righteous.</p>
<p align="blockquote">Afterwards, this wisdom came to the masters of the Mishnah.</p>
<p align="blockquote">At the hour of his death,</p>
<p align="blockquote">R. Judah the Prince transmitted the tradition of wisdom</p>
<p align="blockquote">to his son Simon.</p>
<p align="blockquote">Thus R. Akiba and his companions entered the Garden.</p>
<p align="blockquote">And when R. Yohanan b. Zakkai and R. Eliezer b. Arakh</p>
<p align="blockquote">discoursed upon the mysteries of the Chariot,</p>
<p align="blockquote">an angel responded from heaven, saying:</p>
<p align="blockquote">&#x201C;Such indeed is the work of the Chariot.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn9">9</xref></sup></p>
<p align="blockquote">Since then God&#x2019;s Temple has been destroyed</p>
<p align="blockquote">and the numbers of sages has dwindled,</p>
<p align="blockquote">wisemen have ceased</p>
<p align="blockquote">and the pious and saints</p>
<p align="blockquote">for whose sake miracles were wrought</p>
<p align="blockquote">are no more.</p>
<p align="blockquote">The exile continues to worsen</p>
<p align="blockquote">and our sufferings proceed,</p>
<p align="blockquote">indeed undergoing constant renewal,</p>
<p align="blockquote">there being neither anyone to impart knowledge</p>
<p align="blockquote">nor comprehend tradition.</p>
<p align="blockquote">And thus this wisdom ceased from Israel.</p>
<p align="blockquote">Wisdom was lost and with it Torah.</p>
<p align="blockquote">No one knew its interpretation and subtleties,</p>
<p align="blockquote">exegesis and the reasons for its commandments.</p>
<p align="blockquote">For a powerful connection exists between this wisdom</p>
<p align="blockquote">and the commandments&#x2019; meanings,</p>
<p align="blockquote">the Torah&#x2019;s interpretation and the words of tradition,</p>
<p align="blockquote">many passages of Scripture being based upon it.</p>
<p align="blockquote">Instead, interpreters arose</p>
<p align="blockquote">possessing neither wisdom nor insight,</p>
<p align="blockquote">whether they turned either towards the right or the left.</p>
<p align="blockquote">They turned words of holiness into profanity,</p>
<p align="blockquote">diminishing Scripture</p>
<p align="blockquote">adding, subtracting, enhancing,</p>
<p align="blockquote">interpreting passages spoken through the holy spirit,</p>
<p align="blockquote">from a quarry of sacred gems,</p>
<p align="blockquote">in terms never to be entertained by human</p>
<p align="blockquote">consciousness,</p>
<p align="blockquote">let alone spoken,</p>
<p align="blockquote">and how much more so transcribed in a book.</p>
<p align="blockquote">I call such interpreters</p>
<p align="blockquote">those who</p>
<p align="blockquote">&#x201C;overturn the words of the living God, the Lord of Hosts&#x201D; [Jer. 23:36].</p>
<p align="blockquote">Concerning this dual cessation of wisdom</p>
<p align="blockquote">and its nullification in Israel,</p>
<p align="blockquote">the prophet, trembling, devastated, and sighing, said:</p>
<p align="blockquote">&#x201C;Many are the days which will pass in Israel</p>
<p align="blockquote">without the God of truth and without instruction&#x201D; [Isa. 30:21].</p>
<p align="blockquote">By the phrase &#x201C;without the God of truth&#x201D;</p>
<p align="blockquote">he referred to the interruption in the knowledge of God in Israel.</p>
<p align="blockquote">&#x201C;Without instruction&#x201D;</p>
<p align="blockquote">designates that on account of this negative situation</p>
<p align="blockquote">we lack clarity</p>
<p align="blockquote">concerning the reasons for the Torah&#x2019;s commandments</p>
<p align="blockquote">and its mysteries.</p>
<p align="blockquote">Just as it is with the words of Torah and Scripture,</p>
<p align="blockquote">so is it with the words of our sages of blessed memory,</p>
<p align="blockquote">who expounded upon this wisdom</p>
<p align="blockquote">in their homiletic compendia and narratives</p>
<p align="blockquote">in the form of parables and ciphers,</p>
<p align="blockquote">so as to hide these matters and conceal them.</p>
<p align="blockquote">They scattered one here and one there,</p>
<p align="blockquote">so as to hide their place.</p>
<p align="blockquote">When encountering them,</p>
<p align="blockquote">a person does not sense their inner meaning</p>
<p align="blockquote">but instead takes them at their face value.</p>
<p align="blockquote">He does not contemplate</p>
<p align="blockquote">the inner dimensions of their details,</p>
<p align="blockquote">pays no heed,</p>
<p align="blockquote">lacks the knowledge or insight to say:</p>
<p align="blockquote">&#x201C;How is it possible for our sages to have written such things,</p>
<p align="blockquote">to have put them into writing in a book,</p>
<p align="blockquote">unless a delightful treasure is hidden and concealed</p>
<p align="blockquote">within them?&#x201D;</p>
<p align="blockquote">So have I seen again and again</p>
<p align="blockquote">over the course of many years.</p>
<p align="blockquote">Yet I kept my silence,</p>
<p align="blockquote">placing hand to mouth</p>
<p align="blockquote">until I reached my fifth rung<sup><xref rid="fn10">10</xref></sup></p>
<p align="blockquote">and saw that the days of my life were setting before me,</p>
<p align="blockquote">that old age was rapidly approaching.</p>
<p align="blockquote">Therefore, I pressed forward to interpret</p>
<p align="blockquote">one of Scripture&#x2019;s twenty-four books,</p>
<p align="blockquote">encompassing every delight,</p>
<p align="blockquote">bespeaking matters weighty,</p>
<p align="blockquote">mysteries and secrets whose memory was lost</p>
<p align="blockquote">to Scripture&#x2019;s interpreters,</p>
<p align="blockquote">neglecting its perdurance and splendor:</p>
<p align="blockquote">that is the Song of Songs.</p>
<p align="blockquote">In accord with my strength,</p>
<p align="blockquote">I have interpreted it as I have received from our rabbis.</p>
<p align="blockquote">I have crowned it with the meanings of the commandments</p>
<p align="blockquote">and composed it in accord with the mysteries of creation.<sup><xref rid="fn11">11</xref></sup></p>
<p align="blockquote">I have observed</p>
<p align="blockquote">that concerning the Song of Songs</p>
<p align="blockquote">there are three classes of individuals</p>
<p align="blockquote">with three distinct sets of opinions.</p>
<p align="blockquote">The first group,</p>
<p align="blockquote">possessing neither understanding nor insight,</p>
<p align="blockquote">has left the world scattered with corpses.</p>
<p align="blockquote">They contend that its words are those of sexual desire,</p>
<p align="blockquote">seductive enchantment and falsehood,</p>
<p align="blockquote">vanity lacking all value.</p>
<p align="blockquote">Let their mouths be stuffed&#x0021;</p>
<p align="blockquote">Their eyes blinded&#x0021;</p>
<p align="blockquote">For if their words were true,</p>
<p align="blockquote">it would not have been composed among the works of Scripture</p>
<p align="blockquote">nor counted among them.</p>
<p align="blockquote">The second group</p>
<p align="blockquote">views it as an allegory of the love of the Creator,</p>
<p align="blockquote">the God of the entire world,</p>
<p align="blockquote">for the splendor of Israel,</p>
<p align="blockquote">His special treasure and unique inheritance,</p>
<p align="blockquote">comparable to the desire of the lover for his beloved,</p>
<p align="blockquote">of a man for his wife.</p>
<p align="blockquote">They have established their words,</p>
<p align="blockquote">suggested their interpretations,</p>
<p align="blockquote">in accord with this allegory.</p>
<p align="blockquote">The third group,</p>
<p align="blockquote">those who receive <italic>shekhinah</italic>,</p>
<p align="blockquote">who possess a portion in God&#x2019;s Torah</p>
<p align="blockquote">and remember it well,</p>
<p align="blockquote">the true wise men of Israel</p>
<p align="blockquote">who have revealed its secrets</p>
<p align="blockquote">and hidden mysteries,</p>
<p align="blockquote">who have brought forth its occult depths</p>
<p align="blockquote">through wisdom&#x2019;s path and knowledge,</p>
<p align="blockquote">have interpreted the entire text</p>
<p align="blockquote">with that pithy principle</p>
<p align="blockquote">enunciated by our sages in the tractate on Oaths:</p>
<p align="blockquote">&#x201C;Every Solomon mentioned in the Song of Songs is holy,<sup><xref rid="fn12">12</xref></sup></p>
<p align="blockquote">referring to Him who is the possessor of peace,</p>
<p align="blockquote">save one:</p>
<p align="blockquote">&#x2018;I have my own vineyard: You may have the thousand O Solomon &#x2026;&#x2019; [Cant. 8:12].&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn13">13</xref></sup></p>
<p align="blockquote">Our sages state further in Sanhedrin,</p>
<p align="blockquote">the chapter called &#x201C;Portion&#x201D;:<sup><xref rid="fn14">14</xref></sup></p>
<p align="blockquote">&#x201C;Anyone who recites a verse of the Song of Songs</p>
<p align="blockquote">treating it as a mere song,</p>
<p align="blockquote">brings evil into the world.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn15">15</xref></sup></p>
<p align="blockquote">In the tractate Hands</p>
<p align="blockquote">R. Akiva states</p>
<p align="blockquote">that &#x201C;the entire world&#x2019;s value</p>
<p align="blockquote">can not be compared to the day</p>
<p align="blockquote">upon which the Song of Songs was given to Israel.</p>
<p align="blockquote">For while all of the Writings are holy,</p>
<p align="blockquote">the Song of Songs is the Holy of Holies.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn16">16</xref></sup></p>
<p align="blockquote">I have therefore directed my attention</p>
<p align="blockquote">and proposed in my mind and thoughts</p>
<p align="blockquote">to reveal in my commentary that true principle</p>
<p align="blockquote">which our sages have transmitted through allusion.</p>
<p align="blockquote">I have established it upon the pillars of their words,</p>
<p align="blockquote">supported it upon the pedestals of their exegesis,</p>
<p align="blockquote">and the wise will understand.</p>
<p>However, I must commence with three fundamental principles, in order to instruct you and provide your understanding with illumination.</p>
<p>The first principle serves to inform you that Solomon wrote this book in his old age,<sup><xref rid="fn17">17</xref></sup> inspired by the holy spirit. He referred to God&#x2019;s name as Solomon, like his own name. For we have found God designated as &#x201C;Peace,&#x201D; as in Judges 6:24: &#x201C;Gideon built an altar there and called it &#x201C;the Lord of Peace.&#x201D; The name possesses two usages, one revealed, the second esoteric.<sup><xref rid="fn18">18</xref></sup> Through it Solomon glimpsed all that would occur in the future with regard to the construction of the Temples and Israel&#x2019;s exiles. He concealed the mention of the exile in an allusive manner for it was not to be mentioned in poetic language. His first words contained hidden within them wondrous songs, and an awesome righteousness,<sup><xref rid="fn19">19</xref></sup> making mention of the construction of God&#x2019;s throne, its appearance, height, work, and shape and the number of steps <italic>[ma&#x2018;alot</italic>] which it possessed. He made mention of all of the events which would befall Israel from the Exodus, at which time they attained the appellation of God&#x2019;s people. For God&#x2019;s name is united with His people until the seventh millennium, the day which is entirely Shabbat and rest eternal. At the conclusion he concealed, indeed sealed, the work with an allusion to the exile&#x2019;s end and the fact that Israel would hold fast to their Torah and stand firm in faith in every location, even when suffering from intensified destruction and evil decrees.</p>
<p>Solomon called it the Song of Songs, a song composed in the form of an allegorical parable replete with inner meaning. A person must thus interpret the song, establishing upon its foundations. But he must understand that it is filled with many elements provided for the sake of the narrational continuity of the allegory and the context of its imagery, rather than for any other purpose or function. For example, let me quote one verse from this book. It states: &#x201C;Let him kiss me with the kisses &#x2026;&#x201D; [Cant. 1:2]. The kiss symbolizes the soul&#x2019;s adhesion to God, as we will explain. The verse further states &#x201C;the kisses of his mouth.&#x201D; There is no additional meaning here. But having analogized the soul&#x2019;s adhesion to God with a kiss, the verse is constrained to state &#x201C;the kisses of his mouth&#x201D; in order to tie the allegorical figure to its context. Thus one of the wise men of the generation has already written. Know that there are parables in this work whose details should in no manner undergo exegesis, such as: &#x201C;the buds appear in the land, the time of pruning has come, the song of the turtledove is heard in our land&#x201D; [Cant. 2:12]. We are not to minutely examine such and similar texts. Rather, we are simply to interpret it as an allegorical figure referring to the efflorescence of the coming days of release, while the winter rains refer to departing days of exile. Similarly: &#x201C;Your belly is a heap of wheat&#x201D; [Cant. 7:3&#x2013;4]; and &#x201C;Your breasts are like twin gazelles&#x201D; [Cant. 4:5]. Neither through the exercise of rational nor traditional means of exegesis should you seek out their detailed meaning, for you will mire your mind in a multitude of words, vanities, and obstacles galore: &#x201C;Hear this and accept it&#x201D; [Job 5:27].</p>
<p>The second principle serves to inform you with words truly reliable that this text possesses words whose meaning is not revealed by any book, yet which serve as the foundation of its allegory and edifice. Among them are those whose meaning we have received from tradition; others have been found scattered in the homiletic dicta and exegetic texts of our sages, deep wells in which no drop of water is wasted. All of their words possess an inner heart free of an obstructive husk.</p>
<p>We have been taught by tradition that the following phrases refer to divine Wisdom:<sup><xref rid="fn20">20</xref></sup> &#x201C;of wood from Lebanon&#x201D; [Cant. 3:9], &#x201C;the scent of Lebanon&#x201D; [Cant. 4:11], &#x201C;Come with me from Lebanon&#x201D; [Cant. 4:8], &#x201C;flowing streams from Lebanon&#x201D; [Cant. 4:15]. This too was the intention of our sages when they interpreted &#x201C;of wood from Lebanon&#x201D; [Cant. 3:9] as referring to the counsel of Torah, which is refined [<italic>ha-melubbenet</italic>] in its words. The Aramaic translation also took this tact &#x201C;From this goodly mountain and Lebanon&#x201D; as &#x201C;that goodly mountain and sanctuary&#x201D; [Deut. 3:25].</p>
<p>We have further received from tradition that &#x201C;your love is more delightful than wine&#x201D; [Cant. 1:2] and &#x201C;I will let you drink of the spiced wine&#x201D; [Cant. 8:2] also symbolize divine Wisdom. So too, we have discovered that the number seventy designates the seventy divine names emanated from Wisdom. For Wisdom&#x2019;s numerical equivalent is seventy-three; the meaning of the remaining three is well-established.<sup><xref rid="fn21">21</xref></sup> All that which we have mentioned is support and aid for this matter in addition to what has been received from tradition. Similarly, the terminology of &#x201C;perfume&#x201D; or &#x201C;spice&#x201D; as in &#x201C;all choice perfumes&#x201D; [Cant. 4:14], &#x201C;to the bed of spices&#x201D; [Cant. 6:2], &#x201C;than any spice&#x201D; [Cant. 4:10], &#x201C;that its perfume might spread&#x201D; [Cant. 4:16], and &#x201C;to the mountain of spices&#x201D; [Cant. 8:14] figure Wisdom. For it constitutes the beginning of being; from the point of Wisdom commences the propagation and expansion of scent.<sup><xref rid="fn22">22</xref></sup></p>
<p>Similarly, tradition imparts that the following figure the glory of the <italic>shekhinah</italic>: &#x201C;like the apple among the forest&#x2019;s trees&#x201D; [Cant. 2:3]; &#x201C;your breath is like apples&#x2019; fragrance&#x201D; [Cant. 7:9]; &#x201C;refresh me with apples&#x201D; [Cant. 2:5]; and &#x201C;under the apple tree I aroused you&#x201D; [Cant. 8:5]. This figure derives from the change of the apple&#x2019;s cover from green to red to white, like the appearance of the rainbow within the cloud.<sup><xref rid="fn23">23</xref></sup> The apple also figures the two cherubim, as it states in the tractate <italic>Shabbat</italic>: &#x201C;&#x2018;Like the scent of a field blessed by God&#x2019; [Gen. 27:27]. R. Yehudah states in the name of Rav: &#x2018;Like the scent of a field of apple trees.&#x2019;&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn24">24</xref></sup></p>
<p>&#x201C;The shepherd among the lilies&#x201D; [Cant. 6:3], &#x201C;hedged about by lilies&#x201D; [Cant. 7:3], &#x201C;a lily of the valleys&#x201D; [Cant. 2:1], and &#x201C;to gather lilies&#x201D; [Cant. 6:2] refer to that plant known as &#x201C;lidi,&#x201D; which possesses six leaves and figures the six supernal boundaries.<sup><xref rid="fn25">25</xref></sup> On the other hand, &#x201C;to browse in the gardens&#x201D; [Cant. 6:2], &#x201C;who lingers in the garden&#x201D; [Cant. 8:13], &#x201C;the garden spring&#x201D; [Cant. 4:15], and &#x201C;a garden locked&#x201D; [Cant. 4:12] refer to the <italic>shekhinah</italic>, as we will explain further on.</p>
<p>The third principle comes to inform you briefly concerning the principles of Kabbalah inherent in these verses which serve as the pillar upon which all things rely, the peg upon which they hang, so that the interpretation of this book might be absorbed like water, directing your mind in the proper path.</p>
<p>The wise man stated in an allegorical parable:<sup><xref rid="fn26">26</xref></sup></p>
<p align="blockquote">There is a mine for silver,</p>
<p align="blockquote">And a place where gold is refined,</p>
<p align="blockquote">Iron is taken out of the earth,</p>
<p align="blockquote">And copper smelted from the rock [Job 28:1&#x2013;2].</p>
<p>He mentions the four metals smelted from the rock, corresponding to the four types of elements as manifest in a human: white, red, green, and black biles. Similarly, every living thing, whether sentient or non-sentient, draws its life from the primary spiritual principles which exist among the ten <italic>sefirot</italic>. These are the primal progenitors of all generated things. When the verse enumerates the four terrestrial elements: silver, gold, iron, and copper, it is alluding to the four primary elements, informing us that they possess a place of origin.<sup><xref rid="fn27">27</xref></sup></p>
<p>The verse furthermore explicates and designates the source of their origin: &#x201C;He sets bounds for darkness&#x201D; [Job 28:3]. It is common knowledge that darkness designates absolute nullity.<sup><xref rid="fn28">28</xref></sup> Under no circumstances can nullity be described with the terminology of formation [<italic>yetzirah</italic>] but rather that of creation [<italic>beriah</italic>]. In this context creation designates the manner in which God differentiated another principle and rung of emanation from darkness, which in itself lacks boundary or end. In stating &#x201C;He sets bounds for darkness,&#x201D; the intention is that God set a boundary to darkness, infixing within it border and limit. &#x201C;To, every limit man probes&#x201D; [Job 28:3]. The possibility of speculative analysis inheres within each and every quality and being existing by the creative power of that nullity. That is to say, after these forces were actualized from their potential state, He made them into qualities and instruments that are subject to measure and hence to inquiry. For this reason Scripture speaks of darkness in terms of creation, and the light which existed within the creative capacity of darkness in terms of formation, as it says: &#x201C;He forms light and creates darkness&#x201D; [Isa. 48:7]. This is also the meaning of: &#x201C;He draws mysteries out of the darkness, and brings obscurities into light&#x201D; [Job 12:22]. Nullity is designated as darkness and obscurity. Inherent within its creative power were light and other entities. This is further the meaning of: &#x201C;rocks in deepest darkness&#x201D; [Job 28:3]. Understand this, for it comprises a fundamental principle.</p>
<p>The verse further states: &#x201C;A stream sprang forth from a dwelling-place, forgotten by wayfarers, destitute of men, far removed&#x201D; [Job 28:4]. That is to say, the source of the channel watering all things was hidden and sealed. The figure of the stream refers to the path of Transcendent Wisdom. There was therefore neither modality nor place to water Lebanon&#x2019;s trees or its planted cedars. But, Scripture says, &#x201C;a stream sprang forth&#x201D; from the place from which it was appropriate to flow. Due to the extraordinary mysteriousness of that place from which the stream flowed, it was parabolically and with poetic richness described as being &#x201C;forgotten by wayfarers, destitute of men, far removed&#x201D; [Job 28:4].</p>
<p>The text further states: &#x201C;Earth, out of which food grows, is changed below as if into fire. Its rocks are a source of sapphires; it contains gold dust too&#x201D; [Job 28:5&#x2013;6]. That locus which is the origin of existence, the awakening of desire, is designated as the &#x201C;earth.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn29">29</xref></sup> Providing sustenance for all things, it is the source of life, supplying the needs of the upper and lower worlds. &#x201C;[It] is changed below as if into fire&#x201C;: the figure refers to its wondrous illumination and pure light, transcending all likeness and comparison.<sup><xref rid="fn30">30</xref></sup></p>
<p>&#x201C;Its rocks are a source of sapphires&#x201D;: the quarry of the holy gems, the twenty-two primordial letters, each and every one an object of value, transformed into a creative vessel. From them holiness draws nigh, a tower of might is constructed and quarried, &#x201C;to which the righteous man runs and is safe&#x201D; [Prov. 18:10].</p>
<p>&#x201C;No bird of prey knows the path to it, the falcon&#x2019;s eye has not gazed upon it&#x201D; [Job 28:7]. Wisdom&#x2019;s thirty-two pathways are designated as a &#x201C;path,&#x201D; for they were previously hidden and sealed, unknown to the ministering angels. For &#x201C;the falcon&#x2019;s eye has not gazed upon it&#x201D; until the time of favor.</p>
<p>&#x201C;Man sets his hand against the flinty rock and overturns mountains by the roots&#x201D; [Job 28:9]. Wisdom is compared to a flinty rock on account of the paths hidden within it, the depth of Wisdom being analogized to an entity hidden in a hard and difficult place, whose foundation must be overturned.</p>
<p>&#x201C;He carves out channels through rock; His eyes behold every precious thing&#x201D; [Job 28:10]. Channels [<italic>ye &#x2018;orim</italic>] refers to the totality of all of the sefirotic existences [<italic>havayot</italic>] and is derived from &#x201C;light&#x201D; [<italic>&#x2018;or</italic>] as in &#x201C;the waters [&#x003D;lights] lift up their voices [Ps. 93:3].<sup><xref rid="fn31">31</xref></sup> These primordial existences are implied by the term &#x201C;water&#x201D; in the Biblical account of creation, as it is written: &#x201C;And the spirit of God hovered over the face of the waters&#x201D; [Gen. 1:2]. After all of these channels flowed forth, &#x201C;his eyes beheld every precious thing.&#x201D;</p>
<p>Among the phenomena emanated on the first day were ten entities commingled one with the other: heaven and earth; primordial chaos;<sup><xref rid="fn32">32</xref></sup> light and darkness; wind and water; and the quality of day and the quality of night.<sup><xref rid="fn33">33</xref></sup> This is the intent of &#x201C;He dams up the sources of the streams&#x201D; [Job 28:11]. Since these ten entities were considered as one, the cosmos being in the inchoate state of water intermixed with water, God dammed those watery channels, separating the waters with the command: &#x201C;Let there be an expanse in the midst of the water &#x2026;&#x201D; [Gen 1:6]. Thus the verse continues, &#x201C;from its hiddenness He brought forth light.&#x201D; The hiddenness of transcendent Wisdom brought forth light.</p>
<p>&#x201C;Whence [<italic>me-ayin</italic>] can Wisdom be found?&#x201D; [Job 28:12]. This Wisdom itself derives from Nought [<italic>ayin</italic>], the primordial Nought, no mortal knowing its value [<italic>&#x2018;erkah</italic>] which here means its order and array. That is to say, no one knows how to order the primal existences that are situated within her or how to know its characteristics. As it is written: &#x201C;Who like Me can announce, can foretell it&#x2014;and match Me thereby? Even as I told the future to an ancient people &#x2026;&#x201D; [Isa. 44:7]. &#x201C;[For Wisdom] can not be found in the land of the living&#x201D; [Job 28:13]. Even the angels do not know it. Thus the text states figuratively: &#x201C;The deep says: &#x2018;It is not in me.&#x2019; The sea says: &#x2018;I do not have it&#x2019;&#x201D; [Job 28:14]. Similarly we find &#x201C;But whence does wisdom come?&#x201D; [Job 28:20] and &#x201C;it is hidden from the eyes of all of the living&#x201D; [Job 28:21], from them whose lives are eternal. &#x201C;Concealed from all the fowl of heaven&#x201D;&#x2014;the ministering angels.</p>
<p>&#x201C;<italic>Abaddon</italic> and death say&#x201D; [Job 28:22]&#x2014;this is primal void, whence comes the emanation of all of the existences. &#x201C;God understands its way&#x201D; [Job 28:23]&#x2014;by meditating upon it. It traced and emanated the four primal elements, these being &#x201C;For He sees to the ends of the earth, observes all that is beneath the heavens, when he fixed the weight of the winds, set the measure of the waters&#x201D; [Job 28:24].</p>
<p>&#x201C;Then He saw and gauged it&#x201D; [Job 28:27]&#x2014;gazing upon Purity of Thought [<italic>keter</italic>], just as a man considering an enterprise first examines it within his heart and then begins to undertake it. Thus our sages say: &#x201C;the thought of the righteous preceded all.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn34">34</xref></sup> In accord with the images within, it traced the totality which emanated from it. &#x201C;He saw it and gaged it&#x201D;: the three primal &#x201C;books&#x201D;&#x2014;Wisdom, Understanding, and Knowledge. &#x201C;He measured it&#x201D;&#x2014;the existences were not arrayed in accord with the order of the sefirotic structure. Rather God, be He praised, brought the existences into being, arrayed them in order, transformed them into a structure, after combining, measuring, and transposing the twenty-two letters, binding each and every one to its colleague, so that they paralleled one another. &#x201C;And He probed it&#x201D;: He affixed boundary to the sefirotic qualities, rendered them accessible to probing, although they in principle possessed no boundary from their beginning.</p>
<p>&#x201C;He said to man: &#x201C;See, fear of the Lord is Wisdom&#x201D; [Job 28:28]. For Wisdom [<italic>&#x1E25;okhmah</italic>] is the Holy One&#x2019;s quality of goodness, all existing, going forth and being emanated from the luminescence of Wisdom and continually blessed through it without cessation. Because their origin is from it, it provides the essence of their sustenance. The remaining <italic>sefirot</italic> possess but one request, toward which the entirety of their desire is directed. That is to ascend and enter into the sacred sanctuary, to draw water from the honored fonts of Wisdom, as we are about to explain. Having provided you with these three introductory principles, I will explicate the text with the help of God.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<h1>Text</h1>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[1:1] The Song of Songs, which is Solomon&#x2019;s.</bold></p>
<p><bold>The Song of Songs:</bold> The most pleasant of canticles, the choicest of songs; words of might recited by the Throne of Glory,<sup><xref rid="fn35">35</xref></sup> day to day expressing utterance, standing in prayer in good order arrayed, its speech lucid, in all things well ordered and sure.</p>
<p><bold>Which is Solomon&#x2019;s:</bold> This is a name designating the Holy One, blessed be He. As it is written: &#x201C;Gideon built there an altar to the Lord and called it &#x2018;the Lord of peace&#x2019;&#x201D; [Judges 6:24]. This is the meaning of the statement of our Sages of blessed memory: &#x201C;The song which the Holy One blessed be He recites daily.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn36">36</xref></sup></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[1:2] Oh, let him kiss me the kisses of his mouth; for your love is more delightful than wine.</bold></p>
<p><bold>Oh let him kiss me:</bold> These are the Glory&#x2019;s<sup><xref rid="fn37">37</xref></sup> words, full of longing, desiring to make its ascent, to adhere to the light of the supernal luminescence to which nothing else is like. It ascends in thought and idea and thus speaks in third person. The kiss symbolizes the joy attained by the soul in its adhesion to the source of life and the additional infusion of the holy spirit.<sup><xref rid="fn38">38</xref></sup> Thus the verse specifies &#x201C;kisses.&#x201D; For each and every sefirotic power<sup><xref rid="fn39">39</xref></sup> receives consciousness and a superabundance from that sweet light and pure refulgence. When it speaks to the Glory, gateway to the entities [i.e., the <italic>sefirot</italic>], it speaks in third person.</p>
<p><bold>For your love is better</bold> [<italic>tovim</italic>] <bold>than wine:</bold> This emanated light expands over me because it comes from You, that is to say, it is derived from &#x201C;wine,&#x201D; from divine Wisdom called &#x201C;I,&#x201D; the rung of supernal luminescence. All desire and will is to ascend and adhere to Wisdom.</p>
<p><bold>For your love is better</bold> [<italic>tovim</italic>] <bold>than wine:</bold> The phrase &#x201C;is better&#x201D; [<italic>tovim</italic>] refers to the outpouring and amplification of that clear light, which divides and shines in all directions.<sup><xref rid="fn40">40</xref></sup> As it says: &#x201C;when Aaron lights <italic>[behetivo]</italic> the lamps&#x201D; [Exod. 30:8]&#x2014;which the Aramaic translation renders as &#x201C;kindles.&#x201D; Such also is the meaning of &#x201C;God saw that the light was good&#x201D; [Gen. 1:4].<sup><xref rid="fn41">41</xref></sup></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[1:3] Your oils are of fine aroma;</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>your name is like oil poured forth.</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Therefore the maidens love you.</bold></p>
<p><bold>Your oils are of fine aroma:</bold> He calls the effulgent flow from the Glory, the gateway to the entities, &#x201C;aroma.&#x201D; From there it increases and flows down into the seventy branches that surround the central column. Counting it, there are seventy-one. Because of this, the text says: &#x201C;from the kisses of his mouth&#x201D;: from that very light.<sup><xref rid="fn42">42</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>Your name is like oil poured forth:</bold> Your name is like fine oil, poured from one vessel into another. The seventy names are emanated from the seven <italic>sefirot. tiferet</italic> and the Crown<sup><xref rid="fn43">43</xref></sup> are for Israel, the singular people, for Israel nurse from the trunk of the tree, <italic>tiferet</italic> and Crown, all joined as one. But its aroma travels a great distance. So too Your name increases and is poured forth as pure light to <italic>shekhinah</italic>, which is contained and sealed into all.<sup><xref rid="fn44">44</xref></sup> Counting her they are seventy-two. This is the meaning of &#x201C;therefore the maidens love you.&#x201D;</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[1:4] Draw me after you, let us run&#x0021;</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>The king has brought me to his chambers.</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Let us delight and rejoice in your love,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Savoring it more than wine&#x2014;</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>They love you sincerely&#x0021;</bold></p>
<p><bold>Draw me after you:</bold> The Glory says: &#x201C;May it be your will that I might ascend towards you.&#x201D; <bold>Let us run:</bold> When the middle column [the Glory] ascends, all of the branches ascend with it. When it receives a superabundance of blessing, all of them are blessed, as I will explain further on.</p>
<p>He calls forth, saying: <bold>The king has brought me to his chambers.</bold> His desire is that I should ascend and enter his chambers by means of his paths whose number is thirty-two. And upon my entrance: <bold>We will delight and rejoice.</bold> This joy consists of the additional infusion of the holy spirit into the seventy-two names of the Holy One, blessed be He.</p>
<p><bold>We will savor it</bold> [<italic>nazkirah</italic>]: <italic>Nazkirah</italic> is derived from <italic>azkarah</italic>,<sup><xref rid="fn45">45</xref></sup> for the soul&#x2019;s delight is derived from the pleasure of scent.</p>
<p><bold>The upright</bold> [<italic>meisharim</italic>] <bold>love you:</bold> By the upright Solomon refers to the simple infants and sucklings lacking complexity [<italic>harkavah</italic>], as it says: &#x201C;it is You who have established the upright&#x201D; [Ps. 99:4]. <bold>Love you:</bold> The goal of their desire and intention is to ascend and adhere to the place from which they draw nourishment.<sup><xref rid="fn46">46</xref></sup> Our sages have accordingly instituted liturgical blessings, the recitation of the Sanctus, and the affirmation of divine unity so as to draw forth and emanate the energies of the Fathers [<italic>&#x1E25;esed, gevurah, tiferet</italic>] to the other <italic>sefirot</italic>, their children. With respect to this matter and in accord with the interpretation which I have provided here, our Sages have stated in the Midrash to Canticles: &#x2018;&#x201C;The King has brought me to his chambers&#x2019;: These are the chambers of the Garden of Eden.&#x201D;</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[1:5] I am dark, but comely,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>O daughters of Jerusalem&#x2014;</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Like the tents of Kedar,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Like the pavilions of Solomon.</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[1:6] Do not stare at me because I am swarthy,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Because the sun has gazed upon me.</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>My mother&#x2019;s sons quarreled with me,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>They made me guard the vineyards;</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>My own vineyard I did not guard.</bold></p>
<p>These are the <italic>shekhinah</italic>&#x2019;s words, who descended with our father Jacob to Egypt, as it is written: &#x201C;I will descend with you to Egypt&#x201D; [Gen. 46:4]. She participated in Israel&#x2019;s exile, as our sages state: &#x201C;When they were exiled to Egypt, the Presence was with them, as it states: &#x2018;Was I not exiled with you with the house of your fathers when you were in Egypt?&#x2019; [I Sam. 2:27].&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn47">47</xref></sup> She complains and thunders forth about her being in exile, traveling darkened with the angelic forces apportioned to the world&#x2019;s nations. She says, <bold>I am dark:</bold> Swarthy from exile. If I am not lovely <bold>like the pavilions of Solomon:</bold> The name of the Holy One, blessed be He,<sup><xref rid="fn48">48</xref></sup> like the essence of the heavens in its purity. And so it says: &#x201C;He stretches the heavens like a tent&#x201D; [Ps. 104:2].<sup><xref rid="fn49">49</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>Do not stare at me:</bold> Do not despise me because I am swarthy, <bold>because the sun has gazed upon me,</bold> because I am situated amongst my children who are enslaved, at hard labor, performing all of their work in the field. My <bold>mother&#x2019;s sons:</bold> The similitude refers to the holy spirit, from which all things are emanated; that is to say the remaining angelic princes appointed as custodians over each and every nation.</p>
<p><bold>Quarreled with me:</bold> They raged against me and banished me from my place, as our sages say: &#x201C;No nation falls until his angelic prince is first cast down. As it says: &#x2018;On that day, the Lord will punish the host of heaven in heaven and the kings of the earth on the earth&#x2019; [Isa. 24:21]; and: &#x2018;How are you fallen from heaven, O Shining One, son of Dawn&#x0021; How are you felled to earth, O vanquisher of nations&#x0021;&#x2019; [Isa. 14:12]; and says further: &#x2018;For My sword shall be seen in the sky; Lo, it shall come down upon Edom&#x2019; [Isa. 34:5].&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn50">50</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>They made me guard the vineyards:</bold> I am belabored in fulfilling the needs of the nations and ensuring their preservation. I have no leisure to watch over My people, for they are not in their land and I accompany them in their exile. The nation is designated a vineyard, for just as a vineyard requires labor, pruning, and watering, so too does a people. Everything existing within the world is in need of the primary forces for their growth and blossoming.</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[1:7] Tell me, whom I love so well;</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Where do you pasture your sheep?</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Where do you rest them at noon?</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Let me not be like one who strays</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Beside the flocks of your fellows.</bold></p>
<p><bold>Tell me:</bold> Show me your place so that I might go there; so that you might dwell with me as before; so that my children might return as in ancient days.</p>
<p><bold>Where do you pasture your sheep?:</bold> Pasturing refers to the satisfaction derived from the joy of emanation and its superabundance. Our sages designated this as &#x201C;eating.&#x201D; As they stated in <italic>Midrash Shemot Rabbah: &#x201C;</italic>They saw God&#x201D; [Exod. 24:11], their eyes drew their nourishment from the <italic>shekhinah</italic>. R. Yohanan states that this was true eating. As it says: &#x201C;In the King&#x2019;s countenance resides life&#x201D; [Prov. 16:15].<sup><xref rid="fn51">51</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>Where do you rest them at noon?:</bold> The parable refers to the removal of the Glory and its ascension to highest heights of heaven.</p>
<p><bold>Let me not be as one who strays beside the flocks of your fellows&#x0021;:</bold> For how long will you desire that I be intermingled among the other nations, who are the flocks of your fellows? The text states &#x201C;beside&#x201D; [&#x2018;<italic>al</italic>&#x2014;literally &#x201C;over&#x201D;] because the Central Pillar is exalted over all.</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[1:8] If you do not know, O fairest of women,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Go follow the tracks of the sheep,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>And graze your kids</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>By the shepherds&#x2019; tents.</bold></p>
<p>The Glory replies: <bold>If you do not know, O fairest of women</bold> the cause of my removal and the delay of the End and desire to return with your children to your cities and to your place, <bold>go follow the tracks of the sheep</bold>&#x2014;direct your children with goodly instruction&#x2014;in rectitude, fear of heaven, and propriety, so that they might hold fast to My service and faith and follow the practice of the patriarchs and shepherds rather than the nations&#x2019; laws, which are vain and deceitful. So Ezekiel expounds: &#x201C;Cast away, every one of you, the detestable things that you are drawn to, and do not defile yourselves with the fetishes of Egypt. I am the Lord your God &#x2026;&#x201D; [20:7]. &#x201C;Walk in My statutes &#x2026;&#x201D; [20:19]. Daniel promised that throughout this lengthy period of exile, Israel would observe Torah and hold fast to their faith, as it is written: &#x201C;The enlightened will shine like the radiance of the firmament and those who lead the multitudes to righteousness will be like the stars forever&#x201D; [Dan. 12:3].</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[1:9] I have likened you, my darling,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>To a mare in Pharaoh&#x2019;s chariots.</bold></p>
<p><bold>To a mare:</bold> These are the words of the Glory. The figure refers to Pharaoh&#x2019;s pursuit of Israel, the Glory and the Presence of Its might accompanying them, with his chariots and cavalry.</p>
<p><bold>I have likened you, my darling:</bold> Israel gazed at the <italic>shekhinah</italic> just like an individual sees the image of [<italic>ha-medammeh le</italic>-]<sup><xref rid="fn52">52</xref></sup> his companion and says: &#x201C;It&#x2019;s so and so&#x0021;&#x201D; So did Israel gaze upon the <italic>shekhinah</italic>, point towards her and say: &#x201C;This is my God and I will glorify Him&#x0021;&#x201D; [Isa. 15:2].</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[1:10] Your cheeks are comely with plaited wreaths&#x2026;</bold>.</p>
<p>The figure is that of the <italic>shekhinah</italic> leaving exile and entering the bridal chamber. Wreaths and strings of pearls are women&#x2019;s jewelry, the ornaments of a bride.</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[1:11] We will add wreaths of gold</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>to your points<sup><xref rid="fn53">53</xref></sup> of silver.</bold></p>
<p>The parable conveys that both written and oral Torah are conveyed by the <italic>shekhinah</italic>. The two are compared to gold and silver: &#x201C;I prefer the teaching You proclaimed to thousands of gold and silver pieces&#x201D; [Ps. 119:72]. Similarly, they are compared to wine and milk, and honey and milk, as in &#x201C;All who are thirsty, come for water &#x2026; buy &#x2026; wine and milk without cost&#x201D; [Isa. 55:1]. And &#x201C;Sweetness drops from your lips O bride; honey and milk are under your tongue&#x201D; [Song of Songs 4:11]. That is to say that they are all the image and appearance: water from wind and fire from water. Because redness is closer to us, the verse gives precedence to the red. But the Holy One gives precedence to the white, as it says: &#x201C;Mine is silver and mine is gold&#x201D; [Hag. 2:8].<sup><xref rid="fn54">54</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>To your points of silver:</bold> Oral Torah is emanated from the written and it sustains her, just as the spirit upholds the body. Thus written Torah has been compared to points [<italic>nekudot</italic>], since the vowels [<italic>nekudot</italic>] function among the consonants like the spirit in the body, as our sages say.<sup><xref rid="fn55">55</xref></sup> Both Torahs, oral and written, were given through the <italic>shekhinah</italic> as they state in the Midrash to Psalms, &#x201C;The Lord gives a command; the women who bring the news are a great host&#x201D; [Ps. 68:12].<sup><xref rid="fn56">56</xref></sup> From here it is clear that the innermost voice was not differentiated and rendered audible until it reached the end of the chain of emanation, the tenth <italic>sefirah</italic>.</p>
<p>Of this Scripture says: &#x201C;They dance about, dance about; the beautiful one of the house divides the spoils&#x201D; [Ps. 86:13].</p>
<p>Now you have to know that which is taught in the Tractate <italic>Berakhot</italic><sup><xref rid="fn57">57</xref></sup>: &#x201C;Whoever partakes of a wedding-feast and does not make the bridegroom rejoice transgresses five &#x2018;voices,&#x2019; as Scripture says: &#x2018;The voice of gladness, the voice of joy, the voice of bridegroom and the voice of bride, a voice saying &#x201C;Praise to the Lord&#x201D;&#x2019; [Jer. 33:11], and so forth. And if one does give joy to the bridegroom, what is his reward? He attains Torah, which was given with five &#x2018;voices,&#x2019; as its says: &#x2018;It was morning on the third day and there were thunderings<sup><xref rid="fn58">58</xref></sup> &#x2026; and the sound of the shofar &#x2026;&#x2019; [Exod. 19:16]. &#x2018;There was the sound of the shofar &#x2026; and God responded in thunder&#x2019; [Exod. 19:19].&#x201D; Is it true that there are five? Does it not also say: &#x201C;And all the people saw the thunderbolts?&#x201D; [Exod. 20:18].<sup><xref rid="fn59">59</xref></sup> Those had already occurred previously.</p>
<p>Here they spoke of five voices. But we have also noted seven voices, those mentioned by King David in the Psalm [29]: &#x201C;Render unto the Lord, O sons of gods&#x0021;&#x201D; Our sages have said that the divine Word was divided into seven voices.<sup><xref rid="fn60">60</xref></sup></p>
<p>In the <italic>Mekhilta</italic> [to Exod. 15:26] it says: &#x201C;If you surely listen to the voice of the Lord your God.&#x201D; These are the ten commandments, given from mouth to mouth by ten voices.</p>
<p>Now you attune your ear and listen to my words, so that the words of the sages be fulfilled. That which Moses and all Israel attained on that occasion, when they saw eye to eye, was only five voices, no more. That is why they forced Rabbi Helbo to admit that &#x201C;And all the people saw the thunderbolts&#x201D; referred to previously heard voices. These five are the totality. Moses asked to attain more, but was not answered. These five voices contain all seven extensions of space.<sup><xref rid="fn61">61</xref></sup> From them are derived the seventy divine names that are appointed over the seventy nations. Together with the innermost voice they comprise seventy-one. That innermost voice split [into seventy] as it addressed the seventy nations. Every nation heard the Word, and that is the &#x201C;great voice that did not cease&#x201D; [Deut. 5:19]. All this is compared to a hammer, whose power is one but which fragments the rock into multiple pieces. So the totality of all is five voices, their specification is seven, except for the innermost voice, parallel to the singular nation. Of this it says: &#x201C;A great voice that did not cease.&#x201D; But the one who refers to ten voices holds fast to the highest total, that of the ten <italic>sefirot</italic>. All these lead in the same direction, having been &#x201C;given by a single shepherd&#x201D; [Eccles. 12:11].</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[1:12] While the king was on his couch,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>My nard gave forth its fragrance.</bold></p>
<p>When the Glory resided upon its throne, this being the revelation at Sinai, the <italic>shekhinah</italic> said: <bold>My nard gave forth its fragrance.</bold> Israel desired to view God eye to eye, stating: &#x201C;It is our desire to see our King&#x0021;&#x201D; They received a positive answer, as it is written: &#x201C;He said to Moses: &#x2018;Ascend to God&#x2019;&#x201D; [Exod. 24:1]. And it says: &#x201C;they gazed upon God&#x201D; [Exod. 24:11].</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[1:13] My beloved to me is a bag of myrrh</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Lodged between my breasts.</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[1:14] My beloved to me is a spray of henna blooms</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>From the vineyards of Ein Gedi.</bold></p>
<p><bold>A bag of myrrh:</bold> The forms existing occulted within the Glory are likened to a bag of myrrh. <bold>A spray of henna blooms:</bold> The forms which are revealed and rendered accessible. The Glory is similarly called the bundle of life, because souls are bound and connected there. Thus they say in the Midrash to Canticles<sup><xref rid="fn62">62</xref></sup>: &#x201C;&#x2018;Within it was decked with love&#x2019;&#x2014;these are the souls of the righteous which are present with God on high.&#x201D; Three penetrated [the divine realms], each deeper than the other. &#x201C;Moses approached the deep darkness&#x201D; [Exod. 20:9]. The Targum<sup><xref rid="fn63">63</xref></sup> interprets this as: &#x201C;towards the dense cloud.&#x201D; That is, he perceived divine Will, Wisdom and Understanding, but not through the Speculum. Thus Righteousness and Justice are further inward,<sup><xref rid="fn64">64</xref></sup> as it is written: &#x201C;Righteousness and justice are the base of Your throne&#x201D; [Ps. 89:16]. Further beyond are the souls of the righteous, as it says: &#x201C;In his hands is the soul of every living thing&#x201D; [Job 12:10] and &#x201C;May the soul of my lord be bound up in the bond of life&#x201D; [I Sam. 25:29].<sup><xref rid="fn65">65</xref></sup></p>
<p>And it says: <bold>My beloved to me</bold> because he exists near to her and for her sake.</p>
<p><bold>From the vineyards of Ein Gedi:</bold> in that place the henna is of the finest quality.</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[1:15] Ah, you are fair, my darling,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Ah, you are fair,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>With your dove-like eyes&#x0021;</bold></p>
<p><bold>Ah, you are fair:</bold> This bespeaks the construction of the tabernacle and the entrance into the bridal chamber, as it is written: &#x201C;It was the day on which Moses completed [<italic>k &#x2018;lot</italic>] the tabernacle&#x201D; [Num. 7:1]. Concerning this our sages said: &#x201C;The text spells &#x2018;completed&#x2019; [<italic>k &#x2018;lot</italic>] as though comparable to the day upon which the bride [<italic>kalah</italic>] enters the bridal chamber.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn66">66</xref></sup> The parable&#x2019;s meaning points to the holy of holies, that is the <italic>shekhinah</italic>.</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[1:17] Cedars are the beams of our house,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Cypresses the rafters.</bold></p>
<p><bold>Cedars are the beams of our house:</bold> The beams of the tabernacle were of acacia wood, cedar being a type of acacia. So it is written: &#x201C;I will plant cedars in the wilderness, acacias and myrtles and oleasters&#x201D; [Isa. 41:19].</p>
<p><bold>Cypresses the rafters:</bold> So too were the tabernacle poles which ran from one extremity [of the sanctuary] to the other.<sup><xref rid="fn67">67</xref></sup> All this is a parable referring to union and intimate closeness: the time of love.</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[2:1] I am a rose of Sharon,</bold></p>
<p><bold>A lily of the valleys.</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[2:2] As a lily among the thorns,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>So is my darling among the maidens.</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[2:3] Like an apple tree among trees of the forest,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>So is my beloved among the youths.</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>In his shade is my delight,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>And his fruit is sweet to my mouth.</bold></p>
<p><bold>I am a rose of Sharon:</bold> Our sages said: &#x201C;Sharon designates song [<italic>shirah</italic>]. She sang to the One who created the world.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn68">68</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>As a lily among the thorns:</bold> The lily is that plant known as the <italic>lida</italic> which possesses six leaves. Thus the <italic>shekhinah</italic> has six boundaries.</p>
<p>The Glory is likened to an apple which possesses multiple colors: green, red, and white. <bold>Among the trees of the forest:</bold> This passage is a figure referring to the Central Column, standing in the medial position. None of the trees can produce their own fruit by their own devices since all draw their nourishment [<italic>yenikatam</italic>] from there.</p>
<p><bold>In his shade is my delight:</bold> My existence is through His power and causal agency and for His very sake.</p>
<p><bold>And his fruit is sweet to my mouth:</bold> The fruit of the Holy One, blessed be He, are the souls, as it is written: &#x201C;From me comes your fruit&#x201D; [Hosea 4:9]. Also &#x201C;Light is sown for the righteous&#x201D; [Ps. 97:11] and &#x201C;Sweet is the light&#x201D; [Eccles. 11:7].</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[2:4] He brought me to the banquet room<sup><xref rid="fn69">69</xref></sup></bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>And his banner of love was over me.</bold></p>
<p><bold>He brought me to the banquet room:</bold> A figure of the ascent of the Glory and the greatness of its joy and pleasure within the supernal light.</p>
<p><bold>And his banner of love was over me:</bold> He arrayed the four tribal banners and the <italic>shekhinah</italic>&#x2019;s camp in the middle, just as He surrounded His throne with the four camps of angels. Michael stands to His right, for he is the angel of love and compassion, corresponding to Reuben, whose banner is situated in the south, who began his career with an act of compassion and rescue, as it says: &#x201C;Reuben heard and saved him from their hands&#x201D; [Gen. 37:21]. Uriel is positioned on the left, for he is appointed over justice and vengeance. He corresponds to the tribe of Dan, who produced Micah&#x2019;s statue and received Jeroboam&#x2019;s calf.<sup><xref rid="fn70">70</xref></sup> Gabriel stands before Him, corresponding to the kingdom of the house of Judah, whose banner was situated in the east. As it says: &#x201C;For Judah triumphed over his brothers&#x201D; [I Chron. 5:2]. Raphael is behind him, corresponding to Ephraim situated in the west, fulfilling the need for healing caused by the sin of Jeroboam.</p>
<p>This order corresponds to the world&#x2019;s four directions: the east, whence light enters the world; the west, in which lie the treasuries of snow and hail and whence come coldness and warmth; the south, whence dews and rains of blessing come; and the north, from which darkness enters the world. Thus is the structure ordered: by day it faces to the east, ruling over command of the day. But at night it faces west to pray; that is opposed to what we have said.<sup><xref rid="fn71">71</xref></sup> Just as the tribal banners are arrayed to symbolize the world to come and this world as we have explained, so too has the tabernacle been constructed according to the order of the upper world, the building of the holy of holies, where the <italic>shekhinah</italic> rests between the two cherubim. Corresponding to the intermediate angelic world, in which serve those angels whose authority is over the earth, is the tent of meeting, in which are situated the showbread table, the candelabrum and the golden altar, these being inner and spiritual vessels. The golden altar was not designated for wholly burnt offerings or sacrifices, but rather for the incense, which was a matter subtle and spiritual. Facing it was the candelabrum and the light from its six branches issuing as hammered work from its central branch, radiating light at the front of the lamp stand. Corresponding to the terrestrial world is the sacrificial altar, situated in the tabernacle court, upon which all of the sacrifices might be offered.</p>
<p>Similarly, three worlds exist within a human being: the world of speech corresponding to the head; that of the life-force from the navel and above; and the natural world from the navel and below, in which are situated multitudinous obstacles.</p>
<p>Thus Scripture states, <bold>His banner of love was over me,</bold> alluding to the camp of the <italic>shekhinah</italic> located in the midst of the four tribal ensigns, as it is written: &#x201C;Then, midway between the divisions, the Tent of Meeting, the division of the Levites, shall move&#x201D; [Num. 2:17].</p>
<p>And we have similarly found that the figures of the Tabernacle constitute a symbol of the Holy One, blessed be He, and of the world. So our sages have said: &#x201C;R. Joshua of Sikhnin said in the name of R. Levi: &#x2018;When the Holy One, blessed be He, told Moses &#x201C;Make Me a sanctuary that I might dwell among you,&#x201D; he was to erect four poles and stretch out the tabernacle upon them. This teaches that the Holy One showed him red fire, green fire, black fire, and white fire. He said to him: &#x201C;follow the patterns &#x2026; that are being shown to you on the mountain&#x201D; [Exod. 25:40].&#x2019;</p>
<p>&#x201C;R. Berechyah said: &#x2018;This can be likened in a parable to a king who had a wonderful garment made of pearls. He said to his retainer: &#x201C;Make me another like this one.&#x201D; The retainer said to him: &#x201C;My lord king, can I really make one like it?&#x201D; The king said: &#x201C;I in accord with my glory, you in accord with your own material.&#x201D; Similarly, our teacher Moses said to God: &#x201C;Can I construct something like these?&#x201D; God said: &#x201C;In accord with their patterns, using blue, purple, and crimson yarns and fine linen.&#x2019;&#x201D;</p>
<p>&#x201C;Thus is the entire world included within the construction of the sanctuary. Concerning the world it is written: &#x2018;God created the heavens and the earth&#x2019; [Gen. 1:1] and &#x2018;He stretches the heavens out like a curtain&#x2019; [Ps. 104:2]. The Tabernacle contained goat skins for its tent. On the second day it is written: &#x2018;Let there be an expanse in the midst of the water, separating water from water&#x2019; [Gen. 1:6]. Concerning the tabernacle it states: &#x2018;the curtain shall serve as a partition between the Holy and the Holy of Holies&#x2019; [Exod. 26:33]. On the third day of creation, &#x2018;Let the waters under the sky be gathered into one area &#x2026;&#x2019; [Gen. 1:9]. Concerning the sanctuary: &#x2018;You shall make a brass basin&#x2019; [Exod. 30:18]. On the fourth day: &#x2018;Let there be luminaries in the expanse of the sky&#x2019; [Gen. 1:14] while in the tabernacle there was the candelabrum of pure gold. On the fifth day of creation: &#x2018;&#x2026; and birds that fly above the earth&#x2019; [Gen. 1:20] while in the Sanctuary: &#x2018;Let there be cherubim with outstretched wings&#x2019; [Exod. 25:20]. Humanity was created on the sixth day. Concerning the sanctuary it states: &#x2018;Bring forward Aaron your brother&#x2019; [Exod. 28:1]. On the seventh day: &#x2018;The heaven and the earth were completed&#x2019; [Gen. 2:1]. Concerning the tabernacle: &#x2018;Thus was completed all of the work of the Tabernacle &#x2026;&#x2019; [Exod. 39:32]. Concerning the work of Creation, it is written: &#x2018;God blessed them&#x2019; [Gen. 1:33] and concerning the construction of the tabernacle: &#x2018;Moses blessed them &#x2026;&#x2019; [Exod. 39:43]. On the seventh day it states: &#x2018;On the seventh day God finished the work that He had been doing&#x2019; [Gen. 2:2], concerning the tabernacle: &#x2018;On the day which Moses completed &#x2026;&#x2019; [Num. 7:1]. On the seventh day: &#x2018;God sanctified it&#x2019; [Gen. 2:3]; concerning the tabernacle: &#x2018;Moses consecrated it &#x2026;&#x2019; [Num. 7:1].&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn72">72</xref></sup></p>
<p>All of the above alludes to the fact that this world draws its life and is connected and adheres to the name of the Holy One, blessed be He. So too the ark and its utensils are symbolic allusions. Above &#x201C;seraphim stand&#x201D; [Isa. 6:2]; below &#x201C;acacia wood stands&#x201D; [Exod. 26:16]. Above &#x201C;He sits upon the cherubim&#x201D; [Ps. 80:2]; below &#x201C;cherubim of outstretched wing&#x201D; [Exod. 37:9]. Above are the holy wheels (of Ezekiel&#x2019;s vision); below &#x201C;the structure of the wheels was like the structure of the wheel of the heavenly chariot-throne&#x201D; [I Kings 7:33].</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[2:5] Sustain me with raisin cakes,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Refresh me with apples,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>For I am faint with love.</bold></p>
<p><bold>Sustain me with raisin cakes:</bold> A figure of great pleasure. Raisin cakes [<italic>ashishot</italic>] are those entities which are the foundations [<italic>ashyot</italic>] of the worlds above and below.</p>
<p><bold>Refresh me with apples:</bold> With the two cherubim between whom I am situated, and from whom I receive blessing.</p>
<p><bold>For I am faint with love:</bold> Faint with love from all of the joy of the heart and the weakness of the soul.</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[2:7] I adjure you, O maidens of Jerusalem,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>By the hosts [<italic>tsevaot</italic>] or by the hinds of the field:</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Do not wake or rouse</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Love until it please&#x0021;</bold></p>
<p><bold>I adjure you:</bold> She speaks to Israel: beware lest sin causes the <italic>shekhinah</italic> to depart.</p>
<p><bold>By the hosts:</bold> Hosts [<italic>tsevaot</italic>]: by the name of the Holy One, blessed be He, for the Holy One&#x2019;s name is His hosts.</p>
<p><bold>By the hinds of the field:</bold> The Presence of His might, as it says: &#x201C;the voice of God causes hinds to calve&#x201D; [Ps. 29:9].</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[2:8] Hark&#x0021; My beloved&#x0021;</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>There he comes,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Leaping over mountains,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Bounding over hills.</bold></p>
<p><bold>Hark&#x0021; My beloved&#x0021;:</bold> The words of the <italic>shekhinah</italic>. This was on the twentieth of Iyyar when the cloud arose from the tabernacle of the covenant.<sup><xref rid="fn73">73</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>Leaping over the mountains:</bold> That is to say that the Glory lept from mountain to hill, God&#x2019;s ark being in the midst of the tent cloth.</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[2:9] My beloved is like a gazelle</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Or like a young stag.</bold></p>
<p>Thus it says: <bold>My beloved is like a gazelle</bold> &#x2026; : I found no rest from all of the places to which he journeyed: the burning bush, Sinai, the tent of meeting, until he dwelt in the Temple in Jerusalem, by the western wall. As our sages say: &#x201C;The Shechinah has never departed the western wall. As it says: &#x2018;There he stands behind our wall, gazing &#x2026;&#x2019; [Cant. 2:9] from there watching over and observing humanity.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn74">74</xref></sup></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[2:10] My beloved spoke thus to me:</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>&#x201C;Arise, my darling;</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>My fair one, come away&#x0021;&#x201D;</bold></p>
<p><bold>Arise, my darling:</bold> To move from her place and go before the congregation of Israel. And such is the meaning of &#x201C;Let me see your face&#x201D; [Cant. 2:14]. These verses are a parable concerning this, as our sages said: &#x201C;&#x2018;The Lord God has returned with you from captivity and taken you back in love&#x2019; [Deut. 30:3]. The verse does not state &#x2018;God will restore you from captivity&#x2019; but rather &#x2018;God has returned.&#x2019;&#x201C;<sup><xref rid="fn75">75</xref></sup> This teaches that the <italic>shekhinah</italic> returned with Israel from exile. And so too: &#x201C;I set my heart by the highway, the road by which you traveled&#x201D; [Jer. 31:21]. The received text<sup><xref rid="fn76">76</xref></sup> is &#x201C;the road by which I traveled.&#x201D; So too where Micah [4:10] is read as &#x201C;So now you must leave the city and dwell in the country,&#x201D; the received text is &#x201C;I will dwell in the country.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn77">77</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[2:11] For now the winter is past:</bold> A parable referring to the final fulfillment and the end of exile.</p>
<p><bold>[2:12] The blossoms have appeared in the land:</bold> This refers to the nearness of the days of ease and the coming of the time of inheritance and rest.</p>
<p><bold>[2:14] O my dove, in the cranny of the rocks:</bold> Until now the <italic>shekhinah</italic> has dwelt with Israel in exile, as our sages said: &#x201C;&#x2018;He sets the childless woman among her household as a happy mother of children&#x2019; [Ps. 113:9]. The community of Israel said before the Holy One, blessed be He: &#x2018;My children have made me to dwell, like a weasel, in ruined houses.&#x2019;&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn78">78</xref></sup></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[2:15] Catch us the foxes</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>The little foxes</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>That ruin the vineyards&#x2014;</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>For our vineyard is in blossom.</bold></p>
<p><bold>Catch us the little foxes:</bold> The parable refers to the spies, who were weak like foxes. They said: &#x201C;However, the people who dwell in the land are powerful &#x2026; the Amalekites dwell in the south country&#x201D; [Num. 13:28].</p>
<p><bold>That ruin the vineyards:</bold> The parable refers to the nations that profited through Israel&#x2019;s arrival in the land and the construction of the Temple, as our Sages said: &#x2018;&#x201C;All of the earth&#x2019;s families shall be blessed through you&#x2019; [Gen. 12:3]&#x2014;even the foreign families in the land are blessed only on account of Israel.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn79">79</xref></sup></p>
<p>When Israel dwelled in their land, the Temple altar atoned for them [the nations]. Thus our sages said: &#x201C;Abbaye said: &#x2018;The seventy bullocks offered during the holiday corresponded to the world&#x2019;s seventy nations.&#x2019; What was the purpose of the single bullock? It corresponded to that singular nation. A parable concerning a king who said: &#x2018;Prepare a banquet for me.&#x2019; At the end, he said to his favorite: &#x2018;Make me a small meal so that I might take pleasure with you.&#x2019; R. Yohanan said: &#x2018;Woe to the world&#x2019;s nations&#x0021; For they have suffered a loss yet do not realize what they have lost&#x0021; For throughout the existence of the Temple, the altar atoned for them. Now, who can atone for them?&#x0021;&#x2019;&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn80">80</xref></sup></p>
<p>All of the above is readily explainable. When the central column is nourished, so are all of its branches.<sup><xref rid="fn81">81</xref></sup> This is comparable to the [manifestation] of vitality from the brain to the spine, whence it passes throughout all of the sinews.</p>
<p><bold>For our vineyard is in blossom:</bold> The parable refers to Israel, who at the time of their origins, their entrance into the land, were in blossom. When their redemption was revealed, it was like the appearance of fruit upon a blossoming vine.</p>
<p>Judgment was decreed and an oath sworn that Israel would not enter the land. The Glory and prophecy removed themselves and the <italic>shekhinah</italic> said in the Glory&#x2019;s departure:</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[2:16] My beloved is mine</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>And I am his</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Who browses among the lilies.</bold></p>
<p><bold>My beloved is mine</bold> &#x2026; : who directs His world through six manifestations which are the ultimate source of all things generated below.</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[2:17] Until the day blows gently</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>And the shadows flee,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Set out my beloved,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>As a gazelle</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Or a young stag,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>For the hills of spices&#x0021;</bold></p>
<p><bold>Until the day blows gently:</bold> When the sin of the Amorites will attain its consummation and their power and might be removed.</p>
<p><bold>And the shadows flee:</bold> Our Sages said in the Midrash to the Song of Songs: &#x201C;These are the celestial princes of the nations and their angels.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn82">82</xref></sup> This is the true interpretation of the verse: &#x201C;their protection has departed from them&#x201D; [Num. 14:9] as I have interpreted the verse &#x201C;I delight to sit in his shade&#x201D; [Cant. 2:3].</p>
<p><bold>As a young gazelle:</bold> That is to say, &#x201C;stand&#x201D; as you stood when you went from mount to hill and tent to tabernacle.</p>
<p><bold>For the hills of spices:</bold> An allusion to the departure of the Glory.</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[3:1] Upon my couch at night</bold></p><p><bold>I sought the one I love&#x2014;</bold></p><p><bold>I sought but found him not.</bold></p>
<p><bold>Upon my couch:</bold> &#x201C;Couch&#x201D; refers to Israel&#x2019;s forty year sojourn in the wilderness, when they were denied permission to enter the land of Israel.</p>
<p><bold>At night:</bold> When Israel was in trouble, distress, and darkness.</p>
<p><bold>I sought:</bold> Israel said: &#x201C;I have repented in order that the Glory might return to me as at the beginning.&#x201D;</p>
<p><bold>I sought him but found him not:</bold> Throughout those forty years, the <italic>shekhinah</italic> had departed and prophecy had ceased. As it is written: &#x201C;When all the warriors among the people had died off, the Lord spoke to me, saying &#x2026;&#x201D; [Deut. 2:16&#x2013;17]. To me was the Word. This reveals that Moses had not prophesied until this moment.</p>
<p>[3:2] <bold>I must rise and roam the town:</bold> Israel adds further, saying: &#x201C;I engaged in many supplications and circumambulated the Throne of Glory, but to no avail.&#x201D;</p>
<p><bold>[3:3] I met the watchmen who patrol the town:</bold> These are Moses and Aaron, engaged in holy service, as it is written: &#x201C;You and your sons shall take care in performing your priestly duties in everything pertaining to the altar&#x201D; [Num. 18:7]. I asked them: &#x201C;Have you seen the one I love?&#x201D;</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[3:4] Scarcely had I passed them</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>When I found the one I love.</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>I held him fast, I would not let him go</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Till I brought him to my mother&#x2019;s house,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>To the chamber of her who conceived me.</bold></p>
<p><bold>Scarcely had I passed them:</bold> When Moses died I departed from them until I found Joshua. As it is written: &#x201C;After the death of Moses, the servant of God, the Lord said to Joshua&#x201D; [Josh. 1:1] and it says: &#x201C;Now, cross this river Jordan&#x201D; [Josh. 1:2].</p>
<p><bold>I held him fast, I would not let him go:</bold> A parabolic metaphor, indicating that I (Israel) did not stumble in sin until I entered the land during the days of Joshua.</p>
<p><bold>To my mother&#x2019;s house:</bold> This is Jerusalem, &#x201C;within which Righteousness resides&#x201D; [Isa. 1:21].<sup><xref rid="fn83">83</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>To the chamber of her who conceived me:</bold> This is the Temple.</p>
<p>[3:5] <bold>I adjure you, O maidens of Jerusalem:</bold> Since I stand in glory and a lofty state, take care that you not sin and cause the departure of the Glory.</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[3:6] Who is she who comes up from the desert</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Like columns of smoke,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Perfumed with clouds of myrrh and frankincense,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>With all of the powders of the merchant?</bold></p>
<p><bold>Who is she who comes up from the desert like columns of smoke:</bold> When journeying before the Israelite camp, the <italic>shekhinah</italic> seemed like a column of smoke, rising upwards and ascending. The verse states &#x201C;smoke&#x201D; for she is derived from fire, as it is written: &#x201C;Now Mount Sinai was all in smoke, for the Lord had come down upon it in fire, the smoke rose like the smoke of a kiln&#x201D; [Exod. 19:18]. The <italic>shekhinah</italic> receives her emanative energy primarily from the left side, from darkness.<sup><xref rid="fn84">84</xref></sup> Darkness is elemental fire, as it says concerning it: &#x201C;Let me not see this great fire anymore, lest I die&#x201D; [Deut. 18:16]. And it says: &#x201C;When you heard the voice from amidst the darkness&#x201D; [Deut. 5:19].</p>
<p><bold>Perfumed with clouds of myrrh and frankincense:</bold> The verse states &#x201C;perfumed&#x201D; for she is energized through her reception of emanative energy from the other <italic>sefirot</italic>. Myrrh and frankincense are visual polarities, myrrh being red, frankincense white.<sup><xref rid="fn85">85</xref></sup> Attend and carefully contemplate the wonders of this parabolic image. It refers to the two cherubim, the world&#x2019;s fathers. She is situated and receives emanation from both of them.</p>
<p><bold>With all of the powders of the merchant:</bold> The verse says that while all this is true, she includes all of the other spiritual entities and is sealed with them all.</p>
<p>To this point we have the enquiry of the questioner, the order of the sefirotic entities, and an account of their likeness.</p>
<p>Now for the answer to the question:</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[3:7] This is Solomon&#x2019;s couch,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Encircled by sixty warriors</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Of the warriors of Israel.</bold></p>
<p><bold>This is Solomon&#x2019;s couch:</bold> Of the name of the Holy One, blessed be He.</p>
<p><bold>Encircled by sixty warriors:</bold> The verse designates sixty corresponding to the six directions.<sup><xref rid="fn86">86</xref></sup> The ten <italic>sefirot</italic> are reflected in each of them. Since the seventh is an intermediate boundary, a spiritual entity upholding them all, and from it all things derive nurturance, it is not included in the sum, as we will explain further on. The verse designates them as warriors as they receive their being from the side of divine justice. And it enquires further over what they are appointed&#x2014;over justice.</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[3:8] All of them trained in warfare,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Skilled in battle,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Each with sword on thigh,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Because of terror by night.</bold></p>
<p>All of this constitutes the context of the parable, as we explained earlier in the introduction to the text. As a similar example we find: &#x201C;From the mouths of infants and sucklings you have founded strength on account of Your foes, to put an end to enemy and avenger&#x201D; [Ps. 8:3]. And &#x201C;Mighty king who loves equity&#x201D; [Ps. 99:4].</p>
<p><bold>Because of terror by night:</bold> The Sages said: &#x201C;from the terror of hell which is likened to night.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn87">87</xref></sup> This is said in truth for it is from night (divine Justice) that the <italic>shekhinah</italic> receives her emanation.</p>
<p>The text begins to set forth the hierarchy of emanation.</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[3:9] Behold King Solomon made for himself a palanquin</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Of wood from Lebanon.</bold></p>
<p>From the outpouring of Wisdom and its luminescence, He radiated light, and from it drew forth emanation. Concerning this it states in Genesis Rabbah [3:4]: &#x201C;Whence was the light created? The Holy One, blessed be He, enwrapped Himself as in a robe, and radiated His luster from one end of the world to the other.&#x201D; The robe designates the invocation of the emanation of wisdom which encompasses the totality of all things. The act of enwrapping conveys that He received radiance from that emanational outflow and literally sparked forth light. This is furthermore the opinion of Rabbi Eliezer the Great who said:</p>
<p align="blockquote">Whence were the heavens created? He took from the light of His garment; He wrapped Himself as in a robe. The light extended outwards, as it says: &#x201C;wrapped in a robe of light, You spread the heavens like a tent cloth&#x201D; [Ps. 104:2]. Whence was the earth created? God took hold of some of the snow underlying the Throne of Glory and cast it downwards. As it says: &#x201C;He commands the snow: &#x2018;Fall to the ground&#x0021;&#x2019;&#x201D; [Job 37:6].<sup><xref rid="fn88">88</xref></sup></p>
<p>This accords with the opinion of Plato, who argued that it was vain to believe that the Creator created something from nothing, but rather there was a preexistent matter. This is not the same as clay in the potter&#x2019;s hands or the smith&#x2019;s iron, who shape from them whatsoever they desire, so that the Creator, be He praised, shaped heaven and earth from primordial matter, but sometime might create something else of it. That God does not create something from nothing should not be considered a diminution of His power, just as there is no diminution in His inability to create logically impossible entities, such as a square whose diagonal is equal to its side or the simultaneous conjunction of two opposites. Just as in these cases, there is no diminution in His capacity, so too there is no denigration if He does not emanate something from nothing, but rather uses a primal element. For this too is included in the general category of impossibility. Solomon too spoke of this, revealing lucid wisdom and sound reasoning, through the aegis of the holy spirit of prophecy.</p>
<p><bold>Of wood from Lebanon:</bold> Thence originates the emanation of all, including the [sefirotic] existences. [There] emanation began, as our sages say: &#x201C;&#x2018;Let there be light and there was light.&#x2019; Not &#x2018;then there was light,&#x2019; but &#x2018;there <italic>was</italic> light&#x2019;&#x2014;light which already existed.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn89">89</xref></sup> For it was already emanated from the supernal light which existed in the transcendent potentiality.</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[3:10] He made its posts of silver,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Its back of gold,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Its seat of purple wool.</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Within, it was decked with love</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>By the maidens of Jerusalem.</bold></p>
<p><bold>He made its posts of silver:</bold> This is the &#x201C;right hand&#x201D; of the Holy One, blessed be He, which the Book of Creation [2:1] designates as the &#x201C;scale of merit.&#x201D;</p>
<p><bold>Its back of gold:</bold> This is the left hand, designated &#x201C;the scale of guilt.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn90">90</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>Its seat of purple wool:</bold> This is the central pillar designated as the central &#x201C;tongue of the statute&#x201D; mediating between them. So our Sages say: &#x201C;&#x2018;Upon this semblance of a throne, there was the semblance of a human form&#x2019; [Ezek. 1:26]. It was designated as purple,&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn91">91</xref></sup> for just as purple wool is woven out of many types of colors, so too the central pillar receives from this one and that. And so it states: &#x201C;like the appearance of the bow in the cloud was the appearance of the likeness of the Glory of God&#x201D; [Ezek. 1:28].</p>
<p><bold>Within, it was decked with love:</bold> This is the <italic>shekhinah</italic>.</p>
<p><bold>By the maidens of Jerusalem:</bold> The Central Column. This is the meaning of &#x201C;a man&#x2019;s wife,&#x201D; concerning which the prophet said (of those men who brought home foreign wives): &#x201C;Has not one done this out of excess of spirit? What does one seek but godly seed?&#x201D; [Mal. 2:15].<sup><xref rid="fn92">92</xref></sup></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[3:11] Go forth and see, O daughters of Jerusalem</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>King Solomon, in the crown with which</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>His mother crowned him</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>On the day of his wedding,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Day of his heart&#x2019;s delight.</bold></p>
<p><bold>King Solomon:</bold> The king of peace.</p>
<p><bold>The crown with which his mother crowned him on his wedding day:</bold> The entire sefirotic edifice coheres and is unified and ascends towards infinity, nor does it suffer a departure of the holy spirit. The crown stands for the emanation of blessing and superabundance from the spirit of the living God designated as the mother in the Midrash to Proverbs,<sup><xref rid="fn93">93</xref></sup> in the Rabbis&#x2019; exegesis of &#x201C;May your father and mother rejoice&#x201D; [Prov. 23:25]. Rabbi Akiba states: &#x201C;Even the Holy One, blessed be He, rejoiced in him, as Wisdom rejoiced in him. As it says: &#x2018;Let your father rejoice&#x2019;: this is the Holy One, blessed be He. &#x2018;And your mother&#x2019;: this is that wise woman of whom it is written: &#x2018;You shall call understanding a mother&#x2019; [Prov. 2:3].&#x201D; Consequently, blessing, sanctification and unification which draw energy from the negation of thought are designated as the diadem and crown. Our sages say in the Midrash to Psalms [19:2]: &#x201C;The angel assigned to Israel&#x2019;s prayers waits until her final congregation has prayed and weaves them into a crown for the Holy One. As it says: &#x2018;Blessings alight upon the head of the righteous, the life of all worlds&#x2019; [Prov. 10:6].&#x201D; For this reason, the sages ordained the Sanctus and blessing within the blessings attached to the recitation of the <italic>shema</italic>, and placed the unification of <italic>shema</italic> in close proximity to them. And they ordained that all three<sup><xref rid="fn94">94</xref></sup> should be recited in the great Sanctus of the Additional Prayer. For these three enter under the rubric of the unity of divine Wisdom, Understanding and Knowledge, the emanational edifice containing the seven (lower) <italic>sefirot</italic>. Because all of the ten <italic>sefirot</italic> are included within the (upper) three: Wisdom, Knowledge, and Understanding, the three recitations of the Sanctus<sup><xref rid="fn95">95</xref></sup> exist to unify them. Within their totality, all things are included. So we have found in the Chapters of Rabbi Eliezer:<sup><xref rid="fn96">96</xref></sup> &#x201C;The world was created with ten statements but these were included in three. As it says: &#x2018;God established the earth in wisdom, founded the heavens in understanding, through His knowledge the depths were split and the heavens shower dew&#x2019; [Prov. 3:19].&#x201D;</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[4:1] Ah, you are fair, my darling,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Ah, you are fair.</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Your eyes are like doves</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Behind your veil.</bold></p>
<p>These are the words of the Glory when he dwelt with His mighty Presence in the House built by Solomon. For that generation was perfect; the time was a period of peace and joy; anguish and sighing were put to flight. The Glory sets forth the praise of Her eyes and hair, her lips and neck. All these are similes and parables known to the mystical illuminati.</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[4:6] When the day blows gently</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>And the shadows flee,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>I will betake me to the mount of myrrh,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>To the hill of frankincense.</bold></p>
<p><bold>When the day blows gently:</bold> This refers to the removal of the sovereignty of the nations.</p>
<p><bold>And the shadows flee;</bold> As we have explained.</p>
<p><bold>I will betake myself to the mountain of myrrh:</bold> This is Jerusalem, as it is written: &#x201C;In Jerusalem which is upon Mt. Moriah&#x201D; [II Chron. 3:1].</p>
<p><bold>To the hill of frankincense:</bold> This is Mt. Zion. Jerusalem is compared to myrrh which is red, referring to the attribute of justice, as it says: &#x201C;Within her righteousness dwells&#x201D; [Isa. 1:21]. Mt. Zion is compared to a hill of frankincense, the attribute of compassion. This verse refers to the time when Israel acts in accordance with rectitude, in accord to justice and the Torah. The <italic>shekhinah</italic> was lovely, beautified by the Holy Spirit. Indeed, over all the glory hangs a canopy and crown. In contrast to this, she is like a bird wandering from her nest, departing her house and kingdom, as it states: &#x201C;A son who causes shame and disgrace, plunders his father, puts his mother to flight&#x201D; [Prov. 19:26].</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[4:8] From Lebanon come with me;</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>From Lebanon, my bride with me.</bold></p>
<p><bold>From Lebanon my bride with me:</bold> The Glory says (to the <italic>shekhinah</italic>): &#x201C;You were with me among the profound essences,<sup><xref rid="fn97">97</xref></sup> hidden within primordial Wisdom.&#x201D;</p>
<p><bold>From Lebanon come with me:</bold> You came forth and were emanated with me from a single place.<sup><xref rid="fn98">98</xref></sup> The parable refers to the journeying of the <italic>shekhinah</italic> before the Israelite camp to seek out resting places, as it is written: &#x201C;The Ark of the Covenant traveled in front of them on that three days&#x2019; journey to seek out a resting place for them&#x201D; [Num. 10:33].</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[4:9] You have ravished my heart,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>My sister, my bride,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>With one of your eyes,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>With one coil of your necklace.</bold></p>
<p><bold>You have ravished my heart &#x2014; my bride:</bold> Your extraordinary attractiveness has stopped my heart. This [ravishing of the heart] is the thing and its opposite, similar to &#x201C;they shall ash the altar&#x201D; [Num. 4:13].<sup><xref rid="fn99">99</xref></sup> For desire and inclination and their union are drawn to her lofty beauty.</p>
<p><bold>With one of your eyes:</bold> This refers to the generation of Solomon, a perfect one, all righteous, including the Sanhedrin of sages who know the wisdom of the proper times. They are called &#x201C;eyes&#x201D; for they are the light of the world, as in &#x201C;if it was in error, hidden from the eyes of the community&#x201D; [Num. 15:24]. It says &#x201C;one&#x201D; because that generation was singular; there was never another like it, either earlier or later.</p>
<p><bold>With one coil of your necklace:</bold> This is an allusion to the king, the glory of his people. Because he foresaw through the holy spirit of prophecy that in the future the kingdom would be split asunder into two states after his demise, he specified &#x201C;with one coil of your necklace,&#x201D; meaning &#x201C;while the kingdom is yet one.&#x201D;</p>
<p>The Glory begins to expound upon the pleasantness of her love, the scent of her ointments and garments, the honey of her lips.</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[4:10] How sweet is your love &#x2026;</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>How much more delightful your lover than wine,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Your ointments more fragrant</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Than any spice&#x0021;</bold></p>
<p>He said: <bold>How sweet is your love</bold> emanating forth from the wine of Torah, that is to say, Wisdom&#x2019;s font and its paths.</p>
<p><bold>Your ointments more fragrant:</bold> The allusion is to the expanding light of Wisdom, descending via its attributes, drawn out of that place encompassing all spices.<sup><xref rid="fn100">100</xref></sup></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[4:11] Sweetness drops</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>From your lips, O bride;</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Honey and milk</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Are under your tongue;</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>And the scent of your robes</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Is like the scent of Lebanon.</bold></p>
<p><bold>Honey and milk:</bold> The allusion is to the two modalities of Torah (written and oral) and the fact that the <italic>shekhinah</italic> is situated between the two cherubim.</p>
<p><bold>And the scent of your robes:</bold> The robe is not an entity distinct from Her. Rather, it is the overflow of Wisdom&#x2019;s brightness which surrounds her. Our Sages state in Genesis Rabbah [21:5] concerning the verse &#x201C;I looked and saw a man dressed in linen&#x201D; [Daniel 10:5]: &#x201C;He was comparable to a snail whose shell is inseparable from his body.&#x201D; Since Wisdom&#x2019;s brightness, encompassing thirty-two paths, surrounds the Glory, as in &#x201C;Your faithful ones surround You&#x201D; [Ps. 89:8], it is called &#x201C;the garment of God,&#x201D; as it says: &#x201C;You are garbed in splendor and majesty&#x201D; [Ps. 104:1].</p>
<p>In order to fulfill the verse &#x201C;You shall walk in His ways&#x201D; [Deut. 28:9], Israel were commanded to wrap themselves in the <italic>tallit</italic>,<sup><xref rid="fn101">101</xref></sup> which possesses thirty-two fringes. Concerning the <italic>tallit</italic> it is written: &#x201C;You shall gaze upon them and remember all of God&#x2019;s commandments&#x201D; [Num. 15:39]. Now Wisdom encompasses, is endiademed and crowned<sup><xref rid="fn102">102</xref></sup> with six hundred and thirteen precious gems. For each of the thirty-two paths within is divisible into two portions: good and evil, the positive and negative commandments. This division finds allusion in the ten divine statements (revealed directly at Sinai) in the words &#x201C;remember&#x201D; and &#x201C;keep&#x201D; the Sabbath day.<sup><xref rid="fn103">103</xref></sup> Thus there are sixty-four paths. And as each and every one contains the ten [<italic>sefirot</italic>], their sum is six hundred and forty. If one deletes the twenty-seven letters of the Torah,<sup><xref rid="fn104">104</xref></sup> the final sum is six hundred and thirteen. Thus concerning the fringes, Scripture states: &#x201C;You shall gaze upon them and remember all of God&#x2019;s commandments&#x201D; [Num. 15:39]. Therefore our sages said in the tractate <italic>Shavuot</italic>: &#x201C;The precept of fringes equals all of the commandments.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn105">105</xref></sup></p>
<p>It is incumbent upon us to engage in a detailed enquiry concerning all of the commandments, to find an allusion pointing to them in the ten divine statements revealed at Sinai. This is comparable to the manner in which the sages of Israel sought an allusion in the Torah for every aspect of fundamental ethics and courtesy which was not included within its commandments. Thus our sages<sup><xref rid="fn106">106</xref></sup> stated that R. Yohanan encountered a child who was reciting: &#x201C;A man&#x2019;s folly subverts his way and his heart rages against the Lord&#x201D; [Prov. 19:3]. He said: &#x201C;Does Scripture<sup><xref rid="fn107">107</xref></sup> contain anything which is not already intimated in the Torah? An allusion to this indeed appears in the Torah. Their hearts sank; and, trembling, they turned to one another, saying, &#x2018;What is this that God has done to us?&#x2019; [Gen. 42:28]. How much the more so should we say concerning the fundamentals of the Torah and its precepts that there is no doubt that the six hundred and thirteen commandments find their allusion in that divine voice described as &#x2018;a great voice, which went on no more&#x2019; [Deut.5:19].&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn108">108</xref></sup></p>
<p>We should interpret each and every commandment in accord with our path, determining from which <italic>sefirah</italic> it derives and finding allusion to all of the reasons for the commandments which are not explicitly stated in the Torah. The reasons of many precepts are indeed explicated, an example being the law concerning the first born: &#x201C;When Pharaoh stubbornly refused to let us go, the Lord slew every first-born in the land of Egypt, the first-born of man and beast. Therefore I sacrifice to the Lord every first male issue of the womb, but redeem every first-born among my sons&#x201D; [Exod. 13:15]. A similar case is that of tithes: &#x201C;You shall consume the tithes of your new grain &#x2026; before the Lord&#x201D; which concludes &#x201C;so that you might learn to revere the Lord your God forever&#x201D; [Deut. 14:23]. Like these are many other commandments whose meaning is explained. But there are many whose purpose are not explicated, such as the reason for sacrifice, the Sabbatical year and Jubilee, circumcision, the blowing of the ram&#x2019;s horn at New Year&#x2019;s, forbidden acts of sexual union, oaths, vows and phylacteries, ritual fringes, Naziriteship, the palmfrond and citron, the ban on the consumption of the produce of fruit-bearing trees during their first three harvest years, the mixing of seeds in a field, the sacrifice of the red heifer, and many others, excluding those whose meaning is hinted at where they are mentioned.</p>
<p>You should realize that all of the precepts depend upon two fundamental principles: the positive and negative commandments. The positive commandments are born of the quality of remembrance [<italic>zakhor</italic>]; the negative commandments of the quality of observance [<italic>shamor</italic>]. It is also well known that remembrance and observance correspond to two of the attributes of the Holy One, blessed be He. Consequently, an individual who performs the command of his master and fulfills it, does so as a consequence of the quality of love. This constitutes the highest degree [of service] and the most excellent virtue, and corresponds to the category of positive commandments. An individual who desists from performing a deed out of fear of his master, does so as a consequence of the quality of awe. This stands on a lower rung than the quality of love, just as negative commandments occupy a gradation lower than the positive. For the person who fulfills the command of his master with his body and his possessions is not to be likened to one who is scrupulous about desisting from evil out of fear of him. Thus our Sages say: &#x201C;Concerning what situation were these matters related? Concerning negative commandments. That is to say that the transgressor is smitten with forty lashes. However, with respect to positive commandments, such as the case when they instruct him to construct a Sukkah but he does not build it, or take a palm frond but he does not do so, they smite him until his soul departs his body.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn109">109</xref></sup></p>
<p>All of the above derives from the principles of &#x201C;remembrance&#x201D; and &#x201C;observance,&#x201D; for the quality of remembrance occupies a gradation higher than that of observance and the branches which derive from it are in its likeness. Since Abraham our father took divine love as his portion, corresponding to remembrance, and he knew God&#x2019;s name with a true and real knowledge, the Omnipresent One called him &#x201C;My lover.&#x201D; Nor is the [attainment of the] quality of love possible save through perfect knowledge. Thus one finds that many principles of the negative commandments are derived from the positive. For the quality of love exists within the quality of awe, since awe derives from love and is thus included within it.</p>
<p>You should know that a human being, by nature and the process of generation, contains and is impressed with the stamp of these two qualities, that is to say the essential force of the positive and negative commandments, that is water and fire, the former at his right hand, the latter at his left. This is as our sages said: &#x201C;Two angels escort an individual, one good and one evil.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn110">110</xref></sup> And as that wise man said: &#x201C;A wise man&#x2019;s heart tends towards the right hand, a fool&#x2019;s to the left&#x201D; [Eccles. 10:2]. It is the truth that right conduct and the inclination to good are on the right while evil behavior and the inclination towards wickedness are on the left, as is the Accuser. Concerning this David said: &#x201C;I am ever mindful of the Lord&#x2019;s presence; He is at my right hand, I shall never be shaken&#x201D; [Ps. 16:8]. &#x201C;I shall not be shaken&#x201D;: I shall never neglect, even for an instant, that inclination towards the good that stands at my right hand.</p>
<p>Since these two qualities, the inclination to the good and the inclination to evil, which correspond to the positive and negative commandments, are impressed upon human nature, the Torah was given with positive and negative commandments to direct an individual and habituate him towards positive qualities. The inclination towards evil would be drawn after the good and annihilated within it. Concerning this our sages said: &#x201C;&#x2018;You shall love the Lord your God with all your heart&#x2019; [Deut. 6:5]&#x2014;with your two inclinations, towards good and evil.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn111">111</xref></sup> This is the purpose of the commandments, the acts of worship, prayers, and fasting. They serve to subjugate the evil inclination so that it might be rendered subordinate to the impulse towards good. Thus the body, whose foundation is dust and nature evil and which descends below, will be drawn after the faculty of the soul, whose foundation is life, whose nature is wholly for the good and ascends upwards. Give careful heed and listen to my wondrous words, let them always be present before your eyes, for they are pleasant and should be stored inside you.</p>
<p>[There ensues a listing of the six hundred and thirteen commandments, as derived from the ten. See Chavel&#x2019;s edition of the Hebrew text in <italic>Kitvey RaMBaN</italic> II, pp. 521&#x2013;48. The concluding summary of that discussion follows.]</p>
<p>These<sup><xref rid="fn112">112</xref></sup> are the six hundred and thirteen commandments, positive and negative, derived from the ten commandments as &#x201C;Remember&#x201D; and &#x201C;Observe.&#x201D; Of this our rabbis said: &#x201C;&#x2018;Remember&#x2019; and &#x2018;Observe&#x2019; were proclaimed in a single utterance, something no mouth could speak nor any ear hear.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn113">113</xref></sup> No one voice could simultaneously speak two things, opposite to one another, positive and negative; such is beyond the capacity of the human mouth or ear. He explained the two hundred forty-eight positive commandments guiding the human limbs,<sup><xref rid="fn114">114</xref></sup> which number two hundred forty-eight, in a goodly and upright path, thus purifying, cleansing, and sanctifying the person that he might resemble his Maker. The remaining three hundred sixty-five commandments guide the sinews, which are of that number, in a goodly and upright way, keeping the person from evil paths and ugly qualities. Thus body and soul will be on a single path in harmony with one another.</p>
<p>You should know that the Torah is entirely clear, spoken by the divine dynamis,<sup><xref rid="fn115">115</xref></sup> containing not a single letter or vowel point that is not needed. All of it is a divine structure, hewn out in the name<sup><xref rid="fn116">116</xref></sup> of the blessed Holy One. There is no difference between &#x201C;Timna was the concubine of Eliphaz&#x201D; [Gen. 36:12] or &#x201C;the chieftain of Magdiel, the chieftan of Eram&#x201D; [Gen. 36:43] and the ten commandments or &#x201C;Hear O Israel&#x201D; [Deut. 6:4]. Whoever deletes a single letter is like one who deletes God&#x2019;s whole name and a whole world. Therefore it was necessary that the letters and words be counted, that <italic>plene</italic> and <italic>lene</italic><sup><xref rid="fn117">117</xref></sup> spellings be recorded, forms written but not pronounced, as well as forms pronounced but not written, open and closed beginnings of sections [i.e., paragraph divisions], larger and smaller letters. Let this be implanted in your heart and inscribed within you. Take care for your soul and lend no ear to [those who] say that Ezra the Scribe added things of his own accord as he copied it, such as &#x201C;The Canaanites were then in the land&#x201D; [Gen. 13:6] or &#x201C;Behold his bed, a bed of iron&#x201D; [Deut. 3:11].<sup><xref rid="fn118">118</xref></sup> This is total heresy, that of which the rabbis spoke in the chapter called &#x201C;A Portion,&#x201D; on the verse &#x201C;For he has despised the word of the Lord&#x201D; [Num. 15:31]: &#x201C;This refers to one who says &#x2018;Torah is not from heaven.&#x2019; Even one who says that all of Torah is from heaven except for a single verse that Moses spoke on his own: such a person &#x2018;despises the word of the Lord.&#x2019;&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn119">119</xref></sup></p>
<p>Because the commandments are the very body of purity and holiness, and the one concerned with them becomes purified and holy, Scripture said <bold>the fragrance of your garments is like that of Lebanon,</bold><sup><xref rid="fn120">120</xref></sup> for that fragrance is the life of both worlds.</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[4:12] A garden locked</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Is my own, my bride,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>A fountain locked,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>A sealed-up spring.</bold></p>
<p><bold>A garden locked is my own, my bride:</bold> The <italic>shekhinah</italic> is compared to a garden, since a person plants and fences it, bringing in water to irrigate it and producing all manner of lovely herbiage and plants. The <italic>shekhinah</italic>&#x2019;s fence is the cherubim, the plants are the seventy nations, the trees are the angels. All these are supplied by that spring which proceeds from Wisdom&#x2019;s paradise, within which souls flower in joy. It flows forth without ceasing either day or night; on its account the world is sustained. As our sages said in tractate Yoma:<sup><xref rid="fn121">121</xref></sup> &#x201C;On account of the righteous one is the world created and sustained,&#x201D; as it says: &#x201C;The righteous one is the world&#x2019;s foundation&#x201D; [Prov. 10:25].<sup><xref rid="fn122">122</xref></sup> Our sages also said concerning this: &#x201C;The circumference of the tree of life is a journey of five hundred years and all of the waters of creation are divided forth from it.&#x201D; Rabbi Yehudah said: &#x201C;It is not the circumference of its bough, but its trunk that constitutes a journey of five hundred years.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn123">123</xref></sup></p>
<p>&#x201C;A river goes forth from Eden to water the garden&#x201D; [Gen. 2:10]. The garden constitutes the beginning of the differentiated universe. As it says: &#x201C;from there it divides and becomes four branches&#x201D; [ibid.]. The verse is in present tense, the process is eternal. Thus it says: &#x201C;There is a river whose streams gladden God&#x2019;s city, the holy dwelling-place of the Most High&#x201D; [Ps. 46:5]. And &#x201C;You make springs gush forth in torrents; they make their way between the hills, giving drink to all the wild beasts&#x201D; [Ps. 104:10&#x2013;11].</p>
<p>Concerning this spring, it states: &#x201C;a garden spring, a well of fresh water, flowing streams from Lebanon&#x201D; [Cant. 4:15]. Our Sages of blessed memory said: &#x201C;&#x2018;a garden spring&#x2019;: this is Jacob who is a spring for the garden. &#x2018;A well of fresh water&#x2019;: this is Isaac. &#x2018;Flowing streams&#x2019;: this is Abraham.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn124">124</xref></sup> Everything is sated from that Lebanon which is divine Wisdom.<sup><xref rid="fn125">125</xref></sup></p>
<p>Contemplate the wonders of this symbolism and you will know and understand what our Sages wrote, the manner in which their words constitute the height of completeness and perfection. Such truly befits sages like these, whose every word was uttered through the holy spirit in allegoric allusion, so as to arouse the consciousness of the Kabbalistic illuminati, rather than the fools, idiots, and confused who treat their words as if they were fox fables&#x0021; Thus we find in the tractate Sanhedrin: &#x201C;&#x2018;As I looked upon, thrones were set down &#x2026;&#x2019; [Dan. 7:9]&#x2014;one for God and one for David: these are the words of R. Akiba. R. Yose the Galilean said to him: &#x2018;Akiba, how long are you going to profane the <italic>shekhinah</italic>&#x0021;? Rather, one throne is for justice and one is for righteousness.&#x2019; R. Elazar b. Azaryah said to Akiba: &#x2018;What are you doing occupying yourself with words of <italic>aggadah</italic>&#x0021;? Desist from your discourse and occupy yourself with the laws of leprosy and tents.<sup><xref rid="fn126">126</xref></sup> Rather one is a throne and one is for a footstool: a throne upon which to sit, a footstool to rest the feet.&#x2019;&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn127">127</xref></sup> Surely these sages had no essential argument with one another, but they differed on whether it was appropriate to reveal the secret meaning. This occurs in several places where the rabbis are in dispute.</p>
<p><bold>A garden locked:</bold> A closed gate.</p>
<p><bold>A fountain sealed:</bold> The light lacks nothing for it is preserved in its &#x201C;grapes&#x201D; from the seven days of creation.<sup><xref rid="fn128">128</xref></sup></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[4:13] Your limbs are an orchard of pomegranates And of all luscious fruits&#x2026;.</bold></p>
<p>Solomon mentions here [Cant. 4:14] the twelve types of spices, corresponding to the twelve channels of the Holy One, blessed be He, through which the fragrance of divine Wisdom spreads forth and is directed towards the Patriarchs.</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[4:16] Awake, O north wind,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Come, O south wind,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Blow upon my garden,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>That its perfume might spread.</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Let my beloved come to his garden</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>And enjoy its luscious fruits.</bold></p>
<p><bold>Awake, O north wind:</bold> Awake O attribute of the north, that great fire which consumes the holocaust offering and the fat upon the altar.</p>
<p><bold>Come, O south wind:</bold> After the attribute of the north takes its portion, the attribute of the south draws its sustenance.<sup><xref rid="fn129">129</xref></sup> The two of them draw forth and supply us from that spirit which overabounds in its provision and support. This is the meaning of <bold>blow upon my garden, that its perfume might flow.</bold> The spiced perfumes represent the emanation of the radiance of Wisdom with the addition of the Holy Spirit,<sup><xref rid="fn130">130</xref></sup> drawn closer in great abundance to the Patriarchs<sup><xref rid="fn131">131</xref></sup> on account of the sacrifice.</p>
<p>Concerning this our sages stated allusively: &#x201C;&#x2018;Awake, O north wind&#x2019;&#x2014;this is the holocaust offering slaughtered on the northern side of the altar. &#x2018;Come, O south wind&#x2019;&#x2014;these are the whole offerings slaughtered on the southern side of the altar. &#x2018;That its perfume might spread&#x2019;: this is incense. &#x2018;Let my beloved come to his garden&#x2019;: this is the <italic>shekhinah</italic>. &#x2018;And enjoy its luscious fruits&#x2019;: these are the sacrifices.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn132">132</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>And enjoy its luscious fruits:</bold> This is the sifted flour refined of its waste matter. In accordance with this theme it is said: &#x201C;An offering by fire, of pleasing odor to the Lord&#x201D; [Lev. 1:17]. Our sages say in <italic>Torat Kohanim</italic>: &#x201C;&#x2018;An offering&#x2019;: it must be specifically for an offering.&#x201D; This refers to the tenth <italic>Sefirah</italic> [the <italic>shekhinah</italic>] which ascends above to the place of its origin.<sup><xref rid="fn133">133</xref></sup> &#x201C;&#x2018;By fire&#x2019;: for the sake of the fires.&#x201D; Our master, the Hasid of blessed memory,<sup><xref rid="fn134">134</xref></sup> explained that these are corporeal things. &#x201C;&#x2018;For an aroma&#x2019;: for the sake of providing an aroma&#x201D;&#x2014;the spiritual dimension of physical things. &#x201C;&#x2018;A pleasing aroma&#x2019;: in order to be pleasing (to God).&#x201D; Pleasure entails the invocation of Penitence, the hidden place of His power. &#x201C;&#x2018;For the Lord&#x2019;: for the One who created the world.&#x201D;</p>
<p>The intent of the sacrifice is to provide sustenance to each and every divine attribute. This was the intent of the princes of Israel when they offered twelve goats, twelve rams, twelve lambs for a burnt offering, and twelve billy goats for a sin offering when the altar was consecrated. Everything is transmuted into spirit via the sefirotic channels which number twelve. And twenty-four bullocks were offered as sacrifices of well being, corresponding to the power of the left side of divinity, the aspect of Might, which is twenty-four [<span dir="rtl">&#x05D3;&#x05F4;&#x05DB;</span>], as it is written: &#x201C;I will lay carbuncles [<italic>kadkod</italic>] as your foundation stones&#x201D; [Isa. 54:12]. This alludes to the twenty-four permutations of the divine name <italic>Adonai</italic>. The sacrifices of well-being constituted sixty rams, sixty billy goats, and sixty yearling lambs [Num. 7:88]. These correspond to the sixty steps, the sixty heroes [Cant. 3:7], and the three-score queens [Cant. 6:8]. The meaning of a pleasing [<italic>ni&#x1E25;oa&#x1E25;</italic>] aroma is that of descent, the Aramaic of descent [<italic>yarad</italic>] being <italic>na&#x1E25;at</italic>. Through the sacrifice, divine spirit descends and the force of holiness unites and is drawn into close continguity within the channels. For this reason, sacrifice is designated <italic>korban</italic>. This is the meaning of &#x201C;Let my beloved come to his garden and enjoy its luscious fruits.&#x201D;</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[5:1] I have come to my garden,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>My own, my bride;</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>I have plucked my myrrh and spice,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Eaten my honey and honeycomb,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Drunk my wine and my milk.</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Eat, lovers and drink:</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Drink deep of love&#x0021;</bold></p>
<p><bold>I have plucked my myrrh and spice:</bold> The incense composed of frankincense and the frankincense added to the meal offering.</p>
<p><bold>Eaten my honey and honeycomb:</bold> The daily offerings and the additional offerings of New Moons, Sabbaths and holidays, vows and votive offerings, sin and guilt offerings, sacrifices of the firstborn and tithes.</p>
<p><bold>Eat, lovers:</bold> These are the priests.</p>
<p><bold>And drink: Drink deep of love&#x0021;:</bold> This is the community of Israel. This verse relates to the generation of King Solomon, when Israel enjoyed a peaceful respite from wars.</p>
<p align="blockquote">All of its people were saintly,</p>
<p align="blockquote">Cleansed of iniquity and sin,</p>
<p align="blockquote">Rejoicing in God&#x2019;s service,</p>
<p align="blockquote">Forgiven through their sacrifices,</p>
<p align="blockquote">Amongst them dwelled <italic>shekhinah</italic>,</p>
<p align="blockquote">&#x201C;A mother joyous amid her children&#x201D; [Ps. 113:9].</p>
<p>Within this text you will find the term bride used six times.<sup><xref rid="fn135">135</xref></sup> This corresponds to the six appearances of the name Solomon which are regarded as designating the divine within this book, alluding to the six sefirotic dimensions.</p>
<p align="blockquote">As her name so is her praise,</p>
<p align="blockquote">She is the bride</p>
<p align="blockquote">Encompassing all</p>
<p align="blockquote">Of Wisdom&#x2019;s paths.</p>
<p align="blockquote">Stamped with the seal</p>
<p align="blockquote">Of the whole.</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[5:2] I was asleep,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>But my heart was wakeful.</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Hark, my beloved knocks&#x0021;</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>&#x201C;Let me in, my own,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>My darling, my faultless dove&#x0021;</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>For my head is drenched with dew&#x0021;&#x201D;</bold></p>
<p><bold>I was asleep:</bold> The <italic>shekhinah</italic> states, I was asleep in Babylonian exile.</p>
<p><bold>But my heart was wakeful:</bold> Anticipating the time of redemption, &#x201C;until the time of the fulfillment of Jerusalem&#x2019;s desolation, seventy years.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn136">136</xref></sup> This was actually eighteen years after Cyrus&#x2019; declaration, which preceded the fulfillment of the seventy years promised for Babylonian domination.<sup><xref rid="fn137">137</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>Hark, my beloved knocks&#x0021;:</bold> This parable alludes to the Glory arousing the prophets to prophecy to Israel that they should ascend from Babylon to Jerusalem.</p>
<p><bold>For my head is drenched with dew:</bold> I&#x2019;ve had enough of dwelling outside of the Temple.</p>
<p><bold>[5:3]</bold> The people Israel says <bold>&#x201C;I had taken off my robe; was I to don it again?&#x201D;</bold>: I had stripped myself of my adornments. The parable refers to the Glory which had dwelled within me and had departed.</p>
<p><bold>&#x201C;I had bathed my feet; was I to soil them again?&#x201D;:</bold> I have dwelled here and built houses, planted gardens and orchards. How could I depart?</p>
<p><bold>[5:4] My beloved took his hand off the latch:</bold> The Glory sent punitive decrees from the heavens for I did not believe in the prophets&#x2019; words and did not ascend.</p>
<p><bold>And my heart was stirred for him:</bold> I realized that these troubles were caused by that sin.</p>
<p><bold>[5:5] I arose to let in my beloved&#x201D;</bold> The parable means that a portion of them ascended to the land of Israel.</p>
<p><bold>My hands dripped myrrh, my fingers, flowing myrrh:</bold> That is to say that I succeeded in the enterprise. As it is stated in Ezra [6:14]: &#x201C;So the elders of the Judeans progressed in the building, urged on by the prophesying of Haggai the prophet&#x2026;.&#x201D;</p>
<p><bold>[5:6] I opened the door for my beloved:</bold> The parable refers to the rebuilt Temple.</p>
<p><bold>But my beloved had turned and gone:</bold> The <italic>shekhinah</italic> did not dwell there and prophecy in Israel ceased. Forty years after the Temple was built, prophetic vision was sealed. As our sages state in <italic>Seder Olam:</italic> &#x201C;Alexander, king of Macedonia, reigned twelve years and died.&#x201D; Until this time the prophets prophesied through the holy spirit. From this time onwards, &#x201C;Incline your ears and listen to the sages&#x2019; words&#x201D; [Prov. 22:17]. As our Sages said in tractate Yoma: &#x201C;Why is it written: &#x2018;rebuild the House, then I will look on it with favor and I will glorify it&#x2019; [Haggai 1:8] where the transmitted text states &#x2018;I will be glorified.&#x2019;<sup><xref rid="fn138">138</xref></sup> These are the five differences distinguishing the first Temple from the second. They are: the Ark of the Covenant, the Urim and Tummim, the annointing oil, the heavenly fire upon the altar and the divine presence.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn139">139</xref></sup> This is the proper rendition of the text.</p>
<p><bold>[5:7]</bold> Consequently, upon the departure of the <italic>shekhinah</italic>, many and horrific troubles befell me, caused by the watchmen patrolling the town. These are the seventy angels who surround God&#x2019;s Throne of Glory; through them harsh decrees enter the world. As it states in the Chapters of R. Eliezer [chap. 24] concerning: &#x201C;&#x2018;Let us, then, go down and confound their speech &#x2026;&#x2019; [Gen. 11:7]. The Holy One, blessed be He, said to the angels surrounding His Throne of Glory: &#x2018;let us go and confound their speech.&#x2019;&#x201D; They are similarly called <italic>shomrei homot:</italic> &#x201C;the guards of the walls.&#x201D; This passage is a parable for the evil decrees and persecutions which befell the Jewish people during the period of the Second Temple by the hands of the Greeks.</p>
<p>One thing you need to know is that a decree was enacted that Israel would be subjugated to four kingdoms, not counting the period of servitude in Egypt, for Israel was not yet a people and not designated as the people of God until they entered the land and constructed the Temple. These four nations were revealed to our father Abraham during &#x201C;the covenant between the pieces&#x201D; [Gen. 15], just as they were shown to Daniel.<sup><xref rid="fn140">140</xref></sup> The three year old calf of Abraham&#x2019;s vision is the kingdom of Babylon, that is to say Nebuchadnezzar its king; the three-year old goat is Greece, that is, Alexander the Macedonian, and he is the ram [<italic>tzfir &#x2018;izim</italic>] mentioned in Daniel [8:4]. The turtledove represents Rome, also known as Edom.</p>
<p>The kingdom of Babylon is referred to as being threefold because three kings arose from it: Nebuchadnezzar, Ebel Merodach, and Balshezzar. Thus it is written in Jeremiah [27:7]: &#x201C;All of the nations shall serve him, his son and grandson, until the turn of his own land comes, when many nations and great kings shall subjugate him.&#x201D; Greece is referred to as a three-year old goat because Alexander was the king of the north who conquered the other three directions of the world and governed them just as Nebuchadnezzar had ruled the entire world. As it is written: &#x201C;raising from their thrones, all of the kings of the nations&#x201D; [Isa. 14:9]. The three-year old ram represents the Medeans, these being the kings of Assyria, Cyrus and Darius. As it is written: &#x201C;They joyfully celebrated the Feast of Unleavened Bread for seven days, for the Lord had given them cause for joy by inclining the heart of the Assyrian king toward them so as to give them the support in the work of the House of God, the God of Israel&#x201D; [Ezra 6:22]. Because they were Shem&#x2019;s descendants, they merited that the Temple be constructed on their account, and it was not destroyed by the hand of Senacherib.</p>
<p>Scripture refers to them as a three-year old [ram] for they were the kings of the east, who conquered the other three directions of the world. As we find in Isaiah [46:11]: &#x201C;I summoned that swooping bird from the east&#x201D; and &#x201C;Who has roused a victor from the east?&#x201D; [Isa. 41:2]<sup><xref rid="fn141">141</xref></sup> He conquered the three remaining directions of the world, as it states: &#x201C;I saw a ram butting westward, northward, and southward&#x201D; [Dan. 8:4]. And it says: &#x201C;So says Cyrus, the king of Persia: &#x2018;The Lord, God of heaven, has granted me all of the kingdoms of the world&#x2019;&#x201D; [II Chron. 36:23]. The turtledove represents the wicked one, the fourth awful and mighty beast viewed by Daniel. He desired to comprehend its true meaning, as it is written: &#x201C;I approached one of the attendants and asked him the true meaning of all of this&#x201D; [Daniel 7:16]. It is said concerning this beast: &#x201C;it will devour the whole earth, tread it down and crush it.&#x201D; R. Yohanan said: &#x201C;It is requisite that Rome&#x2019;s nature spread throughout the entire world.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn142">142</xref></sup></p>
<p>Israel underwent subjugation to these nations in accord with the following order. Senacherib, king of Assyria, who was also king of Medea, exiled the ten tribes. &#x201C;He settled them in Halah, along the Habor [and] the river Gozan, and in the towns of Media&#x201D; [II Kings 18:11]. Nebuchadnezzar, king of Babylon, at the appointed time, exiled Judah and Benjamin. Isaiah the prophet forecast the downfall of Babylon by the hands of the Medeans, just as he forecasted Cyrus&#x2019; command for Israel&#x2019;s manumission. &#x201C;Behold, I will stir up the Medes against them, who do not value silver or delight in gold&#x201D; [Isa. 13:17]. At the prophecy&#x2019;s conclusion he states: &#x201C;And when the Lord has given you rest from your sorrow and trouble, and from the hard service that you were made to serve, you shall recite this song of scorn over the king of Babylon&#x201D; [Isa. 14:3&#x2013;4]. Then follows the song&#x2019;s content until it comes to its conclusion &#x201C;I will rise up against them &#x2026; and will wipe out of Babylon name and remnant, kith and kin &#x2026;&#x201D; [Isa. 14:22]. Isaiah similarly prophesied regarding Cyrus&#x2019; decree concerning Israel: &#x201C;So says the Lord to Cyrus His anointed, whose right hand I strengthened&#x201D; [Isa. 45:1], &#x201C;He will build my city&#x201D; [Isa. 45:13]. We find similarly in Daniel [5:30&#x2013;6:1]: &#x201C;During that very night Belshazzar the King was killed and Darius the Mede received the kingdom.&#x201D; He reigned one year to complete the seventy years apportioned to the sovereignty of Babylon.<sup><xref rid="fn143">143</xref></sup> During the first year of Cyrus&#x2019; reign, the decree concerning Israel was issued and Israel came under the jurisdiction of the kingdom of Medea. Afterwards, the kingdom of Greece arose, that is, Alexander the Macedonian, the three-year old goat and Daniel&#x2019;s <italic>tzfir &#x2018;izim</italic>.<sup><xref rid="fn144">144</xref></sup> He fought with the ram [Dan. 8:7], these being the kings of Medea, Darius the Persian, putting him to the sword, as it is written: &#x201C;There was no one to rescue the ram from his power&#x201D; [Dan. 8:7]. Israel, both those in Babylon and those in Jerusalem during the period of the second Temple, came under the rule of the king of Greece. The rule of the kings of Greece lasted one hundred and eighty years, as it states in the tractate <italic>Avodah Zarah</italic> [9a]. At that time war broke out between Greece and Rome, as our sages taught in <italic>Avodah Zarah</italic> [8b]: &#x201C;The Romans engaged in thirty-two battles with Greeks and were not able to overcome them until Israel allied itself with Rome.&#x201D; Israel revolted against the Greeks during the period of the second Temple, coming under Roman authority and keeping faithful alliance with them for twenty-six years. Then the Romans turned against them, destroyed the second Temple, and the kingdom of Greece was subjugated by the Romans. Nor will the son of David come until the dominion of the kingdom of Rome spreads over the entire world for nine months, just as the other three kingdoms spread over the entire world. For this reason, our sages ordained the drinking of four cups of wine,<sup><xref rid="fn145">145</xref></sup> corresponding to the four terms for redemption appearing in the pericope <italic>Va&#x2018;era</italic> [Exod. 6:6&#x2013;7], conveying the glad tidings to Israel that they will go forth from their subjugation to the four kingdoms.</p>
<p>I have written all of this because I have seen an interpretation in Genesis Rabbah in which the three-year old goat is correlated with the kingdom of Greece, with the two-horned ram appearing in Daniel [8:3] brought as corroborating evidence. This seems to me to be either a mistake or a case of scribal error, for it is clearly stated in Daniel that the two-horned ram represents the kings of Medea and Persia.</p>
<p>I have also seen someone dispute the words of our Sages and state that the fourth beast shown to Daniel represents the kingdom of Ishmael, for they have expanded throughout the majority of the inhabited world, their kingdom being great and widespread. They find it difficult to refer to Greece [and Rome] as representing two kingdoms when they really are one nation. Thus it states: &#x201C;the offspring of Greece [<italic>Yavan</italic>] are Elisha, Tarshish and the Kittim&#x201D; [Gen. 10:4]. The Kittim are the Romans. So we find in the first chapter of Josippon:<sup><xref rid="fn146">146</xref></sup> &#x201C;And Sappho the son of Eliphaz ruled there.&#x201D; If this is the case, the Greeks and the Romans constitute one people. All of this is found in his commentary to the Pentateuch and also at the conclusion of the pericope Balak, concerning the verse: &#x201C;Ships come from the quarter of Kittim&#x201D; [Num. 24:24].</p>
<p>The essential interpretation is in accord with the words of our sages. Since the verse mentioned the kingdom of Babylon, it has already mentioned Ishmael, for Babylon stands at their head; all are under its dominion and conform to its discipline.<sup><xref rid="fn147">147</xref></sup> Furthermore, although the Greeks and Romans constitute one ethnos, they are two distinct kingdoms, and in the past they engaged in war with one another. Similarly, the kings of Judah and Israel were one people who split into two kingdoms.</p>
<p>It is said in Daniel [7:25] concerning the fourth beast: &#x201C;He will speak words against the Most High,&#x201D; that is, he will say words that can not conceivably be said: &#x201C;these are my words.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn148">148</xref></sup> &#x201C;And he will harass the holy ones of the Most High&#x201D; [Dan. 7:25]: Israel. This is the meaning of &#x201C;in the presence of the vengeful foe&#x201D; [Ps. 44:17]. &#x201C;He will think of changing times and laws&#x201D; [7:25]: in their interpretation and to change the law. &#x201C;And they will be delivered into his hands for time, times and half a time&#x201D; [Dan. 7:25]: that is to say that redemption will not come to Israel until &#x201C;time, times and half a time.&#x201D; As it is said: &#x201C;the beast was killed &#x2026; its body was destroyed and it was consigned to the flames&#x201D; [Dan. 7:11]. It is written afterwards: &#x201C;As I looked on in the night vision,&#x201D;</p>
<p align="blockquote">One like a human being</p>
<p align="blockquote">Came with the clouds of heaven &#x2026;</p>
<p align="blockquote">Dominion, glory, and kingship were given to him</p>
<p align="blockquote">All peoples and nations of every language must</p>
<p align="blockquote">serve him [Dan. 7:13&#x2013;14].</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[5:8] I adjure you O maidens of Jerusalem&#x0021;</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>If you meet my beloved, tell him this:</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>That I am faint with love.</bold></p>
<p>All this is a parable concerning the ascent of the Glory, and the <italic>shekhinah</italic> complaining bitterly about his departure.</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[5:9] How is your beloved fairer than another,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>O fairest of women?</bold></p>
<p>From all of the seventy thrones of Kingship.</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[5:10] My beloved is clear skinned and ruddy,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Preeminent among ten thousand.</bold></p>
<p>Our sages say in the Midrash to Canticles: &#x201C;<bold>My beloved is clear skinned and ruddy:</bold> His appearance is ruddy, black, green, and white. Thus the appearance of the Holy One is like &#x2018;the appearance of the rainbow which is within the cloud&#x2019; [Ezek. 1:28].&#x201D;</p>
<p><bold>Preeminent among ten thousand:</bold> Surrounding Him is the divine camp; myriad holy ones are about Him. He is distinguished among His hosts, is recognized among His camps. As our Sages said concerning Rabbi Akiba when he entered the Orchard: &#x201C;&#x2018;What did you see?&#x2019;<sup><xref rid="fn149">149</xref></sup> &#x2018;The Lord of Hosts [<italic>tzevaot</italic>] is His name&#x2019; [Isa. 47:4]. He is distinguished [<italic>ot</italic>] amidst His Host [<italic>tzeva shelo</italic>].&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn150">150</xref></sup></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[5:11] His head is finest gold,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>His locks are curled,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Black like a raven.</bold></p>
<p><bold>His head is finest gold:</bold> All inclusive, crowned and endiademed.<sup><xref rid="fn151">151</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>His locks are black curls:</bold> As the verse states: &#x201C;He made darkness His screen; dark thunder heads, dense clouds of the sky were His pavilion round about Him&#x201D; [Ps. 18:12]. For they constitute the beginning of the generation of water. This is as the sages said in Exodus Rabbah [15:22]: &#x201C;The waters engendered and birthed darkness.&#x201D;</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[5:12] His eyes are like doves&#x2026;.</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Bathed in milk,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Set by a brimming pool.</bold></p>
<p><bold>His eyes are like doves:</bold> &#x201C;For the eyes of the Lord set about the whole earth&#x201D; [II Chron. 16:9].</p>
<p><bold>Bathed in milk:</bold> And they are as pure as milk.</p>
<p><bold>Set by a brimming pool:</bold> Situated by the dwelling places of perfection and beauty.</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[5:13] His cheeks are like a bed of spices,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Banks of perfume,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>His lips are like lilies,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>They drip flowing myrrh.</bold></p>
<p><bold>His cheeks are like a bed of spices</bold> The parable alludes to that illuminated countenance which no mortal may see and live. No mortal creature can attain satiety<sup><xref rid="fn152">152</xref></sup> from that illumination.</p>
<p><bold>Like a bed of spices:</bold> This is wisdom, the countenances illuminated by the luminosity of Wisdom. Concerning this it is said: &#x201C;In the light of the king&#x2019;s countenance is life&#x201D; [Prov. 16:14]. And it says: &#x201C;May God shine His countenance upon you and deal graciously with you&#x201D; [Num. 6:25].</p>
<p><bold>His lips are like lilies:</bold> The six <italic>sefirot</italic> are directed by His word and the spirit of His mouth.</p>
<p><bold>They drip flowing myrrh:</bold> These are the words of Torah which all nations and tongues acknowledge. It is like that goodly myrrh which passes from place to place and contains no impurity.</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[5:15] He is as majestic as Lebanon,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Stately as the cedars.<sup><xref rid="fn153">153</xref></sup></bold></p>
<p>In similar fashion Scripture states: &#x201C;I am like a leafy cypress; your fruit comes from Me&#x201D; [Hos. 14:9]. Souls are the fruit of the blessed Holy One. If Rava created a man,<sup><xref rid="fn154">154</xref></sup> he returned it to dust, for it contained no power of the soul.</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[6:2] My beloved has gone down to his garden,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>To the beds of spices,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>To browse in the gardens,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>And to pick lilies.</bold></p>
<p><bold>My beloved has gone down to his garden:</bold> An all-encompassing entity does not differentiate between such distinctions as &#x201C;above&#x201D; and &#x201C;below.&#x201D; Descent is equivalent to ascent; ascent to descent. Because exile has caused it to be occulted amidst its sefirotic manifestations, Scripture refers to it as engaging in an act of &#x201C;descent.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn155">155</xref></sup> Whence has it [descended] to the garden?</p>
<p><bold>To the beds of spices:</bold> That is to say, [from] transcendent Wisdom, the locus from which this aroma and emanative energy spread forth.</p>
<p><bold>To browse in the gardens:</bold> To provide nurturance for itself and to pour forth its luminescence to the gardens and the <italic>shekhinah</italic>.<sup><xref rid="fn156">156</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>And to gather the lilies:</bold> This is Thought, the luminescence of Wisdom flowing forth to the six cosmic boundaries [<italic>ketzavot</italic>]. All this takes place during the period of exile, a time bereft of festal offerings, sacrifices of thanksgiving and the meal offerings. The spiritual entities ascend and are drawn to that place from which they nurse. This is the meaning of: &#x201C;on evil&#x2019;s account, the righteous one dies&#x201D; [Isa. 57:1].<sup><xref rid="fn157">157</xref></sup> For this reason, one must strive to invoke and emanate an outflow of blessing to the Fathers,<sup><xref rid="fn158">158</xref></sup> so that the sons too be imbued with emanative energy. In this verse this process of emanation and outpouring is referred to as &#x201C;gathering.&#x201D;</p>
<p>Our sages have likewise referred to the emanation of the <italic>sefirot</italic> and their revelation as an act of displacement [<italic>&#x2018;akirah</italic>]. It states in Genesis Rabbah [15:1]: &#x201C;&#x2018;The Lord God planted a garden in Eden&#x2019; [Gen. 2:8]. As it is written: &#x2018;Let the trees of the Lord be sated, the cedars of Lebanon, his own planting&#x2019; [Ps. 104:16]. R. Hanina said: &#x2018;They were like the antennae of locusts [<italic>karnei hagavim</italic>]. The Holy One uprooted them and replanted them in the Garden of Eden.&#x2019;&#x201D; Comprehend this wondrous statement. The planter must have in his hands a plantling. Similarly, the emanation and manifestation of the divine entities [<italic>havayot</italic>] was like an act of &#x201C;displacement&#x201D; while their creation and nurturance in their respective places was an act of planting. Those who plant &#x201C;seedlings lovingly attended&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn159">159</xref></sup> need to water them regularly. This is the meaning of R. Haninah&#x2019;s statement. It states further in the Midrash: &#x201C;Let the trees of the Lord drink and be sated&#x201D; [Ps. 104:16]: &#x201C;May their lives be sated; may their waters be sated; may their planting be sated.&#x201D; The meaning here is that each sefirotic power receives its energy from the power above it, life drawing from the source of life, water from life, and the plantlings drawing from water. All this is intimated here. And it is also germane to the next verse which states:</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[6:3] I am my beloved&#x2019;s and my beloved is mine; he browses among the lilies.</bold></p>
<p>The meaning is that I receive from my beloved and my beloved, who browses among the lilies, receives [its energy] from transcendent Wisdom. Each and every sefirotic power ascends and &#x201C;gazes&#x201D; upon the power surmounting it, each attribute drawing forth from attribute, that which is carved out from that which is engraved, that which is engraved from that which is traced, that which is traced from that which is concealed. All are within each other, all derive from each other, all are connected to each other and bound to one another.</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[6:4] You are as beautiful, my darling, as Tirzah, comely as Jerusalem.</bold></p>
<p>This entire verse constitutes a parable concerning Wisdom, and is to be read in accord with the principle which we enunciated at the book&#x2019;s beginning.</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[6:5] Your hair is like a flock of goats</bold></p>
<p>The text begins to relate the praises of the <italic>shekhinah</italic>, her hair, eyes, and brow: &#x201C;Your brow behind your veil [gleams] like a pomegranate split open&#x201D; [Cant. 6:6]. &#x201C;Hedged around with lilies&#x201D; [Cant. 7:3]: She encompasses the six cosmic boundaries and is sealed by them all. Thus the verse states &#x201C;There are sixty queens &#x2026;&#x201D; [Cant. 6:8].<sup><xref rid="fn160">160</xref></sup></p>
<p>[Here begins an excursus on Ps. 104. The commentary on the Song of Songs resumes on p. 129 below.]</p>
<p>I have decided at this point to relate the tale of creation in order to apprize you of the truth concerning this verse: &#x201C;There are sixty queens.&#x201D; And I will expound: &#x201C;O Lord my God, you are very great; You are clothed with glory and majesty&#x201D; [Ps. 104], which propounds the entire issue of creation from its beginning until its end. This is the gist of the psalm.</p>
<p>[104:2]: &#x201C;You &#x2026; are wrapped in a robe of light&#x201D; corresponds to the light created on the first day of creation. That is, the emanation of that light from Nothing.</p>
<p>[104:3]: &#x201C;He sets His rafters in the waters&#x201D; corresponds to the command &#x201C;Let there be a firmament&#x201D; created on the second day to &#x201C;separate water from water&#x201D; [Gen. 1:6]. The verse from Psalms clarifies that that separation encompassed many matters.<sup><xref rid="fn161">161</xref></sup></p>
<p>[104:5]: &#x201C;He established the earth on its foundations so that it shall never totter&#x201D; parallels &#x201C;Let the waters be gathered into one place and let dry land appear&#x201D; [Gen. 1:9] and designates the length of time established for its existence.</p>
<p>[104:14]: &#x201C;You make the grass grow for the cattle&#x201D; parallels &#x201C;Let the earth bring forth herbs &#x2026;&#x201D; [Gen. 1:11].</p>
<p>[104:19]: &#x201C;He made the moon to mark the seasons; the sun knows when to set&#x201D; corresponds to the command &#x201C;Let there be luminaries &#x2026;&#x201D; [Gen. 1:14].</p>
<p>[104:22&#x2013;3]: &#x201C;When the sun rises [the lions] come home and couch in their dens. Man then goes out to his work, to his labor until the evening&#x201D; corresponds to &#x201C;God made the two great luminaries&#x201D; [Gen. 1:16].</p>
<p>[104:25]: &#x201C;There is the sea vast and wide, with its creatures without number&#x201D; corresponds to &#x201C;Let the waters teem with living creatures&#x201D; [Gen. 1:20].</p>
<p>[104:31]: Paralleling the sixth day, on which it is said: &#x201C;And God created the human being&#x201D; [Gen. 1:27], it states: &#x201C;May the glory of God endure forever.&#x201D;</p>
<p>[104:32]: Corresponding to the seventh day of creation which points towards the seventh millennium when the world will be annihilated, it states: &#x201C;He gazes upon the earth and it trembles.&#x201D;</p>
<p>[104:33]: The joy experienced by the souls of the righteous during that time finds its intimation in &#x201C;I will sing to the Lord with all my life force.&#x201D;</p>
<p>[104:35]: Allusion to the nullification of the evil inclination during that period appears in &#x201C;Sinners will disappear from the earth and the wicked will be no more.&#x201D;</p>
<p>I will now proceed to explicate this psalm as well as expound upon the narrative of creation. And the enlightened will understand.</p>
<p>[104:1] &#x201C;O Lord my God, You are very great&#x201D;: The psalm alludes to the illumination of Wisdom, extending in every direction. From that flow, each Cause and attribute nurses like an infant.</p>
<p>&#x201C;Enclothed in glory and majesty&#x201D;: So is Wisdom bounded. Never will we find Her in Your absence. Thus it was prior to the world&#x2019;s creation, when the Holy One was alone in His world, when the primal existences [<italic>havayot</italic>] were still deeply hidden within Wisdom.</p>
<p>The text then explicates the manner of the creation of the two worlds, above and below.</p>
<p>[104:2]: &#x201C;Wrapped in a robe of light; You spread the heavens like a tent cloth&#x201D;: This denotes the invocation of Wisdom&#x2019;s emanation enveloping the entirety of being. &#x201C;Enwrapment&#x201D; means that it receives illumination from that flow. Its amplification sparked a light which was among the ten entities emanated upon that first day, all as one, without differentiation. These are: heaven and earth; primeval chaos&#x2014;formless and void, darkness and light, water and wind, the quality of day and the quality of night.<sup><xref rid="fn162">162</xref></sup></p>
<p>And thus [Gen. 1:2 states]: &#x201C;The world was chaotic, empty&#x201D;: Chaos is an entity lacking all form; but primal Emptiness enclothed that chaos, until it traced a tracing finer than spirit. &#x201C;Darkness was upon the face of the deep&#x201D;: The depth of the supernal heights, the depth below.<sup><xref rid="fn163">163</xref></sup> &#x201C;And the spirit of God hovered over the waters&#x201D;: The Messiah&#x2019;s spirit, the spirit of Wisdom and Understanding, hovered over the waters, covering all. This is all that was emanated upon that first day.</p>
<p>The essence of all things was emanated upon the first day, just as our Sages taught concerning the primordial human: &#x201C;In the first hour of the day the dust from which he was created was gathered together.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn164">164</xref></sup> When Scripture states: &#x201C;Let there be light&#x201D; [Gen. 1:3] its meaning is that Divinity enwrapped Itself in that light as we have explained, meaning that through the amplification of that luminescence, the light entered into a state of actualization.</p>
<p>In this first passage we find the word &#x201C;light&#x201D; five times, just as the phrase &#x201C;it was good&#x201D; appears five times. In the second passage the term &#x201C;water&#x201D; is repeated five times. Five were the drops of water, five were the drops of light in their midst. These were the five voices uttered at Torah&#x2019;s revelation.<sup><xref rid="fn165">165</xref></sup> It is for this reason that Scripture states, &#x201C;it was good,&#x201D; for the light was kindled candle from candle, granting the primal essences the power to expand and flow forth.</p>
<p>&#x201C;God separated the light from the darkness&#x201D; [Gen. 1:4]: God set a boundary to the effluence and expansion of each and every one. This is the intent of &#x201C;Let there be light and there was light&#x201D; [Gen. 1:3], meaning &#x201C;the speculum that shines.&#x201D; &#x201C;And there was darkness&#x201D; [Gen. 1:2]: &#x201C;the speculum that does not shine.&#x201D;</p>
<p>Concerning both of them it said: &#x201C;It was good.&#x201D; This is the meaning of: &#x201C;God called the light day, the darkness He called night&#x201D; [Gen. 1:5]. He drew forth the effluence of the attribute of Day to daytime, the attribute of Night to nighttime. &#x201C;And there was one day&#x201D; [Gen. 1:5] all remained unified, in all of this the primal essence came to manifestation. Another interpretation: &#x201C;There was evening&#x201D;: the speculum that does not shine. &#x201C;There was morning&#x201D;: the speculum which does shine. &#x201C;One day&#x201D;: unique and unified in His names.</p>
<p>[Ps. 104:3]: &#x201C;Let there be a firmament in the midst of the waters&#x201D; [Gen. 1:6] parallels: &#x201C;Who lays the beams of Your Upper chambers in the waters.&#x201D;</p>
<p>&#x201C;Let there be a firmament&#x201D;: let the firmament expand into the midst of the waters, like the expansion of the soul into form. On the second day, God created the boundaries of space. For this reason, Scripture did not state &#x201C;it was good&#x201D; on the second day. For the work of the divine attribute of goodness remained incomplete. Such is the meaning of: &#x201C;Let the firmament divide the waters from the waters.&#x201D; The basic act of separation is this division into two: the upper waters and the lower waters. The upper waters are allegorically designated as male: the lower waters as female. This division works out in multifarious details. Consequently, Scripture states: &#x201C;He builds His upper chambers in the heaven&#x201D; [Amos 9:6]. For they are constructed as rungs upon rungs, as it is written: &#x201C;For one higher above the higher, watches&#x201D; [Eccles. 5:7]. All of these entities are traced, one within the other, each encompassing the other. Thus half of the waters are on high, half are below. So it is said: &#x201C;Just as the <italic>shekhinah</italic> is above, is the <italic>shekhinah</italic> below.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn166">166</xref></sup></p>
<p>Corresponding to this matter there are eighteen thousand worlds.<sup><xref rid="fn167">167</xref></sup> As David the King states: &#x201C;God&#x2019;s chariots are myriads, even thousands upon thousands&#x201D; [Ps. 68:18]. Having stipulated that God&#x2019;s chariots are myriads, that is twenty thousand worlds, corresponding to ten <italic>sefirot</italic> above and ten below, he subtracts two thousand from their number, for they are the nought. All of the above is true. The worlds number twenty thousand. But two thousand are not included in the count, for they are Nought. Each and every world consists of a thousand generations. There are consequently eighteen thousand worlds. The primal essences originate in the mystery of Wisdom and its Cause. For this reason, it is fitting that the phrase &#x201C;God said&#x201D; appears but nine times in the narrative of Creation. The tenth is an allusion to the Nought. It appears in the phrase &#x201C;In the beginning.&#x201D; It is proper that it not be enunciated.</p>
<p>&#x201C;Who makes the clouds His riding-mount&#x201D;: The total of divisions wrought in the upper waters is seventy, excepting that at the center, which makes them seventy-one. Facing them are the lower waters, stamped in their image yet considered but one, leading to a total of seventy-two. This is the meaning of &#x201C;clouds,&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn168">168</xref></sup> as in &#x201C;Behold the Lord rides upon a light cloud&#x201D; [Isa. 19:1] or &#x201C;Behold I come unto you in a dense cloud&#x201D; [Exod. 19:9].</p>
<p>The seventy divisions are the five &#x201C;voices&#x201D; divided into seven directions, excepting the central one that gives stability to them all and is not one of them. Actually there are six directions, each of them multiplied by ten. That is why &#x201C;it was good&#x201D; is said six times in the chapter on creation. This too is why Scripture speaks of &#x201C;sixty queens&#x201D; [Cant. 6:1] and &#x201C;sixty warriors surround it&#x201D; [Cant. 3:7]. All of this refers to a single matter, as we are to explain. Counting the seventh [central] direction also as ten, they make up seventy. Adding the innermost spiritual direction they are seventy-one. This is the totality of distinctions made on the second day.</p>
<p>Each setting of limits is in fact a division of space. Thus it says of man&#x2019;s creation that in the second hour He &#x201C;limited&#x201D; him. This is like a person who is building up a ruined place; he needs to trace out where he will put the upper stories and the chambers. The building is completed by means of these divisions. That is why division exists.</p>
<p>&#x201C;He walks upon the wings of the winds&#x201D;: The blessed Holy One is revealed in and is raised up through the world. His footsteps are known through those attributes, just as the soul&#x2019;s action is revealed through the body. This is the meaning of &#x201C;God called the firmament heaven&#x201D; [Gen. 1:5]. All the names are included in the word &#x201C;heaven.&#x201D; Thus Scripture says: &#x201C;And you hear, O heaven&#x201D; [II Chron. 6:27], &#x201C;the Lord, God of heaven&#x201D; [Neh. 1:8], &#x201C;He who rides in heaven&#x201D; [Deut. 33:26].</p>
<p>[Ps. 104:4]: &#x201C;He makes the winds His messengers&#x201D;: This alludes to the fact that the angels were created on the second day. These are His hosts on whose account He is designated the &#x201C;God of hosts.&#x201D; For they are neither replaced nor annihilated as are the other angels created on the fifth day, as we shall explain.</p>
<p>[Ps. 104:10]: &#x201C;You make springs gush forth in torrents, they make their way between the hills&#x201D; corresponds to &#x201C;Let the water below the sky be gathered into one area, so that dry land may appear&#x201D; [Gen. 1:9].<sup><xref rid="fn169">169</xref></sup> This is the preparation of the channels leading into the sea of Wisdom.<sup><xref rid="fn170">170</xref></sup></p>
<p>[Ps. 104:5]: &#x201C;He established the earth upon its foundations&#x201D; indicates that the separation became truly distinct and visible. Therefore, it is in this place that the verse repeats &#x201C;God saw that it was good&#x201D; instead of on the second day. Just as our sages said concerning the creation of the primordial human, &#x201C;God shaped his limbs in the third hour,&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn171">171</xref></sup> similarly, it was on the third day &#x201C;that dry land was seen&#x201D; [Gen. 1:9]. For when the world existed as undifferentiated water<sup><xref rid="fn172">172</xref></sup> the land could not become visible. Paralleling the Genesis text is &#x201C;He established the world on its foundations, so that it should never totter&#x201D; [Ps. 104:5]. That is the time allotted it, one thousand generations. That is fifty thousand years, fifty years for a generation.<sup><xref rid="fn173">173</xref></sup></p>
<p>[Ps. 104:6]: &#x201C;You made the deep cover it as a garment&#x201D;: The deep coexists with the world like a pot and its lid. Thus [the verse continues] &#x201C;the waters stood above the mountains.&#x201D; How were the waters gathered to one side? For you rebuked them &#x201C;and they fled from your rebuke&#x201D; [Ps. 104:7], as in: &#x201C;The voice of the Lord is over the waters, the God of glory thunders, the Lord, over the mighty waters&#x201D; [Ps. 29:3]. That is why it repeats the word: &#x201C;Water, water.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn174">174</xref></sup></p>
<p>[Ps. 104:8]: &#x201C;They rise up to the mountains, flow down to the valleys, to that place You have assigned to them&#x201D;: This refers to the ocean, as in &#x201C;Let the waters be gathered to one place&#x201D; [Gen. 1:9]. &#x201C;God called the dry place &#x2018;land&#x2019;&#x201D; [Gen 1:10] means that He drew forth the Will, which is the [upper] end of Thought, to the &#x201C;dry place,&#x201D; &#x201C;dry&#x201D; refers to that which does not bear fruit.<sup><xref rid="fn175">175</xref></sup> He drew to her this end of Thought, which is the totality of all the entities. Thus Scripture says: &#x201C;Let the land bring forth grass&#x201D; [Gen 1:11] and &#x201C;Let the waters be gathered,&#x201D; making channels through which the river then proceeds from Eden, flowing on the fifth day to water the garden. But for now those channels appeared as raw form [<italic>golem</italic>]; there was as yet no drawing forth. The channels were only preparations for the flowing springs.<sup><xref rid="fn176">176</xref></sup> Therefore it says:</p>
<p>[Ps. 104:10&#x2013;11]: &#x201C;He sends forth springs in the river-beds; they run between the mountains, giving drink to all the beasts of the field&#x201D;: This refers to the well-known &#x201C;beast,&#x201D; the one who is also called &#x201C;garden,&#x201D; of which it says: &#x201C;A river flows forth from Eden to water the garden&#x201D; [Gen. 2:10].</p>
<p>[Ps. 104:11]: &#x201C;The wild beasts quench their thirst&#x201D;: The angels are thus called, those appointed to serve over matters of this world, as it is conducted. These are also &#x201C;the young lions roar for prey&#x201D; [Ps. 104:21]. And thus: &#x201C;the gathering of waters He called seas&#x201D; [Gen. 1:10]. He drew forth the central line, the one that nurses from the Source, like a spinal column drawing sustenance from the brain, into an attribute of day, passing through the cosmic Foundation, as in &#x201C;all the rivers flow into the sea&#x201D; [Eccles.1:6]. All the channels flow from the attribute of day to that of night by means of the cosmic Foundation.<sup><xref rid="fn177">177</xref></sup></p>
<p>[Ps. 104:12]: &#x201C;Upon them dwell the birds of heaven&#x201D;: Upon these two attributes; because of them, the ministering angels exist. &#x201C;From amid the branches they give forth their voice&#x201D;: The voices proceed from the seventy names, all of them deriving from the primal and innermost soft voice, the singular nation, parallel to the power of Israel, making seventy-one.</p>
<p>[Ps. 104:13]: &#x201C;He gives the mountains drink from His upper chambers&#x201D;: Because grasses and plants do not grow until the rain falls, it says: &#x201C;He gives the mountains drink.&#x201D; Right after this it says: &#x201C;He causes grass to grow for the cattle; earth is sated by the fruit of Your deeds&#x201D; [Ps. 104:14&#x2013;15]. And where do they all come from? The &#x201C;upper chambers,&#x201D; which is to say &#x201C;the fruit of Your deeds.&#x201D; From the upper chambers, the glorious palaces which are the primal spiritual elements, come the forces that bring about rain for the world. This is the fruit of those &#x201C;deeds,&#x201D; for they are the cause of all being and non-being in the world, the cause of light and darkness. Of them are born the clouds<sup><xref rid="fn178">178</xref></sup> over the earth, from which the rain comes. The Land of Israel drinks of the innermost and purest of these, since it is parallel to the central column, the innermost, while the rest of the world drinks of them in diluted form. Of this Scripture says: &#x201C;He builds His upper chambers in the heavens and founds His vault upon the earth; He calls to the waters of the sea and pours them out over the face of the earth&#x201D; [Amos 9:6]. After mentioning the upper chambers, he speaks of the rain that comes about through them. Job too mentions first the primal causes and then the rain that comes about because of them: &#x201C;He looks to the ends of the earth and sees beneath all of heaven, making a weight for the wind and measuring out the waters. He makes a decree for the rain and a way for the thunderstorm&#x201D; [Job 28:24&#x2013;26]. The rain is sent forth as a result of those primal causes. Of this Scripture says: &#x201C;Depth calls unto depth by the sound of Your channels&#x201D; [Ps. 42:8]. Understand this. The drops of rain are the drops of sexual coupling, coming from that which is without end [<italic>eyn sof</italic>].</p>
<p>Parallel to &#x201C;Let the earth bring forth grasses&#x201D; [Gen. 1:11], which sets out the pattern of all generation, it says here: &#x201C;He causes grass to grow for the cattle&#x201D; [Ps. 104:14&#x2013;15]. After telling us that rain is sent forth as a result of those primal forces, he says that grasses and plants grow because of forces attached to those same primal entities, for there is no blade of grass below that does not have a power attached to it above by which it comes to be and grows, and for the sake of which it exists. The Psalm goes on to say:</p>
<p>[Ps. 104:15]: &#x201C;Grass for man&#x2019;s labors &#x2026; wine to make man&#x2019;s heart glad, and food to satisfy the heart&#x201D;: The rain and the grasses that grow because of it are human food, and drinks bring us joy. So too: &#x201C;May the trees of the Lord be sated, the cedars of Lebanon He has planted, there where the birds make their nests&#x201D; [Ps. 104:16&#x2013;17]. The mountain goats and rabbits up on the boulders and the high mountains, all sensate beings, need those primal entities which are the first source of the entire birth process. How &#x201C;may the trees of the Lord<sup><xref rid="fn179">179</xref></sup> be sated&#x201D;? They are sated first from the Source of Life, giving of the overflow of their water to living creatures, both feeling and unfeeling. &#x201C;The cedars of Lebanon that He planted&#x201D; [Ps. 104:16] are those delicate entities, as we have explained. This is the meaning of &#x201C;where the birds make their nests&#x201D; [Ps. 104:17]. &#x201C;The high mountains are for the mountain-goats; the boulders are hiding-places for rabbits&#x201D; [Ps. 104:18]. Here it has been explained that everything draws life from those primal entities, nursing from those that emerged and appeared on the third day.<sup><xref rid="fn180">180</xref></sup> This was fixed in their nature as a primal and eternal desire. He placed their rule over the earth, that all creatures be attached to them and sustained by them, and in the end that all return to them. Of this it says here [on the third day] &#x201C;And it was good.&#x201D;</p>
<p>[Ps. 104:19]: Parallel to &#x201C;Let there be lights&#x201D; [Gen. 1:14], the Psalmist says: &#x201C;He made the moon for fixed seasons.&#x201D; The word &#x201C;Let there be&#x201D; indicates a drawing forth from Wisdom; therefore it is used in the account of creation only when referring to inward things:<sup><xref rid="fn181">181</xref></sup> light, firmament, luminaries. But of whatever was formless it says &#x201C;Let there appear,&#x201D; so that potential form or soul might appear in them.<sup><xref rid="fn182">182</xref></sup> So it is said of Adam, that in his fourth hour the soul-breath was cast into him. [The following line, having to do with the hiding of the light after seven days, and quoting Ps. 97:11, is quite garbled in the manuscript as well as the printed edition, and must be considered untranslatable. It may refer to the light of the seven sefirotic &#x201C;days&#x201D; transferred to the <italic>shekhinah</italic>.]</p>
<p>[Ps. 104:20]: &#x201C;God made the two great lights, the greater light &#x2026;&#x201D; [Gen. 1:16]. He gave it dominion over those servants appointed to rule the night. Thus it says &#x201C;You bring on darkness and it is night, when all the beasts of the forest stir.&#x201D; This refers to the well-known &#x201C;beast&#x201D; who rules at night and the servants appointed over the night, who seek from her their appropriate role and tasks. These are &#x201C;the young lions roar for prey, asking of God their food&#x201D; [Ps. 104:21]. This means to draw it forth to them and lead them, so that which they are appointed over might exist. Of this it is also said: &#x201C;She rises while it is yet night, giving food to her household and portions to her maidservants&#x201D; [Prov. 31:15].</p>
<p>[Ps. 104:22]: &#x201C;When the sun shines they return home, crouching in their dens&#x201D;: This refers both to those who serve at night and to the one who rules over them.</p>
<p>[Ps. 104:23]: &#x201C;Man goes forth to his work&#x201D;: the attribute of day; &#x201C;and to his work unto evening&#x201D;: serving the attribute of night. That is why it says here &#x201C;and it was good&#x201D; [Gen. 1:18], for the lights were kindled to receive the power of the soul. Thus far the completion of the fourth day, including the attributes of day and night. It is said that all creatures are attached and bound to these, the source of all that they bring forth. These rule, as master rules over servant, one over the day and the other over the night. Thus the passage concludes: &#x201C;How many are Your works, O Lord, You have made them all in wisdom,<sup><xref rid="fn183">183</xref></sup> the earth is filled with Your creations&#x201D; [Ps. 104:24].</p>
<p>Now the Psalm begins to speak of how the divine will flows into all the secondary beings who were created in the sea of wisdom, of the completion of the structure through them, and of the further extension of those well-springs that had begun to flow into the sea of wisdom on the fifth day.</p>
<p>[Ps. 104:25]: Parallel to &#x201C;Let the waters bring forth creeping things&#x201D; [Gen. 1:20] it says: &#x201C;There is the sea, vast and wide, its creatures beyond number, beings both small and great.&#x201D; &#x201C;The face of the cherub is like that of a man,&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn184">184</xref></sup> the cherub being in the form of a little child. When it says &#x201C;birds shall fly&#x201D; [Gen. 1:20], it refers to the two cherubim which draw blessing forth, the attributes of south and north. Of these Scripture says: &#x201C;Awake, O north, and come forth, O south. blow your winds in my garden&#x201D; [Cant. 4:16], as we have explained it. Once heaven and earth are doing their work, the power of these other two attributes is drawn toward them and added to them.</p>
<p>[Ps. 104:26]: &#x201C;There go the ships&#x201D;: those channels created on the third day. Of this it says: &#x201C;She is like a merchant ship, she brings her food from afar&#x201D; [Prov. 31:14]. She brings them through those channels, well-springs, and streams, and they flow into this sea and appear there.</p>
<p>&#x201C;God created the great sea-monsters&#x201D; [Gen. 1:21]: These are the four camps outside the <italic>shekhinah</italic> of the blessed Holy One, glorifying and exalting Him with words of song and praise. Of this it says &#x201C;You created him to delight in him&#x201D; [Ps. 104:26].</p>
<p>&#x201C;And all the living creatures who creep&#x201D; [Gen. 1:21]: This is the being with four faces, those of man, lion, ox, and cherub. Each of those faces itself has four faces and four wings, the wings spread out above the faces. Their appearance and their deeds have the appearance of fire. Within the red fire there is a black fire. This is the one spoken of in the [prophetic] tradition, where it says: &#x201C;That is the being I saw beneath the God of Israel on the River Chebar, and I knew that they were cherubs&#x201D; [Ezek. 10:22]. That is why the verse says: &#x201C;which the waters caused to swarm forth after their kind&#x201D; [Gen. 1:21]: They are [collectively] called &#x201C;beast&#x201D; [or &#x201C;being&#x201D;], for their bodies are joined but the faces are separate.<sup><xref rid="fn185">185</xref></sup> Therefore it says: &#x201C;which the waters caused to swarm forth after their kind.&#x201D;</p>
<p>&#x201C;And each winged bird after its kind&#x201D;:This refers to those angels created on the fifth day, for there are various rungs, some lower than others and some higher than others. There is a fire that pushes out fire and a fire that consumes fire. Some of them are from water, still others from air. The mission of each is in accord with its essence: the one sent on an errand of mercy is from water; the one who goes as an emissary of justice is derived from fire. Therefore no one angel is sent for both justice and mercy.</p>
<p>&#x201C;God blessed them, saying: &#x2018;Be fruitful and multiply, filling the land and the waters of the seas&#x2019;&#x201D; [Gen. 1:22]. As Scripture says, &#x201C;Like entities in the full belly&#x201D; [Eccles. 11:5], since water did not flow forth from wisdom until the sixth day, of which Scripture says &#x201C;Let earth bring forth a living being after its kind&#x201D; [Gen. 1:24]. The angels that were created on the fifth day are negated, just as the spark is reabsorbed into the coal, once they have sung their song. The reason [for their existence] is external to them and they are not sufficiently strong to stand before their Creator. They are incarnated a second time, sing their song, and then they disappear. Of this matter it has been said: &#x201C;New each morning, great is Your faith&#x0021;&#x201D; [Lam. 3:23]. Here our Psalm continues: &#x201C;All of them look to You to give them their food in its due time&#x201D; [Ps. 104:27]. This refers to their flowing forth.</p>
<p>[Ps. 104:28&#x2013;30]: &#x201C;You give to them and they gather &#x2026; when You hide Your face, they are terrified; when You take their breath, they die. Send Your breath and they are created&#x2026;.&#x201D; All I have created is for your sake; that is why it says here: &#x201C;it was good&#x201D; [Gen. 1:21]. Thus it says of Adam, that in the fifth hour he stood up on his feet.</p>
<p>Of the sixth day Scripture says: &#x201C;Let earth bring forth&#x201D; [Gen. 1:24]. Let it bring forth all the generations, and with them the spirit of the first human came forth. Parallel to &#x201C;God created man in His image&#x201D; [Gen. 1:27], the completion of the structure, replete with its future implications and potentials, conducting it in such a way that each part is joined to the others, the Psalm says: &#x201C;May the glory of YHVH be forever&#x0021;&#x201D; [Ps. 104:31]. For the name was not complete until Adam was created in God&#x2019;s image. Only then was the seal complete, about which the prophet said to the prince of Tyre: &#x201C;you are the seal of the account&#x201D; [Ezek. 28:12]. He meant to say that you are on the rung of Adam, who completed the ten <italic>sefirot</italic>. The word <italic>tokhnit</italic> here means &#x201C;account,&#x201D; as in &#x201C;a full account of the bricks&#x201D; [Exod. 5:18]. Of this it says: &#x201C;May the glory of YHVH be forever&#x0021;&#x201D;: a complete name spoken over a complete world.</p>
<p>&#x201C;May YHVH rejoice in His creatures,&#x201D; He caused the holy spirit to lie upon him, for he was crowned and adorned with the ten <italic>sefirot.</italic> So too it says of Adam that in the sixth hour he gave the creatures names. Here He concludes His words regarding the sixth day, sealing them with &#x201C;it was good,&#x201D; the name of God. Here the phrase is repeated a second time in the verse &#x201C;God saw all that He had made, and behold it was very good&#x201D; [Gen. 1:31]. The word &#x201C;very&#x201D; refers to attachment to the Nothing, which is [the primal] good, that which brings about the renewal of generations. Thus it said in the Torah scroll of Rabbi Meir: &#x201C;and behold, death was good.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn186">186</xref></sup> For this reason too they established the blessing &#x201C;who is good and does good&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn187">187</xref></sup> to be recited in the house of mourning, for if one generation did not pass, no new one could come in its place.</p>
<p>The six extensions parallel the six days of the week and the six thousand times 365, the years of the world. The river that flows from Eden never ceases, and souls return and are reincarnated.</p>
<p>From here on the Psalmist is speaking of the seventh extension, which is something like the backbone in the human body, providing a basis for each of the six extensions. It is the blessed Holy One&#x2019;s chamber of strength.<sup><xref rid="fn188">188</xref></sup> Of it <italic>Sefer Yesirah</italic> says: &#x201C;The extensions have a holy place prepared in His place. The holy palace is placed at the center and it maintains them all.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn189">189</xref></sup> It is parallel to the Sabbath and to the seventh millennium, which is entirely Sabbath rest, life eternal. All souls cleave and are joined to the Throne of Glory: &#x201C;there is no breaching and none goes out&#x201D; [Ps. 144:14].</p>
<p>This is the meaning of &#x201C;Heaven and earth were completed, and all their hosts&#x201D; [Gen. 2:1]. They were perfected and made into lovely and perfect vessels,<sup><xref rid="fn190">190</xref></sup> perfect in physical form, in structure, and in type.</p>
<p>&#x201C;On the seventh day God completed the work that He had made&#x201D; [Gen. 2:2]. He included within that central column all that he had wrought in the six extensions, indicating that the seventh day is the end of the flow which is the world&#x2019;s existence, and thus that the world will be destroyed. &#x201C;And He rested on the seventh day from all the work that He had made&#x201D; [Gen. 2:2]: Sabbath, the Holy Spirit amid the six extensions.</p>
<p>&#x201C;God blessed the seventh day&#x201D; [Gen. 2:3]: He blessed it above the other entities by an infusion of the Holy Spirit. This indicates also that in the seventh millennium all souls will be in the Bond of Life, delighting in it.</p>
<p>&#x201C;And He called it holy, for on it He rested&#x201D; [Gen. 2:3]: The power of soul was added to it, distinguishing it from all the other entities.</p>
<p>&#x201C;That God had made&#x201D; [Gen. 2:3]: Actions, including the calling forth of future generations. It further indicates that the entire seventh millennium, which parallels the seventh extension, is holy, without Satan and without the evil urge, as it says: &#x201C;He called it holy.&#x201D;</p>
<p>Thus there are three allusions to the seventh millennium: the destruction of the world, the delight of souls, and the negation of the evil urge. Parallel to the world&#x2019;s destruction, David says in our Psalm: &#x201C;He looks to earth and it trembles; He touches the mountains and they smoke&#x201D; [Ps. 104:32]. Of the delight of souls he says: &#x201C;I will sing to the Lord as I live&#x0021;&#x201D; [Ps. 104:33]. &#x201C;In [that millennium] there will only be the righteous seated and crowned&#x2026;.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn191">191</xref></sup> There will be haloes about them of the clear light that hovers over the soul&#x2019;s light. Of that great delight, the taste of which is unequaled, he says &#x201C;as I live,&#x201D; referring to life eternal, about which he further says: &#x201C;I shall rejoice in the Lord&#x201D; [Ps. 104:34]. This joy is the added Holy Spirit, basking in the light of <italic>shekhinah</italic> as it cleaves to the soul. Of the negation of the evil urge and the passing away of the spirit of defilement, he says: &#x201C;Sins will vanish from the earth&#x201D; [Ps. 104:35]. Of this the sages said: &#x201C;David composed one hundred and three Psalms, but he did not say &#x2018;Hallelujah&#x2019; until he saw the fall of the wicked,<sup><xref rid="fn192">192</xref></sup> meaning the negation of the evil urge. When David foresaw in the holy spirit the soul&#x2019;s delight and its rest, he cried out &#x2018;Praise the Lord. O my soul, Hallelujah&#x0021;&#x2019;&#x201D;</p>
<p>[Here resumes the commentary on the Song of Songs:]</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[6:8] Sixty are the queens and eighty concubines, maidens without number</bold></p>
<p><bold>Sixty are the queens:</bold> It is known that the emanation of both worlds took place at once. They are parallel to one another, facing one another. The World to Come has seven spatial extensions, of which Solomon in his wisdom said: &#x201C;Wisdom has built her house, hewn out her seven pillars&#x201D; [Prov. 9:1]. Of those the seventh is holy, the six being the six extensions, as we have explained. From these derive seventy names, standing within the twelve cosmic &#x201C;arms.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn193">193</xref></sup></p>
<p>So too is this world sevenfold, divided into seventy nations which stand within those twelve directions. Below too, the central column is drawn forth as the holy one. It is Zion, as Scripture says: &#x201C;From Zion, perfect in beauty, God appears&#x201D; [Ps. 50:2]. This is what the sages meant when they said: &#x201C;Whoever lives outside the land is like one who has no God.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn194">194</xref></sup> Each people derives its power from the extension to which it is parallel, from which it has been drawn forth. Thus it must be that there are seventy nations. Deduct from these ten those that belong to the spiritual central line, the Land of Israel, of which it will not be said in the future: &#x201C;they did not utterly destroy them&#x201D; [Josh. 13:13]. All of them as one will be wiped away and will cease to exist, both from the world and from the Throne of Glory. They are the Kenite, the Kenizite, the Kadmonite, the Canaanite, the Hittite, the Amorite, the Hivite, the Girgashite, the Jebusite, and the Perizite. There thus remain sixty, of whom it says: &#x201C;Sixty are the queens.&#x201D;</p>
<p><bold>And eighty concubines:</bold> These are the chieftains of Esau, the princes of Ishmael, and the children of Keturah. They make up eighty.</p>
<p><bold>And maidens beyond number:</bold> These are the countries and cities.</p>
<p>This is why the sages of Israel composed six orders [of Mishnah], parallel to the six extentions, comprising sixty tractates, parallel to the sixty queens. In the order called &#x201C;Women&#x201D; there are seven tractates, comprising seventy-one chapters. The Sanhedrin number seventy-one, since they are in charge of justice.<sup><xref rid="fn195">195</xref></sup> The rabbis said in the tractate Kiddushin:<sup><xref rid="fn196">196</xref></sup> &#x201C;You do not check [for impurities in the family tree] beyond membership in the Sanhedrin. Why? Because it is taught that just as the court is pure with regard to its judgment, so is it pure of any other defect. Said Amemar: &#x2018;What is the basis in Scripture? &#x201C;You are entirely beautiful, my love; there is no defect in you&#x201D; [Cant. 4:7].&#x2019;&#x201D; This means to say that they are like the <italic>shekhinah</italic>, which comprises seventy-one, and they have to be as free of any defect as She is.</p>
<p>The sages also said, regarding the verse &#x201C;I have said, &#x2018;How shall I place you among the sons and give you a land of delight?&#x2019;&#x201D; [Jer. 3:19], that this is like the tale of a king who had concubines and many children born of them. He also had a single son from the queen, his wife, whom he loved very greatly. The king gave fields and vineyards to all the sons of the concubines. Then he gave his son but a single orchard, saying to him: &#x201C;By your life&#x0021; All my treasuries are filled only by this orchard&#x0021; Because I love you so much more than your brothers I have given it to you.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn197">197</xref></sup> Thus the blessed Holy One created the nations of the world, as it says: &#x201C;Sixty are the queens and eighty concubines, maidens without number.&#x201D; These are the nations.</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[6:9] One is my dove, my perfect one</bold></p>
<p>[This] refers to the community of Israel. God divided the world among the nations, giving them fields and vineyards, as Scripture says: &#x201C;When the Most High caused the nations to inherit&#x201D; [Deut. 32:8]. But to Israel He gave the Land of Israel, God&#x2019;s own treasury. From it come the sacrifices, the shewbread, the first fruits, and all good things. Why so much? Because he distinguished between the son of the queen and the sons of the concubines. &#x201C;I have said, &#x2018;How shall I place you among the sons?&#x2019;&#x201D; [Jer. 3:19].</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[6:10] Who is this who appears</bold> [<italic>ha-nishkafah</italic>]?</p>
<p>A reference to <italic>shekhinah,</italic> as Scripture says: &#x201C;The Lord looked forth [<italic>hishkif</italic>] from heaven at the children of man&#x201D; [Ps. 14:2];<sup><xref rid="fn198">198</xref></sup> &#x201C;Look forth [<italic>hashkifah</italic>] from Your holy dwelling&#x201D; [Deut. 26:15].</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[6:11] I went down into the garden of nuts:</bold></p>
<p><italic>Shekhinah</italic> says: &#x201C;My eyes and heart are toward Israel, to see among them an enlightened person who seeks God.&#x201D; This refers to the Second Temple period. Israel are compared to a nut because they are all responsible for one another.<sup><xref rid="fn199">199</xref></sup> Of this Scripture says: &#x201C;They stumble, each over his brother&#x201D; [Lev. 26:15]. Thus it was during the Second Temple: there were righteous and pious among them, but they were punished because of the audacious. Israel replied: &#x201C;I do not know what my soul has done to me;&#x201D; I myself caused &#x201C;my people&#x2019;s chariots to be given freely&#x201D; [Cant. 6:12]. Those who behaved toward me with abusive power, the kings of Greece.<sup><xref rid="fn200">200</xref></sup></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[7:1] Turn back, turn back,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>O maid of Shulem&#x0021;</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Turn back, turn back,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>That we might gaze upon you.</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>&#x201C;How will you gaze at the Shulamite?</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>In the Mahanaim dance.&#x201D;</bold></p>
<p><bold>Turn back, turn back, O maid of Shulem&#x0021; Turn back, turn back that we might gaze upon you:</bold> The <italic>shekhinah</italic> says: &#x201C;If Israel returns in penitence, then we will gaze upon you, we will see you in joy and honor.&#x201D; Israel replies: <bold>How will you gaze at the Shulamite? In the Mahanaim dance:</bold> As in a dance performed together by two camps [<italic>mahanot</italic>]: the Glory and the <italic>shekhinah</italic> of His power. This means that He will cause the Presence to dwell in your midst.</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[7:2] How lovely are your feet in sandals, O daughter of nobles&#x0021;</bold></p>
<p>The verse continues to array the praises of the <italic>shekhinah.</italic></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[7:6] A King is held captive in your tresses&#x2026;.</bold></p>
<p>This refers to the intimacy [<italic>kirvah</italic>] of Glory to Glory and her unification.</p>
<p>The [sefirotic] form is likened to a palm tree [Cant. 7:8], in image and in parable, a tree that unites the male and female within it, possessing one body and two branches. We have received this interpretation from the mouth of an enlightened kabbalist.</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[7:9] I say: Let me climb the palm,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Let me take hold of its branches;</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Let your breasts be like clusters of grapes,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Your breath like the fragrance of apples.</bold></p>
<p><bold>I say: Let me climb the palm:</bold> Israel said: &#x201C;Although sin has caused separation [between God and myself], I planned to ascend to greatness through the merit of the <italic>shekhinah</italic> who is compared to a palm tree.&#x201D;</p>
<p><bold>Let me take hold of its branches:</bold> With our hands we will grasp hold of its deeds and merits.</p>
<p><bold>Let your breasts be like clusters of grapes, your breath like the fragrance of apples:</bold> The locus of her nursing [<italic>yenikah</italic>] is like the grape cluster, for you receive illumination and outpouring of emanation from the source, Wisdom.</p>
<p><bold>Your breath like the fragrance of apples:</bold> The simile refers to her receiving [the energy of emanation] from the two cherubim.</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[7:10] And your mouth is like the choicest wine.</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Let it flow to my beloved as new wine</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Gliding over the lips of sleepers.</bold></p>
<p><bold>And your mouth is like the choicest wine:</bold> Your words are nothing less than an advocate, championing the cause of Israel before the Glory, giving expression to the lips of the sleepers&#x2014;these are Israel in their exile.</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[7:12] Come my beloved,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Let us go into the field&#x2026;.</bold></p>
<p><bold>Come my beloved:</bold> The <italic>shekhinah</italic> said to the Glory, after the decree of Israel&#x2019;s exile was enacted: &#x201C;Why do you stand afar, and ascend to the uttermost heights?&#x201D;</p>
<p><bold>Let us go to the field:</bold> Do not remove your presence from me. Here in my exile are sages, expounders of Torah, houses of prayer and houses of study. This is the meaning of vineyards, blossoms, pomegranates and mandrakes.</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[8:1] If only you could be like my brother,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>As if you had nursed at my mother&#x2019;s breast:</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Then I could kiss you</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>When I met you in the street,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>And no one would despise me.</bold></p>
<p><bold>If only you could be like my brother:</bold> The Glory responded: &#x201C;If you desire and yearn for me to join myself to you, &#x2018;so will all of my desire be directed towards you&#x2019; [Ps. 38:10], that you might be a brother to me and that I might not be separated from you.&#x201D;</p>
<p><bold>As if you had nursed at my mother&#x2019;s breast:</bold> You would receive your nurturance from the place of my suckling, that is the spirit of the living God.<sup><xref rid="fn201">201</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>When I met you in the street:</bold> When I find you during the period of exile, all of my desire and will is that you be with them in their suffering.</p>
<p><bold>Then I could kiss you:</bold> You would adhere to me.</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[8:2] I would lead you, I would bring you</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>To the house of my mother,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Of her who taught me.</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>I would let you drink of the spiced wine&#x2026;.</bold></p>
<p><bold>I would lead you:</bold> I would raise you to my Holy of Holies [<italic>dvir ha-kodesh</italic>] and to my sanctuary. That is <bold>to the house of my mother, who taught me.</bold> The soul can not reveal its activities without the body and the body possesses no capacity for action without the soul. So too the Holy One, blessed be He, reveals His awesome deeds and signs by means of His attributes.</p>
<p><bold>I would let you drink &#x2026;</bold> : This is a parable referring to the provision of the transcendent light from which the parents and children<sup><xref rid="fn202">202</xref></sup> are blessed together.</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[8:3] His left hand was under my head</bold></p>
<p>The language is in third person, referring to the Glory, who doesn&#x2019;t descend but rather ascends.</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[8:4] I adjure you, O maidens of Jerusalem:</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Do not wake or rouse</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Love until it please&#x0021;</bold></p>
<p><bold>I adjure you &#x2026;</bold> : These are the words of the <italic>shekhinah</italic> during the time of exile, adjuring Israel not to force the coming of the End and not to arouse love until the time of favor arises. The verse does not stipulate either by the gazelles or hinds of the field [Cant. 2:7], for the <italic>shekhinah</italic> is not in her place.</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[8:5] Who is she that comes from the desert,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Leaning upon her beloved?</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Under the apple tree I roused you,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>It was there your mother conceived you,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>There she who bore you conceived you.</bold></p>
<p><bold>Who is she who comes up from the desert?</bold>: This is the tenth of the ten journeys which the <italic>shekhinah</italic> undertook. As our Sages said: &#x201C;The <italic>shekhinah</italic> undertook ten journeys when she departed the Temple: from the altar cover to the cherub, from the cherub to the threshold of the Temple, from the threshold to the court, from the court to the altar, from the altar to the Temple roof, from the roof to the wall, from the wall to the city, from the city to the mountain, from the mountain to the wilderness. From the wilderness she ascended and dwelt within her place as it is written: &#x2018;I will go and return to my place&#x2019; [Hosea 5:15].&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn203">203</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>Yearning for her beloved:</bold> Yearning for and bemoaning her beloved&#x2019;s separation from her.</p>
<p>As for the text&#x2019;s statement, <bold>under the apple tree I roused you</bold>, this parable refers to the Cherub of the Left Side, that is the locus of the beginning of form. The usage &#x201C;roused you&#x201D; alludes to the intimacy and the awakening of love during the time when Israel are present in their land, performing the will of the Omnipresent, as our Sages said: &#x201C;One verse states: &#x2018;Their faces were directed towards each other&#x2019; [Exod. 25:20]. The other verse stipulates: &#x2018;they were standing up facing the House&#x2019; [II Chron. 3:13]. There is no contradiction here. Their countenances face each other when Israel are performing God&#x2019;s will. Their faces are directed towards the House when Israel are not performing God&#x2019;s will.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn204">204</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>It is there your mother conceived you:</bold> The spirit of the living God.</p>
<p><bold>There she who bore you conceived you:</bold> The spiritual entities [i.e., the <italic>sefirot</italic>]. Given that we had been intimate and had aroused love, having been emanated from a single place, she said:</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[8:6] Place me like a seal upon your heart,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Like the seal upon your arm&#x2026;.</bold></p>
<p><bold>Place me like a seal:</bold> When we separate during the time of exile, place me like that well known seal.</p>
<p><bold>Like the seal upon your arm:</bold> Which corresponds to the heart, as our Sages said: &#x201C;Whence do we know that the Holy One, blessed be He wears phylacteries?&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn205">205</xref></sup></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[8:7] If a man offered all of his wealth for love,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>He would be laughed to scorn.</bold></p>
<p><bold>If a man offered all of his wealth for love:</bold> All of his heart, soul, and might.</p>
<p><bold>For love:</bold> To adhere to the <italic>shekhinah</italic>.</p>
<p><bold>He would be laughed to scorn:</bold> They will publicly offer him splendor and majesty,<sup><xref rid="fn206">206</xref></sup> his head lifted in honor, and he will ascend to the highest level to be favored and accounted among those who receive the countenance of the divine Presence.</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[8:8] We have a little sister,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Whose breasts are not yet formed,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>What shall we do for our sister</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>When she is spoken for?</bold></p>
<p><bold>We have a little sister:</bold> The parable refers to Israel in exile, despised and degraded.</p>
<p><bold>Whose breasts are not yet formed:</bold> They have no place to nurse since they have left the land of life and are separated from the place of Torah. As it is written: &#x201C;Torah shall go forth from Zion, God&#x2019;s word from Jerusalem&#x201D; [Isa. 2:3]. Concerning the exile it is said: &#x201C;For many days Israel will be bereft of the God of truth and Torah&#x201D; [II Chron. 15:2].</p>
<p><bold>What shall we do for our sister when she is spoken for?:</bold> What shall we do for them? How shall we sustain them? How to provide them with a future, with hope in their exile?</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[8:9] If she be a wall,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>We will build upon it a silver battlement,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>If she be a door,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>We will panel it in cedar.</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[8:10] I am a wall,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>My breasts are like towers.</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>So I became in his eyes,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>Like one who found favor.</bold></p>
<p><bold>If she be a wall, we build upon it a silver battlement:</bold> If she stands up to her enemies who entice her to deny her faith, <bold>we will build upon it a silver battlement:</bold> The parable indicates that no mortal will overcome them.</p>
<p><bold>If she be a door:</bold> Which is easily opened, they similarly might be easily seduced, then even if <bold>we will panel</bold> [<italic>natzor</italic>] <bold>it in cedar</bold>, in accord with: &#x201C;build a siege-work [<italic>matzor</italic>], the enemy will fight them and overcome them&#x201D; [Deut. 20:20].</p>
<p>The Community of Israel answers, <bold>I am a wall and my breasts are like towers:</bold> She takes pride that she will be like a fortified wall, holding firmly to her faith in the two Torahs, written and oral, which are an individual&#x2019;s vitality, just as the breasts provide vitality to the infant.</p>
<p>&#x201C;Then,&#x201D; she says, &#x201C;I will appear in God&#x2019;s eyes <bold>like one who finds favor</bold>.&#x201D;</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[8:11] Solomon had a vineyard</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>In Baal-hamon,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>He had to post guards in the vineyard:</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>A man would give for its fruit</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>A thousand pieces of silver.</bold></p>
<p><bold>Solomon had a vineyard:</bold> To Him who is the possessor of peace, Israel is designated as His vineyard, as it says: &#x201C;For the vineyard of the Lord of Hosts is the House of Israel&#x201D; [Isa. 5:7] and &#x201C;I the Lord keep watch over it&#x201D; [Isa. 27:3].</p>
<p><bold>In Baal-hamon:</bold> The parable refers to the people, great, splendorous, and numerous. But as a result of her sin, God gave her to the nations of the world.</p>
<p><bold>A man would give for its fruit:</bold> They put both the bodies and material resources of Israel to hard labor.</p>
<p><bold>A thousand pieces of silver:</bold> An allusion to the days of exile, the text not paying precise attention to those few years of our exile which extend beyond one thousand.<sup><xref rid="fn207">207</xref></sup></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[8:12] I have my very own vineyard:</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>You may have the thousand, O Solomon,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>And the guards of the fruit two hundred&#x0021;</bold></p>
<p><bold>I have my very own vineyard:</bold> I will bring them forth from exile and they will be under My supervision as in the beginning.</p>
<p><bold>You may have the thousand, O Solomon&#x0021;:</bold> Solomon here possesses a secular meaning, referring to the House of David. What is intimated here is that the days of the Messiah will last a thousand years, this being the sixth millennium of the world&#x2019;s existence, which will extend for six thousand years.</p>
<p>Two hundred years out of this millennium belong to <bold>those who guard its fruit:</bold> to those meriting the reward of the study of Torah and the observance of its commandments who had died previously and had yearned for the coming of the Messianic consummation and the resurrection of the dead. That is to say that the resurrection of the dead will occur two hundred years after the redemption. Thus in the sixth millennium, two hundred years before the resurrection of the dead, redemption and salvation will be revealed.</p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[8:13] O you who linger in the gardens,</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>A lover is listening&#x2026;.</bold></p>
<p>Thus it states <bold>who lingers in the gardens:</bold> This is the <italic>shekhinah</italic> who is of the Central Column.</p>
<p><bold>A lover is listening&#x2026;</bold>: This is Israel who listen for your voice to gather their exiles, when you shall go forth before them as in the past. It is known that the ten tribes were exiled forty years before Judah and Benjamin. These underwent exile in three waves, as it is written: &#x201C;for the first time brought abasement to the land of Naphtali and Zebulun while the later time was severe&#x201D; [Isa. 8:23]. This is clarified in <italic>Seder &#x2018;Olam</italic>, based on the verses. Judah and Benjamin also underwent exile in three waves, as it is written: &#x201C;You walked in your sister&#x2019;s path; therefore I will place her cup in your hands&#x201D; [Ezek. 23:31]. And so it is clearly explicated in the verse.</p>
<p>Those who first went forth into exile will be the first to return. Some time later, the children of Judah will return. So Isaiah prophesied when he said: &#x201C;In that day my Lord will apply His hand a second time to redeem the other part of His people from Assyria&#x2014;as also from Egypt, Pathos, Nubia, Elam, Shinar, Hamath, and the coastlands&#x201D; [Isa. 11:11]. The verse specifies &#x201C;a second time,&#x201D; for the redemption of the ten tribes will come first. And thus &#x201C;the other part of His people&#x201D; who will have remained in Assyria. In the following verse Isaiah lists the two exiles and makes mention of the two acts of redemption, referring to each and every one with its proper name. He says: &#x201C;He will hold up a signal to the nations and assemble the banished of Israel; and gather the dispersed of Judah from the four corners of the earth&#x201D; [Isa. 11:12]. He refers to the ten tribes as the &#x201C;banished of Israel&#x201D; as they dwell together but are banished from their land. The exile of Judah is designated as a dispersion, &#x201C;and he will gather the dispersed of Judah.&#x201D; The house of Israel will anoint a Messiah called Messiah ben Joseph; he will conquer lands and kingdoms and go to Jerusalem and rebuild it, as it is written: &#x201C;The Lord builds Jerusalem, He gathers in the dispersed of Israel&#x201D; [Ps. 147:2]. But he will die in battle. Of him it states: &#x201C;In that day, the wailing in Jerusalem shall be great&#x201D; [Zach. 12:11] and &#x201C;they shall lament to Me about those who are slain&#x201D; [Zach. 12:10]. Afterwards, the dispersed and scattered among the nations shall come and appoint a single leader, the Messiah, son of David, who was with them in exile. They will come to the Land of Israel with the permission of the kings of the nations and with their assistance. As it is written: &#x201C;And out of all of the nations, said the Lord, they shall bring all your brothers on horses, in chariots and drays, on mules and dromedaries to Jerusalem, My holy mountain, as an offering to the Lord&#x201D; [Isa. 66:20]. This kingdom will continue and never end. This is the meaning of &#x201C;Thus declares the Lord God, Who gathers the banished of Israel&#x201D; [Isa. 56:8]: these are the ten tribes. &#x201C;I will gather still more to those already gathered&#x201D; [ibid.]: I add yet another gathering to the first, the dispersed of Judah. This is the meaning of &#x201C;The Lord your God will restore your exile and have mercy upon you. He will return and gather you from among all the nations among whom He scattered you&#x201D; [Deut. 30:3]. It is possible that there may be a substantial period of time between these two ingatherings. Afterwards they might yet have to be as herdsmen in the wilderness of the nations, in order to separate out and purify the wicked among Israel, and to smelt them just as silver is smelt in the refining furnace, as happened during the Exodus from Egypt&#x2026;.<sup><xref rid="fn208">208</xref></sup></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[8:14] Flee, my beloved</bold></p>
<p align="blockquote"><bold>[And be like a deer on the mountain of spices]</bold></p>
<p>By means of the holy spirit he looked forward and prophesied concerning the seventh millennium, the day that is entirely Sabbath and rest, for life eternal. Souls will be bound up in the bond of life and they will be a throne for the Lord. Then the river which is the life and existence of the world, flowing forth from the Eden of Wisdom, will cease its flow. This is the meaning of <bold>Flee, my beloved:</bold> pointing to the rising of the Glory, its ascent into the upper light.</p>
<p><bold>And be like a deer on the mountain of spices:</bold> That is a place containing all beings, filled up with all bodies, wondrous in counsel, entering all those heights. May I deserve to be counted among those who make less of themselves; &#x201C;after two days may He quicken us&#x201D; [Hos. 6:2] to see the glory of Jerusalem, when the moon&#x2019;s light is bright as the sun, and the sun has sevenfold its light. Thus Scripture has foretold: &#x201C;The light of the moon shall be as the light of the sun, and the light of the sun shall be sevenfold, like the light of the seven days, on the day when the Lord binds up the bruise of His people, and heals the stroke of their wound&#x201D; [Isa. 30:26].</p>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<ftnote id="fn1"><sup>1</sup> Distinguished from &#x201C;practical&#x201D; Kabbalah, essentially the magical side of esoteric Judaism, and also (primarily thanks to the writings of Moshe Idel) &#x201C;ecstatic&#x201D; Kabbalah, a contemplative praxis transmitted primarily in the school of Abraham Abulafia.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn2"><sup>2</sup> <italic>Through a Speculum that Shines: Vision and Imagination in Medieval Jewish Mysticism</italic> (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1994), pp. 383ff.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn3"><sup>3</sup> <italic>Gates of Light: Sha&#x2018;are Orah</italic>, trans. Avi Weinstein (San Francisco: Harper Collins, 1994).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn4"><sup>4</sup> The commentary of R. Moshe is lost. That of R. Isaac was published from a single surviving manuscript by A. Green in &#x201C;Rabbi Isaac Ibn Sahola&#x2019;s commentary to the Song of Songs,&#x201D; <italic>Jerusalem Studies in Jewish Thought</italic> 6 (1987), 393&#x2013;491.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn5"><sup>5</sup> See the discussion by Gershom Scholem in <italic>Origins of the Kabbalah</italic> (Philadelphia: Jewish Publication Society, 1987), pp. 370&#x2013;71. See also the frequent references to R. Ezra in Moshe Idel&#x2019;s <italic>Kabbalah: New Perspectives</italic> (New Haven: Yale University Press, 1988), index s.v. Ezra of Gerona and Elliot Wolfson&#x2019;s work cited above, index s.v. Ezra ben Solomon. &#x201C;The Secret of the Tree of Knowledge&#x201D; is translated in G. Scholem&#x2019;s <italic>On the Mystical Shape of the Godhead</italic> (New York: Shocken Books, 1991), p. 65ff.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn6"><sup>6</sup> <italic>Le Commentaire d&#x2019;Ezra de Gerone sur le Cantique des Cantiques</italic> (Aubier-Montaigne: Paris, 1969).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn7"><sup>7</sup> Adam and Eve.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn8"><sup>8</sup> Following Ezek. 12:13&#x2013;14, referring to the angels.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn9"><sup>9</sup> b. <italic>&#x1E24;agigah</italic> 13a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn10"><sup>10</sup> Probably his fiftieth year.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn11"><sup>11</sup> Referring to the two major excurses within the text.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn12"><sup>12</sup> I.e., a name of God.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn13"><sup>13</sup> b. <italic>Shavu&#x2018;ot</italic> 35b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn14"><sup>14</sup> The final chapter of the Talmudic tractate Sanhedrin.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn15"><sup>15</sup> b. <italic>Sanhedrin</italic> 101a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn16"><sup>16</sup> m. Yadayim 3:5.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn17"><sup>17</sup> Following the view of R. &#x1E24;iyya the Great in Cant. Rabbah. 1:10.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn18"><sup>18</sup> Designating God as Solomon <italic>(Shelomo&#x003D;Shalom)</italic> refers especially to <italic>tiferet</italic>, the sixth of the ten <italic>sefirot</italic>, the central &#x201C;male&#x201D; element of the Godhead, the aspect of divinity understood by the kabbalists as the bridegroom of the Song of Songs.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn19"><sup>19</sup> &#x201C;Righteousness&#x201D; for the kabbalist can be a designation of <italic>shekhinah</italic>, who is also God&#x2019;s throne. See Prov. 25:5, etc. The passage here is obscure.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn20"><sup>20</sup><italic>&#x1E24;okhmah</italic>, the second of the ten <italic>sefirot</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn21"><sup>21</sup> Obscure. He may be referring to a tripartite division of <italic>keter</italic>, the first <italic>sefirah</italic>, related to a notion of three primal flashes of light (<italic>tza&#x1E25;tze&#x1E25;ot</italic>) that precede the <italic>sefirot</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn22"><sup>22</sup> Rea&#x1E25; or scent is a metaphoric figure for the vivifying outflow of emanational energy, wafting forth from &#x1E25;<italic>okhmah</italic> through the sefirotic world.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn23"><sup>23</sup> Ezek. 1:28.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn24"><sup>24</sup> b. <italic>Ta &#x2018;anit</italic> 29b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn25"><sup>25</sup> The <italic>sefirot</italic> from <italic>&#x1E25;esed</italic> to <italic>yesod</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn26"><sup>26</sup> From here through the end of the introduction R. Ezra is explicating Job 28, which he employs to introduce sefirotic discourse.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn27"><sup>27</sup> Silver is <italic>&#x1E25;esed</italic>; gold is <italic>din</italic>; copper is <italic>tiferet</italic>; and iron is <italic>malkhut</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn28"><sup>28</sup> <italic>Afisah</italic> or nullity designates the highest <italic>sefirah</italic>, usually described in negative terms. Here that most primordial seed of existence is not clearly separated from <italic>Eyn Sof</italic>, the primordial boundless &#x201C;darkness&#x201D; of the unknown and unknowable God.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn29"><sup>29</sup> In the sense of a divine &#x201C;ground of being.&#x201D; The passage refers to <italic>keter</italic>, the primal will of God.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn30"><sup>30</sup> The light flowing forth from <italic>keter</italic>, the channel of infinite divine energy.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn31"><sup>31</sup> Here he calls upon an ancient connection between the Hebrew and Aramaic words for &#x201C;light&#x201D; and &#x201C;water.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn32"><sup>32</sup> Primordial chaos is twofold: <italic>tohu va-vohu</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn33"><sup>33</sup> v. <italic>Hagigah</italic> 12a. The kabbalists associate this list with the ten <italic>sefirot</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn34"><sup>34</sup> Bereshit Rabbah 1:5. The first <italic>sefirah</italic> already includes and implies the last, associated with righteousness.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn35"><sup>35</sup> Usually understood by Kabbalists as referring to <italic>malkhut</italic>, the tenth <italic>sefirah</italic>, the feminine-receptive aspect of the Godhead.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn36"><sup>36</sup> Canticles Rabbah 6:12. The Song is thus sung by <italic>tiferet</italic> and <italic>malkhut</italic>, bridegroom and bride within the Godhead.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn37"><sup>37</sup> The Glory is <italic>tiferet</italic>, the masculine pole of creative energy in the realm of divine emanation.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn38"><sup>38</sup> Source of life (<italic>mekor ha-&#x1E25;ayyim</italic>) and holy spirit (<italic>rua&#x1E25; ha-kodesh</italic>) generally symbolize <italic>&#x1E25;okhmah</italic> in Geronan sources.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn39"><sup>39</sup> Literally <italic>sibah</italic> or cause.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn40"><sup>40</sup> The word <italic>tovim</italic> is plural: your love is an improvement upon the wine of <italic>&#x1E25;okhmah</italic>, as it flows in multiple directions.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn41"><sup>41</sup> &#x201C;Goodness&#x201D; is the ongoing flow of light from lamp to lamp, the ceaseless flow of divine life, through the <italic>sefirot</italic> and into the world.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn42"><sup>42</sup> Each of the branches is &#x201C;kissed&#x201D; or nourished directly from His mouth, from <italic>tiferet</italic> or the central column.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn43"><sup>43</sup> The term here is &#x2018;atarah, referring to <italic>malkhut</italic>, the last of the ten <italic>sefirot</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn44"><sup>44</sup> It would seem that a distinction is made here between &#x2018;atarah, the tenth sefirah, and <italic>shekhinah</italic>, which is the indwelling presence of God in the world, as in the older rabbinic sources. The passage is however difficult.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn45"><sup>45</sup> The memorial offering of flour and frankincense providing a <italic>rea&#x1E25; ni&#x1E25; oa&#x1E25;</italic>, a &#x201C;pleasing odor to the Lord.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn46"><sup>46</sup> <italic>Mekom yenikatam</italic>: literally &#x201C;the place from which they nurse.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn47"><sup>47</sup> In Tractate Megillah 29a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn48"><sup>48</sup> &#x201C;Solomon&#x201D; here refers to God, specifically to <italic>tiferet</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn49"><sup>49</sup> The rest of the sefirotic world is pure and lovely; only <italic>shekhinah</italic> is &#x201C;darkened&#x201D; because of her involvement with the lower world.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn50"><sup>50</sup> Cf. <italic>Mekhilta Shirta</italic> 2.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn51"><sup>51</sup> Compare <italic>Vayikra Rabbah</italic> 20:10.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn52"><sup>52</sup> The phrase would alternatively be rendered: &#x201C;imagines.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn53"><sup>53</sup> Points or studs (<italic>nekudot</italic>). The term is used as well to designate the vowel signs that are placed above and below the consonants of the Hebrew alphabet and look very much like points (<italic>nekudot</italic>). R. Ezra will construct an elaborate exegetic pun upon the multiple meanings of the term in which the studs (<italic>nekudot</italic>) of silver&#x2014;the teachings of written Torah&#x2014;will serve as the animating force of the wreaths of gold&#x2014;oral Torah&#x2014;just as the vowels (<italic>nekudot</italic>) transform inert consonants into pliable words and living discourse.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn54"><sup>54</sup> &#x201C;Wine,&#x201D; &#x201C;red,&#x201D; and &#x201C;gold&#x201D; are symbols of the left side, while &#x201C;white,&#x201D; &#x201C;milk,&#x201D; and &#x201C;silver&#x201D; symbolize the right. Isa. 55:1, referring to human access, mentions wine before milk. The Haggai verse, referring to God, reverses the symbolic order: God prefers silver (<italic>&#x1E25;esed</italic>) to gold (<italic>din</italic>).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn55"><sup>55</sup> See Ecclesiastes Rabbah 8:11, where R. Haninah interprets Zach. 12:1 &#x201C;God created [<italic>yatzar</italic>] humanity&#x2019;s spirit within it&#x201D; as meaning that the spirit has been tied or bound up within the body in order to animate. See Chavel (cited on page 10 of the editor&#x2019;s note above), note 39 <italic>ad locum</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn56"><sup>56</sup> Concerning this verse, the Midrash states: &#x201C;As for the Holy One, blessed be He, His name and might, when He declaims in enunciated speech, the sound is divided into seven voices.&#x201D; Divine speech creates the cosmogenerative septet ranging from <italic>&#x1E25;esed</italic> to the <italic>shekhinah</italic>. However, it only becomes audible, giving rise to the differentiated cosmos and producing prophetic discourse through the aegis of the <italic>shekhinah</italic>, the final rung in the chain of divine being.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn57"><sup>57</sup> b. <italic>Berakhot</italic> 6b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn58"><sup>58</sup> The term for &#x201C;thunder&#x201D; and &#x201C;sound&#x201D; throughout this passage is <italic>kol</italic>, the same as &#x201C;voice&#x201D; in the Jeremiah passage. The thunderbolts are the &#x201C;voice&#x201D; of God as Torah is given. From the reading of the Jeremiah passage it appears that the five &#x201C;voices&#x201D; are the five lower <italic>sefirot</italic> from <italic>tiferet</italic> to <italic>malkhut</italic>, or from bridegroom to bride.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn59"><sup>59</sup> This might mean there were six or seven, thus breaking the parallel of five (wedding shouts) to five (Torah-sounds). Sinai is frequently depicted in the Midrash as the marriage of God and Israel.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn60"><sup>60</sup> <italic>Shemot Rabbah</italic> 28, end.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn61"><sup>61</sup> North, east, south, west, up, down, and inward. These will be associated below with the seven lower <italic>sefirot</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn62"><sup>62</sup> Midrash Shir ha-Shirim Zuta 3:10.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn63"><sup>63</sup> Targum Onkelos <italic>ad locum</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn64"><sup>64</sup> Probably <italic>malkhut</italic> and <italic>yesod</italic>. See <italic>R. Azriel: Perush ha-Aggadot</italic>, ed. Tishby (Jerusalem: Mekize Nirdamim, 1945), index of symbols.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn65"><sup>65</sup> The &#x201C;hand&#x201D; is higher than the &#x201C;throne.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn66"><sup>66</sup> Midrash Be-Midbar Rabbah 12:10.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn67"><sup>67</sup> The poles and rafters of the tabernacle are depicted as the lines that flow between the various <italic>sefirot</italic>, the divine construct holding them all together.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn68"><sup>68</sup> Midrash Shir ha-Shirim Zuta 2:1.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn69"><sup>69</sup> Lit. <italic>beit ha-yayin:</italic> house of wine, a symbol of <italic>&#x1E25;okhmah</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn70"><sup>70</sup> The association of <italic>din</italic>, or the left side, with the demonic is strongly enunciated here.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn71"><sup>71</sup> Perhaps implying that darkness should come from the west (opposite to the east) rather than from the north.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn72"><sup>72</sup> Midrash Pesikta de-Rav Kahana 1.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn73"><sup>73</sup> See Numbers 10:11: &#x201C;In the second year, on the twentieth day of the second month, the cloud lifted from the Tabernacle of the Covenant and the Israelites set out on their journeys from the wilderness of Sinai.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn74"><sup>74</sup> Exodus Rabbah 2:2.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn75"><sup>75</sup> b. <italic>Megillah</italic> 29a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn76"><sup>76</sup> The Masoretic text as written, without the note for proper reading preserved in the margin.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn77"><sup>77</sup> All these readings hint at <italic>shekhinah</italic>&#x2019;s participation in Israel&#x2019;s exile.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn78"><sup>78</sup> b. <italic>Pesahim</italic> 118b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn79"><sup>79</sup> b. <italic>Yebamot</italic> 63a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn80"><sup>80</sup> b. <italic>Sukkah</italic> 55b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn81"><sup>81</sup> The energy flows through the central column of the <italic>sefirot</italic> and thence to the right and left branches.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn82"><sup>82</sup> The source of this quotation is unknown. Compare Nahmanides&#x2019; commentary to Numbers 14:9.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn83"><sup>83</sup> Righteousness [<italic>tzedek</italic>] symbolizes the <italic>shekhinah</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn84"><sup>84</sup> &#x201C;Darkness&#x201D; and &#x201C;fire&#x201D; here refer to <italic>din</italic>, the force of divine judgment.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn85"><sup>85</sup> Red&#x003D;<italic>din;</italic> white&#x003D;<italic>&#x1E25;esed</italic> or divine love.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn86"><sup>86</sup> The six <italic>sefirot</italic> from <italic>&#x1E25;esed</italic> to <italic>yesod</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn87"><sup>87</sup> Midrash Yalkut Shim &#x2018;oni <italic>ad locum</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn88"><sup>88</sup> Pirkei deRabbi Eliezer, 3. <italic>Havei aretz</italic>, &#x201C;fall to the ground,&#x201D; means literally &#x201C;become ground.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn89"><sup>89</sup> Gen. Rabbah 3:2.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn90"><sup>90</sup> Ms. reading is quite different here: the right hand is &#x201C;water from air,&#x201D; the left is &#x201C;fire.&#x201D; The central pillar is &#x201C;truth, justice, peace, seal of the structure, the seal of God.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn91"><sup>91</sup> In Numbers Rabbah 12:4?</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn92"><sup>92</sup> The obscure passage seems to mean that <italic>shekhinah</italic> is wife to the Central Column, source of godly seed; so too should Israel, husbands and wives, bear godly seed.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn93"><sup>93</sup> Midrash Mishle, ed. B. Wissocsky, p. 57.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn94"><sup>94</sup> Sanctification [<italic>kadosh</italic>], blessing [<italic>barukh</italic>], and <italic>shema&#x2018;</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn95"><sup>95</sup> This could refer either to the threefold repetition of &#x201C;Holy&#x201D; or to the three <italic>kedushot</italic> of the daily morning service.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn96"><sup>96</sup> Chapter 3, end.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn97"><sup>97</sup> <italic>Ha-havayot ha-&#x2018;amukot</italic>, i.e., the uppermost <italic>sefirot</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn98"><sup>98</sup> Following ms. <italic>mi-makom e&#x1E25;ad. Shekhinah</italic>&#x2019;s origin is one with that of the Glory, in the most hidden sefirotic realms.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn99"><sup>99</sup> Ravishing excites and stops the heart at once. &#x201C;Ashing&#x201D; the altar means <italic>removing</italic> the ashes.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn100"><sup>100</sup> The light of Wisdom is the flow of sefirotic energy, coming from supernal <italic>&#x1E25;okhmah</italic>, the source of all the <italic>sefirot</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn101"><sup>101</sup> Prayer shawl, a rectangular garment bearing fringes at its four corners.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn102"><sup>102</sup> <italic>Me-&#x2018;uteret u-mukhteret</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn103"><sup>103</sup> The two versions of the decalogue (Exod. 20 and Deut. 5) differ in the wording of the Sabbath command. Exodus says &#x201C;Remember the Sabbath Day&#x201D; and Deuteronomy says &#x201C;keep.&#x201D; These are taken to refer to positive and prohibitive aspects of Sabbath observance, and then generalized to refer to positive and negative commandments altogether. For kabbalists they also refer to the two <italic>sefirot yesod</italic> and <italic>malkhut</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn104"><sup>104</sup> Twenty-two plus the five final forms.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn105"><sup>105</sup> b. <italic>Nedarim</italic> 25b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn106"><sup>106</sup> In b. <italic>Ta&#x2018;anit</italic> 9a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn107"><sup>107</sup> The prophetic and hagiographic sections of the Bible.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn108"><sup>108</sup> And thus everything must be included within it. Alternatively the concluding phrase <italic>ve-lo&#x2019; yasaf</italic> can be understood as &#x201C;and He added nothing [further].&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn109"><sup>109</sup> b. <italic>Ketubot</italic> 86a. The two examples given refer to the commandments of the <italic>Sukkot</italic> festival, but could be any positive commandments of the Torah.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn110"><sup>110</sup> Shabbat 119b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn111"><sup>111</sup> b. <italic>Berakhot</italic> 54a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn112"><sup>112</sup> The following, down to the resumption of the commentary with 4:12, is found on p. 548 of Chavel&#x2019;s Hebrew edition.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn113"><sup>113</sup> b. <italic>Rosh Hashanah</italic> 27a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn114"><sup>114</sup> Also said to number 248, according to a Talmudic source (<italic>Makkot</italic> 23b).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn115"><sup>115</sup> Or: from the mouth of <italic>gevurah</italic>, the God of power.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn116"><sup>116</sup> Perhaps should read: &#x201C;hewn out of&#x201D;; <italic>mi-shemo</italic> rather than <italic>bi-shemo</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn117"><sup>117</sup> &#x201C;Full&#x201D; and &#x201C;lacking,&#x201D; two ways of spelling Hebrew words.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn118"><sup>118</sup> These passages seem to indicate a later narrative voice, as was already noted by several medieval authors. See commentary of Abraham Ibn Ezra to Deut. 1:2.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn119"><sup>119</sup> b. <italic>Sanhedrin</italic> 99a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn120"><sup>120</sup> Deriving &#x201C;Lebanon&#x201D; from <italic>libbun</italic>, &#x201C;cleansing.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn121"><sup>121</sup> b. <italic>Yoma</italic> 38b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn122"><sup>122</sup> <italic>Zaddik</italic> or &#x201C;the righteous&#x201D; is <italic>yesod</italic>, the source of sefirotic energy as it flows into the <italic>shekhinah</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn123"><sup>123</sup> Genesis Rabbah 15:7.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn124"><sup>124</sup> No such interpretation is found in the extant rabbinic sources. It is also found, however, in Zohar 1:135b, a passage possibly dependent upon R. Ezra.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn125"><sup>125</sup> The three patriarchs represent <italic>&#x1E25;esed, gevurah</italic>, and <italic>tiferet</italic>, way-stations in the flow of life from Wisdom, the primal sefirotic font, to the <italic>shekhinah</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn126"><sup>126</sup> Return to your safe haven of halakhic expertise.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn127"><sup>127</sup> b. <italic>Sanhedrin</italic> 38b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn128"><sup>128</sup> Here the light imagery becomes that of wine. The primal flow is as perfect and undiminished as it was before creation, before the flow through the seven primal &#x201C;days.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn129"><sup>129</sup> &#x201C;North&#x201D; is kabbalistically <italic>din</italic>, divine judgment, and &#x201C;South&#x201D; is <italic>&#x1E25;esed</italic>, divine love.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn130"><sup>130</sup> <italic>&#x1E24;okhmah</italic> and <italic>binah</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn131"><sup>131</sup> The intermediate <italic>sefirot</italic>: Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob represent <italic>&#x1E25;esed, din</italic>, and <italic>tiferet</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn132"><sup>132</sup> Cant. Rabbah 4:31.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn133"><sup>133</sup> Literally &#x201C;an ascent for ascent.&#x201D; Or &#x201C;an ascent unto the Name.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn134"><sup>134</sup> The reference is to R. Isaac the Blind.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn135"><sup>135</sup> From Cant. 4:8 to 5:1.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn136"><sup>136</sup> Daniel 9:2.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn137"><sup>137</sup> v. Jer. 29:8. also look at Seder Olam ch. 30 ala Milikovsky.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn138"><sup>138</sup> We are dealing with <italic>ketiv/keri</italic>&#x2014;the written text is <italic>akhabed</italic> (I will be glorified) but it is pronounced <italic>akhabdah</italic> (I will glorify it). The difference between the text as written and pronounced is the letter <italic>heh</italic>, whose numerical equivalent is five.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn139"><sup>139</sup> b. <italic>Yoma</italic> 21b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn140"><sup>140</sup> See Daniel 8.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn141"><sup>141</sup> The verses refer to Cyrus.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn142"><sup>142</sup> b. <italic>Avodah Zarah</italic> 2b. &#x201C;Rome&#x201D; and &#x201C;Edom&#x201D; for the medieval Jews refer to Christendom, which they view as a continuation of the Roman empire.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn143"><sup>143</sup> See Megillah 12a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn144"><sup>144</sup> See p. 96 above.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn145"><sup>145</sup> On the eve of Passover, celebrating the first redemption but anticipating the last.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn146"><sup>146</sup> The popular medieval Hebrew adaptation of Josephus&#x2019;s <italic>History of the Jews</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn147"><sup>147</sup> Babylon equals Baghdad, the capital of Islam.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn148"><sup>148</sup> This would seem to be Christianity&#x2019;s appropriation of Jewish scripture. There has been considerable censorship of the manuscript in the following lines.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn149"><sup>149</sup> This variant reading is found only in the printed text. Alternatively: &#x201C;What is the meaning of the verse.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn150"><sup>150</sup> b. <italic>&#x1E24;agigah</italic> 16a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn151"><sup>151</sup> The following lines may be read as a progression through the <italic>sefirot</italic>, beginning here with <italic>keter</italic>, but the individual referents are kept somewhat murky.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn152"><sup>152</sup> He seems to mean that no one could be sufficiently satisfied in order to <italic>depart</italic> from such a vision. For that reason &#x201C;No man can see Me and live&#x201D; [Exod. 33:20].</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn153"><sup>153</sup> There follows a long quotation from <italic>Sefer ha-Bahi</italic>r, Scholem&#x2019;s sections 64, 67&#x2013;69.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn154"><sup>154</sup> b. <italic>Sanhedrin</italic> 65b. The reference is to the primary Talmudic source for the later <italic>Golem</italic> tradition.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn155"><sup>155</sup> A radically different and ironic reading. At the time of exile, the omnipresent divine &#x201C;descends&#x201D; as it were back into its recesses&#x2014;the source of creative manifestation&#x2014;divine Wisdom, from whence it must be reinvoked through prayer and the performance of the commandments.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn156"><sup>156</sup> <italic>Tiferet</italic>, the Beloved, &#x201C;descends&#x201D; from <italic>&#x1E25;okhmah</italic>, bringing sustenance for Himself and <italic>shekhinah</italic>, His garden.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn157"><sup>157</sup> Because of this cosmic exile, the <italic>sefirot</italic> turn &#x201C;upward&#x201D; and <italic>tzaddik</italic>, the righteous one [<italic>yesod</italic>] is not nourished by them.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn158"><sup>158</sup> <italic>&#x1E24;esed, gevurah, tiferet</italic>, symbolized by the Patriarchs.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn159"><sup>159</sup> <italic>Neta sha &#x2018;ashuim</italic>, after Isa. 5:7.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn160"><sup>160</sup> &#x201C;Lilies&#x201D; [<italic>shoshanim</italic>] is derived from &#x201C;six&#x201D; [<italic>shesh</italic>]. Each of the six intermediate or &#x201C;directional&#x201D; <italic>sefirot</italic>, multiplied by ten for the fact that the <italic>sefirot</italic> all contain one another, gives us the &#x201C;sixty queens.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn161"><sup>161</sup> I.e., water is separated from cloud and wind, the entire verse reading: &#x201C;He sets the rafters of His lofts in the waters, makes the clouds His chariot, moves on the wings of the wind.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn162"><sup>162</sup> The author is linking the ten <italic>sefirot</italic> of the upper world to these ten attributes which, according to the Talmud [<italic>&#x1E24;agigah</italic> 12a], underlay the creation of this world. They are heaven, earth, formlessness, void, darkness, light, water, wind, day, and night. This is one of several such lists of primordial entities to be found in rabbinic sources.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn163"><sup>163</sup> The depth above: <italic>omek rom</italic> &#x003D; <italic>keter; omek tahat</italic> &#x003D; <italic>malkhut</italic>. See the Commentary of R. Azriel to <italic>Sefer Yetzirah</italic> 1:5.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn164"><sup>164</sup> b. <italic>Sanhedrin</italic> 38b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn165"><sup>165</sup> See comments to Canticles 1:8.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn166"><sup>166</sup> This quotation is not found in the extant rabbinic sources.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn167"><sup>167</sup> b. <italic>Avodah Zarah</italic> 3b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn168"><sup>168</sup> &#x201C;Cloud [<italic>&#x2018;av</italic>] is numerically 72.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn169"><sup>169</sup> The gathering of the waters and the appearance of dry land occurs on the third day of creation.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn170"><sup>170</sup> <italic>Malkhut</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn171"><sup>171</sup> b. <italic>Sanhedrin</italic> 38b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn172"><sup>172</sup> Lit. <italic>mayim be-mayim</italic>, water within water.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn173"><sup>173</sup> This alludes to the doctrine of <italic>shemitot</italic>, or cosmic sabbaths, claiming that the world goes through a series of seven-thousand year cycles and then returns to its source.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn174"><sup>174</sup> The repetition in Ps. 29:3 is not direct. There may be an allusion here to the tale of R. Akiva&#x2019;s ascent to the <italic>pardes</italic>, as described in b. <italic>&#x1E24;agigah</italic> 14b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn175"><sup>175</sup> He derives &#x2018;<italic>erets</italic> from <italic>r-ts-h</italic>, meaning &#x201C;will.&#x201D; <italic>Keter</italic> is extended to meet <italic>malkhut</italic>. The circle of the <italic>sefirot</italic> is thus closed.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn176"><sup>176</sup> The <italic>sefirot</italic> as <italic>kelim</italic>, or the ordering of the sefirotic structure, &#x201C;precedes&#x201D; (better &#x201C;underlies&#x201D;) the actual flow of divine energy into these channels.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn177"><sup>177</sup> <italic>Tiferet</italic>, the male energy of the central column, reaches into the heights of <italic>keter</italic>, the Will that is above the upper reaches of Mind, and flows down through <italic>yesod</italic>, its sexual manifestation, into <italic>malkhut</italic>, the &#x201C;garden&#x201D; or female.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn178"><sup>178</sup> Hebrew term obscure.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn179"><sup>179</sup> Here &#x201C;trees&#x201D; and &#x201C;cedars&#x201D; are taken as symbols of the <italic>sefirot</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn180"><sup>180</sup> The seven lower <italic>sefirot</italic> are born of <italic>binah</italic>, the third <italic>sefirah</italic>, or possibly referring to <italic>tiferet</italic>, the third of the seven upper &#x201C;days.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn181"><sup>181</sup> <italic>Sefirot</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn182"><sup>182</sup> Hebrew obscure; translation conjectural.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn183"><sup>183</sup> Both <italic>tiferet</italic>, the sun or power of day, and <italic>shekhinah</italic>, the moon or power of night, rule by the power of <italic>hokhmah</italic>, source of the flow that animates them.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn184"><sup>184</sup> b. <italic>Hagigah</italic> 13b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn185"><sup>185</sup> The author plays on the inconsistency of number in these texts.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn186"><sup>186</sup> Bereshit Rabbah 9:5.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn187"><sup>187</sup> b. <italic>Berakhot</italic> 46b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn188"><sup>188</sup> The seventh extension or direction is mysterious, beyond the six directions of space. It seems here to be the direction called &#x201C;inward&#x201D; or &#x201C;innermost.&#x201D; the center from which all the others radiate.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn189"><sup>189</sup> Sefer Yetsirah 4:2.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn190"><sup>190</sup> A play on words, reading <italic>ve-yekhulu</italic>, &#x201C;were completed,&#x201D; as derived from <italic>keli</italic>, &#x201C;vessel.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn191"><sup>191</sup> b. <italic>Berakhot</italic> 17a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn192"><sup>192</sup> b. <italic>Berakhot</italic> 9b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn193"><sup>193</sup> Sefer Yesirah 5:1 uses this term (based on Deut. 33:27) for twelve directions, a refinement of the original six.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn194"><sup>194</sup> <italic>Ketubut</italic> 110b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn195"><sup>195</sup> The text may be assuming the special relationship, well known in later Kabbalah, between the female and <italic>din</italic> or &#x201C;justice.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn196"><sup>196</sup> Kiddushin 76a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn197"><sup>197</sup> Midrash Tan&#x1E25;uma, Kedoshim 12.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn198"><sup>198</sup> <italic>Shekhinah</italic> is the power of providence, coming forth from &#x201C;heaven&#x201D; or <italic>tiferet.</italic></ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn199"><sup>199</sup> Nuts grow in clusters that cannot easily be separated.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn200"><sup>200</sup> The text is somewhat obscure, but seems to mean that Israel, because of the way they related to one another, brought upon themselves the Seleucid oppressor.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn201"><sup>201</sup> Most likely <italic>&#x1E25;okhmah</italic> as <italic>ruah hayyim</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn202"><sup>202</sup> The <italic>sefirot</italic> and Israel below.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn203"><sup>203</sup> Rosh ha-Shanah 31a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn204"><sup>204</sup> Baba Batra 99a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn205"><sup>205</sup> In <italic>Berakhot</italic> 6a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn206"><sup>206</sup> The word <italic>buz</italic> is interpreted to mean &#x201C;loot&#x201D; or &#x201C;bounty&#x201D; rather than &#x201C;scorn.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn207"><sup>207</sup> The sixth millennium, thought by many to be the end of exile, began in 1240, shortly before the completion of this commentary.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn208"><sup>208</sup> An eschatological discussion of Zech. 9:9 etc. has been ellipted.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn209"><sup>209</sup> Midrash Tanhuma, <italic>shemot</italic> 10.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn210"><sup>210</sup> <italic>Aikhah</italic>, the opening word (and Hebrew name) of Lamentations, is read as a word (<italic>Ei</italic>) and an abbreviation (<italic>KoH</italic>&#x003D;25) to mean &#x201C;Where is twenty-five?&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn211"><sup>211</sup> To the <italic>shekhinah</italic>, referred to in the text literally with the appellation &#x201C;<italic>koh</italic>.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn212"><sup>212</sup> <italic>Et</italic> is an untranslated participle indicating the direct object.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn213"><sup>213</sup> The word &#x2018;<italic>af</italic>, in this case translated &#x201C;really,&#x201D; can also be a noun meaning &#x201C;anger,&#x201D; and thus the name of a destructive angel.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn214"><sup>214</sup> The note on <italic>ishah</italic> is a <italic>pazer</italic> and is an ascending crescendo recited three times.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn215"><sup>215</sup> Reading <italic>kol be-Ramah</italic> (&#x201C;a voice in Ramah&#x201D;) as <italic>kol be-ruma</italic> &#x2018;(&#x201C;a voice in the heights&#x201D;).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn216"><sup>216</sup> Referring to the mixed multitude, held responsible for the sins of Israel in the wilderness. See Prov. 30:23.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn217"><sup>217</sup> b. <italic>Berakhot</italic> 3a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn218"><sup>218</sup> See b. <italic>Sanhedrin</italic> 97a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn219"><sup>219</sup> See b. <italic>Sanhedrin</italic> 24a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn220"><sup>220</sup> <italic>Baraitot</italic> are quotations of early rabbinic teaching within the Talmud.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn221"><sup>221</sup> A fast day commemorating the Romans&#x2019; breaching the walls of Jerusalem.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn222"><sup>222</sup> The great summer fast day in memory of the destruction of the First and Second Temples.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn223"><sup>223</sup> b. <italic>Sanhedrin</italic> 81a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn224"><sup>224</sup> The ten martyrs of the Hadrianic persecution.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn225"><sup>225</sup> The reincarnation of the ten sons of Jacob as the ten martyrs.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn226"><sup>226</sup> See b. <italic>Avodah Zarah</italic> 16b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn227"><sup>227</sup> <italic>The Kabbalah in the Writings of R. Bahya ben Asher Ibn Halawa.</italic> Jerusalem: Kiryat Sepher, 1970.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn228"><sup>228</sup> Construct clauses occur when two or more words, usually nouns, are conjoined to form a compound idea. The opening phrase of the Hebrew text of Gen. 1:1 is a prepositional phrase <italic>bereshit</italic>, &#x201C;in the beginning of,&#x201D; followed immediately by the verb <italic>bara</italic>, &#x201C;created.&#x201D; The prepositional phrase lacks nominal closure. Rashi resolves the grammatical difficulty by reading <italic>bara</italic> as a gerund on the order of Hosea 1:2. Thus, the opening words of Genesis are to be read as &#x201C;in the beginning of God&#x2019;s creating heaven and earth.&#x201D; The Jewish Publication Society translation (henceforth: JPS) essentially adopts Rashi&#x2019;s interpretation and translates Gen. 1:1 as: &#x201C;When God began to create the heavens and the earth&#x2026;.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn229"><sup>229</sup> Tan&#x1E25;uma Buber, <italic>bereshit</italic> 1.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn230"><sup>230</sup> The classic Aramaic Targum or translation of the Pentateuch.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn231"><sup>231</sup> Onkylos is following the second half of the verse: &#x201C;nor put a curse upon a chieftain of your people,&#x201D; treating the text as a parallelism.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn232"><sup>232</sup> The letter <italic>yod</italic> [<span dir="rtl">&#x05D9;</span>] is numerically ten; the reference is to the multiplicity of the ten <italic>sefirot</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn233"><sup>233</sup> The yod indicates plural in this possessive form, referring both to the same plurality as in <italic>Elohim</italic>, but also to its meaning as &#x201C;ten&#x201D; <italic>sefirot</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn234"><sup>234</sup> b. <italic>Kiddushin</italic> 40b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn235"><sup>235</sup> Rather than representing contentless chaos and the forces of entropy, <italic>bohu</italic> or the void represents the potentially emergent aspects of primordial reality.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn236"><sup>236</sup> Though in the Platonic system, whence all discussion of the four elements derives, fire is light and represents the most elevated of the four, Bahya sees a negative aspect attributed to fire in the biblical sources. Therefore, <italic>Elohim</italic> is associated rather with &#x201C;wind&#x201D; or air.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn237"><sup>237</sup> See b. <italic>Baba Batra</italic> 15a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn238"><sup>238</sup> Although this is nominally the Midrashic section, Bahya already begins to build his argument for a Kabbalistic reading of the verse. Kabbalists so insinuated their readings into the earlier rabbinic tradition that it is sometimes difficult to know where Midrash ends and Kabbalah begins. This, of course, was precisely their intent.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn239"><sup>239</sup> Thus <italic>bereshit</italic> would consonantally divide into <span dir="rtl">&#x05E8;&#x05E9;&#xFB30;</span> and <span dir="rtl">&#x05EA;</span>&#x2019;, which numerically equals 410.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn240"><sup>240</sup> b. <italic>Pesahim</italic> 54a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn241"><sup>241</sup> Here he precedes forward to a Midrashic (mostly eschatological) reading of Gen. 1:3&#x2013;4.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn242"><sup>242</sup> Bereshit Rabbah 2:5.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn243"><sup>243</sup> A saying attributed to Aristotle, widely quoted by Jewish thinkers throughout the Middle Ages.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn244"><sup>244</sup> b. <italic>Sukkah</italic> 49a. Again a purely rabbinic reference, but one that has Kabbalistic echoes. The phrase <italic>bara shit</italic> is taken by the Zohar to mean &#x201C;He created six,&#x201D; referring to the six <italic>sefirot</italic> clustered around <italic>tiferet</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn245"><sup>245</sup> Avot 5:6.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn246"><sup>246</sup> Avot 5:1. In the Kabbalah the ten utterances of creation are often homologized into the ten <italic>sefirot</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn247"><sup>247</sup> It could be read as <italic>be-tishre</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn248"><sup>248</sup> And R. Joshua said it was created in Nissan. This debate reflects the dual calendar of Judaism. The Biblical calendar begins in the spring, Aviv or Nissan being the first month. The Babylonian calendar, adopted by Jews at a very early date, starts the year in the fall, with Tishre, the seventh month on the Bblical calendar.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn249"><sup>249</sup> On Rosh Hashanah, the first of Tishre. b. <italic>Rosh Hashanah</italic> 10b&#x2013;11a,27a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn250"><sup>250</sup> Ma &#x2018;aseh Merkavah, Chapter 7, in Wertheimer, <italic>Battey Midrashot</italic>, v. 1, p. 61. Schaefer, <italic>Synopsis zur Hekhalot-Literatur</italic>, v228, paragraph 68.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn251"><sup>251</sup> v. chap. 2.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn252"><sup>252</sup> The <italic>molad</italic>, or the moment when the moon is directly between earth and sun and thus totally invisible, is the technical beginning of the new month. For purposes of this fixing, the hour divided into 1080 parts.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn253"><sup>253</sup> The point is that the first of <italic>Tishre</italic> is supposed to be the date when Adam and Eve were created. But since that was the &#x201C;sixth day&#x201D; of creation, we have to count back five preceding days to get to the actual Beginning. But it is impossible to do that, to determine the moment of creation other than mathematically, since until the fourth day there were no luminaries which would allow for the demarcation of days.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn254"><sup>254</sup> These are the sixth and tenth <italic>sefirot</italic>: <italic>tiferet</italic> (&#x201C;splendor&#x201D;) and <italic>malkhut</italic> (&#x201C;kingdom&#x201D;), respectively.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn255"><sup>255</sup> The numerical value of the letter <italic>bet</italic> is two, alluding to the fact that <italic>&#x1E25;okhmah</italic> is the second rung in the chain of divine emanation.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn256"><sup>256</sup> The beginning of the top line of the letter <italic>bet</italic> points slightly upward.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn257"><sup>257</sup> Sefer Yetsirah 1:1.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn258"><sup>258</sup> Three nominal forms derivable from the root S-F-R [<span dir="rtl">&#x05E1;&#x05E4;&#x05D3;</span>].</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn259"><sup>259</sup> <italic>Sippur</italic> means &#x201C;tale&#x201D; or &#x201C;narration;&#x201D; these lower <italic>sefirot</italic> can be the subject of narration.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn260"><sup>260</sup> <italic>Vav</italic> [<span dir="rtl">&#x05D5;</span>] is the sixth letter, representing the number six. <italic>Tiferet</italic> also represents a cluster of six central <italic>sefirot,</italic> those between <italic>binah</italic> and <italic>malkhut. binah</italic> and <italic>malkhut</italic> are the upper and lower female <italic>sefirot.</italic> The six forces between them are a male cluster; the form of the letter vav may itself be understood as a symbol of masculinity.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn261"><sup>261</sup> The word &#x201C;there&#x201D; [<span dir="rtl">&#xFB2A;&#x05E1;</span>; <italic>sham</italic>] appears twice in the verse, along with &#x201C;gave&#x201D; [<span dir="rtl">&#xFB2B;&#x05E1;</span>; <italic>sam</italic>]. Each of these is numerically 340, representing <italic>sefer, sefor,</italic> and <italic>sippur.</italic> This passage, which is taken by the midrash as representing a pre-Sinaitic giving of law and teachings, here is seen as the moment when the sefirotic secrets of Kabbalah are handed over to Israel.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn262"><sup>262</sup> The term is <italic>teshuvah,</italic> meaning &#x201C;return to God&#x201D; or &#x201C;penitence.&#x201D; The kabbalists give it a cosmic meaning: the return of all things to their source. This third <italic>sefirah,</italic> here designated as <italic>teshuvah,</italic> but more often called <italic>binah,</italic> is that primal source to which all return.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn263"><sup>263</sup> <italic>Malkhut,</italic> the tenth <italic>sefirah.</italic></ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn264"><sup>264</sup> That is, she is the middle of five.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn265"><sup>265</sup> <italic>Gedullah</italic> and <italic>gevurah,</italic> the fourth and fifth <italic>sefirot,</italic> also known as <italic>&#x1E25;esed</italic> (&#x201C;grace&#x201D;) and <italic>din</italic> (&#x201C;judgment), the right and left &#x201C;hands&#x201D; of the divine.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn266"><sup>266</sup> <italic>Tiferet,</italic> the sixth <italic>sefirah.</italic></ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn267"><sup>267</sup> <italic>Netza&#x1E25;</italic> and <italic>hod,</italic> the seventh and eighth <italic>sefirot.</italic></ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn268"><sup>268</sup> <italic>&#x1E92;addik</italic> or <italic>yesod</italic> (&#x201C;foundation&#x201D;), the ninth <italic>sefirah.</italic></ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn269"><sup>269</sup> <italic>Malkhut</italic> (&#x201C;kingdom&#x201D;), the tenth and feminine receptive <italic>sefirah.</italic></ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn270"><sup>270</sup> b. <italic>Rosh Hashanah</italic> 31a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn271"><sup>271</sup> ABG (numerically &#x201C;six&#x201D;) <italic>yitats</italic> (&#x201C;he will destroy&#x201D;).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn272"><sup>272</sup> The reference is to <italic>binah,</italic> the third <italic>sefirah,</italic> which is the source of the six lower <italic>sefirot</italic>, &#x201C;the heavens.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn273"><sup>273</sup> b. <italic>Berakhot</italic> 34a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn274"><sup>274</sup> b. <italic>Pesahim</italic> 54a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn275"><sup>275</sup> Various letters in this verse refer to the count of 2, 5, 204.</ftnote>
</chapter>
</book>
