<book>
<chapter>
<h1><bold>Introduction</bold></h1>
<p>Rabbi Bahya ben Asher, a judge and preacher in Saragossa in the late thirteenth century, is a key transmitter of Kabbalistic exegesis. His <italic>Commentary on the Torah,</italic> composed in 1291 and first printed in Naples in 1492, is one of the most popular and accessible Kabbalistic commentaries, as attested by its frequent publication over the centuries and the quotations from it throughout later Jewish literature.</p>
<p>R. Bahya is the best-known Jewish follower of the four-fold interpretation of Scripture. Rather than using the widespread acronym of PaRDeS (<italic>Peshat</italic>, simple or literal interpretation; <italic>Remez</italic>, allegorical or philosophical interpretation; <italic>Derash</italic>, homiletical interpretation; <italic>Sod</italic>, mystical interpretation), he prefers rather more explicit terminology. He refers to the four paths as <italic>peshat</italic>, <italic>midrash</italic>, <italic>sekhel</italic> (lit. &#x201C;intellectual,&#x201D; mostly philosophical), and <italic>Kabbalah</italic>, meaning &#x201C;received&#x201D; or esoteric interpretations. This nomenclature is partly adapted from R. Moses ben Nahman (or Nahmanides, 1194&#x2013;1270), the leading rabbinic figure in northern Spain in the thirteenth century. An early publicizer of Kabbalistic secrets, Nahmanides was the first to include them within an otherwise exoteric and immensely popular Commentary to the Torah. R. Bahya, a student of Nahmanides&#x2019; follower R. Solomon ben Adret (1235&#x2013;c.1310), seems to derive much of his Kabbalistic tradition from the school of Nahmanides and from his Geronese contemporaries. His work is almost precisely contemporaneous with the writing of the Zohar, the most important literary creation of Castilian Kabbalah. The relationship between R. Bahya and the Zohar, along with other aspects of R. Bahya&#x2019;s work, has been studied in great detail by the late Ephraim Gottlieb.<sup><xref rid="fn227">227</xref></sup></p>
<p>In addition to his <italic>Commentary on the Torah</italic>, R. Bahya is author of a commentary on the Tractate Avot, an ethical work known as <italic>Kad ha-Kema&#x1E25;</italic> (&#x201C;The Jar of Flour,&#x201D; referring to I Kings 17:16), and a treatise on the meaning of eating and proper behavior at meals called <italic>Shul&#x1E25;an shel Arba&#x2018;</italic> (&#x201C;The Table of Four;&#x201D; cf. Ezek. 40:41). Annoted additions of all these works have been edited by C. Chavel, and are currently published by the Rabbi Kook Institute Press in Jerusalem.</p>
<p>The sample offered here, R. Bahya&#x2019;s comments on the opening verses of Genesis (from his <italic>Commentary on the Torah</italic>), gives a particularly rich illustration of the fourfold method as it was practiced by Jewish scholars. We see him drawing from several of the bodies of knowledge available to thinking men of his day: grammatical insights, highly developed among Jewish exegetes from the tenth century onward; rabbinic tradition; Aristotelian philosophy; mathematics; astrology; and the &#x201C;new,&#x201D; or at least newly revealed method of reading known as Kabbalah. All of these exist side by side with one another, serving as complementary bodies of knowledge. As we see in parts of this passage, however, it is Kabbalah that has now become &#x201C;queen&#x201D; of the sciences, and the others are occasionally used in subservience to this reading that so fascinates our author.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<h1><bold>[Text]</bold></h1>
<p>[1:1&#x2013;2] <bold>In the beginning, God created the heavens and the earth. The earth was chaotic and void, with darkness over the surface of the deep and a wind from God sweeping over the waters.</bold></p>
<p><bold>In the beginning</bold> [<italic>bereshit</italic>]: According to the plain meaning, <italic>bereshit</italic> is to be read as meaning &#x201C;at first.&#x201D; However, it does not state &#x201C;at first&#x201D; because the word &#x201C;in the beginning&#x201D; connotes many great, powerful and highly significant meanings which are not included in the phrase &#x201C;at first.&#x201D;</p>
<p>According to the opinion of R. Solomon b. Isaac [Rashi], &#x201C;in the beginning&#x201D; is the first member of a construct clause (literally meaning &#x201C;in the beginning of&#x201D;), as is the case in all of its appearances in Scripture.<sup><xref rid="fn228">228</xref></sup> Consequently, only light was created on the first day. The verse is to be interpreted: &#x201C;In the beginning of the creation of heaven and earth, the earth being chaotic and void, God said: &#x2018;Let there be light&#x0021;&#x2019; And there was light.&#x201D; Everything else followed the light. Rashi says that this is similar to Hosea [1:2]: &#x201C;The beginning of the Lord&#x2019;s speaking to Hosea. The Lord said to Hosea&#x2026;.&#x201D; His opinion is that if the verse&#x2019;s intent was that heaven and earth were created on the first day, it should have stipulated &#x201C;At first God created the heavens and the earth, etc.&#x201D;</p>
<p>However, the true meaning is that &#x201C;in the beginning&#x201D; is a distinct word. It is not the subject of a construct clause and it is to be read as if the verse was stating &#x201C;at first.&#x201D; The cantillation supports this. The meaning of the pericope is that heaven and earth and all of their generations were created on the first day from complete nothingness and absolute non-existence, as is denoted by verb &#x201C;created&#x201D; [<italic>bara</italic>], which refers to the creation of being from nought. This follows the opinion of R. Nehemiah that the entire world was created on the first day. Thus we find in the Midrash:</p>
<p align="blockquote">Rabbi Yehudah and Rabbi Nehemiah:</p>
<p align="blockquote">Rabbi Yehudah says: &#x201C;The entire world was created in six days. For it is written in the account of each and every day: &#x2018;And it was so.&#x2019;&#x201D;</p>
<p align="blockquote">R. Nehemiah says: &#x201C;The entire world was created on the first day. As it is written: &#x2018;God said: &#x201C;Let the earth bring forth every living creature &#x2026; &#x201D;&#x2019; [Gen. 1:24], a matter entrusted in her hands and prepared from the beginning.&#x201D;</p>
<p align="blockquote">A parable exemplifying the matter. It is like a man who sows six measures at once, this coming forth on the first day, this on the second, this on the third, and thus all of them.<sup><xref rid="fn229">229</xref></sup></p>
<p>R. Nehemiah&#x2019;s opinion on this parable is readily apparent. The matter from which everything was derived was created on the first day. Afterwards, during the six days, the creatures were created from the particularizations of the matter, each and every one on his day. This is what is written: &#x201C;For He spoke and it was; He commanded and it endured&#x201D; [Ps. 33:9]. David explained that everything came to be in one statement and act of existence. Afterwards, God commanded each thing on its specific day, established them and brought them forth into actuality.</p>
<p><bold>God</bold> [<italic>Elohim</italic>]: According to the plain meaning, a term for divinity whose meaning is the possession of all powers. For this reason, the verse does not use such singular terms for God as El or Eloah but rather the plural <italic>Elohim</italic>, as in Joshua [24:19]: &#x201C;He is a holy God [<italic>Elohim kedoshim</italic>], for He contains all forms of holiness. One finds similar linguistic usage when dealing with sovereignty in the lower worlds, as in &#x201C;I will place the Egyptians at the mercy of a harsh master[s]&#x201D; [Isa. 19:4], where &#x201C;masters&#x201D; is in plural form, on account of the greatness of the lord&#x2019;s qualities and the multiple forms of governance which He possesses. If such is the case with mortals, it is even more so the case with God, be He blessed, Whose forms of governance have no number and from Whom alone all rulers derive their rulership, while He is one and His powers are many. One finds this linguistic usage with many words, such as, &#x201C;a night of watching[s]&#x201D; [Exod. 12:42] and, &#x201C;a day of atonement[s]&#x201D; [Lev. 23:28].</p>
<p>One can further explain that God is designated <italic>Elohim</italic> during the creation of the world, for He created it in wisdom and understanding as it is written: &#x201C;The Lord founded the earth with wisdom, He established the heavens by understanding&#x201D; [Prov. 3:19].</p>
<p>In accord with midrashic interpretation, this name can designate a judge. Thus it is written: &#x201C;You shall not curse God&#x201D; [Exod. 22: 27]. Onkylos<sup><xref rid="fn230">230</xref></sup> translates this as judge.<sup><xref rid="fn231">231</xref></sup> The conjunction finds full enunciation in: &#x201C;For God is a judge, humbling this one and raising that one&#x201D; [Ps. 75:8]. God is designated here by this name, because He created the world through the attribute of judgment.</p>
<p>In accord with the mystical path, this name <italic>ELoHiM</italic> is comprised of two words: &#x201C;These are God&#x201D; [<italic>EL HeM</italic>]. Behold, &#x201C;these are&#x201D; is the interpretation of the <italic>yod</italic> [in <italic>Elohim</italic>].<sup><xref rid="fn232">232</xref></sup> [Similarly] &#x201C;Remember your Creator&#x201D; [Eccles. 12:1], [where &#x201C;Creator&#x201D; (<italic>bor &#x2018;ekha</italic>) is written out in full orthographic form with a <italic>yod</italic>].<sup><xref rid="fn233">233</xref></sup> And the enlightened will understand.</p>
<p><bold>The heavens and the earth</bold> [<italic>et ha-shamayim ve-et ha-aretz</italic>]: In all situations, the direct object marker <italic>et</italic> serves an inclusive function. According to the plain meaning, these two direct object markers preceding &#x201C;the heavens and the earth&#x201D; include the two modalities of matter which God created. From one of these He created the heavens and from the other the earth.</p>
<p>And this is the meaning of &#x201C;the earth was chaotic and void.&#x201D; Scripture elucidates that after this act of creation, the earth was chaotic and empty. The meaning of &#x201C;chaotic and void&#x201D; is matter and form. That is to say, God enclosed form into that matter, as it is written &#x201C;&#x2018;All of this was made by My hand, and thus it all came into being,&#x2019; declares the Lord&#x201D; [Isa. 66:2]. The verse states &#x201C;all of this&#x201D;&#x2014;that is to say all of these creatures&#x2014;were &#x201C;made by My hand,&#x201D; in their current form. The meaning of this is that matter was created first. Afterwards, there was no further <italic>creatio ex nihilo</italic> but rather formation and making, for God brought everything into being from the matter and enclothed it within forms. From out of this tiny and subtle point, having no substantiality, were created all of the creatures within heaven and earth.</p>
<p>In accord with midrashic interpretation, &#x201C;the heavens and the earth,&#x201D; the presence of the direct object marker before &#x201C;the heavens&#x201D; includes the sun, moon, stars, and constellations, while the direct object indicator preceding &#x201C;the earth&#x201D; includes the trees, grasses, and the Garden of Eden. These comprise the totality of embodied creatures.</p>
<p><bold>The earth was chaotic and void</bold> [<italic>tohu va-vohu</italic>]: Chaos [<italic>tohu</italic>] is primordial matter, lacking substantiality and nominal designation. Chaos is designated <italic>tohu</italic> as in rabbinic usage: &#x201C;one who reconsiders [<italic>be-tohe</italic>] his prior deeds.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn234">234</xref></sup> For if one comes to make any designations concerning chaos he is confounded and reconsiders, calling it by another name, for it has not enclothed itself in any form through which it might be conceived of by a name. In the Torah&#x2019;s terminology, this matter is called <italic>tohu</italic>; among the philosophers [it is called] <italic>hyle.</italic></p>
<p><italic>Bohu</italic> is the form enclothed in matter. It is a compound word: <italic>bo hu</italic>, &#x201C;it is within it&#x201D;&#x2014;that is to say, an entity possessing form.<sup><xref rid="fn235">235</xref></sup></p>
<p>It is for this reason that the verse states: &#x201C;He shall measure it with a line of chaos [<italic>kav tohu</italic>] and with the blocks of emptiness [<italic>avnei vohu</italic>]&#x201D; [Isa. 34:11]. The architect&#x2019;s line is analogized to chaos, the primordial matter lacking substantiality. For it is through the plumber&#x2019;s line that the architect marks out the design of the building which he hopes to construct. The term for line [<italic>kav</italic>] is derived from: &#x201C;I put my hope [<italic>kavoh kiviti</italic>] in the Lord&#x201D; [Ps. 40:2]. The building blocks are analogized to <italic>bohu</italic>, for the empty void is form, just as blocks constitute the form of the building.</p>
<p>Let us conjoin the common elements of these verses. The Omnipotent first concreated from naught the primordial matter of the heavens and the primordial matter of the earth. After this creation the earth was in a state of chaos. That is to say that it was unsubstantial matter [<italic>tohu</italic>] and an empty void, enclothed with form. It [Gen. 1:2] designates the four elements which existed within this form: fire, air, water, and earth. The word &#x201C;earth&#x201D; includes all four elements as it delimits the totality of the lower world. Although earth is the lowest in the ontological hierarchy of elements, it is mentioned first as it is the subject of the verse. Thus the verse commences with the earth, which is a point. So the philosophers call her, for she is situated below the spheres and emplaced within them like a point within a circle. They also designate her as &#x201C;point&#x201D; for she is permanently enfixed, possessing movement in her parts but not in her totality, as it is written: &#x201C;the earth stands forever&#x201D; [Eccles. 1:4]. It is thus the opposite of the ultimate, all-encompassing sphere, which is the summit of refinement and purity. In contrast, this lowly world is the height of substantiality and ugliness.</p>
<p>Having begun with the earth, the verse returns and enumerates the elements in the hierarchical order proper to them: fire, air, and water. The darkness on the face of the deep is elemental fire, which is darkened. It precedes the wind, for the sphere of fire encompasses the sphere of the air, while the wind precedes the water, for the sphere of the air encompasses that of water and water that of the earth.</p>
<p>We have also found this order in the books of Ecclesiastes and Job. Just as here [Gen. 1] it commences with the point which is the earth, as it states: &#x201C;The earth was chaotic and void&#x201D; [Gen. 1:2], so too does it state &#x201C;the earth stands forever&#x201D; [Eccles. 1:4], and then mentions &#x201C;the sun rises and the sun sets&#x201D; [Eccles. 1:5], this being the element of fire. Then it states &#x201C;ever turning blows the wind&#x201D; [Eccles. 1:6] and &#x201C;all the streams flow to the sea&#x201D; [Eccles. 1:7].</p>
<p>So too in Job, the enumeration begins with the terrestrial point&#x2014;&#x201C;[God] sees to the ends of the earth, observes all that is beneath the heavens&#x201D; [Job 28:24]&#x2014;the heavens being the element of fire. &#x201C;When he fixed the weight of the winds, set the measure of the waters&#x201D; [Job 28:25] is precisely the order here in Genesis as well as in Ecclesiastes. All three of them are works of philosophical speculation, founded upon natural science. By stating &#x201C;the earth was chaotic and void,&#x201D; the verse informs us that it enclothed itself in form and that darkness, the sphere of fire, encompassed the intermingled water and earth, designated together as &#x201C;the deep.&#x201D; Similarly, earth is intermingled with the waters of the sea, which are thus called the deep, as is written: &#x201C;the deep engulfed me&#x201D; [Jonah 2:6]. And the wind was blowing and entered the darkness, hovering over the waters. That the verse states &#x201C;a divine wind&#x201D; [<italic>rua&#x1E25; Elohim</italic>], correlating it to the name <italic>Elohim</italic>, when it would have been more fitting to state &#x201C;the wind hovered&#x201D; is to due to its great refinement. Even though fire is more elevated than air, Scripture did not desire to correlate it with the divine, due to its appearance under the designation of darkness.<sup><xref rid="fn236">236</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>In the beginning God created heaven and earth,</bold> according to the way of Midrash: The world was created by the merit of three offerings: the dough, the tithe, and the first fruits.</p>
<p>&#x201C;Beginning&#x201D; refers only to hallah, the dough-offering: &#x201C;The first [<italic>reshit</italic>] of your dough-kneading troughs you shall offer&#x201D; [Num. 15:2]. &#x201C;Beginning&#x201D; refers only to tithes: &#x201C;The first of your produce&#x201D; [Deut. 18:4]. &#x201C;Beginning&#x201D; refers only to the first fruits: &#x201C;The first fruits of your land&#x201D; [Exod. 23:19].</p>
<p>They also said: By the merit of Moses, of whom it says: &#x201C;He foresaw that the beginning [Torah] was for him&#x201D; [Deut. 33:19].<sup><xref rid="fn237">237</xref></sup></p>
<p>All of these commandments partake of a single path, pointing to the oneness of <italic>&#x1E25;okhmah</italic> [wisdom],<sup><xref rid="fn238">238</xref></sup> which is called &#x201C;beginning.&#x201D; The Jerusalem translation of the Torah thus renders &#x201C;In the beginning&#x201D; as &#x201C;In wisdom.&#x201D; The first fruits point to this oneness, as does the commandment of tithing, since the number ten explicates and thus reveals the potency of the One. The dough offering does so too, since it is the single commandment with regard to dough. As for what they said about the merit of Moses, we find a &#x201C;first&#x201D; in him as well, and it was from there that he merited to receive the Torah.</p>
<p>If you apply your mind, you will further note that &#x201C;In the beginning&#x201D; hints at the building of the first Temple, which stood for 410 years.<sup><xref rid="fn239">239</xref></sup> Four hundred ten is also the numerical value of &#x201C;with this,&#x201D; as in &#x201C;With this shall Aaron come into the holy place&#x201D; [Lev. 16:3]. You know the rabbis said<sup><xref rid="fn240">240</xref></sup> that the Temple was built before heaven and earth; that is why Scripture first says, &#x201C;In the beginning created&#x201D; and only then, &#x201C;heaven and earth.&#x201D; And because the Temple would one day be destroyed, He said, &#x201C;The earth was chaotic and void,&#x201D; since the divine presence was to depart from Israel.</p>
<p><bold>And a wind from God sweeping over the waters:</bold> refers to Torah, since we have been promised that it will not be forgotten by our offspring, even in exile.<sup><xref rid="fn241">241</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>God said: &#x201C;Let there be light&#x201D;</bold> [Gen. 1:3]: This refers to the messianic times, of which Scripture says: &#x201C;Arise, my light, for your light is come; the glory of the Lord shines upon you&#x201D; [Isa. 60:1].</p>
<p><bold>And God distinguished between the light and the darkness</bold> [Gen. 1:4]: For thus would God distinguish between Israel, who hope for salvation, and the nations who abide in darkness. Our rabbis <sup><xref rid="fn242">242</xref></sup> were pointing to this when they found in this verse a reference to the four empires: &#x201C;The earth was chaotic&#x201D;&#x2014;this is the Babylonian Empire; &#x201C;and void&#x201D;&#x2014;the Medean Empire; &#x201C;and darkness&#x201D;&#x2014;the Hellenistic Empire; &#x201C;the deep&#x201D;&#x2014;the Roman Empire; &#x201C;a wind from God&#x201D;&#x2014;the spirit of messiah.</p>
<p>The meaning of this midrash is that in this chapter the blessed Lord was foretelling the end from the beginning; Scripture intended to refer to the end of time at the beginning of time, showing that the purpose intended by creation is the messianic time. &#x201C;The beginning of thought is the end of deed.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn243">243</xref></sup></p>
<p>If you apply your mind further, you will note that in <italic>bereshit</italic> [<span dir="rtl">&#x05D1;&#x05E8;&#x05E9;&#x05D9;&#x05EA;</span>] one can find the words &#x201C;fire of the covenant&#x201D; [<italic>esh berit</italic>; <span dir="rtl">&#x05D0;&#x05E9; &#x05E8;&#x05D9;&#x05EA;</span>]. One can also divide it into the two words &#x201C;created the pit&#x201D; [<italic>bara shit</italic>; <span dir="rtl">&#x05D1;&#x05E8;&#x05D0; &#x05EA;&#x05D9;&#x05E9;</span>], referring to the pits beneath the Temple altar, which were created during the six days of creation.<sup><xref rid="fn244">244</xref></sup> So too: &#x201C;He created a ram&#x201D; [<italic>bara tayish</italic>; <span dir="rtl">&#x05D1;&#x05E8;&#x05D0; &#x05EA;&#x05D9;&#x05E9;</span>], referring to the ram of Isaac, that was created during the six days.<sup><xref rid="fn245">245</xref></sup> <italic>Bereshit</italic> could also be derived from <italic>areshet</italic> [<span dir="rtl">&#x05D0;&#x05E8;&#x05E9;&#x05EA;</span>], which means &#x201C;utterance,&#x201D; [Ps. 21:3]. Its meaning would be &#x201C;By ten utterances;&#x201D; these are the ten statements [&#x201C;Let there be&#x201D;] by which the world was created.<sup><xref rid="fn246">246</xref></sup></p>
<p>Know and understand that the world was created in [the month] Tishre [<span dir="rtl">&#x05EA;&#x05E9;&#x05E8;&#x05D9;</span>]; the word <italic>bereshit</italic> hints at that.<sup><xref rid="fn247">247</xref></sup> On this matter there was a Talmudic debate between R. Eliezer and R.Joshua. R. Eliezer said the world was created in Tishre.<sup><xref rid="fn248">248</xref></sup> Even though in debates between R. Eliezer and R. Joshua we generally accept the rulings of R. Joshua, the Talmud already decided this case in favor of R. Eliezer. Thus it says: &#x201C;According to whose view do we now pray:<sup><xref rid="fn249">249</xref></sup> &#x2018;This day is the beginning of Your deeds?&#x2019; According to Rabbi Eliezer.&#x201D;</p>
<p><bold>In the beginning, God created the heavens and the earth</bold>: In accord with the path of reason.</p>
<p>The entirety of reality is comprised of three divisions: the first being the world of the angels; the second that of the heavenly spheres; and the third, this lower worlds&#x2014;all three created by the Occult Power. The phrase &#x201C;in the beginning&#x201D; alludes to the Occult Power, the beginning of all, the beginningless Primordium. It first created the world of the angels, designated in scriptural texts as divinities [<italic>Elohim</italic>], then the world of the spheres which are &#x201C;the heavens,&#x201D; and this lower world which is &#x201C;the earth.&#x201D;</p>
<p>For this reason the verse does not commence with the divine epithet <italic>Elohim</italic>, stating <italic>Elohim bara bereshit</italic>&#x2014;God created at first the heavens and the earth. Rather, the verse necessarily reads, <italic>bereshit bara Elohim</italic>&#x2014;&#x201C;In the beginning, created <italic>Elohim</italic>,&#x201D; in order that the verb &#x201C;created&#x201D; refer back to the phrase &#x201C;in the beginning.&#x201D; From this, the reader will understand that the Occult Power, which is designated by &#x201C;beginningless primordium&#x201D; [<italic>reshit</italic>], created the <italic>Elohim</italic>&#x2014;these being the angels, and the heavens, i.e., the spheres and the earth&#x2014;the lower world extending from the sphere of the moon downwards, all of its constituents being generically designated by the term &#x201C;earth.&#x201D; The succeeding verse clarifies this: &#x201C;The earth was chaotic and void&#x201D; [Gen. 1:2]. That is to say that the earth, mentioned generically [in 1:1], was in a state of chaos at its creation. It was matter which received the forms of the four elements alluded to in the verse.</p>
<p>The term &#x201C;earth&#x201D; is thus a homonym, referring to both genus and species, as in: &#x201C;God called the dry land earth&#x201D; [Gen. 1:10]. If such is the case, read the phrase &#x201C;and the earth&#x201D; [Gen. 1:2] as referring to the totality of the four elements, while &#x201C;unformed and void&#x201D; refers to the particular element of earth. &#x201C;Chaotic and void&#x201D; signifies that the element of earth lacked substantiation.</p>
<p>The reader should know that the heavenly spheres number 945, in accord with the numerical equivalent of the word &#x201C;the heavens.&#x201D; So one finds in &#x201C;The Chapters of the Chariot&#x201D;:<sup><xref rid="fn250">250</xref></sup> &#x201C;In the hour when the Holy One, blessed be He, descends from the heavens of the heavens, from nine hundred and forty-five firmaments, and sits upon His throne of glory in Aravot, all of the gates of the firmament and all of the gates of Aravot proclaim: &#x2018;O gates, lift up your heads&#x0021;&#x2019; [Ps. 24:7].&#x201D; So too, in the midrash Derekh Eretz Zuta:<sup><xref rid="fn251">251</xref></sup> &#x201C;The Holy One, blessed be He, reigns on high alone. He is one and His name is one and He dwells in three hundred and ninety firmaments, each and every firmament inscribed with His name and its liturgical pronunciation.&#x201D; They quote this name in the context of: &#x201C;Give ear O you heavens and let me speak&#x0021;&#x201D; [Deut. 32:1]. With God&#x2019;s help, I will transcribe this midrash there, but at the very least, I did not want to exclude their number.</p>
<p>According to our teachers, the mystics, the heavens number seven, following tractate <italic>&#x1E24;agigah</italic> [12a]:</p>
<p align="blockquote">R. Judah says: There are two firmaments, as it says: &#x201C;The heavens and the heavens of heavens are the Lord your God&#x2019;s&#x201D; [Deut. 10:14].</p>
<p align="blockquote">Resh Lakish says: &#x201C;There are seven. These are: Vilon, Raki&#x2019;a, Shehakim, Zevul, Ma&#x2019;on, Makhon, Aravot.&#x201D;</p>
<p>The philosophers claim that there are nine. These are the primum mobile, second to whom is the sphere of the fixed stars, followed by the seven spheres of the planets: Saturn, Jupiter, Mars, the sun, Venus, Mercury and the moon. The nine spheres are succeeded by the four elements, whose order is fire, air, water and earth and whose mnemonic is <italic>arma</italic>&#x2018;. Solomon already mentioned them in this order in: &#x201C;Who has ascended heaven and come down? Who has gathered up the wind in the hollow of his hand? Who has wrapped the waters in his garment? Who has established all of the extremities of the earth?&#x201D; [Prov. 30:4].</p>
<p>The opinion of the philosophers is that the element of fire derives its warmth from the sphere of the moon which is immediately above and adjacent to it. This is on account of the incessant movement of the sphere. For it is known that every moving object warms and ignites everything in its proximity, on account of its constant movement. It is ever more so the case that when the moving object is large and of great might, it will impart enormous and exceedingly powerful heat. Consequently, the sphere of the moon warms and enkindles everything close to it without itself being ignited. Unlike the material substance of the elements, its matter is pure and refined and not receptive of the influence of external affects. For this reason, fire does not ascend infinitely upwards, although it is its nature to ascend above. As its matter is as solid as cast glass, the surface of the sphere blocks it. Fire ascends there to its boundary, which it does not transgress. Similarly, the earth blocks the waters, although it is their nature to descend downwards. Nevertheless, they too do not transgress.</p>
<p>We have already informed you above that the world was created in <italic>Tishre</italic>, whose Zodiac sign is Libra. This is taught by the second verse: &#x201C;A wind from God sweeping over the waters.&#x201D; Libra, as is known, is the sign for air, &#x201C;sweeping over the waters,&#x201D; adjacent to Scorpio, the sign for water. The reason they are called Libra [&#x201C;scales&#x201D;], Scorpio [&#x201C;scorpion&#x201D;], or the others signs, is that stars are grouped in the forms of scales, a scorpion, and so forth. They came to be grouped this way at the time of the flood: a group of stars in the form of a lamb; in the form of a bull; in the form of twins, which is the human form; the form of a crab, which is a sort of creature; in the forms of scales and scorpion; and in the form of a dipper, which is a person dipping water. Afterwards they were called by these names, following the forms they had taken at the time of the flood. It seems that the reason they appeared this way at the time of the flood was that so we be aroused to contemplate divine providence, following from the meaning of these names, as is found in the rabbis&#x2019; midrash.</p>
<p>You should also know that the birth-moment [<italic>molad</italic>] of Tishre, when the world was created, would have been on the eve of the second day, in the fifth hour, the 204th part,<sup><xref rid="fn252">252</xref></sup> had the luminaries been created. We can determine this from the <italic>molad</italic> of the Nissan that follows it. But since the luminaries were not created until the fourth day, we know clearly that there never was a second day, fifth hour, 204th part <italic>molad.</italic> Nevertheless, this is the proper calculation according to the mathematicians. As for what we say in the prayers&#x2014;&#x201C;this day is the beginning of Your deeds&#x201D;&#x2014;it could apply whether you begin with the second day as stated or with the sixth day and the fourteenth hour.<sup><xref rid="fn253">253</xref></sup> If we begin with this latter count, beginning with the creation of man after the passage of twelve hours of the sixth day&#x2019;s night and two hours of daytime, the meaning of &#x201C;the beginning of Your deeds&#x201D; would refer to Adam&#x2019;s judgment. Taking the former count, however, &#x201C;Your deeds&#x201D; would refer to the second day, the beginning of divine doing, when it says: &#x201C;God made the firmament&#x201D; [Gen. 1:7]. On the first day there is no doing, just creating, and the prayer refers to &#x201C;Your deeds&#x201D; and not &#x201C;Your creation.&#x201D;</p>
<p><bold>In the beginning, God created the heavens and the earth:</bold> In accord with the path of [mystical] tradition.</p>
<p>This verse bears within it the mystery of the ten <italic>sefirot.</italic> The &#x201C;heavens&#x201D; and the &#x201C;earth&#x201D; refer to the supernal heavens and earth, which are not included within the category of the spheres. They are called the primordial heavens and the land of the living.<sup><xref rid="fn254">254</xref></sup></p>
<p>The phrase &#x201C;in the beginning&#x201D; [<italic>bereshit</italic>] alludes to Wisdom, as it is written: &#x201C;Beginning [<italic>reshit</italic>] is Wisdom&#x201D; [Ps. 111:10]. Similarly, the <italic>bet</italic> of <italic>bereshit</italic> alludes to Wisdom which is the second of the <italic>sefirot</italic>.<sup><xref rid="fn255">255</xref></sup> Thus the first letter and the entire word testify to Wisdom. And because all things are drawn forth and emanate out of Wisdom, the <italic>bet</italic> is written larger than the other letters. For while it may be the second in the sef&#x00ED;rotic count, Wisdom is the first in our perception. Thus the <italic>bet</italic> of <italic>bereshit</italic> refers to Wisdom, which is &#x201C;beginning&#x201D; [<italic>reshit</italic>], for we are not empowered to think about the <italic>sefirah</italic> which precedes it. For this reason, the first <italic>sefirah</italic> is designated as &#x201C;Naught&#x201D; [<italic>Ayin</italic>]. This is the esoteric meaning of [Job 28:20], &#x201C;Wisdom derives from Naught,&#x201D; read as a statement rather than as a question. Nonetheless, the upward stroke<sup><xref rid="fn256">256</xref></sup> of the <italic>bet</italic> [<span dir="rtl">&#x05D1;</span>] alludes to the Naught. For this purpose, the mystics expounded: &#x201C;They said to the <italic>bet</italic>: &#x2018;Who created you&#x2019;? With her upward stroke, she pointed them towards alef&#x201D; which is <italic>keter</italic>.</p>
<p>Know and understand that the Cause of Causes transcends <italic>keter.</italic> This is the meaning of the statement in the Book of Creation: &#x201C;Ten mysterious <italic>sefirot.</italic> Ten and not nine. Ten and not eleven.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn257">257</xref></sup> The meaning of &#x201C;ten and not nine&#x201D; is that <italic>keter</italic> is to be included within the totality of the ten <italic>sefirot.</italic> All of the other <italic>sefirot</italic> emanate from it; it is the outflowing source upon which the rest rely. &#x201C;Ten and not eleven&#x201D; reveals that the One which transcends <italic>keter</italic> is not to be included within the totality of the ten <italic>sefirot.</italic> This is the Cause of Causes, a hidden entity, which can be designated as neither being nor nothingness. And thus the terminology <italic>&#x2019;eser sefirot belimah</italic>, the ten <italic>sefirot</italic> of <italic>belimah</italic>&#x2014;that is to say, emanated from <italic>beli mah</italic>, that which transcends all substantiality. For this reason, the mystics explained the need for a point upward upon the letter Y [<span dir="rtl">&#x05D9;</span>]. It alludes to the Cause of Causes and its transcendence of the entirety of the ten <italic>sefirot.</italic> Since the entirely of the ten are emanated, the Emanator, which is the Cause of Causes, is distinct from them. This is the meaning of &#x201C;ten and not eleven.&#x201D;</p>
<p>When <italic>Sefer Yetsirah</italic> says, &#x201C;Engraved,&#x201D; but does not say who does the engraving, the reference is to <italic>keter.</italic> That which is engraved consists of three books, three letters inscribed by <italic>keter</italic>, and they are Y-H-V, letters that are blessed and bless every blessed one. They are also <italic>sefer</italic>, <italic>sefor</italic>, and <italic>sippur</italic>.<sup><xref rid="fn258">258</xref></sup> <italic>Sefer</italic> refers to <italic>&#x1E25;okhmah</italic>; it is called <italic>sefer</italic> or &#x201C;book&#x201D; because generations pass on and wisdom is preserved only in a book. That is why divine wisdom is referred to as a book. <italic>Sefor</italic> is <italic>binah</italic>, the intellect a person uses for counting. It comes from the meaning &#x201C;count&#x201D; as in the word <italic>sefirah.</italic> Thus Scripture says in the Book of Chronicles [II 2:16]: &#x201C;Solomon counted all the sojourners living in the Land of Israel as his father David had counted them.&#x201D; <italic>Sippur</italic> refers to the remaining <italic>sefirot,</italic> those which can be conceived and discussed by humans.<sup><xref rid="fn259">259</xref></sup> Know that <italic>sefer</italic> is the <italic>Yod, sefor</italic> is the <italic>He</italic>, and <italic>sippur</italic> is the <italic>Vav</italic>, which is <italic>tiferet</italic>, the sixth level. Understand this.<sup><xref rid="fn260">260</xref></sup></p>
<p>It is known that the numerical value of S-F-R is 340. The three forms of S-F-R are thus three terms for mind. Even if their power are diverse, all have the same root. The same is true of the three letters of the the divine name; they too have a single root. They all came out of that single root, the One that engraves the world, <italic>keter</italic>, deriving from the Cause of Causes that is also called &#x201C;the Endless.&#x201D; You should contemplate the passage on Marah [Exod. 15:22&#x2013;27], where it says: &#x201C;There He gave him engraved judgments, and there He tried him&#x201D; [Exod. 15:25].<sup><xref rid="fn261">261</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>God</bold> [<italic>Elohim</italic>]: Return;<sup><xref rid="fn262">262</xref></sup> This is the <italic>sefirah</italic> which created the world [of emanation]. The intentionality of our prayers is directed towards Return on Rosh ha-Shanah. In &#x201C;Abraham prayed to God&#x201D; [Gen. 20:17], the intention is towards the final H of the tetragrammaton.<sup><xref rid="fn263">263</xref></sup> So it is too with David the King, peace be upon him, &#x201C;As for me, I will call to God&#x201D; [Ps. 55:17]. However, in Proverbs&#x2014;&#x201C;You shall call out to Understanding as to a mother&#x201D; [Prov. 2:3]&#x2014;the intention is toward Return. And Return is called Understanding [<italic>binah</italic>] because it is situated between [<italic>ben</italic>] the five higher <italic>sefirot</italic>.<sup><xref rid="fn264">264</xref></sup> Both &#x201C;I will call&#x201D; and &#x201C;You shall call&#x201D; refer to prayer as in: &#x201C;Abraham called there to the Lord&#x201D; [Gen. 13:4]. The Aramaic translation of call is <italic>tsalei</italic>&#x2014;he prayed.</p>
<p><bold>The Heavens and the Earth:</bold> The direct object indicators [<italic>et</italic> and <italic>ve-et</italic>] include Greatness and Might.<sup><xref rid="fn265">265</xref></sup> &#x201C;The heavens&#x201D; refers to Splendor,<sup><xref rid="fn266">266</xref></sup> which is Eden. The two columns Perdurance and Majesty<sup><xref rid="fn267">267</xref></sup> are included in the word Heavens&#x2014;that is to say, the heavens and its two columns. Since we have not found any mention of the creation of the columns of heaven, we must conclude that they were included in the totality of the heavens. The Righteous One<sup><xref rid="fn268">268</xref></sup> was also included with them as it is the column sustaining the world. Or it is possible to contend that the addition of the &#x201C;and&#x201D; of &#x201C;and the earth&#x201D; serves to include these three columns.</p>
<p><bold>And the Earth</bold>: This is the Garden<sup><xref rid="fn269">269</xref></sup> which receives from Eden.</p>
<p><bold>And the earth was chaotic and empty</bold>: Scripture now mentions that which first existed. The [tenth <italic>sefirah</italic>] is designated &#x201C;earth&#x201D; because she is the conclusion of the edifice of emanation. The past tense &#x201C;was&#x201D; indicates that the essence of her existence is derived from that prior existent which is Wisdom, anteceding all. Chaos is Understanding, the green plumbline encompassing the entirety of the world. The Void, indicating that which is beginning to be formed, this is Greatness. And darkness, this is divine Might.</p>
<p>This text [Gen. 1:1] also bears within it an intimation concerning the temporal duration of the world, a fact well known from the saying of our sages of blessed memory &#x201C;The world exists for six thousand years and lies destroyed for a millennium.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn270">270</xref></sup> The wise will understand. Thus Scripture states immediately thereafter &#x201C;And the earth was chaotic and void&#x201D; [Gen. 1:2] to allude to the millennium of desolation. One furthermore finds in the first syllables of the forty-two letter name of God derived from these verses intimation that the world created in six days will be destroyed and desolated.<sup><xref rid="fn271">271</xref></sup></p>
<p>Realize that the verse does not explicate what preceded the creation of the heavens as it does for the earth. However, from the explication of the earth one can understand the heavens. Upon this it relied and thus kept its quiet, neither mentioning the heavens nor explaining what the spheres were before they came to their consummation in their current form.</p>
<p>However, in accord with the mystical tradition which I intimated to you is true, [it is] firmly established and fitting that the matter of the heavens was not explicated. For they are the heavenly Eden.<sup><xref rid="fn272">272</xref></sup> How can one explicate that which came first, when the sages have expounded: &#x201C;&#x2018;No eye has seen O God, save You, what you have made for those who trust in You&#x2019; [Isa. 64:3]: this is Eden which no eye has ever seen.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn273">273</xref></sup> Therefore, the verse revealed the matter but concealed the hidden things while speaking at length concerning the revealed. Understand this well. The heavens and the earth of the first verse of Genesis are Splendor and Crown [<italic>tiferet</italic> and <italic>malkhut</italic>], they are Eden and the Garden. This is the meaning of the midrash that the Garden of Eden was created before the world.<sup><xref rid="fn274">274</xref></sup> If this is the case of the Garden, how much the more so of Eden, in which the Garden was planted? As it is written: &#x201C;The Lord God planted a garden in Eden, in the east&#x201D; [Gen. 2:8].</p>
<p>You must know that we possess a tradition regarding this verse of <italic>bereshit,</italic> extending down to <italic>bohu,</italic> that it is the source of the forty-two letter name associated with divine judgment. It comes about through many permutations of letters, but if you enlighten your heart you will find in it the count of two, five, and 204 which I mentioned above. It is inscribed in the text, and between each of its four letters there are forty-two letters. The intelligent person will understand that this is no coincidence, but a complete demonstration that the world was created. This was &#x201C;before the mountains were born&#x201D; [Ps. 90:2].<sup><xref rid="fn275">275</xref></sup> There was no 2, 5, 204, but only the cosmic force of justice in its place, operating with no instrument but bringing forth the instrument of its deeds. This is understood.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<ftnote id="fn1"><sup>1</sup> Distinguished from &#x201C;practical&#x201D; Kabbalah, essentially the magical side of esoteric Judaism, and also (primarily thanks to the writings of Moshe Idel) &#x201C;ecstatic&#x201D; Kabbalah, a contemplative praxis transmitted primarily in the school of Abraham Abulafia.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn2"><sup>2</sup> <italic>Through a Speculum that Shines: Vision and Imagination in Medieval Jewish Mysticism</italic> (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1994), pp. 383ff.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn3"><sup>3</sup> <italic>Gates of Light: Sha&#x2018;are Orah</italic>, trans. Avi Weinstein (San Francisco: Harper Collins, 1994).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn4"><sup>4</sup> The commentary of R. Moshe is lost. That of R. Isaac was published from a single surviving manuscript by A. Green in &#x201C;Rabbi Isaac Ibn Sahola&#x2019;s commentary to the Song of Songs,&#x201D; <italic>Jerusalem Studies in Jewish Thought</italic> 6 (1987), 393&#x2013;491.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn5"><sup>5</sup> See the discussion by Gershom Scholem in <italic>Origins of the Kabbalah</italic> (Philadelphia: Jewish Publication Society, 1987), pp. 370&#x2013;71. See also the frequent references to R. Ezra in Moshe Idel&#x2019;s <italic>Kabbalah: New Perspectives</italic> (New Haven: Yale University Press, 1988), index s.v. Ezra of Gerona and Elliot Wolfson&#x2019;s work cited above, index s.v. Ezra ben Solomon. &#x201C;The Secret of the Tree of Knowledge&#x201D; is translated in G. Scholem&#x2019;s <italic>On the Mystical Shape of the Godhead</italic> (New York: Shocken Books, 1991), p. 65ff.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn6"><sup>6</sup> <italic>Le Commentaire d&#x2019;Ezra de Gerone sur le Cantique des Cantiques</italic> (Aubier-Montaigne: Paris, 1969).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn7"><sup>7</sup> Adam and Eve.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn8"><sup>8</sup> Following Ezek. 12:13&#x2013;14, referring to the angels.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn9"><sup>9</sup> b. <italic>&#x1E24;agigah</italic> 13a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn10"><sup>10</sup> Probably his fiftieth year.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn11"><sup>11</sup> Referring to the two major excurses within the text.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn12"><sup>12</sup> I.e., a name of God.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn13"><sup>13</sup> b. <italic>Shavu&#x2018;ot</italic> 35b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn14"><sup>14</sup> The final chapter of the Talmudic tractate Sanhedrin.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn15"><sup>15</sup> b. <italic>Sanhedrin</italic> 101a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn16"><sup>16</sup> m. Yadayim 3:5.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn17"><sup>17</sup> Following the view of R. &#x1E24;iyya the Great in Cant. Rabbah. 1:10.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn18"><sup>18</sup> Designating God as Solomon <italic>(Shelomo&#x003D;Shalom)</italic> refers especially to <italic>tiferet</italic>, the sixth of the ten <italic>sefirot</italic>, the central &#x201C;male&#x201D; element of the Godhead, the aspect of divinity understood by the kabbalists as the bridegroom of the Song of Songs.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn19"><sup>19</sup> &#x201C;Righteousness&#x201D; for the kabbalist can be a designation of <italic>shekhinah</italic>, who is also God&#x2019;s throne. See Prov. 25:5, etc. The passage here is obscure.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn20"><sup>20</sup><italic>&#x1E24;okhmah</italic>, the second of the ten <italic>sefirot</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn21"><sup>21</sup> Obscure. He may be referring to a tripartite division of <italic>keter</italic>, the first <italic>sefirah</italic>, related to a notion of three primal flashes of light (<italic>tza&#x1E25;tze&#x1E25;ot</italic>) that precede the <italic>sefirot</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn22"><sup>22</sup> Rea&#x1E25; or scent is a metaphoric figure for the vivifying outflow of emanational energy, wafting forth from &#x1E25;<italic>okhmah</italic> through the sefirotic world.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn23"><sup>23</sup> Ezek. 1:28.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn24"><sup>24</sup> b. <italic>Ta &#x2018;anit</italic> 29b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn25"><sup>25</sup> The <italic>sefirot</italic> from <italic>&#x1E25;esed</italic> to <italic>yesod</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn26"><sup>26</sup> From here through the end of the introduction R. Ezra is explicating Job 28, which he employs to introduce sefirotic discourse.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn27"><sup>27</sup> Silver is <italic>&#x1E25;esed</italic>; gold is <italic>din</italic>; copper is <italic>tiferet</italic>; and iron is <italic>malkhut</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn28"><sup>28</sup> <italic>Afisah</italic> or nullity designates the highest <italic>sefirah</italic>, usually described in negative terms. Here that most primordial seed of existence is not clearly separated from <italic>Eyn Sof</italic>, the primordial boundless &#x201C;darkness&#x201D; of the unknown and unknowable God.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn29"><sup>29</sup> In the sense of a divine &#x201C;ground of being.&#x201D; The passage refers to <italic>keter</italic>, the primal will of God.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn30"><sup>30</sup> The light flowing forth from <italic>keter</italic>, the channel of infinite divine energy.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn31"><sup>31</sup> Here he calls upon an ancient connection between the Hebrew and Aramaic words for &#x201C;light&#x201D; and &#x201C;water.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn32"><sup>32</sup> Primordial chaos is twofold: <italic>tohu va-vohu</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn33"><sup>33</sup> v. <italic>Hagigah</italic> 12a. The kabbalists associate this list with the ten <italic>sefirot</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn34"><sup>34</sup> Bereshit Rabbah 1:5. The first <italic>sefirah</italic> already includes and implies the last, associated with righteousness.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn35"><sup>35</sup> Usually understood by Kabbalists as referring to <italic>malkhut</italic>, the tenth <italic>sefirah</italic>, the feminine-receptive aspect of the Godhead.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn36"><sup>36</sup> Canticles Rabbah 6:12. The Song is thus sung by <italic>tiferet</italic> and <italic>malkhut</italic>, bridegroom and bride within the Godhead.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn37"><sup>37</sup> The Glory is <italic>tiferet</italic>, the masculine pole of creative energy in the realm of divine emanation.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn38"><sup>38</sup> Source of life (<italic>mekor ha-&#x1E25;ayyim</italic>) and holy spirit (<italic>rua&#x1E25; ha-kodesh</italic>) generally symbolize <italic>&#x1E25;okhmah</italic> in Geronan sources.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn39"><sup>39</sup> Literally <italic>sibah</italic> or cause.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn40"><sup>40</sup> The word <italic>tovim</italic> is plural: your love is an improvement upon the wine of <italic>&#x1E25;okhmah</italic>, as it flows in multiple directions.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn41"><sup>41</sup> &#x201C;Goodness&#x201D; is the ongoing flow of light from lamp to lamp, the ceaseless flow of divine life, through the <italic>sefirot</italic> and into the world.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn42"><sup>42</sup> Each of the branches is &#x201C;kissed&#x201D; or nourished directly from His mouth, from <italic>tiferet</italic> or the central column.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn43"><sup>43</sup> The term here is &#x2018;atarah, referring to <italic>malkhut</italic>, the last of the ten <italic>sefirot</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn44"><sup>44</sup> It would seem that a distinction is made here between &#x2018;atarah, the tenth sefirah, and <italic>shekhinah</italic>, which is the indwelling presence of God in the world, as in the older rabbinic sources. The passage is however difficult.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn45"><sup>45</sup> The memorial offering of flour and frankincense providing a <italic>rea&#x1E25; ni&#x1E25; oa&#x1E25;</italic>, a &#x201C;pleasing odor to the Lord.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn46"><sup>46</sup> <italic>Mekom yenikatam</italic>: literally &#x201C;the place from which they nurse.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn47"><sup>47</sup> In Tractate Megillah 29a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn48"><sup>48</sup> &#x201C;Solomon&#x201D; here refers to God, specifically to <italic>tiferet</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn49"><sup>49</sup> The rest of the sefirotic world is pure and lovely; only <italic>shekhinah</italic> is &#x201C;darkened&#x201D; because of her involvement with the lower world.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn50"><sup>50</sup> Cf. <italic>Mekhilta Shirta</italic> 2.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn51"><sup>51</sup> Compare <italic>Vayikra Rabbah</italic> 20:10.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn52"><sup>52</sup> The phrase would alternatively be rendered: &#x201C;imagines.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn53"><sup>53</sup> Points or studs (<italic>nekudot</italic>). The term is used as well to designate the vowel signs that are placed above and below the consonants of the Hebrew alphabet and look very much like points (<italic>nekudot</italic>). R. Ezra will construct an elaborate exegetic pun upon the multiple meanings of the term in which the studs (<italic>nekudot</italic>) of silver&#x2014;the teachings of written Torah&#x2014;will serve as the animating force of the wreaths of gold&#x2014;oral Torah&#x2014;just as the vowels (<italic>nekudot</italic>) transform inert consonants into pliable words and living discourse.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn54"><sup>54</sup> &#x201C;Wine,&#x201D; &#x201C;red,&#x201D; and &#x201C;gold&#x201D; are symbols of the left side, while &#x201C;white,&#x201D; &#x201C;milk,&#x201D; and &#x201C;silver&#x201D; symbolize the right. Isa. 55:1, referring to human access, mentions wine before milk. The Haggai verse, referring to God, reverses the symbolic order: God prefers silver (<italic>&#x1E25;esed</italic>) to gold (<italic>din</italic>).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn55"><sup>55</sup> See Ecclesiastes Rabbah 8:11, where R. Haninah interprets Zach. 12:1 &#x201C;God created [<italic>yatzar</italic>] humanity&#x2019;s spirit within it&#x201D; as meaning that the spirit has been tied or bound up within the body in order to animate. See Chavel (cited on page 10 of the editor&#x2019;s note above), note 39 <italic>ad locum</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn56"><sup>56</sup> Concerning this verse, the Midrash states: &#x201C;As for the Holy One, blessed be He, His name and might, when He declaims in enunciated speech, the sound is divided into seven voices.&#x201D; Divine speech creates the cosmogenerative septet ranging from <italic>&#x1E25;esed</italic> to the <italic>shekhinah</italic>. However, it only becomes audible, giving rise to the differentiated cosmos and producing prophetic discourse through the aegis of the <italic>shekhinah</italic>, the final rung in the chain of divine being.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn57"><sup>57</sup> b. <italic>Berakhot</italic> 6b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn58"><sup>58</sup> The term for &#x201C;thunder&#x201D; and &#x201C;sound&#x201D; throughout this passage is <italic>kol</italic>, the same as &#x201C;voice&#x201D; in the Jeremiah passage. The thunderbolts are the &#x201C;voice&#x201D; of God as Torah is given. From the reading of the Jeremiah passage it appears that the five &#x201C;voices&#x201D; are the five lower <italic>sefirot</italic> from <italic>tiferet</italic> to <italic>malkhut</italic>, or from bridegroom to bride.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn59"><sup>59</sup> This might mean there were six or seven, thus breaking the parallel of five (wedding shouts) to five (Torah-sounds). Sinai is frequently depicted in the Midrash as the marriage of God and Israel.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn60"><sup>60</sup> <italic>Shemot Rabbah</italic> 28, end.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn61"><sup>61</sup> North, east, south, west, up, down, and inward. These will be associated below with the seven lower <italic>sefirot</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn62"><sup>62</sup> Midrash Shir ha-Shirim Zuta 3:10.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn63"><sup>63</sup> Targum Onkelos <italic>ad locum</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn64"><sup>64</sup> Probably <italic>malkhut</italic> and <italic>yesod</italic>. See <italic>R. Azriel: Perush ha-Aggadot</italic>, ed. Tishby (Jerusalem: Mekize Nirdamim, 1945), index of symbols.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn65"><sup>65</sup> The &#x201C;hand&#x201D; is higher than the &#x201C;throne.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn66"><sup>66</sup> Midrash Be-Midbar Rabbah 12:10.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn67"><sup>67</sup> The poles and rafters of the tabernacle are depicted as the lines that flow between the various <italic>sefirot</italic>, the divine construct holding them all together.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn68"><sup>68</sup> Midrash Shir ha-Shirim Zuta 2:1.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn69"><sup>69</sup> Lit. <italic>beit ha-yayin:</italic> house of wine, a symbol of <italic>&#x1E25;okhmah</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn70"><sup>70</sup> The association of <italic>din</italic>, or the left side, with the demonic is strongly enunciated here.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn71"><sup>71</sup> Perhaps implying that darkness should come from the west (opposite to the east) rather than from the north.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn72"><sup>72</sup> Midrash Pesikta de-Rav Kahana 1.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn73"><sup>73</sup> See Numbers 10:11: &#x201C;In the second year, on the twentieth day of the second month, the cloud lifted from the Tabernacle of the Covenant and the Israelites set out on their journeys from the wilderness of Sinai.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn74"><sup>74</sup> Exodus Rabbah 2:2.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn75"><sup>75</sup> b. <italic>Megillah</italic> 29a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn76"><sup>76</sup> The Masoretic text as written, without the note for proper reading preserved in the margin.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn77"><sup>77</sup> All these readings hint at <italic>shekhinah</italic>&#x2019;s participation in Israel&#x2019;s exile.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn78"><sup>78</sup> b. <italic>Pesahim</italic> 118b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn79"><sup>79</sup> b. <italic>Yebamot</italic> 63a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn80"><sup>80</sup> b. <italic>Sukkah</italic> 55b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn81"><sup>81</sup> The energy flows through the central column of the <italic>sefirot</italic> and thence to the right and left branches.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn82"><sup>82</sup> The source of this quotation is unknown. Compare Nahmanides&#x2019; commentary to Numbers 14:9.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn83"><sup>83</sup> Righteousness [<italic>tzedek</italic>] symbolizes the <italic>shekhinah</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn84"><sup>84</sup> &#x201C;Darkness&#x201D; and &#x201C;fire&#x201D; here refer to <italic>din</italic>, the force of divine judgment.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn85"><sup>85</sup> Red&#x003D;<italic>din;</italic> white&#x003D;<italic>&#x1E25;esed</italic> or divine love.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn86"><sup>86</sup> The six <italic>sefirot</italic> from <italic>&#x1E25;esed</italic> to <italic>yesod</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn87"><sup>87</sup> Midrash Yalkut Shim &#x2018;oni <italic>ad locum</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn88"><sup>88</sup> Pirkei deRabbi Eliezer, 3. <italic>Havei aretz</italic>, &#x201C;fall to the ground,&#x201D; means literally &#x201C;become ground.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn89"><sup>89</sup> Gen. Rabbah 3:2.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn90"><sup>90</sup> Ms. reading is quite different here: the right hand is &#x201C;water from air,&#x201D; the left is &#x201C;fire.&#x201D; The central pillar is &#x201C;truth, justice, peace, seal of the structure, the seal of God.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn91"><sup>91</sup> In Numbers Rabbah 12:4?</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn92"><sup>92</sup> The obscure passage seems to mean that <italic>shekhinah</italic> is wife to the Central Column, source of godly seed; so too should Israel, husbands and wives, bear godly seed.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn93"><sup>93</sup> Midrash Mishle, ed. B. Wissocsky, p. 57.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn94"><sup>94</sup> Sanctification [<italic>kadosh</italic>], blessing [<italic>barukh</italic>], and <italic>shema&#x2018;</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn95"><sup>95</sup> This could refer either to the threefold repetition of &#x201C;Holy&#x201D; or to the three <italic>kedushot</italic> of the daily morning service.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn96"><sup>96</sup> Chapter 3, end.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn97"><sup>97</sup> <italic>Ha-havayot ha-&#x2018;amukot</italic>, i.e., the uppermost <italic>sefirot</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn98"><sup>98</sup> Following ms. <italic>mi-makom e&#x1E25;ad. Shekhinah</italic>&#x2019;s origin is one with that of the Glory, in the most hidden sefirotic realms.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn99"><sup>99</sup> Ravishing excites and stops the heart at once. &#x201C;Ashing&#x201D; the altar means <italic>removing</italic> the ashes.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn100"><sup>100</sup> The light of Wisdom is the flow of sefirotic energy, coming from supernal <italic>&#x1E25;okhmah</italic>, the source of all the <italic>sefirot</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn101"><sup>101</sup> Prayer shawl, a rectangular garment bearing fringes at its four corners.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn102"><sup>102</sup> <italic>Me-&#x2018;uteret u-mukhteret</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn103"><sup>103</sup> The two versions of the decalogue (Exod. 20 and Deut. 5) differ in the wording of the Sabbath command. Exodus says &#x201C;Remember the Sabbath Day&#x201D; and Deuteronomy says &#x201C;keep.&#x201D; These are taken to refer to positive and prohibitive aspects of Sabbath observance, and then generalized to refer to positive and negative commandments altogether. For kabbalists they also refer to the two <italic>sefirot yesod</italic> and <italic>malkhut</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn104"><sup>104</sup> Twenty-two plus the five final forms.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn105"><sup>105</sup> b. <italic>Nedarim</italic> 25b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn106"><sup>106</sup> In b. <italic>Ta&#x2018;anit</italic> 9a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn107"><sup>107</sup> The prophetic and hagiographic sections of the Bible.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn108"><sup>108</sup> And thus everything must be included within it. Alternatively the concluding phrase <italic>ve-lo&#x2019; yasaf</italic> can be understood as &#x201C;and He added nothing [further].&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn109"><sup>109</sup> b. <italic>Ketubot</italic> 86a. The two examples given refer to the commandments of the <italic>Sukkot</italic> festival, but could be any positive commandments of the Torah.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn110"><sup>110</sup> Shabbat 119b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn111"><sup>111</sup> b. <italic>Berakhot</italic> 54a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn112"><sup>112</sup> The following, down to the resumption of the commentary with 4:12, is found on p. 548 of Chavel&#x2019;s Hebrew edition.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn113"><sup>113</sup> b. <italic>Rosh Hashanah</italic> 27a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn114"><sup>114</sup> Also said to number 248, according to a Talmudic source (<italic>Makkot</italic> 23b).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn115"><sup>115</sup> Or: from the mouth of <italic>gevurah</italic>, the God of power.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn116"><sup>116</sup> Perhaps should read: &#x201C;hewn out of&#x201D;; <italic>mi-shemo</italic> rather than <italic>bi-shemo</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn117"><sup>117</sup> &#x201C;Full&#x201D; and &#x201C;lacking,&#x201D; two ways of spelling Hebrew words.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn118"><sup>118</sup> These passages seem to indicate a later narrative voice, as was already noted by several medieval authors. See commentary of Abraham Ibn Ezra to Deut. 1:2.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn119"><sup>119</sup> b. <italic>Sanhedrin</italic> 99a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn120"><sup>120</sup> Deriving &#x201C;Lebanon&#x201D; from <italic>libbun</italic>, &#x201C;cleansing.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn121"><sup>121</sup> b. <italic>Yoma</italic> 38b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn122"><sup>122</sup> <italic>Zaddik</italic> or &#x201C;the righteous&#x201D; is <italic>yesod</italic>, the source of sefirotic energy as it flows into the <italic>shekhinah</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn123"><sup>123</sup> Genesis Rabbah 15:7.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn124"><sup>124</sup> No such interpretation is found in the extant rabbinic sources. It is also found, however, in Zohar 1:135b, a passage possibly dependent upon R. Ezra.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn125"><sup>125</sup> The three patriarchs represent <italic>&#x1E25;esed, gevurah</italic>, and <italic>tiferet</italic>, way-stations in the flow of life from Wisdom, the primal sefirotic font, to the <italic>shekhinah</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn126"><sup>126</sup> Return to your safe haven of halakhic expertise.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn127"><sup>127</sup> b. <italic>Sanhedrin</italic> 38b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn128"><sup>128</sup> Here the light imagery becomes that of wine. The primal flow is as perfect and undiminished as it was before creation, before the flow through the seven primal &#x201C;days.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn129"><sup>129</sup> &#x201C;North&#x201D; is kabbalistically <italic>din</italic>, divine judgment, and &#x201C;South&#x201D; is <italic>&#x1E25;esed</italic>, divine love.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn130"><sup>130</sup> <italic>&#x1E24;okhmah</italic> and <italic>binah</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn131"><sup>131</sup> The intermediate <italic>sefirot</italic>: Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob represent <italic>&#x1E25;esed, din</italic>, and <italic>tiferet</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn132"><sup>132</sup> Cant. Rabbah 4:31.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn133"><sup>133</sup> Literally &#x201C;an ascent for ascent.&#x201D; Or &#x201C;an ascent unto the Name.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn134"><sup>134</sup> The reference is to R. Isaac the Blind.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn135"><sup>135</sup> From Cant. 4:8 to 5:1.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn136"><sup>136</sup> Daniel 9:2.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn137"><sup>137</sup> v. Jer. 29:8. also look at Seder Olam ch. 30 ala Milikovsky.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn138"><sup>138</sup> We are dealing with <italic>ketiv/keri</italic>&#x2014;the written text is <italic>akhabed</italic> (I will be glorified) but it is pronounced <italic>akhabdah</italic> (I will glorify it). The difference between the text as written and pronounced is the letter <italic>heh</italic>, whose numerical equivalent is five.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn139"><sup>139</sup> b. <italic>Yoma</italic> 21b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn140"><sup>140</sup> See Daniel 8.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn141"><sup>141</sup> The verses refer to Cyrus.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn142"><sup>142</sup> b. <italic>Avodah Zarah</italic> 2b. &#x201C;Rome&#x201D; and &#x201C;Edom&#x201D; for the medieval Jews refer to Christendom, which they view as a continuation of the Roman empire.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn143"><sup>143</sup> See Megillah 12a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn144"><sup>144</sup> See p. 96 above.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn145"><sup>145</sup> On the eve of Passover, celebrating the first redemption but anticipating the last.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn146"><sup>146</sup> The popular medieval Hebrew adaptation of Josephus&#x2019;s <italic>History of the Jews</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn147"><sup>147</sup> Babylon equals Baghdad, the capital of Islam.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn148"><sup>148</sup> This would seem to be Christianity&#x2019;s appropriation of Jewish scripture. There has been considerable censorship of the manuscript in the following lines.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn149"><sup>149</sup> This variant reading is found only in the printed text. Alternatively: &#x201C;What is the meaning of the verse.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn150"><sup>150</sup> b. <italic>&#x1E24;agigah</italic> 16a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn151"><sup>151</sup> The following lines may be read as a progression through the <italic>sefirot</italic>, beginning here with <italic>keter</italic>, but the individual referents are kept somewhat murky.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn152"><sup>152</sup> He seems to mean that no one could be sufficiently satisfied in order to <italic>depart</italic> from such a vision. For that reason &#x201C;No man can see Me and live&#x201D; [Exod. 33:20].</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn153"><sup>153</sup> There follows a long quotation from <italic>Sefer ha-Bahi</italic>r, Scholem&#x2019;s sections 64, 67&#x2013;69.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn154"><sup>154</sup> b. <italic>Sanhedrin</italic> 65b. The reference is to the primary Talmudic source for the later <italic>Golem</italic> tradition.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn155"><sup>155</sup> A radically different and ironic reading. At the time of exile, the omnipresent divine &#x201C;descends&#x201D; as it were back into its recesses&#x2014;the source of creative manifestation&#x2014;divine Wisdom, from whence it must be reinvoked through prayer and the performance of the commandments.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn156"><sup>156</sup> <italic>Tiferet</italic>, the Beloved, &#x201C;descends&#x201D; from <italic>&#x1E25;okhmah</italic>, bringing sustenance for Himself and <italic>shekhinah</italic>, His garden.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn157"><sup>157</sup> Because of this cosmic exile, the <italic>sefirot</italic> turn &#x201C;upward&#x201D; and <italic>tzaddik</italic>, the righteous one [<italic>yesod</italic>] is not nourished by them.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn158"><sup>158</sup> <italic>&#x1E24;esed, gevurah, tiferet</italic>, symbolized by the Patriarchs.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn159"><sup>159</sup> <italic>Neta sha &#x2018;ashuim</italic>, after Isa. 5:7.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn160"><sup>160</sup> &#x201C;Lilies&#x201D; [<italic>shoshanim</italic>] is derived from &#x201C;six&#x201D; [<italic>shesh</italic>]. Each of the six intermediate or &#x201C;directional&#x201D; <italic>sefirot</italic>, multiplied by ten for the fact that the <italic>sefirot</italic> all contain one another, gives us the &#x201C;sixty queens.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn161"><sup>161</sup> I.e., water is separated from cloud and wind, the entire verse reading: &#x201C;He sets the rafters of His lofts in the waters, makes the clouds His chariot, moves on the wings of the wind.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn162"><sup>162</sup> The author is linking the ten <italic>sefirot</italic> of the upper world to these ten attributes which, according to the Talmud [<italic>&#x1E24;agigah</italic> 12a], underlay the creation of this world. They are heaven, earth, formlessness, void, darkness, light, water, wind, day, and night. This is one of several such lists of primordial entities to be found in rabbinic sources.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn163"><sup>163</sup> The depth above: <italic>omek rom</italic> &#x003D; <italic>keter; omek tahat</italic> &#x003D; <italic>malkhut</italic>. See the Commentary of R. Azriel to <italic>Sefer Yetzirah</italic> 1:5.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn164"><sup>164</sup> b. <italic>Sanhedrin</italic> 38b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn165"><sup>165</sup> See comments to Canticles 1:8.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn166"><sup>166</sup> This quotation is not found in the extant rabbinic sources.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn167"><sup>167</sup> b. <italic>Avodah Zarah</italic> 3b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn168"><sup>168</sup> &#x201C;Cloud [<italic>&#x2018;av</italic>] is numerically 72.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn169"><sup>169</sup> The gathering of the waters and the appearance of dry land occurs on the third day of creation.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn170"><sup>170</sup> <italic>Malkhut</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn171"><sup>171</sup> b. <italic>Sanhedrin</italic> 38b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn172"><sup>172</sup> Lit. <italic>mayim be-mayim</italic>, water within water.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn173"><sup>173</sup> This alludes to the doctrine of <italic>shemitot</italic>, or cosmic sabbaths, claiming that the world goes through a series of seven-thousand year cycles and then returns to its source.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn174"><sup>174</sup> The repetition in Ps. 29:3 is not direct. There may be an allusion here to the tale of R. Akiva&#x2019;s ascent to the <italic>pardes</italic>, as described in b. <italic>&#x1E24;agigah</italic> 14b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn175"><sup>175</sup> He derives &#x2018;<italic>erets</italic> from <italic>r-ts-h</italic>, meaning &#x201C;will.&#x201D; <italic>Keter</italic> is extended to meet <italic>malkhut</italic>. The circle of the <italic>sefirot</italic> is thus closed.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn176"><sup>176</sup> The <italic>sefirot</italic> as <italic>kelim</italic>, or the ordering of the sefirotic structure, &#x201C;precedes&#x201D; (better &#x201C;underlies&#x201D;) the actual flow of divine energy into these channels.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn177"><sup>177</sup> <italic>Tiferet</italic>, the male energy of the central column, reaches into the heights of <italic>keter</italic>, the Will that is above the upper reaches of Mind, and flows down through <italic>yesod</italic>, its sexual manifestation, into <italic>malkhut</italic>, the &#x201C;garden&#x201D; or female.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn178"><sup>178</sup> Hebrew term obscure.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn179"><sup>179</sup> Here &#x201C;trees&#x201D; and &#x201C;cedars&#x201D; are taken as symbols of the <italic>sefirot</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn180"><sup>180</sup> The seven lower <italic>sefirot</italic> are born of <italic>binah</italic>, the third <italic>sefirah</italic>, or possibly referring to <italic>tiferet</italic>, the third of the seven upper &#x201C;days.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn181"><sup>181</sup> <italic>Sefirot</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn182"><sup>182</sup> Hebrew obscure; translation conjectural.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn183"><sup>183</sup> Both <italic>tiferet</italic>, the sun or power of day, and <italic>shekhinah</italic>, the moon or power of night, rule by the power of <italic>hokhmah</italic>, source of the flow that animates them.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn184"><sup>184</sup> b. <italic>Hagigah</italic> 13b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn185"><sup>185</sup> The author plays on the inconsistency of number in these texts.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn186"><sup>186</sup> Bereshit Rabbah 9:5.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn187"><sup>187</sup> b. <italic>Berakhot</italic> 46b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn188"><sup>188</sup> The seventh extension or direction is mysterious, beyond the six directions of space. It seems here to be the direction called &#x201C;inward&#x201D; or &#x201C;innermost.&#x201D; the center from which all the others radiate.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn189"><sup>189</sup> Sefer Yetsirah 4:2.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn190"><sup>190</sup> A play on words, reading <italic>ve-yekhulu</italic>, &#x201C;were completed,&#x201D; as derived from <italic>keli</italic>, &#x201C;vessel.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn191"><sup>191</sup> b. <italic>Berakhot</italic> 17a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn192"><sup>192</sup> b. <italic>Berakhot</italic> 9b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn193"><sup>193</sup> Sefer Yesirah 5:1 uses this term (based on Deut. 33:27) for twelve directions, a refinement of the original six.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn194"><sup>194</sup> <italic>Ketubut</italic> 110b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn195"><sup>195</sup> The text may be assuming the special relationship, well known in later Kabbalah, between the female and <italic>din</italic> or &#x201C;justice.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn196"><sup>196</sup> Kiddushin 76a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn197"><sup>197</sup> Midrash Tan&#x1E25;uma, Kedoshim 12.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn198"><sup>198</sup> <italic>Shekhinah</italic> is the power of providence, coming forth from &#x201C;heaven&#x201D; or <italic>tiferet.</italic></ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn199"><sup>199</sup> Nuts grow in clusters that cannot easily be separated.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn200"><sup>200</sup> The text is somewhat obscure, but seems to mean that Israel, because of the way they related to one another, brought upon themselves the Seleucid oppressor.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn201"><sup>201</sup> Most likely <italic>&#x1E25;okhmah</italic> as <italic>ruah hayyim</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn202"><sup>202</sup> The <italic>sefirot</italic> and Israel below.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn203"><sup>203</sup> Rosh ha-Shanah 31a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn204"><sup>204</sup> Baba Batra 99a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn205"><sup>205</sup> In <italic>Berakhot</italic> 6a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn206"><sup>206</sup> The word <italic>buz</italic> is interpreted to mean &#x201C;loot&#x201D; or &#x201C;bounty&#x201D; rather than &#x201C;scorn.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn207"><sup>207</sup> The sixth millennium, thought by many to be the end of exile, began in 1240, shortly before the completion of this commentary.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn208"><sup>208</sup> An eschatological discussion of Zech. 9:9 etc. has been ellipted.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn209"><sup>209</sup> Midrash Tanhuma, <italic>shemot</italic> 10.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn210"><sup>210</sup> <italic>Aikhah</italic>, the opening word (and Hebrew name) of Lamentations, is read as a word (<italic>Ei</italic>) and an abbreviation (<italic>KoH</italic>&#x003D;25) to mean &#x201C;Where is twenty-five?&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn211"><sup>211</sup> To the <italic>shekhinah</italic>, referred to in the text literally with the appellation &#x201C;<italic>koh</italic>.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn212"><sup>212</sup> <italic>Et</italic> is an untranslated participle indicating the direct object.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn213"><sup>213</sup> The word &#x2018;<italic>af</italic>, in this case translated &#x201C;really,&#x201D; can also be a noun meaning &#x201C;anger,&#x201D; and thus the name of a destructive angel.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn214"><sup>214</sup> The note on <italic>ishah</italic> is a <italic>pazer</italic> and is an ascending crescendo recited three times.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn215"><sup>215</sup> Reading <italic>kol be-Ramah</italic> (&#x201C;a voice in Ramah&#x201D;) as <italic>kol be-ruma</italic> &#x2018;(&#x201C;a voice in the heights&#x201D;).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn216"><sup>216</sup> Referring to the mixed multitude, held responsible for the sins of Israel in the wilderness. See Prov. 30:23.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn217"><sup>217</sup> b. <italic>Berakhot</italic> 3a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn218"><sup>218</sup> See b. <italic>Sanhedrin</italic> 97a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn219"><sup>219</sup> See b. <italic>Sanhedrin</italic> 24a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn220"><sup>220</sup> <italic>Baraitot</italic> are quotations of early rabbinic teaching within the Talmud.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn221"><sup>221</sup> A fast day commemorating the Romans&#x2019; breaching the walls of Jerusalem.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn222"><sup>222</sup> The great summer fast day in memory of the destruction of the First and Second Temples.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn223"><sup>223</sup> b. <italic>Sanhedrin</italic> 81a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn224"><sup>224</sup> The ten martyrs of the Hadrianic persecution.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn225"><sup>225</sup> The reincarnation of the ten sons of Jacob as the ten martyrs.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn226"><sup>226</sup> See b. <italic>Avodah Zarah</italic> 16b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn227"><sup>227</sup> <italic>The Kabbalah in the Writings of R. Bahya ben Asher Ibn Halawa.</italic> Jerusalem: Kiryat Sepher, 1970.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn228"><sup>228</sup> Construct clauses occur when two or more words, usually nouns, are conjoined to form a compound idea. The opening phrase of the Hebrew text of Gen. 1:1 is a prepositional phrase <italic>bereshit</italic>, &#x201C;in the beginning of,&#x201D; followed immediately by the verb <italic>bara</italic>, &#x201C;created.&#x201D; The prepositional phrase lacks nominal closure. Rashi resolves the grammatical difficulty by reading <italic>bara</italic> as a gerund on the order of Hosea 1:2. Thus, the opening words of Genesis are to be read as &#x201C;in the beginning of God&#x2019;s creating heaven and earth.&#x201D; The Jewish Publication Society translation (henceforth: JPS) essentially adopts Rashi&#x2019;s interpretation and translates Gen. 1:1 as: &#x201C;When God began to create the heavens and the earth&#x2026;.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn229"><sup>229</sup> Tan&#x1E25;uma Buber, <italic>bereshit</italic> 1.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn230"><sup>230</sup> The classic Aramaic Targum or translation of the Pentateuch.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn231"><sup>231</sup> Onkylos is following the second half of the verse: &#x201C;nor put a curse upon a chieftain of your people,&#x201D; treating the text as a parallelism.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn232"><sup>232</sup> The letter <italic>yod</italic> [<span dir="rtl">&#x05D9;</span>] is numerically ten; the reference is to the multiplicity of the ten <italic>sefirot</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn233"><sup>233</sup> The yod indicates plural in this possessive form, referring both to the same plurality as in <italic>Elohim</italic>, but also to its meaning as &#x201C;ten&#x201D; <italic>sefirot</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn234"><sup>234</sup> b. <italic>Kiddushin</italic> 40b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn235"><sup>235</sup> Rather than representing contentless chaos and the forces of entropy, <italic>bohu</italic> or the void represents the potentially emergent aspects of primordial reality.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn236"><sup>236</sup> Though in the Platonic system, whence all discussion of the four elements derives, fire is light and represents the most elevated of the four, Bahya sees a negative aspect attributed to fire in the biblical sources. Therefore, <italic>Elohim</italic> is associated rather with &#x201C;wind&#x201D; or air.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn237"><sup>237</sup> See b. <italic>Baba Batra</italic> 15a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn238"><sup>238</sup> Although this is nominally the Midrashic section, Bahya already begins to build his argument for a Kabbalistic reading of the verse. Kabbalists so insinuated their readings into the earlier rabbinic tradition that it is sometimes difficult to know where Midrash ends and Kabbalah begins. This, of course, was precisely their intent.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn239"><sup>239</sup> Thus <italic>bereshit</italic> would consonantally divide into <span dir="rtl">&#x05E8;&#x05E9;&#xFB30;</span> and <span dir="rtl">&#x05EA;</span>&#x2019;, which numerically equals 410.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn240"><sup>240</sup> b. <italic>Pesahim</italic> 54a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn241"><sup>241</sup> Here he precedes forward to a Midrashic (mostly eschatological) reading of Gen. 1:3&#x2013;4.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn242"><sup>242</sup> Bereshit Rabbah 2:5.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn243"><sup>243</sup> A saying attributed to Aristotle, widely quoted by Jewish thinkers throughout the Middle Ages.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn244"><sup>244</sup> b. <italic>Sukkah</italic> 49a. Again a purely rabbinic reference, but one that has Kabbalistic echoes. The phrase <italic>bara shit</italic> is taken by the Zohar to mean &#x201C;He created six,&#x201D; referring to the six <italic>sefirot</italic> clustered around <italic>tiferet</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn245"><sup>245</sup> Avot 5:6.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn246"><sup>246</sup> Avot 5:1. In the Kabbalah the ten utterances of creation are often homologized into the ten <italic>sefirot</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn247"><sup>247</sup> It could be read as <italic>be-tishre</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn248"><sup>248</sup> And R. Joshua said it was created in Nissan. This debate reflects the dual calendar of Judaism. The Biblical calendar begins in the spring, Aviv or Nissan being the first month. The Babylonian calendar, adopted by Jews at a very early date, starts the year in the fall, with Tishre, the seventh month on the Bblical calendar.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn249"><sup>249</sup> On Rosh Hashanah, the first of Tishre. b. <italic>Rosh Hashanah</italic> 10b&#x2013;11a,27a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn250"><sup>250</sup> Ma &#x2018;aseh Merkavah, Chapter 7, in Wertheimer, <italic>Battey Midrashot</italic>, v. 1, p. 61. Schaefer, <italic>Synopsis zur Hekhalot-Literatur</italic>, v228, paragraph 68.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn251"><sup>251</sup> v. chap. 2.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn252"><sup>252</sup> The <italic>molad</italic>, or the moment when the moon is directly between earth and sun and thus totally invisible, is the technical beginning of the new month. For purposes of this fixing, the hour divided into 1080 parts.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn253"><sup>253</sup> The point is that the first of <italic>Tishre</italic> is supposed to be the date when Adam and Eve were created. But since that was the &#x201C;sixth day&#x201D; of creation, we have to count back five preceding days to get to the actual Beginning. But it is impossible to do that, to determine the moment of creation other than mathematically, since until the fourth day there were no luminaries which would allow for the demarcation of days.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn254"><sup>254</sup> These are the sixth and tenth <italic>sefirot</italic>: <italic>tiferet</italic> (&#x201C;splendor&#x201D;) and <italic>malkhut</italic> (&#x201C;kingdom&#x201D;), respectively.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn255"><sup>255</sup> The numerical value of the letter <italic>bet</italic> is two, alluding to the fact that <italic>&#x1E25;okhmah</italic> is the second rung in the chain of divine emanation.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn256"><sup>256</sup> The beginning of the top line of the letter <italic>bet</italic> points slightly upward.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn257"><sup>257</sup> Sefer Yetsirah 1:1.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn258"><sup>258</sup> Three nominal forms derivable from the root S-F-R [<span dir="rtl">&#x05E1;&#x05E4;&#x05D3;</span>].</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn259"><sup>259</sup> <italic>Sippur</italic> means &#x201C;tale&#x201D; or &#x201C;narration;&#x201D; these lower <italic>sefirot</italic> can be the subject of narration.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn260"><sup>260</sup> <italic>Vav</italic> [<span dir="rtl">&#x05D5;</span>] is the sixth letter, representing the number six. <italic>Tiferet</italic> also represents a cluster of six central <italic>sefirot,</italic> those between <italic>binah</italic> and <italic>malkhut. binah</italic> and <italic>malkhut</italic> are the upper and lower female <italic>sefirot.</italic> The six forces between them are a male cluster; the form of the letter vav may itself be understood as a symbol of masculinity.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn261"><sup>261</sup> The word &#x201C;there&#x201D; [<span dir="rtl">&#xFB2A;&#x05E1;</span>; <italic>sham</italic>] appears twice in the verse, along with &#x201C;gave&#x201D; [<span dir="rtl">&#xFB2B;&#x05E1;</span>; <italic>sam</italic>]. Each of these is numerically 340, representing <italic>sefer, sefor,</italic> and <italic>sippur.</italic> This passage, which is taken by the midrash as representing a pre-Sinaitic giving of law and teachings, here is seen as the moment when the sefirotic secrets of Kabbalah are handed over to Israel.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn262"><sup>262</sup> The term is <italic>teshuvah,</italic> meaning &#x201C;return to God&#x201D; or &#x201C;penitence.&#x201D; The kabbalists give it a cosmic meaning: the return of all things to their source. This third <italic>sefirah,</italic> here designated as <italic>teshuvah,</italic> but more often called <italic>binah,</italic> is that primal source to which all return.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn263"><sup>263</sup> <italic>Malkhut,</italic> the tenth <italic>sefirah.</italic></ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn264"><sup>264</sup> That is, she is the middle of five.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn265"><sup>265</sup> <italic>Gedullah</italic> and <italic>gevurah,</italic> the fourth and fifth <italic>sefirot,</italic> also known as <italic>&#x1E25;esed</italic> (&#x201C;grace&#x201D;) and <italic>din</italic> (&#x201C;judgment), the right and left &#x201C;hands&#x201D; of the divine.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn266"><sup>266</sup> <italic>Tiferet,</italic> the sixth <italic>sefirah.</italic></ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn267"><sup>267</sup> <italic>Netza&#x1E25;</italic> and <italic>hod,</italic> the seventh and eighth <italic>sefirot.</italic></ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn268"><sup>268</sup> <italic>&#x1E92;addik</italic> or <italic>yesod</italic> (&#x201C;foundation&#x201D;), the ninth <italic>sefirah.</italic></ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn269"><sup>269</sup> <italic>Malkhut</italic> (&#x201C;kingdom&#x201D;), the tenth and feminine receptive <italic>sefirah.</italic></ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn270"><sup>270</sup> b. <italic>Rosh Hashanah</italic> 31a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn271"><sup>271</sup> ABG (numerically &#x201C;six&#x201D;) <italic>yitats</italic> (&#x201C;he will destroy&#x201D;).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn272"><sup>272</sup> The reference is to <italic>binah,</italic> the third <italic>sefirah,</italic> which is the source of the six lower <italic>sefirot</italic>, &#x201C;the heavens.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn273"><sup>273</sup> b. <italic>Berakhot</italic> 34a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn274"><sup>274</sup> b. <italic>Pesahim</italic> 54a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn275"><sup>275</sup> Various letters in this verse refer to the count of 2, 5, 204.</ftnote>
</chapter>
</book>
