<book>
<chapter>
<title>THE WISDOM OF BEN SIRA.</title>
<p><bold>3.</bold> 6 . . . . . . . . that honoureth his mother. <r1>Fol. A 1 recto</r1></p>
<p>8 My son, in word and in deed honour thy father;</p>
<p>That all blessings may overtake thee.</p>
<p>9 The blessing of a father settleth the root;</p>
<p>But the curse of a mother plucketh up the plant.</p>
<p>10 Take not honour to thyself by the shame of thy father;</p>
<p>For it is no honour unto thee.</p>
<p>11 The honour of his father is a man&#x2019;s honour;</p>
<p>And he that curseth his mother doth greatly sin.</p>
<p>12 My son, be stedfast in honouring thy father;</p>
<p>And forsake him not all the days of thy life.</p>
<p>13 Yea, and though his mind fail, bear with (<italic>or</italic> help) him;</p>
<p>And dishonour him not all the days of his life (H).</p>
<p>14 Benefaction to a father shall not be blotted out;</p>
<p>But it shall be planted instead of sin.</p>
<p>15 In the day of affliction it shall be remembered unto thee,</p>
<p>As heat upon hoar frost, to do away thine iniquities.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>ABBREVIATIONS.</title>
<p>The letters G H S stand for Greek, Hebrew, and Syriac.</p>
<p>H is used of Ecclesiasticus only, and M for the margin of H.</p>
<p>G in Ecclesiasticus is in general Fritzsche&#x2019;s text.</p>
<p>E refers to Edersheim on Ecclus. in the <italic>Speaker&#x2019;s Commentary.</italic></p>
<p>A note of interrogation in brackets (?) means that the sense is doubtful, or that a conjectural reading of H has been adopted.</p>
<p>29 A wise heart will understand parables of the wise;</p>
<p>And the ear that hearkeneth to wisdom shall rejoice.</p>
<p>30 Waters quench flaming fire;</p>
<p>So righteousness maketh atonement for sin.</p>
<p>31 Whoso doeth good, it shall meet him in his ways (?);</p>
<p>And in the time that he tottereth he shall find a stay.</p>
<p><bold>4.</bold> 1 My son, mock not at the life of the poor (<italic>or</italic> of affliction);</p>
<p>And make not the soul of him that is poor and bitter of soul (H) to pine.</p>
<p>2 Vex not the spirit (?) of the soul that lacketh;</p>
<p>And hide not thyself from one that is crushed (?) in soul.</p>
<p>3<sup>a</sup> Trouble not the bowels of him that is humbled;</p>
<p>And pain not the inward part of the poor.</p>
<p>3<sup>b</sup> Withhold not a gift from thy needy;</p>
<p>4<sup>a</sup> And thou shalt not despise the supplications of the miserable;</p>
<p>5<sup>b</sup> And thou shalt not give him place to curse thee.</p>
<p>6 He that is bitter of spirit crieth in the anguish of his soul;</p>
<p>And his Rock (H) shall hear the voice of his cry.</p>
<p>7 Make thyself (?) beloved of the congregation;</p>
<p>And to a potentate moreover bow the head.</p>
<p>8 Incline thine ear to the poor;</p>
<p>And answer him Peace with meekness.</p>
<p>9 Save the oppressed from his oppressors;</p>
<p>And let not thy spirit loathe right judgement.</p>
<p>10<sup>a</sup> Be as a father to orphans;</p>
<p>And instead of a husband to widows.</p>
<p>10<sup>c</sup> And God shall call thee Son; <r1>Fol. A 1 verso</r1></p>
<p>And shall be gracious to thee, and deliver thee from the pit.</p>
<p>11 Wisdom teacheth (H) her sons;</p>
<p>And testifieth (H) to all that attend to her.</p>
<p>12 They that love her love life;</p>
<p>And they that seek her shall obtain favour from the Lord.</p>
<p>13 And they that retain her shall find honour from the Lord;</p>
<p>And shall have grace shewed them by the blessing of the Lord.</p>
<p>14 Ministers of holiness are her ministers;</p>
<p>And God loveth them that love her (?).</p>
<p>16 For he that despiseth his father doeth presumptuously;</p>
<p>And he that curseth his mother angereth his Creator.</p>
<p>17 My son, in thy wealth walk in meekness (H S);</p>
<p>And thou shalt be more beloved than he that giveth gifts.</p>
<p>18 Minish thy soul from all the great things of the world;</p>
<p>And before God thou shalt find mercy.</p>
<p>20<sup>a</sup> For great is the mercy of God;</p>
<p>19<sup>b</sup> And he revealeth his secret to the meek.</p>
<p>21 Search not the things that are too wonderful for thee;</p>
<p>And seek not that which is hid from thee.</p>
<p>22 What thou art permitted, think thereupon;</p>
<p>But thou hast no business with the secret things.</p>
<p>23 And intrude not into that which is beyond thee;</p>
<p>For thou hast been shewed that which is too great for thee.</p>
<p>24 For many are the conceits of the sons of men;</p>
<p>And the imaginations of thoughts (H) that make them to err.</p>
<p>26 A hard heart shall fare ill at the last;</p>
<p>But he that loveth good things will guide himself therein.</p>
<p>27 Many are the sorrows of a hard heart;</p>
<p>And he that is confident addeth iniquity to iniquity.</p>
<p>25 Without the apple of the eye light faileth;</p>
<p>And without knowledge wisdom faileth.</p>
<p>28 Haste not to heal the stroke of the scorner;</p>
<p>For there is no healing it: for he is a plant of evil planting.</p>
<p>28 Unto death contend (?) for justice;</p>
<p>And the Lord shall fight for thee.</p>
<p>28<sup>(1)</sup> Be not called a double dealer;</p>
<p>And slander not with (?) thy tongue.</p>
<p>29 Be not boastful with thy tongue;</p>
<p>And slack and negligent (?) in thy business.</p>
<p>30 Be not as a dog (G lion) in thine house;</p>
<p>And strange and fearful in thy business.</p>
<p>31 Let not thine hand be opened to receive;</p>
<p>And clenched in the midst of giving.</p>
<p><bold>5.</bold> 1 Stay not upon thy strength (<italic>or</italic> wealth);</p>
<p>And say not, It is in the power of my hand.</p>
<p>1<sup>(2)</sup> Stay not upon thy force;</p>
<p>To go after the desire of thy soul.</p>
<p>2 Go not after thy heart and thine eyes;</p>
<p>To walk in the pleasures of wickedness.</p>
<p>3 Say not, Who can withstand my (G S) strength?</p>
<p>For the Lord avengeth (H seeketh) them that are persecuted.</p>
<p>4 Say not, I have sinned, and who (?) shall do aught unto me,</p>
<p>For God is slow to anger?</p>
<p>4<sup>(1)</sup> Say not, The Lord is merciful;</p>
<p>And he will blot out all mine iniquities.</p>
<p>5 Trust not to forgiveness;</p>
<p>To add iniquity to iniquity.</p>
<p>6<sup>a</sup> Nor say, His mercy is great:</p>
<p>He will forgive the multitude of mine iniquities.</p>
<p>6<sup>c</sup> For mercy and anger are with him;</p>
<p>And his displeasure shall rest upon (?) the wicked.</p>
<p>7<sup>a</sup> Make no tarrying to turn unto him;</p>
<p>And put not off (?) from day to day.</p>
<p>7<sup>c</sup> For suddenly shall his indignation go forth;</p>
<p>And in the day of vengeance thou shalt perish.</p>
<p>8 Trust not on riches of falsehood;</p>
<p>For they shall not profit in the day of wrath.</p>
<p>9 Be not winnowing with every wind,</p>
<p>And turning the way of the stream (H).</p>
<p>10 Be assured in thine own mind;</p>
<p>And let thy word be one. <r1>Fol. A 2 recto</r1></p>
<p>11 Be swift to give ear;</p>
<p>And with patience of spirit return answer.</p>
<p>15 He that heareth me shall judge truth (G nations);</p>
<p>And he that giveth ear to me shall dwell in my chamber within.</p>
<p>17<sup>a</sup> For I will go with him, making myself strange;</p>
<p>17<sup>c</sup> And at the first I (H he) will try him with temptations.</p>
<p>17<sup>d</sup> And what time his heart is filled with me;</p>
<p>18 I will turn and direct him,</p>
<p>And reveal unto him of my secrets.</p>
<p>19 If he turn away and decline from me (?),</p>
<p>I will train him with fetters (<italic>or</italic> restraints).</p>
<p>19<sup>(1)</sup> If he turn away from after me,</p>
<p>I will cast him off, and deliver him to the spoilers.</p>
<p>20 My son, observe season and time (?);</p>
<p>And fear evil, and be not shamefaced unto thyself.</p>
<p>21 For there is a shame (?) that ladeth with iniquity;</p>
<p>And there is a shame that is honour and grace.</p>
<p>22 Have not respect of thine own person;</p>
<p>And stumble (H) not at thine offences.</p>
<p>23 Withhold not a word (<italic>or</italic> to speak) in season (?);</p>
<p>Nor ever conceal thy wisdom.</p>
<p>24 For by speech wisdom is made known;</p>
<p>And understanding by the answer of the tongue.</p>
<p>25<sup>a</sup> Gainsay not the truth (H God);</p>
<p>And submit thyself unto God.</p>
<p>26 Be not ashamed to turn from iniquity;</p>
<p>And stand not against a stream.</p>
<p>27 Lay not thyself down for a fool to tread upon;</p>
<p>And be not contrary before rulers.</p>
<p>27<sup>(1)</sup> Sit not with one that judgeth unrighteously;</p>
<p>For according to his pleasure (?) thou shalt judge with him.</p>
<p>8 For there is a friend that is for a season;</p>
<p>And that will not (?) continue in the day of affliction.</p>
<p>9 There is a friend that turneth to an enemy;</p>
<p>And he will make bare the strife to thy reproach.</p>
<p>10 There is a friend that is a companion at the table;</p>
<p>But he will not be found in the day of adversity.</p>
<p>11 In thy prosperity he is as thou art;</p>
<p>And in thine adversity he will remove away from thee.</p>
<p>12 If evil overtake thee, he will turn against thee;</p>
<p>And will hide himself from thy face.</p>
<p>13 Separate thyself from thine enemies;</p>
<p>And beware of thy friends.</p>
<p>14 A faithful friend is a firm friend;</p>
<p>And he that findeth him hath found a treasure.</p>
<p>15 There is no exchange for a faithful friend;</p>
<p>Nor price that can be weighed for his goodness.</p>
<p>16 A faithful friend is a balm (G S) of life;</p>
<p>He that feareth God shall obtain it.</p>
<p>17<sup>b</sup> For as he is, so is his neighbour;</p>
<p>17<sup>b(1)</sup> And as his name, so are his works.</p>
<p>19<sup>a</sup> As one that plougheth and as one that reapeth approach unto her;</p>
<p>And wait for the abundance of her increase.</p>
<p>19<sup>c</sup> For in the tillage of her thou shalt toil a little;</p>
<p>And on the morrow (H) thou shalt eat her fruit.</p>
<p>20 Rough is she to the fool;</p>
<p>And he that is void of understanding cannot bear her.</p>
<p>21 As a burdensome weight shall she be upon him;</p>
<p>And he will not tarry to cast her away.</p>
<p>22 For discipline is according to its (?) name;</p>
<p>And to the more part she is not plain (<italic>or</italic> right).</p>
<p>12 If it be in thee, answer thy neighbour;</p>
<p>And if not, be thy hand upon thy mouth.</p>
<p>13 Honour and disgrace are in the hand (?) of talk;</p>
<p>And the tongue of a man is his fall.</p>
<p>14<sup>a</sup> Be not called a double dealer;</p>
<p>And with thy tongue slander not a neighbour.</p>
<p>14<sup>c</sup> For for the thief was created shame;</p>
<p>And sore reproach for (G S) the double dealer.</p>
<p>15 Little or much do not corruptly (H);</p>
<p><bold>6</bold>. 1<sup>a</sup> And instead of a friend become not an enemy.</p>
<p>1<sup>b</sup> Reproach shall inherit (H) an evil name and disgrace:</p>
<p>So an evil man that is a double dealer.</p>
<p>2 Fall not into the hand of thine appetite;</p>
<p>That it should consume thy strength like an ox (?).</p>
<p>3 It shall eat thy leaves and uproot thy fruit;</p>
<p>And leave thee like a dry tree.</p>
<p>4 For fierce appetite corrupteth them that have it;</p>
<p>And the joy of an enemy overtaketh (H) them.</p>
<p>5 Many a friend doth a sweet palate make;</p>
<p>And gracious lips that greet (?) with peace.</p>
<p>6 Be they that are at peace with thee many;</p>
<p>But he that hath thy secret one of a thousand.</p>
<p>7 Hast thou gotten a friend? get him in trial (?);</p>
<p>And be not in haste to trust on him.</p>
<p>4 Seek not of God dominion;</p>
<p>Nor likewise of a king a seat of honour.</p>
<p>5 Justify not thyself before God (H a king);</p>
<p>And before a king profess not understanding.</p>
<p>6<sup>a</sup> Seek not to be a ruler;</p>
<p>If thou hast not ability to quell pride.</p>
<p>6<sup>c</sup> Lest thou fear the person of the noble;</p>
<p>And suffer lucre to corrupt thine integrity (?).</p>
<p>7 Condemn not thyself in the congregation at the gate (?);</p>
<p>And cast not thyself down in the assembly.</p>
<p>8 Conspire not to commit a second sin;</p>
<p>For in one thou shalt not be unpunished.</p>
<p>15 Loathe not appointed service of laborious work;</p>
<p>For it hath been apportioned of God (?).</p>
<p>10 Be not impatient (H short) in prayer;</p>
<p>And in almsgiving hesitate not (?).</p>
<p>11 Despise not a man that is in bitterness of spirit;</p>
<p>Remember that there is one that lifteth up and casteth down.</p>
<p>12 Devise not injury against a brother;</p>
<p>And likewise neither against a companion nor a neighbour.</p>
<p>13 Love not to make any manner of (?) lie;</p>
<p>For the consequence (H hope) thereof shall not be pleasant.</p>
<p>14 Prate (?) not (<italic>or</italic> Be not familiar) in a congregation of princes;</p>
<p>And repeat (?) not a word in prayer.</p>
<p>16 Esteem not thyself among the men of thy (?) people;</p>
<p>Remember that wrath will not tarry (?).</p>
<p>22<sup>(1)</sup> A potter&#x2019;s vessel is for the furnace to bake (?);</p>
<p>And like unto it, a man is according to his thought.</p>
<p>22<sup>(2)</sup> Upon the bough (?) of a tree will be its fruit;</p>
<p>So the thought of a man is according to his mind (?).</p>
<p>25 Incline thy shoulder, and carry her;</p>
<p>And loathe not her cords (?).</p>
<p>27 Search and examine, seek and find;</p>
<p>And hold her fast, and let her not go.</p>
<p>28 For afterward thou shalt find her rest;</p>
<p>And she (?) shall turn to a delight unto thee.</p>
<p>29 And her net shall be to thee a strong defence;</p>
<p>And her cordage robes of fine gold.</p>
<p>30 Her yoke (G Upon her) is an ornament (G) of gold;</p>
<p>And her bands are thread of purple.</p>
<p><l1>Fol. A 2 verso</l1> 31 Thou shalt put her on as robes of honour;</p>
<p>And crown thyself with her as a crown of beauty.</p>
<p>32 If thou be desirous, my son, thou mayest become wise;</p>
<p>And if thou apply thy heart, thou shalt be prudent.</p>
<p>33 If thou art wishful to hear (H);</p>
<p>And incline thine ear (H), thou shalt be instructed.</p>
<p>35 Be desirous to hear all discourse;</p>
<p>And let no proverb of understanding escape thee.</p>
<p>36 See who (?) hath understanding, and seek him early;</p>
<p>And let thy foot wear my (H) threshold.</p>
<p>37<sup>a</sup> And let thy mind be upon the fear of the Most High;</p>
<p>And meditate (?) in his commandments continually.</p>
<p>37<sup>c</sup> And he shall make thy heart discerning (H);</p>
<p>And make thee wise according as thou desirest.</p>
<p><bold>7.</bold> 1 Do not evil to thyself, and evil shall not (?) overtake thee;</p>
<p>2 Keep far from iniquity, and it shall turn aside from thee.</p>
<p>3 Sow not upon the furrows of unrighteousness (?);</p>
<p>Lest thou reap it sevenfold.</p>
<p><bold>11.</bold> 34<sup>b</sup> And estrange thee to them that are dear to thee. <r1>Fol. A 3 recto</r1></p>
<p><bold>12.</bold> 2 Do good to the righteous, and find recompense;</p>
<p>If not from him, from the Lord.</p>
<p>3 No good cometh of bestowing upon (?) him that is wicked;</p>
<p>And (?) that hath not done righteousness.</p>
<p>5<sup>d</sup> A double portion of evil shalt thou obtain in time of need</p>
<p>By all the good thou shalt have brought him.</p>
<p>5<sup>b</sup> Weapons of war (H S) give not to him;</p>
<p>Wherefore should he fight with them against thee?</p>
<p>6 For God also hateth them that are evil;</p>
<p>And to the wicked he will repay vengeance.</p>
<p>7 Give to the good, and withhold from the evil;</p>
<p>4 Honour the humble, and give not to the proud.</p>
<p>8 A friend will not be known in prosperity;</p>
<p>And an enemy will not be hid in adversity.</p>
<p>9 In a man&#x2019;s prosperity even an enemy is a friend;</p>
<p>And in his adversity even a friend separateth himself.</p>
<p>10 Never trust an enemy;</p>
<p>For like as brass his wickedness cankereth.</p>
<p>11<sup>a</sup> And even though he hearken to thee, and go crouching;</p>
<p>Give thy heart to fear him.</p>
<p>11<sup>c</sup> Be to him as one that revealeth a mystery (H S);</p>
<p>And he shall not find opportunity to harm thee.</p>
<p>And know thou the end of jealousy (H S).</p>
<p>17 Abase pride very exceedingly;</p>
<p>For the hope of man is the worm (H S).</p>
<p>17<sup>(1)</sup> Be not in haste to say, A breach (?) <italic>is upon me</italic>;</p>
<p>Commit thyself unto God, and delight in his way.</p>
<p>18 Exchange not a friend at a price;</p>
<p>Neither a brother that is attached (<italic>or</italic> doubted) for gold of Ophir.</p>
<p>19 Despise (<italic>or</italic> Reject) not a wise wife;</p>
<p>Seeing she is well-favoured above rubies.</p>
<p>20 Evil entreat not a servant that laboureth truly (?);</p>
<p>Nor a hireling that giveth his soul (?).</p>
<p>21 Love a wise servant as thyself:</p>
<p>Withhold not liberty from him.</p>
<p>22 Hast thou a beast? see that thine eye be upon it (?);</p>
<p>And if it be trusty (?), keep it.</p>
<p>23 Hast thou sons? instruct them;</p>
<p>And marry wives to them in their youth.</p>
<p>24 Hast thou daughters? guard their flesh;</p>
<p>And make not thy face bright unto them.</p>
<p>25 Give away a daughter, and away with a trouble (?);</p>
<p>But join her to a man of understanding.</p>
<p>26 Hast thou a wife? abominate (H) her not;</p>
<p>Hast thou one that is hated? trust her not.</p>
<p>29 With all thy heart fear . . . . . . . . . .</p>
<p>&#x002A;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#x002A;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#x002A;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#x002A;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#x002A;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#x002A;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#x002A;</p>
<p>2<sup>c(1)</sup> What fellowship shall the rich have with the poor?</p>
<p>3 The rich doeth a wrong, and he boasteth himself of it (?):</p>
<p>The poor is wronged, and he must entreat withal (?).</p>
<p>4 If thou be right for him, he will make thee serve him;</p>
<p>And if thou be brought low, he will be sparing of thee.</p>
<p>5 If thou have substance (?), he will speak thee fair;</p>
<p>And he will impoverish thee, and will not be sorry.</p>
<p>6 Hath he need of thee? then he will toy with thee (?);</p>
<p>And he will smile upon thee, and encourage thee.</p>
<p>7 So long as it profiteth he will cajole thee. <r1>Fol. A 3 verso</r1></p>
<p>Twice or thrice he will shew thee reverence (?);</p>
<p>And then he will look at thee and pass thee by (?);</p>
<p>And will wag his head at thee.</p>
<p>8 Take heed that thou be not urgent (?) overmuch;</p>
<p>And be not like to them that lack intelligence.</p>
<p>9 Doth a noble draw near? be thou distant;</p>
<p>And so much the more he will approach thee.</p>
<p>10 Come not near, lest thou be put far off;</p>
<p>And stand not far off, lest thou be forgotten (G).</p>
<p>11 Make not bold to be free (?) with him;</p>
<p>And mistrust thou his much talk.</p>
<p>11<sup>c</sup> For with his much talk maketh he trial of thee;</p>
<p>And he will smile upon thee, and search thee out.</p>
<p>12 He that is cruel will speak peace (?) and spare not;</p>
<p>While he plotteth a plot against the life of many.</p>
<p>13 Take heed and beware;</p>
<p>And go not with men of violence.</p>
<p>12<sup>a</sup> Make him not to stand beside thee:</p>
<p>Wherefore should he thrust thee away, and stand in thy place?</p>
<p>12<sup>c</sup> Set him not on thy right hand:</p>
<p>Wherefore should he seek thy seat?</p>
<p>12<sup>e</sup> And afterwards thou shalt attain unto my words;</p>
<p>And shalt lament at my lament.</p>
<p>13 Who will pity (?) a charmer that is stung;</p>
<p>Or anyone that cometh nigh to a ravenous beast?</p>
<p>14 So is he that joineth himself to an impious man (G S),</p>
<p>And walloweth in his iniquities.</p>
<p>14<sup>(1)</sup> He shall not escape, until a fire be kindled in him.</p>
<p>14<sup>(2)</sup> When he cometh with thee, he will not bewray himself unto thee;</p>
<p>And if thou fall, thou shalt not be able (S) to deliver thyself (?).</p>
<p>15 So long as thou standest (?), he will not shew himself;</p>
<p>And if thou (G) totter, he will not bear up.</p>
<p>16<sup>a</sup> With his lips will an adversary speak sweetly (G),</p>
<p>While he deviseth deep pitfalls in his heart.</p>
<p>16<sup>c</sup> And even though an enemy weep with his eyes;</p>
<p>When he hath found a season, he will not be satiated with blood.</p>
<p>17 If mischief hath befallen thee, he is found there;</p>
<p>As a man that would help, he will seek reward (<italic>or</italic> to supplant).</p>
<p>18 He will shake his head, and wave his hand;</p>
<p>And with much whispering (?) he will change his countenance.</p>
<p><bold>13.</bold> 1 Whoso toucheth pitch, it shall cleave to his hand (?);</p>
<p>And he that hath fellowship with a scorner will learn his way.</p>
<p>2<sup>a</sup> What is too heavy for thee wherefore shouldest thou lift?</p>
<p>And wherefore have fellowship with one that is richer than thou?</p>
<p>2<sup>c</sup> What fellowship shall earthen pot have with kettle,</p>
<p>When if this smite that, it is dashed in pieces?</p>
<p>2 Happy is the man whose soul hath not reproached (H failed) him;</p>
<p>And whose expectation hath not ceased.</p>
<p>3 Wealth is not comely for a little heart;</p>
<p>And fine gold is not comely for one whose eye is evil.</p>
<p>4 He that stinteth (?) himself gathereth for another;</p>
<p>And a stranger shall revel (?) in his goods.</p>
<p>5 He that is evil to himself, to whom will he be good?</p>
<p>And he will not enjoy (?) his own goods.</p>
<p>6 There is none more evil than he that is evil to himself;</p>
<p>And he hath with him the recompense of his wickedness.</p>
<p>9 In the eye of a fool (S) his portion is small;</p>
<p>But he that taketh his neighbour&#x2019;s portion wasteth his own (?).</p>
<p>10 The eye of him that hath an evil eye (?) is grudging (G) of bread;</p>
<p>And there is famine at his table.</p>
<p>10<sup>(1)</sup> An evil (S) eye lavishing bread</p>
<p>Is as a fountain dried up that should well with water (?).</p>
<p>11 My son, if thou hast wherewithal, minister (S) to thine own self;</p>
<p>And if thou hast, do good unto thyself;</p>
<p>And according to the power of &#x2225; thy hand, make thyself fat. <r1>Fol. A 4 recto</r1></p>
<p>12 Remember that there is no luxury in Sheol;</p>
<p>And death doth not tarry;</p>
<p>And the decree of Sheol (?) hath not been declared to thee.</p>
<p>15 All flesh loveth its kind;</p>
<p>And every man him that is like unto him.</p>
<p>16 The kind of all flesh consorteth therewith;</p>
<p>And a man will have fellowship with his kind.</p>
<p>17 What fellowship shall wolf have with lamb?</p>
<p>Such is the wicked to the righteous;</p>
<p>17<sup>(1)</sup> And so is the rich unto a man that is destitute.</p>
<p>18 How should there be (?) peace between hyena and dog?</p>
<p>How should there be peace between rich and poor?</p>
<p>19 Wild asses of the wilderness are food for the lion:</p>
<p>So the poor are the prey of the rich.</p>
<p>20 Lowliness is the abomination of pride;</p>
<p>And the needy is the abomination of the rich.</p>
<p>21 A rich man when he is shaken is held up (?) of a friend;</p>
<p>But the poor when he is shaken is thrust from evil to evil (?).</p>
<p>22<sup>a</sup> The rich speaketh, and his helpers are many;</p>
<p>And his unseemly words are overlaid (?).</p>
<p>22<sup>c</sup> A poor man speaketh (G S), and they hoot at him (?);</p>
<p>Though he be wise that speaketh, there is no place for him.</p>
<p>23<sup>a</sup> When the rich speaketh, all keep silence;</p>
<p>And (?) they extol his wisdom to the clouds.</p>
<p>23<sup>c</sup> When the poor speaketh, Who is this? say they;</p>
<p>And if he stumble, they will help to overthrow him.</p>
<p>24 Good is wealth, if it be without iniquity;</p>
<p>And evil is poverty in the mouth of arrogancy.</p>
<p>25 The heart of a man changeth his countenance;</p>
<p>Whether for good or for evil.</p>
<p>26 A token of a merry heart is a bright countenance;</p>
<p>And study and meditation is wearisome thought (?).</p>
<p><bold>14.</bold> 1 Happy is the man whom his own mouth hath not troubled;</p>
<p>And whose heart hath not condemned him (?).</p>
<p>24 He that encampeth about her house;</p>
<p>And driveth his pegs (?) into her wall.</p>
<p>25 And he pitcheth his tent by her side;</p>
<p>And dwelleth in good neighbourhood.</p>
<p>26 And he will set his nest on her bough;</p>
<p>And will lodge in her branches.</p>
<p>27 And he sheltereth in her shade from the heat;</p>
<p>And will dwell in her habitations.</p>
<p><bold>15</bold>. 1 For he that feareth the Lord shall do this;</p>
<p>And he that layeth hold on the law shall attain unto her (?).</p>
<p>2 And she shall meet him as mother;</p>
<p>And receive him as wife of youth.</p>
<p>3 And she shall feed him with bread of wisdom;</p>
<p>And give him water of understanding to drink.</p>
<p>4 And he shall be stayed upon her, and shall not be moved;</p>
<p>And in her shall he trust, and he shall not be confounded.</p>
<p>5 And she shall exalt him above his neighbour;</p>
<p>And in the midst of the congregation shall she open his mouth.</p>
<p>6 He shall find joy and gladness;</p>
<p>And she shall cause him to inherit an everlasting name.</p>
<p>7 Men of naught shall not attain unto her;</p>
<p>And men of arrogancy shall not see her (H S).</p>
<p>8 Far is she from scorners;</p>
<p>And liars shall not remember her.</p>
<p>9 Praise is not comely (G S) in the mouth of the wicked;</p>
<p>For it was not apportioned him of God.</p>
<p>10 By the mouth of the wise shall praise be spoken;</p>
<p>And he that mastereth her (H S) shall learn it.</p>
<p>11 Say not, My transgression was of God;</p>
<p>For that which he hateth he made not (H S).</p>
<p>13 Do good to a friend before thou die;</p>
<p>And as thy hand attaineth (?) give unto him.</p>
<p>14 Refuse not the day&#x2019;s good cheer.</p>
<p>But encroach not upon a brother&#x2019;s portion (?);</p>
<p>And covet not the desirable things of a neighbour.</p>
<p>15 Shalt thou not leave thy riches to another;</p>
<p>And thy labour to them that cast lots?</p>
<p>16 Give to a brother (H), and let thy soul fare delicately;</p>
<p>For there is no seeking of luxury in Sheol.</p>
<p>16<sup>(1)</sup> And whatsoever thing is seemly to do;</p>
<p>Do it before (?) God.</p>
<p>17 All flesh waxeth old as a garment;</p>
<p>And the everlasting decree is, They shall surely perish.</p>
<p>18<sup>a</sup> As leaves grow upon a green tree,</p>
<p>Whereof one withereth, and another springeth up;</p>
<p>18<sup>c</sup> So of the generations of flesh and blood,</p>
<p>One perisheth, and another ripeneth (M).</p>
<p>19 All his works shall surely rot;</p>
<p>And his handywork shall draw after him.</p>
<p>20 Happy is the man that shall meditate in wisdom;</p>
<p>And shall have respect to understanding.</p>
<p>21 That setteth his heart upon her ways;</p>
<p>And considereth her paths (S).</p>
<p>22 Going forth after her in search of her;</p>
<p>And spying all her entries.</p>
<p>23 That prieth through her window;</p>
<p>And will hearken at her doors.</p>
<p>5 Many things like these hath mine eye seen;</p>
<p>And mighty things like these (H) hath mine ear heard.</p>
<p>6 In the congregation of the wicked a fire burneth;</p>
<p>And in an ungodly nation wrath is kindled.</p>
<p>7 Seeing that he forgave not the princes of old time,</p>
<p>Who ruled (?) the world by their power.</p>
<p>8 And he spared not them that sojourned with Lot (?),</p>
<p>Who transgressed in their pride.</p>
<p>9 And he spared not the people of perdition,</p>
<p>That were dispossessed (?) in their iniquity.</p>
<p>10 So were the six hundred thousand footmen,</p>
<p>That were taken away in the arrogancy of their heart.</p>
<p>11<sup>a</sup> And if even one stiffen (<italic>or</italic> harden) his neck;</p>
<p>It were a marvel should he be unpunished.</p>
<p>11<sup>c</sup> For mercy and wrath are with him;</p>
<p>And he forgiveth and pardoneth;</p>
<p>But upon the wicked his indignation shall rest (?).</p>
<p>12 According to the greatness of his mercy, so is his correction;</p>
<p>He will judge each according to his doings.</p>
<p>13 He will not (M) let the wrong-doer escape with plunder;</p>
<p>Neither will he frustrate the desire of the righteous for ever.</p>
<p>14 Whosoever doeth righteousness, there is a reward for him;</p>
<p>And according to his works shall every man go forth (H) before him.</p>
<p>15 The Lord hardened the heart of Pharaoh, who knew him not:</p>
<p>16 Whose works are manifest under heaven;</p>
<p>His mercies are seen of all his creatures;</p>
<p>And his light and his darkness (?) hath he apportioned to the sons of men.</p>
<p>17<sup>a</sup> Say not, I am hidden from God;</p>
<p>And who shall remember me on high?</p>
<p>17<sup>c</sup> In the mass of people I shall not be known;</p>
<p>And what is my soul at the end of the spirits of all the sons of men?</p>
<p>12 Lest thou say, He it was that made me stumble;</p>
<p>For there is no need of men of violence.</p>
<p>13 Wickedness and an abomination the Lord hateth;</p>
<p>And will not let it befal them that fear him.</p>
<p>14 For (?) God created man from the beginning;</p>
<p>And put him into the hand of him that would spoil him;</p>
<p>And gave him into the hand of his inclination.</p>
<p>15 If thou choose, thou mayest keep the commandment;</p>
<p>And it is understanding (H) to do his will.</p>
<p>15<sup>(1)</sup> If thou trust in him, thou shalt even live.</p>
<p>16 Fire and water are poured out before thee:</p>
<p>Upon whichsoever thou choosest stretch forth thy hands.</p>
<p>17 Death and life are before a man:</p>
<p>That which he shall choose shall be given him.</p>
<p>18 The wisdom of the Lord aboundeth:</p>
<p>He is mighty in power, and beholdeth all.</p>
<p>19 The eyes of God see his works;</p>
<p>And he will take knowledge of (?) all a man&#x2019;s doing.</p>
<p>20 He commanded not a man to sin;</p>
<p>Neither did he make men of falsehood to dream.</p>
<p>20<sup>(1)</sup> And he hath no mercy on him that worketh vanity;</p>
<p>And on him that discloseth a secret.</p>
<p><bold>16.</bold> 1 Desire not the shapeliness of vain youths;</p>
<p>And rejoice not in sons of wickedness.</p>
<p>2 Yea, and if they increase, delight (?) not in them;</p>
<p>If the fear of the Lord be not with them.</p>
<p>3<sup>a</sup> Trust not in their life, and rely not on their issues (?);</p>
<p>3<sup>a(1)</sup> For they shall not have a good end.</p>
<p>3<sup>c</sup> For better is one that doeth acceptably than a thousand;</p>
<p>And he that dieth childless than he that hath many sons of wickedness (?) ;</p>
<p>And than an ungodly posterity.</p>
<p>4 Of one that (?) feareth the Lord shall a city be peopled;</p>
<p>And by a family of transgressors it shall be made desolate.</p>
<bold>30.</bold> 11 Let him not have rule in his youth; <r1>Fol. B 1 recto</r1>
<p>And bear not with his mischiefs.</p>
<p>11<sup>(1)</sup> Beat his shoulder while it is yet tender (?);</p>
<p>Bruise (?) his loins while he is yet a youth.</p>
<p>12<sup>a</sup> Bow down his head in his youth;</p>
<p>And smite through his loins when he is a little one.</p>
<p>12<sup>c</sup> Wherefore should he harden himself (M), and rebel against thee;</p>
<p>That thou shouldest have (?) faintness of spirit because of him?</p>
<p>13 Chastise (<italic>or</italic> Train) thy son, and make his yoke heavy;</p>
<p>Lest in his folly he lift himself up (M) against thee.</p>
<p>14 Better is one that is poor, and healthy in his body;</p>
<p>Than a rich man that is plagued in his flesh.</p>
<p>15 Health of flesh (?) have I desired more than fine gold;</p>
<p>And a joyful spirit more than rubies.</p>
<p>16 There is no wealth above wealth of sound flesh (?);</p>
<p>And no good above goodness of heart.</p>
<p>17 Better is to die than a life of vanity;</p>
<p>And eternal rest than continual pain.</p>
<p>17<sup>(1)</sup> Better is to die than life that is evil;</p>
<p>And to go down to Sheol than lasting pain.</p>
<p>18 Goodness poured upon a mouth that is closed</p>
<p>Is as an offering laid before a gravestone (?).</p>
<p>19 What can it profit idols of the nations,</p>
<p>Which eat not, neither do they smell?</p>
<p>So whoso hath wealth,</p>
<p>And enjoyeth not of his substance (?).</p>
<p>20<sup>a</sup> With his eye     .     .     .     .     .</p>
<a name="page"/>
<p>18 Behold, the heaven, and the heaven of heavens,</p>
<p>And the deep, and the earth;</p>
<p>When he descendeth upon them, they tremble (?),</p>
<p>At his visitation (?), and when he rageth.</p>
<p>19 The roots also of the mountains and the foundations of the world,</p>
<p>When he looketh upon them, quake exceedingly.</p>
<p>20 Surely upon me he will not set his heart;</p>
<p>And my ways who will consider?</p>
<p>20<sup>(1)</sup> If I have sinned, no eye shall see me;</p>
<p>Or if I deal falsely in any secret place (?), who shall know?</p>
<p>22 Work of right who shall declare unto him?</p>
<p>And of what is there hope, that I should be righteous (?)&#x2026;?</p>
<p>23 They that want understanding will think such things;</p>
<p>And a perverse man (?) will imagine this.</p>
<p>24 Hearken unto me, and receive my proverbs (?);</p>
<p>And set your heart upon my words.</p>
<p>25 I will pour forth my spirit by weight;</p>
<p>And with carefulness will I declare my opinion.</p>
<p>26 When God created his works from the beginning;</p>
<p>According to their parts (H life) &#x2026;.</p>
<p>&#x002A;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#x002A;;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#x002A;;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#x002A;;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#x002A;;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#x002A;</p>
<p>2 Care for sustenance breaketh off slumber;</p>
<p>And sore sickness (M) dissipateth slumber.</p>
<p>2<sup>(1)</sup> Reproach putteth to flight a faithful friend;</p>
<p>But he that hideth a secret is beloved (?) as one&#x2019;s soul.</p>
<p>3 The labour (M) of the rich is to gather (G S) wealth;</p>
<p>And if he rest, it is to take pleasure.</p>
<p>4 The poor toileth for the lack of his house;</p>
<p>And if he rest, he becometh needy.</p>
<p>4<sup>(1)</sup> The labour of the poor is for the lack of his means (?);</p>
<p>And if he rest, it is to his lamentation (<italic>or</italic> he is distressed).</p>
<p>5 He that pursueth after gold shall not be innocent;</p>
<p>And he that loveth hire shall err thereby.</p>
<p>6 Many are there that have been given in pledge (?) to gold;</p>
<p>And that trusted (?) on rubies.</p>
<p>6<sup>(1)</sup> And they found not how to escape from evil;</p>
<p>Neither to save themselves in the day of wrath.</p>
<p>7 For it is a stumblingblock to the fool;</p>
<p>And whoso is simple is enticed thereby.</p>
<p>8 Blessed is the man (H) that hath been found perfect;</p>
<p>And that hath not gone aside after mammon.</p>
<p>9 Who is he? and we will call him blessed:</p>
<p>For he hath done wonderously among his people.</p>
<p>10<sup>a</sup> Who is he? that we may cleave (H) unto him;</p>
<p>And he shall have peace, and he shall have glory.</p>
<p>10<sup>(1)</sup> For when as the peace of his life multiplieth,</p>
<p>I will be a glory unto thee (?).</p>
<p>20<sup>b</sup> As an eunuch (?) embraceth a maiden and groaneth.</p>
<p>20<sup>b(1)</sup> So is he that doeth judgement with violence (?).</p>
<p>20<sup>b(2)</sup> So is an eunuch (?) that lieth with a virgin.</p>
<p>And the Lord requireth at his hand.</p>
<p>21 Give not thy soul to sorrow;</p>
<p>And stumble not by thine iniquity (M counsel).</p>
<p>22 Joy of heart, that is the life of a man;</p>
<p>And a man&#x2019;s cheerfulness lengthens his days (G).</p>
<p>23<sup>a</sup> Rejoice thy soul, and make thine heart joyful (?);</p>
<p>And put vexation far from thee:</p>
<p>23<sup>b</sup> For sorrow hath slain many;</p>
<p>And there is no profit in vexation.</p>
<p>24 Envy and sorrow (G wrath) shorten days;</p>
<p>And care maketh old untimely.</p>
<p><l1>Fol. B 1 verso</l1> 25 The sleep of a good heart is instead of dainties;</p>
<p>And his food is agreeable unto him.</p>
<p><bold>31.</bold> 1 The wakefulness (M) of the rich wasteth his flesh;</p>
<p>His care (M) dissipateth slumber.</p>
<p>4<sup>(1)</sup> As a seal upon a purse of gold,</p>
<p>Is a hymn to God at a banquet of wine.</p>
<p>5 As a boss (?) of ruby on a circlet (M) of gold,</p>
<p>Is a concert of music (?) at a banquet of wine.</p>
<p>5<sup>(1)</sup> As a collar of gold wherein are emerald and sapphire;</p>
<p>So are fine words comely at a banquet of wine.</p>
<p>6 As settings of fine gold and a seal of carbuncle,</p>
<p>Is the voice of music with the pleasance of mead.</p>
<p>7 Speak, O young man, if thou be wanted;</p>
<p>With compulsion if one ask thee twice or thrice.</p>
<p>8 Restrain speaking, and diminish it exceedingly;</p>
<p>And be like to one that knoweth and holdeth his tongue.</p>
<p>9 Among elders set not thyself up;</p>
<p>And press not (?) much on princes.</p>
<p>9<sup>(1)</sup> Before hail (H) speedeth (?) lightning;</p>
<p>And before one that is downcast speedeth favour.</p>
<p>10 Before hail (H) speedeth (?) lightning;</p>
<p>And before one that is shamefast favour.</p>
<p>11 At the appointed time tarry not;</p>
<p>Get thee home and do pleasure (?).</p>
<p>11<sup>(1)</sup> At table time multiply not words;</p>
<p>Even though a thing hath come into thy mind.</p>
<p>12 .&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;.&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;in thy heart (?), and do pleasure;</p>
<p>In the fear of God, and not with lack of understanding (H all).</p>
<p>10<sup>(2)</sup> Who hath blessed it (?), and made his life perfect?</p>
<p>I will be a glory unto thee (?).</p>
<p>10<sup>c</sup> Who was able to stray, and strayed not?</p>
<p>And to do evil to a neighbour, and would not?</p>
<p>11 Therefore his good is sure;</p>
<p>And the congregation shall declare his praise.</p>
<p>&#x002A;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#x002A;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#x002A;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#x002A;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#x002A;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#x002A;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#x002A;</p>
<p><l1>Fol. B 2 recto</l1> <bold>32.</bold> 1<sup>bc</sup> Be to them as one of them;</p>
<p>Take thought for them, and afterward be seated:</p>
<p>2<sup>bc</sup> Supply their want, and afterward recline.</p>
<p>That thou mayest rejoice in their honour;</p>
<p>And receive favour at the table (?).</p>
<p>3 Speak, O elder, for it pertaineth to thee;</p>
<p>And be carefully wise (?), and hinder not song.</p>
<p>4 In a place for wine pour not forth talk;</p>
<p>And in a place for music (?) pour not forth talk:</p>
<p>And wherefore shouldest thou be always (S) wise?</p>
<p>24 He that observeth the law keepeth his soul;</p>
<p>And he that trusteth in the Lord shall not be ashamed.</p>
<p><bold>33.</bold> 1 Evil shall not befall him that feareth the Lord;</p>
<p>But in temptation even again he shall be delivered (?).</p>
<p>2 He that hateth the law shall not be wise;</p>
<p>And he is moved as&#x2026;tossed with tempest (?).</p>
<p>3 A man of discernment discerneth a matter;</p>
<p>And his law&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;.&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;.&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;.&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;.&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;.&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;.&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;.</p>
<p>&#x002A;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#x002A;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#x002A;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#x002A;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#x002A;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#x002A;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#x002A;</p>
<p><bold>35.</bold> 9 In all thy works (H) shew a bright countenance; <r1>Fol. B 3 recto</r1></p>
<p>And dedicate thy tithe with gladness.</p>
<p>10 Give to God (?) according as he hath given to thee;</p>
<p>With goodness of eye, and as thy hand hath found (?).</p>
<p>11 For he is a God that recompenseth;</p>
<p>And sevenfold will he return unto thee.</p>
<p>He that giveth to the poor lendeth to the Lord;</p>
<p>And who is a rewarder but he (M S)?</p>
<p>12<sup>a</sup> Bribe (S Hesitate) not, for he will not receive;</p>
<p>And trust not upon a sacrifice of oppression.</p>
<p>12<sup>c</sup> For he is a God of judgement;</p>
<p>And with him is no respect of persons.</p>
<p>13 He will not shew favour toward the poor;</p>
<p>And he will hear the supplication of the afflicted.</p>
<p>14 He will not reject the cry of the fatherless;</p>
<p>And of the widow, when she maketh much complaint (H).</p>
<p>15 Do not tears run down the cheek?</p>
<p>Doth she not sigh because of her miseries?</p>
<p>16 Bitterness that is well-pleasing (H) is her lamentation (?):</p>
<p>Her (G His) cry hasteth to the clouds.</p>
<p>17<sup>a</sup> The crying of the poor passeth through thick clouds (M);</p>
<p>And resteth not until it come nigh.</p>
<p>17<sup>c</sup> It will not remove till God shall visit;</p>
<p>And till he that judgeth righteously shall do judgement.</p>
<p>18<sup>a</sup> Yea, and God will not tarry;</p>
<p>And as a mighty man he will not refrain himself:</p>
<p>13 And for all these things (?) bless thy Maker;</p>
<p>Which satisfieth thee with his goodness.</p>
<p>13<sup>(1)</sup> He that seeketh God may expect favour (?);</p>
<p>And he that is a madman shall be snared thereby (?).</p>
<p><l1>Fol. B 2 verso</l1> 14 He that seeketh God will receive discipline;</p>
<p>And he that seeketh him diligently shall obtain an answer.</p>
<p>14<sup>(1)</sup> He that seeketh things pleasing to God shall receive instruction;</p>
<p>And he will answer him in his prayer.</p>
<p>15 He that seeketh the law shall obtain her;</p>
<p>And he that is a madman shall be snared thereby.</p>
<p>16 He that feareth the Lord shall discern judgement;</p>
<p>And shall bring forth counsels from twilight (H).</p>
<p>16<sup>(1)</sup> They that fear the Lord shall discern his judgement;</p>
<p>And they shall bring forth much wisdom (M) from their heart.</p>
<p>17 A man of violence (M) will wrest reproofs;</p>
<p>And will draw the law (?) after his need.</p>
<p>17<sup>(1)</sup> A wise man will not conceal wisdom (M);</p>
<p>And a scorner will not keep his tongue.</p>
<p>18<sup>a</sup> A wise man will not take a bribe (H):</p>
<p>One that is proud and a scorner will not keep the law.</p>
<p>19 Without counsel do not anything;</p>
<p>And after thy doings vex not thyself.</p>
<p>20 Go not in a way set with snares;</p>
<p>And stumble not at an offence twice.</p>
<p>21 Trust not in the way of the spoiler (?);</p>
<p>22 And be watchful of thy latter end.</p>
<p>22<sup>(1)</sup> Trust not in the way of the wicked;</p>
<p>And be ware in thy paths.</p>
<p>22<sup>(2)</sup> In all thy ways keep thy soul;</p>
<p>For whoso doeth these things keepeth a commandment.</p>
<p>23 In all thy doings keep thy soul;</p>
<p>For he that doeth this keepeth a commandment.</p>
<p>13 Have mercy upon thy holy city;</p>
<p>Jerusalem, the place of thy dwelling.</p>
<p>14 Fill Sion with thy majesty;</p>
<p>And thy temple from thy glory. </p>
<p>15 Give testimony to the firstling of thy works;</p>
<p>And establish the vision spoken in thy name.</p>
<p>16 Give their reward to them that wait for thee;</p>
<p>And let thy prophets be true.</p>
<p>17<sup>a</sup> Hear the prayer of thy servants;</p>
<p>According to thy good pleasure (?) unto thy people.</p>
<p>17<sup>c</sup> And let all the ends of the earth know (H),</p>
<p>That thou art our God for ever (?).</p>
<p>18 The throat eateth every meat;</p>
<p>Yet is one meat more pleasant than another (M).</p>
<p>21 A woman will receive every man (?);</p>
<p>Yet is one woman beautiful (M).</p>
<p>&#x002A;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#x002A;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#x002A;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#x002A;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#x002A;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#x002A;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#x002A;</p>
<p><bold>37.</bold> 27 My son, prove thy soul in thy life (M in wine); <r1>Fol. B 4 recta</r1></p>
<p>And see thou give it not that which is bad for it.</p>
<p>28 For not all is good for all:</p>
<p>Not every soul chooseth every sort.</p>
<p>29 Be not insatiable (G) for every luxury;</p>
<p>And be not effuse on all dainties.</p>
<p>30 For in much luxury (M food) nesteth sickness;</p>
<p>And he that surfeiteth shall come nigh to loathing.</p>
<p>31 By intemperance many perish utterly (?);</p>
<p>But he that taketh heed shall add to life.</p>
<p><bold>38.</bold> I Honour a physician before need of him (H):</p>
<p>Him also hath God apportioned.</p>
<p>18<sup>c</sup> Till he smite the loins of the unmerciful;</p>
<p>And repay vengeance to the heathen:</p>
<p>18<sup>e</sup> Till he dispossess the sceptre of pride;</p>
<p>And quite cut down the rod of the wicked:</p>
<p>19<sup>a</sup> Till he render to a man his due;</p>
<p>And a man&#x2019;s recompense according to his devising:</p>
<p>19<sup>c</sup> Till he plead (?) the cause of his people;</p>
<p>And make them joyful (M) with his salvation.</p>
<p>20 Mercy from the Lord in time (?) of affliction</p>
<p>Is as cloud (?) of rains in season of drought.</p>
<p>20<sup>(1)</sup>&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;.&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;.&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;.&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;.&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;.&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;.&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;.&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;.&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;.</p>
<p><l1>Fol. B 3 verso</l1> <bold>36</bold>. 1<sup>a</sup> Save us, O God of all;</p>
<p>2 And exalt thy fear over all the nations.</p>
<p>3 Shake thy hand (M) over the strange people;</p>
<p>And let them see thy mighty acts.</p>
<p>4 As thou hast been sanctified in their eyes over us;</p>
<p>So in our eyes get thee honour over them.</p>
<p>5 And let them know as we have known,</p>
<p>That there is no God but thou.</p>
<p>6 Renew signs, and repeat wonders;</p>
<p>Glorify thy hand, and strengthen arm and right hand.</p>
<p>7 Wake up indignation, and pour out wrath;</p>
<p>And subdue the foe, and drive away (?) the enemy.</p>
<p>8<sup>a</sup> Hasten the end, and visit (H) the appointed time (?);</p>
<p>8<sup>(1)</sup> For who shall say unto thee, What doest thou?</p>
<p>10 Make an end of the head of the princes of Moab (H);</p>
<p>That saith, There is none but me.</p>
<p>11 Gather all the tribes of Jacob;</p>
<p>And let them inherit as in the days of old.</p>
<p>12 Have mercy upon the people that is called by thy name;</p>
<p>Israel, whom thou didst surname Firstborn.</p>
<p>16<sup>c</sup> According to the manner of each, bury his (M their) flesh;</p>
<p>And hide not thyself when they die (?).</p>
<p>17<sup>a</sup> Weep bitterly, and make grievous wailing;</p>
<p>And appoint mourning accordingly (?):</p>
<p>17<sup>c</sup> A day or two because of hearsay (?);</p>
<p>And be comforted for the sake of health (?).</p>
<p>18 Out of sorrow (?) cometh harm;</p>
<p>So the sad of heart buildeth up trouble (?).</p>
<p>20 Set not the heart upon him (M) any more;</p>
<p>Dismiss his remembrance, and remember the end.</p>
<p>22 Remember his sentence, for it is thy sentence;</p>
<p>His yesterday, and thine to day.</p>
<p>21 Remember him not, for there is no hope for him;</p>
<p>What shalt thou profit him (?)? and thou shalt hurt thyself.</p>
<p>23 When the dead is at rest, let his remembrance rest;</p>
<p>And be comforted when his soul departeth.</p>
<p>24 The wisdom of the scribe increaseth wisdom (H);</p>
<p>And he that hath little business shall become wise.</p>
<p>25<sup>a</sup> How shall he get wisdom that holdeth the plough (<italic>or</italic> goad),</p>
<p>And glorieth in the stimulant (?) spear?</p>
<p>25<sup>c</sup> He is busied with oxen, and leadeth about cattle (?);</p>
<p>And his discourses are with bullocks.</p>
<p>26 And his wakefulness is to victual (?) the stall:</p>
<p>He setteth his heart to plough furrows.</p>
<p>27 Likewise the artificer&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;.&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;.&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;.&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;.&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;.</p>
<p>Which by night is busied (M)&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;.&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;.&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;.</p>
<p>&#x002A;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#x002A;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#x002A;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#x002A;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#x002A;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#x002A;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#x002A;</p>
<p><bold>49.</bold> 12 And they erected the holy temple; <r1>Fol. B 5 recto</r1></p>
<p>Which was prepared for everlasting glory.</p>
<p>13<sup>a</sup> Nehemiah, glorious is his memory;</p>
<p>Who raised up our ruins:</p>
<p>13<sup>c</sup> And healed our breaches;</p>
<p>And set up gates and bars.</p>
<p>2 From God a physician getteth wisdom;</p>
<p>And from a king he shall receive gifts.</p>
<p>3 The skill of a physician shall lift up his head;</p>
<p>And he shall stand before nobles.</p>
<p>4 God bringeth out medicines from the earth;</p>
<p>And let a prudent man not refuse them.</p>
<p>5 Was not water made sweet with wood,</p>
<p>For to acquaint every man with his (M their) power?</p>
<p>6 And he gave man understanding;</p>
<p>To glory in his (M their) might.</p>
<p>7<sup>a</sup> By them doth the physician assuage pain;</p>
<p>8<sup>a</sup> And likewise the apothecary maketh a confection:</p>
<p>8<sup>b</sup> That his work may not fail (?);</p>
<p>Nor health from among the sons of men (M his earth).</p>
<p>9 My son, in sickness be not negligent (?):</p>
<p>Pray unto God, for he will heal.</p>
<p>10 Flee from iniquity, and from respect of persons;</p>
<p>And from all transgressions cleanse thy heart.</p>
<p>11 Offer a sweet savour (?) as a memorial;</p>
<p>And fatness estimated according to thy substance (?).</p>
<p>12 And to the physician also give (?) a place;</p>
<p>And he shall not remove, for there is need of him likewise.</p>
<p><l1>Fol. B 4 verso</l1> 13 For there is a time when in his hand is good success (?):</p>
<p>14<sup>a</sup> For he too will supplicate unto God,</p>
<p>14<sup>b</sup> That he will prosper (H) to him the treatment (<italic>or</italic> draught),</p>
<p>And the healing, for the sake of his (?) living.</p>
<p>15 He that sinneth against his Maker</p>
<p>Will behave himself proudly (H) against a physician.</p>
<p>16<sup>a</sup> My son, let tears fall over the dead:</p>
<p>Be in bitterness, and wail with lamentation.</p>
<p>7 And as the sun dawning upon (?) the temple of the King;</p>
<p>And as rainbow seen in the cloud.</p>
<p>8<sup>a</sup> As budding branch (?) in the days of the solemn feast;</p>
<p>And as the lotus by the watercourses.</p>
<p>8<sup>c</sup> As flower of Lebanon in the days of summer;</p>
<p>9<sup>bc</sup> And as fire of incense upon the meal-offering:</p>
<p>In (<italic>or</italic> As) a gold plated vessel, and a chalice (<italic>or</italic> weighty),</p>
<p>That is set with pleasant stones.</p>
<p>10 As a green olive full of berries;</p>
<p>And as a wild olive tree with branches full of sap.</p>
<p>11<sup>a</sup> When he put on robes of honour; <r1>Fol. B 5 verso</r1></p>
<p>And clothed himself with robes of beauty.</p>
<p>14 Few have been created upon the earth like Enoch (?);</p>
<p>And he also was taken within (?).</p>
<p>15 Like Joseph was ever a man born?</p>
<p>And also his body was visited.</p>
<p>16 And Shem and Seth and Enosh were visited (H);</p>
<p>And above every living thing was the glory of Adam.</p>
<p><bold>50.</bold> 1<sup>a</sup> Great one of his brethren, and glory of his people,</p>
<p>Was Simon, son of Johanan (H), the priest;</p>
<p>1<sup>bc</sup> In whose generation the house was repaired (?);</p>
<p>And in whose days the temple was fortified.</p>
<p>3 In whose generation a cistern was digged (H);</p>
<p>A pit (<italic>or</italic> store) like the sea (?) in its abundance.</p>
<p>2 In whose days a wall was built;</p>
<p>A bulwark of refuge (?) in the temple of the King.</p>
<p>4 Who took thought for his people against the spoiler;</p>
<p>And fortified his city against the besieger.</p>
<p>5 How glorious was he when he looked forth from the tent;</p>
<p>And when he went out from the house of the veil&#x0021;</p>
<p>6 As the morning star from amid thick clouds;</p>
<p>And as the full moon in the days of (?) the solemn feast.</p>
<p>24 May his mercy stand fast with Simon;</p>
<p>And may he confirm to him the covenant of Phinehas,</p>
<p>24<sup>(1)</sup> Which he executed (?) unto him and unto his seed,</p>
<p>As the days of heaven.</p>
<p>25 Two nations my soul abhorreth;</p>
<p>And the third is no people:</p>
<p>26 The inhabitants of Seir and Philistia;</p>
<p>And the foolish nation that dwelleth in Sichem.</p>
<p>27<sup>a</sup> The instruction of understanding and proverbs fitly spoken (?)</p>
<p>Of Simon, son of Jesus, son of Eleazar, son of Sira.</p>
<p>27<sup>c</sup> Whose heart prophesied as with a harp (?);</p>
<p>And who poured forth understanding.</p>
<p>28 Happy is the man that meditateth on these;</p>
<p>And he that layeth them to his heart shall be wise.</p>
<p>29<sup>b</sup> For the fear of the Lord is life.</p>
<p><bold>51.</bold> 1<sup>b</sup> I will praise thee, O God of my salvation;</p>
<p>1<sup>a</sup> I will give thanks unto thee (?), my God, my Father;</p>
<p>1<sup>c</sup> I will declare thy name, O stronghold of my life.</p>
<p>2<sup>a</sup> For thou hast redeemed my soul from death.</p>
<p>2<sup>b</sup> Thou hast kept back my flesh from corruption;</p>
<p>2<sup>b(1)</sup> And hast delivered my foot from the hand of Sheol.</p>
<p>2<sup>c</sup> Thou hast delivered me from the evil report of the people;</p>
<p>From the scourge of (?) the tongue, and from the lip of them that go aside to lies.</p>
<p>2<sup>e</sup> Thou wast with me against them that rose up against me;</p>
<p>3<sup>a</sup> Thou hast holpen me according to thy great mercy:</p>
<p>3<sup>b</sup> Out of the snare of them that watched for my halting (?);</p>
<p>And from the hand of them that sought my life.</p>
<p>3<sup>d</sup> From many troubles thou hast saved me;</p>
<p>4<sup>a</sup> And from chokings of flaming fire&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;.&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;.</p>
<p>4<sup>b</sup> From flames of a fire not blown (?);</p>
<p>5<sup>a</sup> From the womb of the deep&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;.&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;.&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;.&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;.</p>
<p>5<sup>d</sup> From cunning lips, and weavers of lies;</p>
<p>11<sup>c</sup> When he ascended the altar of majesty;</p>
<p>And made glorious the precinct of the sanctuary.</p>
<p>12<sup>a</sup> When he received the pieces out of the hand of his brethren;</p>
<p>While himself standing by the altar-fires:</p>
<p>12<sup>c</sup> Round him a crown of sons,</p>
<p>Like cedar plants in Lebanon.</p>
<p>12<sup>e</sup> And they compassed him about like willows of the brook:</p>
<p>13<sup>a</sup> All the sons of Aaron in their glory:</p>
<p>13<sup>bc</sup> With the fire-offerings of the Lord in their hand,</p>
<p>Before all the congregation of Israel.</p>
<p>14 Until he finished serving the altar,</p>
<p>And arranging the fires of the Most High.</p>
<p>16<sup>a</sup> Then sounded the sons of Aaron, the priests,</p>
<p>With trumpets of turnery.</p>
<p>16<sup>c</sup> And they sounded, and made their glorious voice heard;</p>
<p>To bring to remembrance (?) before the Most High.</p>
<p>17<sup>a</sup> All flesh together hasted,</p>
<p>And fell down upon their faces to the earth:</p>
<p>17<sup>c</sup> To worship before the Most High;</p>
<p>Before the Holy One of Israel.</p>
<p>18 And the choir uttered its voice;</p>
<p>And over the multitude they made sweet melody (?).</p>
<p>19<sup>a</sup> And all the people of the land chanted,</p>
<p>In prayer before the Merciful.</p>
<p>19<sup>c</sup> Until he finished serving the altar;</p>
<p>And had brought its customary offerings unto it.</p>
<p>20<sup>a</sup> Then he came down, and lifted up his hands</p>
<p>Over all the congregation of Israel.</p>
<p>20<sup>c</sup> And the blessing of the Lord was on his lips;</p>
<p>And in the name of the Lord he gloried.</p>
<p>21 And they bowed down again a second time,</p>
<p>The people all of them, before him.</p>
<p>22<sup>a</sup> Now bless ye the Lord, the God of Israel,</p>
<p>Which doeth wonderously in the land.</p>
<p><l1>Fol. B 6 recto</l1> 22<sup>c</sup> That bringeth up man from the womb;</p>
<p>And maketh him according to his will.</p>
<p>23 May he give you wisdom of heart;</p>
<p>And may there be (?) peace among you.</p>
<p>(8) O give thanks unto him that maketh the horn of the house of David to bud;</p>
<p>For his mercy endureth for ever.</p>
<p>12<sup>c(9)</sup> O give thanks unto him that chose the sons of Zadok to be priests; <r1>Fol. B 7 recto</r1></p>
<p>For his mercy endureth for ever.</p>
<p><sup>(10)</sup> O give thanks unto the Shield of Abraham;</p>
<p>For his mercy endureth for ever.</p>
<p><sup>(11)</sup> O give thanks unto the Rock of Isaac;</p>
<p>For his mercy endureth for ever.</p>
<p><sup>(12)</sup> O give thanks unto the Mighty One of Jacob;</p>
<p>For his mercy endureth for ever.</p>
<p><sup>(13)</sup> O give thanks unto him that chose Zion;</p>
<p>For his mercy endureth for ever.</p>
<p><sup>(14)</sup> O give thanks unto the King of the kings of kings;</p>
<p>For his mercy endureth for ever.</p>
<p><sup>(15)</sup> And he will lift up the horn of his people:</p>
<p>A praise for all his saints;</p>
<p>Even for the children of Israel, a people near unto him.</p>
<p>Praise ye the Lord.</p>
<p>13 I was a youth;</p>
<p>And I delighted in her, and sought her.</p>
<p>13<sup>(1)</sup> My foot trod in her truth;</p>
<p>O my Lord, from my youth I learned wisdom.</p>
<p>5<sup>b</sup> And the arrows of a deceitful tongue.</p>
<p><l1>Fol. B 6 verso</l1> 6 And my soul drew near unto death;</p>
<p>And my life to Sheol beneath.</p>
<p>7<sup>c</sup> And I turned around, and there was none that helped me;</p>
<p>And I looked for one that would succour, and there was none.</p>
<p>8<sup>a</sup> And I remembered the mercies of the Lord;</p>
<p>And his lovingkindnesses which are from everlasting.</p>
<p>8<sup>c</sup> He that delivereth them that trust in him;</p>
<p>And redeemeth them from all evil.</p>
<p>9 And I lifted up my voice from the earth;</p>
<p>And from the gates of Sheol I cried.</p>
<p>10<sup>a</sup> And I exalted the Lord, <italic>saying</italic>, Thou art my Father;</p>
<p>10<sup>a(1)</sup> For thou art the mighty one of my salvation.</p>
<p>10<sup>b</sup> Leave me not in the day of trouble;</p>
<p>In the day of wasteness and desolation.</p>
<p>11<sup>a</sup> I will praise thy name continually;</p>
<p>And I will remember thee with prayer.</p>
<p>11<sup>c</sup> Then the Lord heard my voice;</p>
<p>11<sup>c(1)</sup> And gave ear unto my supplication.</p>
<p>12<sup>a</sup> And he ransomed me from all evil;</p>
<p>And freed me in the day of trouble.</p>
<p>12<sup>c</sup> Therefore I gave thanks, and I will sing praise;</p>
<p>And I will bless the name of the Lord.</p>
<p>12<sup>c(1)</sup> O give thanks unto the Lord, for he is good;</p>
<p>For his mercy endureth for ever.</p>
<p><sup>(2)</sup> O give thanks unto the God of praises;</p>
<p>For his mercy endureth for ever.</p>
<p><sup>(3)</sup> O give thanks unto him that keepeth Israel;</p>
<p>For his mercy endureth for ever.</p>
<p><sup>(4)</sup> O give thanks unto him that formeth all;</p>
<p>For his mercy endureth for ever.</p>
<p><sup>(5)</sup> O give thanks unto him that redeemeth Israel;</p>
<p>For his mercy endureth for ever.</p>
<p><sup>(6)</sup> O give thanks unto him that gathereth the outcasts of Israel;</p>
<p>For his mercy endureth for ever.</p>
<p><sup>(7)</sup> O give thanks unto him that buildeth his city and his sanctuary;</p>
<p>For his mercy endureth for ever.</p>
<p>28 Hear, ye many (?), my teaching in my youth;</p>
<p>And ye shall get silver and gold by me.</p>
<p>29 My soul shall rejoice in my age (<italic>or</italic> his praise);</p>
<p>And ye shall not be ashamed of my song.</p>
<p>30 Work your works in righteousness;</p>
<p>And he shall give you your reward in his season.</p>
<p>30<sup>(1)</sup> Blessed is the Lord for ever;</p>
<p>And praised be his name to generation and generation.</p>
<p>30<sup>(2)</sup> Hitherto are the words of Simon, son of Jesus, who is called Ben Sira.</p>
<p>30<sup>(3)</sup> The Wisdom of Simon, son of Jesus, son of Eleazar, son of Sira.</p>
<p>30<sup>(4)</sup> Be the name of the Lord blessed henceforth and for ever.</p>
<p>14<sup>a</sup> And I prayed a prayer in my youth;</p>
<p>16<sup>b</sup> And I found knowledge abundantly.</p>
<p>17 Her yoke (?) was a glory to me;</p>
<p>And to my teacher will I give thanks.</p>
<p>18 I thought to benefit;</p>
<p>And I would not turn when I found it (?).</p>
<p>18<sup>b(1)</sup> My soul longed for her;</p>
<p>And I would not turn my face from her.</p>
<p>20<sup>a</sup> I gave my soul after her;</p>
<p>20<sup>a(1)</sup> And for ever and ever I will not swerve&#x2026;</p>
<p>20<sup>a(2)</sup> My hand opened her gates;</p>
<p>And I looked for her (?), and beheld her (S);</p>
<p>20<sup>bcd</sup> And in pureness I found her.</p>
<p>And I gat me (?) understanding from her beginning;</p>
<p>Therefore&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;.&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;.&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;.&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;.&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;.&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;.&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;.&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;.</p>
<p><l1>Fol. B 7 verso</l1> 21 My inward parts were hot (?) as an oven for her, to behold her;</p>
<p>Therefore I possessed her as a good possession.</p>
<p>22 The Lord gave me the reward of my lips;</p>
<p>And with my tongue will I give him thanks.</p>
<p>23 Turn unto me, O foolish ones;</p>
<p>And lodge in my house of learning.</p>
<p>24 How long shall ye lack these things,</p>
<p>And your soul be very thirsty?</p>
<p>25 I opened my mouth and spake of her,</p>
<p>Get ye wisdom in possession without money.</p>
<p>26<sup>a</sup> And (?) bring your necks into her yoke;</p>
<p>And let your soul take up her burden.</p>
<p>26<sup>c</sup> She is nigh to them that seek her;</p>
<p>And he that giveth his soul findeth her.</p>
<p>27 See with your eyes that I was a little one;</p>
<p>And I laboured (G S) in her and found her.</p>
</chapter>
</book>
