<book>
<chapter>
<title>1</title>
<p>1. And after the death of Shaul, Dovid returned from defeating Amoleik. Dovid dwelled in Tziklog for two days.</p>
<p>2. On the third day behold a man came from the camp, from Shaul&#x2019;s people. His clothes were torn and dirt was on his head. And when he came to Dovid, he fell to the ground and prostrated himself.</p>
<p>3. Dovid said to him, &#x201C;From where are you coming?&#x201D; The man replied to him, &#x201C;I have escaped from the Yisroelite camp.&#x201D;</p>
<p>4. Dovid said to him, &#x201C;What happened, please tell me?&#x201D; The man replied, &#x201C;The people fled from the war. In addition, many of the people fell and died. And Shaul and his son Yohonoson also died.&#x201D;</p>
<p>5. Dovid said to the young man who was informing him, &#x201C;How do you know that Shaul and his son Yohonoson have died?&#x201D;</p>
<p>6. The young man who was informing him replied, I happened by chance upon Mount Gilboa and there was Shaul impaled upon his spear. Presently, the chariots and horsemen were coming close to him.</p>
<p>7. He turned around and saw me and he called to me, I said, &#x2018;Here I am.&#x2019;</p>
<p>8. He said to me, &#x2018;Who are you?&#x2019; I replied to him, &#x2018;I am an Amoleikite.&#x2019;</p>
<p>9. He said to me, &#x2018;Stand over me and kill me&#x2014;because I am gripped with convulsions&#x2014;while I am still alive.&#x2019;</p>
<p>10. I stood over him and killed him because I knew he would not live after his fall. I took the crown that was upon his head and the bracelet that was on his arm and I have brought them here to my master.&#x201D;</p>
<p>11. Dovid took hold of his clothes and ripped them as did all the men that were with him.</p>
<p>12. The eulogized, they cried and they fasted until the evening over Shaul, and over his son Yohonoson, over the people of Adonoy and over the house of Yisroel because they fell by the sword.</p>
<p>13. Dovid said to the young man who informed him, &#x201C;Where are you from?&#x201D; He replied, &#x201C;I am the son of an Amoleikite convert.&#x201D;</p>
<p>14. Dovid told him, &#x201C;How did you not fear thrusting your hand forth to destroy Adonoy&#x2019;s anointed one?&#x201D;</p>
<p>15. Dovid called one of the young men and said, &#x201C;Come here. Execute him.&#x201D; He struck him and he died.</p>
<p>16. Dovid said to him, &#x201C;Your blood is on your own head because your own mouth testified against yourself, saying, &#x2018;I killed Adonoy&#x2019;s anointed one.&#x2019;&#x201D;</p>
<p>17. Dovid composed this lamentation on Shaul and his son Yohonoson.</p>
<p>18. He said, &#x201C;To teach the Bnei Yehudah archery behold it is written in the Seifer HaYoshor.</p>
<p>19. Pillar of Yisroel, on your heights [you have been rendered] a corpse. How the mighty have fallen.</p>
<p>20. Do not tell [this] in Gass, do not announce [this] in the streets of Ashkelon. Lest the daughters of Plishtim rejoice, lest the daughters of the uncircumsized regale.</p>
<p>21. Mountains in Gilboa, the dew and the rain should not [fall] upon you nor fields [yielding enough for] baking offerings. Because there, the shield of soldiers spit out, the shield of Shaul was not smeared with oil.</p>
<p>22. [Without drawing] from the blood of corpses, [without cutting] from the fat of soldiers, the bow of Yohonasan would not be pulled back. The sword of Shaul was not returned empty.</p>
<p>23. Shaul and Yohonasan, loved and Cherished during their lifetime, During their deaths, they were not separated [from being loved], they were lighter then eagles, they were stronger then lions.</p>
<p>24. Daughters of Yisroel, weep over Shaul who has clothed you in scarlet clothing together with other delights, who has adorned your garments with gold jewelry.</p>
<p>25. How the mighty have fallen during battle. Yohanasan, on your heights, [you were] slain.</p>
<p>26. I anguish over you, my brother Yohansan you were very cherished to me. Your love was more wondrous to me then the love of women.</p>
<p>27. How the mighty have fallen and the weapons of war lost.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>2</title>
<p>1. And after this, Dovid asked of Adonoy saying, &#x201C;Should I go up to one of the cities of Yehudah?&#x201D; Adonoy said to him, &#x201C;Go up.&#x201D; Dovid said, &#x201C;Where should I go up to?&#x201D; And He said, &#x201C;To Chevron.&#x201D;</p>
<p>2. Dovid went up there as did his two wives, Achinoam the Yizraelite and Avigayil the [former] wife of Novol from Carmel.</p>
<p>3. Dovid brought up his men that were with him, each man and his household, and they settled in the cities of Chevron.</p>
<p>4. The people of Yehudah came and anointed Dovid there to be the king over Beis Yehudah. They informed Dovid, telling [him] that the people of Yoveish Gilod had buried Shaul.</p>
<p>5. Dovid sent messengers to the people of Yoveish Gilod and he said to them, &#x201C;You should be blessed before Adonoy for this kindness that you have done for your master, for Shaul, that which you buried him.&#x201D;</p>
<p>6. &#x201C;And now, Adonoy should do kindness and truth unto you. I will also do the same unto you for this good deed, that you have done.&#x201D;</p>
<p>7. &#x201C;Now, strengthen you hands and become brave because your master Shaul has died, and the House of Yehudah have anointed me to be king over them.&#x201D;</p>
<p>8. Avner, the son of Ner, Shaul&#x2019;s military chief of staff took Ish Boshes, the son of Shaul and brought him to Machanoyim.</p>
<p>9. He made him king over Gilod, over Asher, over Yizrael, over Ephraim, over Binyomin and over all Yisroel.</p>
<p>10. Forty year old was Ish Boshes, the son of Shaul when he reigned over Yisroel. He reigned for two years. But the House of Yehuda followed David.</p>
<p>11. And the number of years, that David was king in Chevron, over the house of Yehuda was seven years and six months.</p>
<p>12. Avner, the son of Ner and the servants of Ish Boshes, the son of Shaul left Machanoyim and went to Givon</p>
<p>13. Yoav, the son of Tseruyoh and David&#x2019;s servants went out and met with them at the pool of Givon. One party sat on one side of the pool and the other party sat on the other side.</p>
<p>14. Avner said to Yoav, &#x201C;Let the young soldiers get up and playfight before us.&#x201D; And Yoav said, &#x201C;Let them get up.&#x201D;</p>
<p>15. And they got up and crossed over to the other side [of the pool] in even numbers &#x2014; twelve from [the tribe of] Binyamin, for Ish Boshes, the son of Shaul, and twelve from the servants of Dovid.</p>
<p>16. Each of the men grabbed his opponent&#x2019;s head and [thrust] his sword in his opponent&#x2019;s side, and they all fell [dead] together. That place was called the plain of swords which is in Givon.</p>
<p>17. The fighting was intense on that day, Avner and men of Yisroel were beaten by the servants of Dovid.</p>
<p>18. The three sons of Tseruyoh were there Yoav, Avishai and Asoel. Asoel was light on his feet, like one of the deer in a field.</p>
<p>19. Asoel chased after Avner, and did not stray right or left from pursuing Avner.</p>
<p>20. Avner turned around and said, &#x201C;Are you Asoel?&#x201D; and he replied, &#x201C;It is I.&#x201D;</p>
<p>21. Avner said to him, &#x201C;Stray to your right or your left, and grab for yourself one of the soldiers, and take for yourself his weapon. Asoel did not want to veer off from [running] after him.</p>
<p>22. Avner continued and said to Asoel, &#x201C;Veer off from [running] after me. Why should I strike you [dead] to the ground? How will I face your brother?&#x201D; He refused to veer off and Avner hit him with the back of the spear into the fifth rib. The spear came out from the back of him and he fell there and died in his place. And it was that all [the pursuers] who reached the place where Asoel fell and died, stopped [their pursuit].</p>
<p>24. Yoav and Avishai chased after Avner, and the sun set [as] they had reached Givas Amoh that faces Giach on the way to the desert of Givon.</p>
<p>25. The men of Binyomin regrouped behind Avner and became one unit and they stood atop a mountain.</p>
<p>26. Avner called to Yoav and said, &#x201C;Will the sword be killing forever? You know it will come to a bitter end. For how long will you not tell the people to turn around and not pursue their brothers.&#x201D;</p>
<p>27. Yoav said, By the life of Elokim, if you had not spoken [earlier] then already from the morning the people would have gone up [and left] each man [from pursuing] after his brother.</p>
<p>28. Yoav blew the Shofer. All the people stopped and no longer pursued after [the men of] Yisroel. They no longer continued to fight [with them].</p>
<p>29. Avner and his men traveled in the plain all that night. They crossed the Yardein, and traveled through all of the Bisron [region] and they came to Machanoim.</p>
<p>30. Yoav turned away from [chasing] after Avner and he gathered all the people. There was missing from the servants of Dovid, [a total of] nineteen men and Asoel.</p>
<p>31. Dovid&#x2019;s servants killed [many] from the people of Binyomin and of Avner&#x2019;s men. Three hundred and sixty men died.</p>
<p>32. They carried Asoel and buried him in the grave of his father that is in Beis Lechem. Yoav and his men traveled all night and dawn [broke] for them [as they came] in [to] Chevron.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>3</title>
<p>1. There was a long war between the house of Shaul and the house of Dovid. Dovid was [continuosly] getting stronger, and the house of Shaul was [continuously] getting weaker.</p>
<p>2. Sons were born to Dovid in Chevron, his first born was Amnon by Achinoam the Yiszraelite.</p>
<p>3. His second [son] was Kilov by Avigayil, the wife of Novol the Carmelite. The third [son] was Avsholom, the son of Maachoh, the daughter of Talmai, the king of Geshur.</p>
<p>4. The fourth [son] was Adoniyoh, the son of Chagis. The fifth [son] was Shephatiyoh, the son of Avital.</p>
<p>5. The sixth [son] was Yisrom by Egloh, the wife of Dovid. These [sons] were born to Dovid in Chevron.</p>
<p>6. While the war was [going on] between the house of Shaul and the house of Dovid, Avner was strengthening the house of Shaul.</p>
<p>7. Shaul had a concubine and her name was Rizpah, the daughter of Ayoh [Ish boshes] said to Avner, &#x201C;Why have you visited [conjugally] my father&#x2019;s concubine?&#x201D;</p>
<p>8. Avner became very angry on account of] the words of Ish Boshes and said, &#x201C;Am I the chief dog [watcher] for [the kingdom of] Yehuda? From this day on should I [continue to] be kind to the house of Shaul, your father, to his brothers and to his friends? And I have not delivered you into the hand of Dovid. [But] you [still] remember the sin [involving] the woman, [using it] against me today.&#x201D;</p>
<p>9. &#x201C;This is what Elokim should do to Avner and so may He do further for as Adonoy swore to Dovid so I shall do for him.&#x201D;</p>
<p>10. &#x201C;To remove the monarchy from the house of Shaul and to establish the throne of Dovid over Yisroel and over Yehuda from Don to B&#x2019;er Sheva&#x201D;</p>
<p>11. [Ish Boshes] couldn&#x2019;t answer anything to Avner because of his fear of him.</p>
<p>12. Avner sent messengers to Dovid in his behalf, saying, by He Who [possesses] the land [and] saying [further], &#x201C;Enact a convenant with me and my hand will be with you to bring all of Yisroel around to you.&#x201D;</p>
<p>13. He said [in response] &#x201C;Good, I will enact a convenant with you, but just one thing I ask of you saying, do not see my face unless you first bring Michal, the daughter of Shaul when you come to see my face.&#x201D;</p>
<p>14. And Dovid sent messengers to Ish Boshes, the son of Shaul saying, &#x201C;Give me my wife Michal that I betrothed to me with the one hundred foreskins of the Pelishtim</p>
<p>15. And Ish Boshes sent [messengers] and took her from [her] husband from Paltiel, the son of Loyish.</p>
<p>16. Her husband went with her following and crying after her until Bachurim. Avner said to him, &#x201C;Go return.&#x201D; and he returned.</p>
<p>17. The word of Avner was [sent] to the elders of Yisroel, saying &#x201C;Yesterday and also the day before yesterday, you requested that Dovid be king over you.&#x201D;</p>
<p>18. &#x201C;And now, do it because Adonoy said about Dovid, &#x2018;through the hand of Dovid My servant I will save My people Yisroel from the hand of the Pelishtim and the hand of all their enemies.&#x2019;&#x201D;</p>
<p>19. Avner also spoke to [the people] of Binyomin. Avner also went to speak to Dovid in Chevron all that seemed good in the eyes of Yisroel and in the eyes of all of the house of Binyomin [that Dovid should ascend the throne].</p>
<p>20. Avner came to Dovid in Chevron, and with him were twenty men. Dovid made for Avner and the men with him, a feast.</p>
<p>21. Avner said to Dovid, &#x201C;I&#x2019;ll get up and go and I will gather for my master, the king, all of Yisroel. They will enact a convenant with you and you will reign over all that you desire.&#x201D; Dovid sent Avner [to do this] and he went in peace.</p>
<p>22. And it was that the servants of Dovid and Yoav came back from an attack and brought with them a large booty. Avner was not with Dovid in Chevron because [Dovid] had sent him off and he had gone in peace.</p>
<p>23. Yoav and all of the army with him came and Yoav was told, &#x201C;Avner, the son of Ner came to the king and [the king] sent him off, and he went in peace.&#x201D;</p>
<p>24. Yoav came to the king and said, &#x201C;What did you do? Here Avner came to you, why did you send him off and he went?&#x201D;</p>
<p>25. &#x201C;You know Avner, the son of Ner, he came to seduce you and to know about your goings and comings and to know about everything you do.&#x201D;</p>
<p>26. Yoav went out from [before] Dovid. [He then] sent messengers after Avner and they returned him from Bor HaSiroh. Dovid was unaware [of this].</p>
<p>27. Avner returned to Chevron and Yoav steered him to go within the gate to talk to him, deceptively, [Yoav] hit him there into the fifth rib and [Avner] died on account of the blood of Asoel, [Yoav&#x2019;s] brother.</p>
<p>28. And afterwards, when Dovid heard [about this] he said, I and my kingdom are innocent, from [before] Adonoy forever, from the blood of Avner, the son of Ner.</p>
<p>29. [The guilt] should fall on the head of Yoav and on his father&#x2019;s entire house. There should never cease from the house of Yoav, [the afflictions of] a discharging man, a leper, [a lame person] who leans on a cane, [a person] felled by the sword and [a person] lacking bread.</p>
<p>30. Yoav and his brother Avishai killed Avner because he killed their brother Asoel in Givon, in battle.</p>
<p>31. Dovid said to Yoav and to all the people that were with him, &#x201C;Rent your clothes, tie on sackcloth and eulogize before Avner,&#x201D; and King Dovid himself followed the coffin.</p>
<p>32. They buried Avner in Chevron, and the king lifted up his voice and wept over Avner&#x2019;s grave and all the people wept.</p>
<p>33. The king lamented over Avner and said, &#x201C;Should Avner have died the death of the wicked?</p>
<p>34. Your hands were not bound, your feet were not put into bronze chains. Like those who fell before treacherous men you have fallen.&#x201D; All the people continued to cry over him.</p>
<p>35. All the people came to offer Dovid [the mourner&#x2019;s] bread while it was still daytime. Dovid swore saying, &#x201C;Such should Elokim do to me and even more so if, before sunset, I should taste bread or anything else.&#x201D;</p>
<p>36. All the people recognized [that Dovid wasn&#x2019;t involved] and [this] was good in their eyes. Everything the king did was good in the eyes of all the people.</p>
<p>37. All of the people and all Yisroel knew on that day that it was not [an order] from the king to kill Avner, the son of Ner.</p>
<p>38. And the king said to his servants You know that an officer and a great man fell on this day in Yisroel.</p>
<p>39. I am today weak [as a commoner] and only just annointed king and these men, the sons of Tseruyoh are tougher then me. Adonoy will repay the evildoer according to his evil deed.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>4</title>
<p>1. The son of Shaul heard that Avner had died in Chevron. His hands weakened and all of Yisroel trembled.</p>
<p>2. Two men were officers of troops for the son of Shaul, the name of one was Ba&#x2019;anoh and the name of the second was Raichov. [They were] the sons of Rimon the Be&#x2019;erosite from the people of Binyomin because Be&#x2019;eros was also considered part of Binyomin.</p>
<p>3. The Be&#x2019;erosites fled to Gitoim and they lived there until this day.</p>
<p>4. Yahonoson, the son of Shaul had a son with broken feet. He was five years old when the news came regarding [the deaths of] Yahonoson and Shaul from Yiszrael. His nurse picked him up and fled. [However,] in her haste to flee he fell and was rendered lame, and his name was Mephiboshes</p>
<p>5. The sons of Rimon the Be&#x2019;erosite went, Raichov and Ba&#x2019;anoh, and they came during the heat of the day into the house of Ish Boshes, He was sleeping [during] his afternoon nap.</p>
<p>6. They came into the interior of the house [together with] wheat buyers, and they hit him in the fifth rib. [Then] Raichov and his brother Ba&#x2019;anoh escaped.</p>
<p>7. They came into the house and he was sleeping on his bed in his bedroom. They hit him and killed him, and they removed his head. They took his head and they traveled westwardly all night.</p>
<p>8. They brought the head of Ish Boshes to Dovid in Chevron and they said to the king, &#x201C;Here is the head of Ish Boshes, the son of Shaul, your enemy, that sought to kill you. Adonoy has delivered to my master, the king, vengeance on this day from Shaul and his offspring.&#x201D;</p>
<p>9. Dovid responded to Raichov and his brother Ba&#x2019;ano the sons of Rimon the Be&#x2019;erosite and said to them, &#x201C;By the living Adonoy that saved me from all anguish.</p>
<p>10. When the person told me, saying, &#x2018;Behold, Shaul has died,&#x2019; he thought he was announcing good tidings [but] I seized him and killed him in Ziklog. He thought I would reward him for his good tidings.</p>
<p>11. Even [more so I am displeased] that these wicked men killed a righteous man in his house on his bed. And now, I will seek [vengeance for] his blood from your hands and I will eradicate you from the land.</p>
<p>12. Dovid gave orders to the young soldiers and they killed them. They cut off their hands and their feet and they hung them by the pool in Chevron. They took the head of Ish Boshes and they buried it by Avner&#x2019;s burial place in Chevron.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>5</title>
<p>1. All the tribes of Yisroel came to Chevron, to Dovid and they said, &#x201C;We are your bone and your flesh.&#x201D;</p>
<p>2. Both yesterday and the day before yesterday while Shaul was king over us you were the one who took out and brought back Yisroel, and Adonoy said to you, &#x2018;You will lead my people Yisroel and you will be a prince over Yisroel.&#x2019;&#x201D; All the elders of Yisroel came to Chevron to the king and King Dovid enacted a pact with them in Chevron before Adonoy and they anointed Dovid to be king over Yisroel.</p>
<p>4. Dovid was a man of thirty years when he [first] reigned. He was king for forty years.</p>
<p>5. In Chevron, he reigned over Yehudah for seven years and six months and in Yerushaloyim he reigned for thirty-three years over all of Yisroel and Yehuda.</p>
<p>6. The king and his men went to Yerusholoyim to the Yevusim who dwelled in that land. He said to Dovid, You shall not come lest you [are able to] remove [the idols depicting] the blind and the lame which are saying, &#x2018;Dovid will not come here.&#x2019;</p>
<p>7. Dovid conquored the fortress of Tzion This is [now] the city of Dovid.</p>
<p>8. Dovid said on that day, &#x201C;Whoever kills the Yevusi and touches [and destroys] the tower&#x2019;s spire and [the idols of] the lame and the blind, which were abhored by Dovid, upon which they are saying, &#x2018;[While] the blind one and the lame one [are here], [Dovid] will not come into the house.&#x2019;&#x201D;</p>
<p>9. Dovid settled in the fortress, and he called it the city of Dovid. Dovid built around [the fortress], from it&#x2019;s low wall and inwards.</p>
<p>10. Dovid became continuously greater, and Adonoy, the God of Legions was with him.</p>
<p>11. Chirom, the king of Tzor sent messengers to Dovid [bringing with them] cedarwood and carpenters and stone cutters [who could build] a wall. They built a house for Dovid.</p>
<p>12. Dovid understood that Adonoy had established him king over Yisroel and that his kingdom had been elevated for the sake of His people Yisroel.</p>
<p>13. Dovid took more concubines and wives from Yerusholoyim after he arrived from Chevron. More sons and daughters were born to Dovid.</p>
<p>14. These are the names of the [children] born to him in Yerusholoyim, Shaua, Shovov, Noson and Shlomo.</p>
<p>15. Yivchor, Elishua, Nepheg and Yophia.</p>
<p>16. Elishoma, Elyodo and Elipholet.</p>
<p>17. The Pelishtim heard that they had anointed Dovid to be king over Yisroel. All the Pelishtim went up seeking [to fight] Dovid. Dovid heard [about this] and descended to the tortress.</p>
<p>18. The Pelishtim came and fanned out acros the valley of Rephaim.</p>
<p>19. Dovid asked of Adonoy, saying, &#x201C;Should I go up [to fight] the Pelishtim? Will they be delivered into my hands?&#x201D; Adonoy said to Dovid, &#x201C;Go up, because I will deliver the Pelishtim into your hands.&#x201D;</p>
<p>20. Dovid came into the plain of Perotzim. Dovid smote them there and declared, &#x201C;Adonoy has shatterred my enemies before me like water bursting over [walls]&#x201D; Because of this, he called the name of that place the plain of Perotzim</p>
<p>21. [The Pelishtim] abandoned their idols there and Dovid and his men burnt them.</p>
<p>22. The Pelishtim continued to go up and fan out across the valley of Repahim.</p>
<p>23. Dovid asked Adonoy [what to do] and He answered, &#x201C;Do not go up, circle around to their rear and come at them from opposite the trees.&#x201D;</p>
<p>24. &#x201C;When you hear the sound of stepping on the tops of the trees then shout out [war whoops] because then Adonoy has gone out before you to smite the Plishtim camp.</p>
<p>25. Dovid did as Adonoy commanded him and he smote the Plishtim from Gevah until you come to Gozer.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>6</title>
<p>1. Dovid again gathered all the chosen men of Yisroel, thirty thousand.</p>
<p>2. Dovid arose and went with all the people that were with him from Baalei Yehuda, to bring up from there the Ark of Elokim, whose name is called by the name of Adonoy of Hosts who dwells upon the Cherubim.</p>
<p>3. They had the Ark of Elokim ride on a new wagon. They carried it from the house of Avinodov that is in Givoh. Uzoh and Achyo, the sons of Avinodov were driving the new wagon.</p>
<p>4. They carried it from the house of Avinodov that was in Givoh accompanying the Ark of Elokim, and Achyo went before the Ark.</p>
<p>5. Dovid and all the house of Yisroel were rejoicing before [the Ark of] Adonoy with all [instruments made of] cypress wood [such as] harps, lyres, drums, coronets and cymbals.</p>
<p>6. They came to the grainery of Nochon and Uzoh stretched [his hand] towards the Ark of Elokim and held it because the ox had [made] it slip.</p>
<p>7. Adonoy became angry with Uzoh and Elokim struck him there because of his mistake. He died there by the Ark of Elokim.</p>
<p>8. Dovid was angered [with himself] concerning the breach of Uzoh and he called that place Peretz Uzoh until this day.</p>
<p>9. Dovid feared Adonoy on that day, He said, &#x201C;How shall the Ark of Adonoy come to me.&#x201D;</p>
<p>10. Dovid did not want to bring the Ark of Adonoy towards him, to the city of Dovid. Dovid carried it aside [to] the house of Oveid Edom the Gittite.</p>
<p>11. The Ark of Adonoy dwelled in the house of Oveid Edom the Gittite for three months, and Adonoy blessed Oveid Edom and his entire household.</p>
<p>12. It was told to King Dovid, saying, &#x201C;Adonoy has blessed Oveid Edom and all that he has on account of the Ark of Elokim.&#x201D; Dovid went and brought up the Ark of Elokim from the house of Oveid Edom [to] the city of Dovid, with rejoicing.</p>
<p>13. When the carriers of the Ark of Adonoy stepped six paces, he sacrificed oxen and fattened oxen.</p>
<p>14. Dovid danced with all [his] strength before [the Ark of] Adonoy. Dovid was girded with a linen robe.</p>
<p>15. Dovid and all of the house of Yisroel brought up the Ark of Adonoy with shouting and with the sound of the Shofar.</p>
<p>16. As the Ark of Adonoy came [to] the city of Dovid Michal, the daughter of Shaul was looking through the window. She saw king Dovid dancing and leaping before [the Ark of] Adonoy, and he was disgraced in her heart.</p>
<p>17. They brought the Ark of Adonoy and they set it in its place in the tent that Dovid had spread out for it. Dovid brought up burnt offerings before Adonoy and also peace offerings.</p>
<p>18. Dovid finished bringing up the burnt offering and the peace offerings and he blessed the people with the Name of Adonoy of Hosts.</p>
<p>19. He distributed to all the people, to the whole multitude of Yisroel whether man or woman, for each person one loaf of bread, a portion of meat and a jug [of wine]. The people left, each person to his house.</p>
<p>20. Dovid returned to bless his household. Michal, the daughter of Shaul went out to greet Dovid and she said, &#x201C;How glorious is this day&#x0021; The king of Yisroel revealed [himself] today [before] the eyes of the handmaidens of his servants as one of the riff-raff reveals [himself].&#x201D;</p>
<p>21. Dovid said to Michal, &#x201C;Before Adonoy, Who has chosen me [over] your father and all his household, charging me to be ruler over the people of Adonoy, over Yisroel, I rejoiced before Adonoy.</p>
<p>22. [Had] I made light of myself even more then this, and lowered myself in my [own] eyes and with the handmaidens that you mentioned, I woud be more honoured among them.&#x201D;</p>
<p>23. Michal, the daughter of Shaul had no child until the day of her death.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>7</title>
<p>1. When the king dwelled in his house and Adonoy granted him rest from all his enemies around [him].</p>
<p>2. The king said to the prophet Noson, &#x201C;See now, I dwell in a house of cedar wood and the Ark of Elokim dwells within a curtain.&#x201D;</p>
<p>3. Noson said to the king, &#x201C;All that is in your heart, go do because Adonoy is with you.&#x201D;</p>
<p>4. And it was on that night, the word of Adonoy [came] to Noson saying.</p>
<p>5. Go and say to my servant Dovid, &#x201C;Thus said Adonoy, &#x2018;Is it you that will build for Me a house for My dwelling?&#x2019;</p>
<p>6. &#x2018;For I have not dwelled in a house from the day I brought up the Bnei Yisroel from Egypt until this day, but have travelled within a tent and the Mishkan.&#x2019;</p>
<p>7. &#x2018;In all [the places] that I have traveled amongst the Bnei Yisroel, have I said a word to one of the rulers of Yisroel that I have commanded to lead my people Yisroel saying, &#x2018;Why haven&#x2019;t you built me a house of cedarwood?&#x201D;</p>
<p>8. &#x2018;And now, this is what you should say to my servant Dovid, this is what Adonoy of Hosts says, &#x2018;I have taken you from the corral, from [following] behind the sheep to be a prince over My people Yisroel.&#x201D;</p>
<p>9. &#x2018;I will be with you wherever you go&#x2019; &#x2018;I will destroy all your enemies from before you.&#x2019; I will make for you a great name like the name of great people that are in the land.</p>
<p>10. &#x2018;I will make a place for My people Yisroel and I will root [the people in their land] and [the people] will dwell [in their land] and they will not be removed [from the land], and the wicked will no longer afflict [the people] as before.&#x2019;</p>
<p>11. &#x2018;And from the day that I commanded Judges over My people Yisroel.&#x2019; &#x2018;I will give you respite from all your enemies.&#x2019; Adonoy is telling you that He will establish a monarchy for you.</p>
<p>12. &#x2018;When your days are filled and you are [laid] to rest with your fathers, I will establish your offspring after you that will emerge from your bowels; and I will establish his monarchy.&#x2019;</p>
<p>13. &#x2018;He will build a Temple for My Name and I will establish the throne of his kingdom forever.&#x2019;</p>
<p>14. &#x2018;I will be a Father to him and he will be a son to Me. Should he commit iniquity I will rebuke him with the rod of men and with the afflictions of people.&#x2019;</p>
<p>15. &#x2018;My kindness will not depart from him as I removed it from Shaul Whom I have removed from before you&#x2019;</p>
<p>16. &#x2018;Your House and monarchy will be established forever before you,&#x2019; Your throne will be established forever.&#x2019;</p>
<p>17. All these things and this entire vision, Noson told it to Dovid.</p>
<p>18. King Dovid came and sat before the Ark of Adonoy and said, &#x201C;Who am I, my Master Elokim and who is my household that You have brought me until this point.</p>
<p>19. This was yet small in your eyes, my Master Elokim, that You have spoken also about the house of your servant [and generations] in the distant future. Is this announcement [fitting] for [mere] man, my Master Elokim.</p>
<p>20. What more can Dovid say to You? You know Your servant, my Master Elokim.</p>
<p>21. Because of Your word and due to [the will of] Your Heart, You have made [given me] all this greatness of which You have informed Your servant.</p>
<p>22. Through this [I understand] that You are great my Master Elokim, because there is no other like You and there is no other god but You according to all that we heard with out ears.</p>
<p>23. Who is like Your people, like Yisroel a unique nation in the world, for whom leaders went [telling Yisroel, &#x201C;Our mission is to redeem for Him, a people to put forth His Name, and to make great [things happen] for you.&#x201D; [You have done] awesome things for your land, from before Your people that You have redeemed from Egypt for Yourself, [You have driven out] nations and their gods.</p>
<p>24. You prepared for Yourself your people Yisroel [to be] a people for you until eternity and You Adonoy have been for them, Elokim.</p>
<p>25. And now Adonoy Elokim, the thing that You have spoken concerning You servant and concerning his household establish it forever and do as You said.</p>
<p>26. And Your Name will be great forever [with people] saying, &#x201C;Adonoy of Hosts, Elokim [rules] over Yisroel&#x201D; and may the house of Dovid, Your servant be established before You.</p>
<p>27. Because You Adonoy of Hosts, the God of Yisroel revealed to the ear of Your servant saying, &#x201C;I will build you a House and thus your servant set his heart to pray this prayer to You.</p>
<p>28. And now Adonoy Elokim, You are the Elokim and Your words will be true, and You have spoken, to Your servant, [about] this good [thing to come].</p>
<p>29. And now, may it please You [to] bless the House of Your servant to be forever [servants] before You, for You have spoken, my Master Elokim, and from Your blessings, may the House of Your servant be blessed forever.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>8</title>
<p>1. Afterwords Dovid struck the Pelishtim and humbled them. Dovid took Meseg Hoamoh from the hand of the Pelishtim.</p>
<p>2. He struck Moav and he measured them with a rope. He had them lie down on the ground, those measured with two ropes were killed and those with the fullness of one rope were allowed to live. Moav became Dovid&#x2019;s slaves, bearers of a [yearly] present [for Dovid].</p>
<p>3. Dovid struck Haddadezer, the son of Rechov the king of Tsovoh, as he went to enlarge his border at the P&#x2019;ras river.</p>
<p>4. Dovid captured from him one thousand and seven hundred cavalrymen and twenty thousand men on foot. Dovid destroyed all the chariot [horses], [with] one hundred chariot [horses] remaining.</p>
<p>5. Aram Damesek came to help Haddadezer, the king of Tsovoh. Dovid struck among the Aram twenty-two thousand men.</p>
<p>6. Dovid placed officers in Aram Damesek and [the people of] Aram were slaves to Dovid bearers of [an annual] present. Adonoy protected Dovid wherever he went.</p>
<p>7. Dovid took the golden quivers that had belonged to the servants of Heddadezcr and brought them to Yerushalayim.</p>
<p>8. From Betach and from Bairosy, cities of Haddadezer, King Dovid took a large amount of bronze.</p>
<p>9. Toiy the king of Chamos heard that Dovid struck [down] the entire army of Haddadezer.</p>
<p>10. Toiy sent his son Yorom to king Dovid to ask of his peace and to bless him because he had fought against Haddadezer and had struck him [down], for Toiy was enemies with Haddadezer. In his [Yoram&#x2019;s] hand were silver utensils, gold utensils and bronze utensils.</p>
<p>11. Those [utensils] also king Dovid sanctified for [the service of] Adonoy in addition to the silver and gold that he had sanctified [from what was captured] from all the nations that he had conquered.</p>
<p>12. From Arom, from Moav, from the children of Amon from the Pleshtim and from Amoleik, and from the booty [captured from] Haddadezer, the son of Rechov, the king of Tsovoh.</p>
<p>13. Dovid made a name [for himself] during his return from striking Arom in Gay Melach [and killing] eighteen thousand men.</p>
<p>14. He placed officers in Edom. In all of Edom, he placed officers, and all of Edom were slaves to Dovid. Adonoy protected Dovid wherever he went.</p>
<p>15. Dovid ruled over all of Yisroel and Dovid rendered judgment and righteousness unto all of his people.</p>
<p>16. Yoav, the son of Tsruyoh was [commander] over the army and Yehoshophot, the son of Achilud was the announcer [of halachic cases].</p>
<p>17. Tsodok, the son of Achituv and Achimelech, the son of Evyosor were [leaders of] the Kohanim and Seroyoh was the scribe</p>
<p>18. Venoyohu, the son of Yehoyodoh [was in charge of] the archers and the sling shooters. The sons of Dovid were [prominent] leaders.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>9</title>
<p>1. Dovid said, &#x201C;Is there anyone left of the House of Shaul [so that] I may render kindness unto him for Yohonoson&#x2019;s sake?&#x201D;</p>
<p>2. The House of Shaul had a slave, his name was Tsivoh, and they called him to [meet] Dovid. The king said to him, &#x201C;Are you Tsivoh?&#x201D; He said, &#x201C;I am your servant.&#x201D;</p>
<p>3. The king said, &#x201C;Is there any man left of the House of Shaul [so that] I may render unto him the kindness of Elokim?&#x201D; Tzivoh said to the king, &#x201C;There is still a son left to Yohonoson [crippled with] broken legs.&#x201D;</p>
<p>4. The king said to him, &#x201C;Where is he?&#x201D; Tsivoh said to the king, &#x201C;He is in the house of Mochir, the son of Amiel in Lo Dvor&#x201D;</p>
<p>5. King Dovid sent [for him] and took him from the house of Mochir, the son of Amiel from Lo Dvor.</p>
<p>6. Mephivoshes, the son of Yohonoson, the son of Shaul came to Dovid. He fell on his face and prostrated himself. Dovid said, Mephivoshes? And he said, &#x201C;Here is your servant.&#x201D;</p>
<p>7. Dovid said to him, &#x201C;Do not fear because I will render kindness unto you for the sake of your father Yohonoson. I will return to you the entire field [estate] of your father Shaul and you will eat bread at my table perpetually.&#x201D;</p>
<p>8. He [Mephivoshes] prostrated himself and said, &#x201C;What [am I], your servant that you turned toward a dead dog like myself?&#x201D;</p>
<p>9. The king called Tzivoh Shaul&#x2019;s servant and said to him, &#x201C;All that which belonged to Shaul and to his House, I have given to the son of your master.</p>
<p>10. You will work the land for him, you, your children and your servants. You will bring in [the produce] and it will be food for the son of your master and he will eat it. And Mephivoshes, the son of your master. will always eat bread at my table.&#x201D; Tsivoh had fifteen sons and twenty slaves.</p>
<p>11. Tsivoh said to the king, &#x201C;All that my master, the king commands his servant so will your servant do.&#x201D; &#x201C;Mephivoshes will eat at my table like one of the sons of the king.&#x201D;</p>
<p>12. Mephivoshes had a small son, his name was Michoh, all those who dwelled in the house of Tsivoh were slaves to Mephivoshes</p>
<p>13. Mephivoshes dwelled in Yerusholayim because he always ate at the King&#x2019;s table and he was lame [on] both his legs.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>10</title>
<p>1. And it was, afterwords [that] the king of the people of Amon died and Chonun, his son reigned in his stead.</p>
<p>2. Dovid said, &#x201C;I will act with kindness towards Chonun, the son of Nochosh as his father acted with kindness towards me.&#x201D; Dovid sent to console him by the hand of his servants about his father. The servants of Dovid came to the land of the people of Amon.</p>
<p>3. The officers of the people of Amon said to Chonun, their master, &#x201C;Do you think Dovid honors your father because he has sent [representatives] to console you? It is to investigate the city and to spy on it and to overthrow it [that] Dovid has sent his servants to you.&#x201D;</p>
<p>4. Chonun took Dovid&#x2019;s servants and shaved off half their beards and tore their clothes halfway, [down] to their buttocks and sent them [away].</p>
<p>5. It was told to Dovid and he sent to meet them because the men were very ashamed. The king said, &#x201C;stay in Yeraicho until your beards grow [back] and [then] return.&#x201D;</p>
<p>6. The people of Amon saw that they were disgusting to Dovid. The people of Amon sent and hired Aram, of the house of Rechov and Aram Tsovoh, twenty thousand foot soldiers and king Machoh, a thousand men and Ish Tov, twelve thousand men.</p>
<p>7. Dovid heard [this] and sent Yoav and the whole army of mighty men.</p>
<p>8. The people of Amon went out and arranged war at the opening of the gate. And Aram Tsovoh, Rechov, Ish Tov and Machoh were by themselves [as a second flank] in the field.</p>
<p>9. Yoav saw that the fronts of the battle were [against] him from the front and from the rear. He chose from all the young men of Yisroel and set up to meet the men of Arom.</p>
<p>10. The rest of the people he gave to his brother Avshai and set up to meet the people of Amon.</p>
<p>11. [Yoav] said, &#x201C;If Arom overpowers me you [come] to save me and if the people of Amon overpower you I will go to save you.</p>
<p>12. You be strong and we should be strong for the sake of our people and for the cities of our God and Adonoy will do what&#x2019;s good in His Eyes.&#x201D;</p>
<p>13. Yoav and the people with him approached to [engage in] battle with the men of Arom and they fled from before him.</p>
<p>14. The people of Amon saw that the men of Arom had fled and they fled from before Avishai and went [back into] the city. Yoav returned from [fighting] against the people of Amon and he came to Yerusholoyim.</p>
<p>15. The men of Arom saw that they were stricken before Yisroel and they gathered together.</p>
<p>16. Hadadezer sent and brought out the men of Arom that were across the river. They came to Chailom and Shovach, the commander of Hadadezer&#x2019;s army was in front of them.</p>
<p>17. It was told to Dovid and he gathered all of Yisroel. He crossed over the Yardein and came to Chailomoh. The men of Arom set up to meet Dovid and fought with him.</p>
<p>18. The men of Arom fled from before Yisroel. Dovid killed from Arom the men of seven hundred chariots and forty thousand horseman. He struck Shovach, the commander of their army and he died there.</p>
<p>19. All the kings, the servants of Hadadezer saw that they were stricken before Yisroel. They made peace with Yisroel and served them. The men of Arom were afraid to help the people of Amon any more.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>11</title>
<p>1. And it was at the turn of the year at the time [of year] when kings go forth. Dovid sent Yoav, and his servants with him and all of Yisroel. They destroyed the people of Amon and they beseiged Rabboh [while] Dovid dwelled in Yerushalayim.</p>
<p>2. And it was at evening time, and Dovid got up from his bed and was walking on the palace roof. He saw a woman bathing from [his vantage point] on the rooftop and the woman was very beautiful.</p>
<p>3. Dovid sent and inquired about the woman and he said, &#x201C;Is this not Bas Shevah, the daughter of Eliom the wife of Urioh, the Hitite.&#x201D;</p>
<p>4. Dovid sent messengers and took her. She came to him and he laid with her, for she had purified herself from her uncleanliness and she returned to her house.</p>
<p>5. And the woman conceived and sent and told Dovid and said, &#x201C;I have conceived.&#x201D;</p>
<p>6. Dovid sent to Yoav, &#x201C;Send me Urioh, the Hitite.&#x201D; Yoav sent Urioh to Dovid.</p>
<p>7. Urioh came to him Dovid asked about Yoav&#x2019;s welfare, the welfare of the people and the welfare of the [soldiers at] war.</p>
<p>8. Dovid said to Urioh, &#x201C;Go down to your house and wash your legs.&#x201D; Urioh left the king&#x2019;s palace the king&#x2019;s meal followed him.</p>
<p>9. Urioh slept at the door of the king&#x2019;s palace with all his master&#x2019;s servants and he did not go down to his house.</p>
<p>10. They told to Dovid saying, &#x201C;Urioh did not go down to his house.&#x201D; Dovid said to Urioh, &#x201C;You are coming [back] from travelling, why did you not go down to your house.&#x201D;</p>
<p>11. Urioh said to Dovid, &#x201C;The Ark, Yisroel and Yehudah are living in temporary dwellings, and my master Yoav [along with] my master&#x2019;s servants are camping out in the field, and I am going to go to my house to eat and to drink and to sleep with my wife? [Upon] your life and the life of your soul if I should do such a thing.&#x201D;</p>
<p>12. Dovid said to Urioh, &#x201C;Stay here today and tommorrow I shall send you [back].&#x201D; Urioh stayed in Yerosholoyim on that day and [into] the next.</p>
<p>13. Dovid summoned him and ate before him and drank and inebriated him. At evening he went out to sleep in his bed together with the servants of his master. He did not go down to his house.</p>
<p>14. And it was in the morning Dovid wrote a letter to Yoav and sent it in the hand of Urioh.</p>
<p>15. He wrote in the letter saying, &#x201C;Put Urioh up against the front of the strong [intense] battle and retreat behind him and he will be struck and killed.&#x201D;</p>
<p>16. During Yoav&#x2019;s watching of the city, he put Urioh into a place where he knew mighty soldiers were.</p>
<p>17. The men of the city went out and fought with Yoav. And there fell some of the people, of Dovid&#x2019;s servants, and Urioh the Chitite also died [there].</p>
<p>18. Yoav sent [a message], and told Dovid [about] all the battle&#x2019;s events.</p>
<p>19. He commanded the messenger, saying, &#x201C;When you finish relating all the events of the war to the king.</p>
<p>20. Should the king [then] get angry and say to you, &#x2018;Why did you go [so] close to the city to fight, you knew they would throw [projectiles on you] from [the edge of] the wall?</p>
<p>21. Who struck Avimelech, the son of Yerubeshes? A woman threw [down] on him a millstone from [the edge of] the wall and he died in Tavaitz. Why did you go [so] close to the wall [of the city]?&#x2019; You should say [in reply] &#x2018;Your servant Urioh the Chitite also died.&#x2019; &#x201D;</p>
<p>22. The messenger went and came and told Dovid everything that Yoav sent him [to relate].</p>
<p>23. The messenger said to Dovid, &#x201C;When the [enemy] men overpowered us, they came out to [engage us in] the field. We [then] were upon them until the entrance of the gate.</p>
<p>24. The throwers threw down [objects] on your servants from atop the wall. Some of the king&#x2019;s servants were killed and your servant Urioh, the Chitite also died.&#x201D;</p>
<p>25. Dovid said to the messenger, &#x201C;Say this to Yoav, &#x2018;This thing should not be evil in your eyes for the sword consumes one as well as others. Intensity your war [against] the city and destroy it&#x2019; and encourage him [Yoav].&#x201D;</p>
<p>26. Urioh&#x2019;s wife heard that her husband Urioh had died and she lamented her husband.</p>
<p>27. When the mourning period passed, Dovid sent [for her] and gathered her into his house, and she became a wife to him, and she gave birth to a son by him What Dovid did was bad in the eyes of God.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>12</title>
<p>1. Adonoy sent Noson to Dovid. He came to him and said to him, &#x201C;Two men were in the [same] one city, one rich and one poor.</p>
<p>2. The rich one possesed very many flocks and cattle.</p>
<p>3. The poor one had nothing but one little lamb that he had bought and nourished it and it grew up with him and his sons together. It ate from his bread and drank from his cup and slept in his bosom and was like a daughter to him.</p>
<p>4. A traveler came to the rich man, [who] had pity and took from his flocks and his cattle to make [a meal] for the guest that had come to him. He took the poor man&#x2019;s lamb and made it [a meal] for the man that had come to him.</p>
<p>5. Dovid became very angry with the man and he said to Noson, &#x201C;[By] the life of God, the man who does this is worthy of death.</p>
<p>6. And for the lamb he should pay fourfold because he did this thing and because he had no pity.&#x201D;</p>
<p>7. Noson said to Dovid, &#x201C;You are that man. Thus said God, the God of Yisroel, &#x2018;I have anointed you king over Yisroel and I have saved you from the hand of Shaul.</p>
<p>8. I have given you your master&#x2019;s house and your master&#x2019;s woman in your bosom. I have given you the house of Yisroel and Yehudah if this is [too] little I will add on for you like this and like this.</p>
<p>9. Why did you desecrate the word of God to do [what&#x2019;s] bad in his eyes? You struck [down] Urioh the Chitite with the sword and his wife you took as a wife for yourself. Him, you killed with the sword of the people of Amon.</p>
<p>10. And now the sword will never cease from your house on account of you having degraded Me, and you have taken the wife of Urioh, the Chitite to be for you as a wife.</p>
<p>11. Thus said God, I will cause evil to you from your [own] house, I will take your wives [in front of] your eyes and I will give [them] to your friend. He will lay with your wives in the eyes [sight] of this sun.</p>
<p>12. Because you have done [your misdeed] clandestinely I will do this thing in front of all Yisroel and in front of the sun.&#x2019; &#x201D;</p>
<p>13. Dovid said to Noson, &#x201C;I have sinned [against] Adonoy.&#x201D; Noson said to Dovid, &#x201C;Adonoy has also removed your sin, you shall not die.</p>
<p>14. Because [You have angered] the enemies of Adonoy [through] this affair, the son born to you will also die:</p>
<p>15. Noson went [back] to his house. and Adonoy struck the boy that the wife of Urioh bore to Dovid and he became sick.</p>
<p>16. Dovid supplicated Elokim on behalf of the boy. Dovid fasted and came to repose and lied on the ground.</p>
<p>17. The elders of his house went to him to get him up from the ground. He did not want [to] and he did not eat bread with them.</p>
<p>18. On the seventh day, the boy died. Dovid&#x2019;s servants were afraid to tell him that the boy had died because they [reasoned and] said, &#x201C;When the boy was alive, we spoke to him [Dovid] and he did not heed our voice. How are we going to say to him, &#x2018;The boy died&#x2019;? He will do [something] bad [to himself].&#x201D;</p>
<p>19. Dovid saw that his servants were whispering, Dovid understood that the boy had died. Dovid said to his servants, &#x201C;Did the boy die?&#x201D; They said [in reply], &#x201C;He died.&#x201D;</p>
<p>20. Dovid got up from the ground, he bathed and anointed [himself] and changed his clothes. He went to the House of Adonoy and bowed down. He came [back] to his house and asked [for food]. They put bread [before him] and he ate.</p>
<p>21. His servants said to him, &#x201C;What is this thing that you have done? For a live boy you fasted and cried, and when the boy died you got up and ate bread?&#x201D;</p>
<p>22. He said [in reply], &#x201C;While the boy was [still] alive I fasted and cried because I [reasoned] and said, &#x2018;Who knows? God [may] be gracious to me and [have] the boy live.&#x2019;</p>
<p>23. And now [that the boy is] dead why should I fast? Can I any longer [cause] him to return? I am going to him, he is not returning to me.</p>
<p>24. Dovid consoled his wife Bas Sheva. He came to her and lay with her. She gave birth to a son, She called him the name Shlomo, and God loved him [Shlomo].</p>
<p>25. He [God] sent by the hand of Noson the prophet [a message], and he [Dovid] called his name Yedidyoh because of Adonoy.</p>
<p>26. Yoav battled against [the city] Rabbas of the people of Ammon and captured the royal city.</p>
<p>27. Yoav sent messengers to Dovid and said, &#x201C;I have battled [against] Rabboh. I have also captured the city of water.</p>
<p>28. And now, gather the rest of the people and encamp [against] the city and capture it. Lest I capture the city and my name will be called upon it.</p>
<p>29. Dovid gathered all the people and went to Rabboh. He waged war against it and captured it.</p>
<p>30. He took the crown of Malkom from its head, its weight was a golden kikor and [in it] was a precious stone. It was [hung over] Dovid&#x2019;s head. He took out much booty [from] the city.</p>
<p>31. He took out the people that were in it. He put them in saw-like utensils, iron threshing utensils and iron axes. He had them pass [through] the streets. He did this to all the cities of the people of Ammon. Dovid and all the people returned to Yerushaloyim.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>13</title>
<p>1. And it was after this, that Avsholom, the son of Dovid had a pretty sister, whose name was Tomor and Amnon, the son of Dovid loved her.</p>
<p>2. Amnon was anguished to [the point of] sickness because of [his love for] his sister Tomor because she was a virgin. It was hidden from the eyes of Amnon [how] to do anything to her.</p>
<p>3. Amnon had a friend, whose name was Yonodov, the son of Shimoh the brother of Dovid. Yonodov was a very smart men.</p>
<p>4. He said to him, Why are you like this, so weak every morning, son of the king? Tell me.&#x201D; Amnon said to him, &#x201C;I love Tomor, the sister of my brother Avsholom.&#x201D;</p>
<p>5. Yehonodov said to him, &#x201C;Lie on your bed and [pretend to] be sick. Your father will come to see you, and [then] tell him, &#x2018;Please have my sister Tomor come and feed me a meal. She should make the meal [before] my eyes in order that I should see [it] and I will eat from her hand.&#x2019; &#x201D;</p>
<p>6. Amnon lied down and [pretended] he was sick. The king came to see him. and Amnon said to the king, &#x201C;Please have my sister Tomor come and make two dumplings [before] my eyes and I will eat from her hand.&#x201D;</p>
<p>7. Dovid sent for Tomor in the house saying, &#x201C;Go to the house of your brother Amnon and make him a meal.</p>
<p>8. Tomor went to the house of her brother Amnon and he was lying down. She took dough and kneaded it, she made a paste [before] his eyes and she cooked the dumplings.</p>
<p>9. She took the pan and poured them out before him, but he refused to eat. Amnon said, &#x201C;All men should leave me.&#x201D; And all the men left him.</p>
<p>10. Amnon said to Tomor, &#x201C;Bring me the food into the room and I will eat from your hand.&#x201D; Tomor took the dumplings that she made and brought them into the room to her brother Amnon.</p>
<p>11. She brought them near to him to eat, and he grabbed her and said to her, &#x201C;Come lie with me my sister.&#x201D;</p>
<p>12. She said to him, &#x201C;No, my brother, do not rape me because this is not done in Yisroel. Do not commit this disgrace.</p>
<p>13. And me, where will I take my shame? You will be as one of the lowlives in Yisroel. Now, please speak to the king because he will not keep me from you.</p>
<p>14. He did not want to listen to her voice and he overpowered her, raped her and laid with her.</p>
<p>15. Amnon hated her with very great hatred for greater was the hatred that he hated her then the love with which he had loved her, and Amnon told her, &#x201C;Get up, go.&#x201D;</p>
<p>16. She said to him, &#x201C;Do not do this thing, this is a greater evil then the other [first] one that you have done to me to send me away.&#x201D; He did not want to listen to her.</p>
<p>17. He called his boy that was attending to him and he said, &#x201C;Please send this [women] from before me outside and close the door after her.&#x201D;</p>
<p>18. And upon her was her multicolored robe because the virgin daughters of the king wore [such] robes. His servant brought her outside and closed the door after her.</p>
<p>19. Tomor put dirt on her head and tore the multicolored robe that was on her. She put her hand on her head and she went forth crying [as she went].</p>
<p>20. Her brother said to her, &#x201C;Was your brother Haiminon [Amnon] with you? And now [that its done] my sister keep quiet, he is your brother. Do not put your heart to this matter.&#x201D; Tomor returned desolate to the house of her brother Avsholom.</p>
<p>21. King Dovid heard all these things and became very angry.</p>
<p>22. Avsholom did not speak with Amnon neither bad or good because Avsholom hated Amnon because he had raped his sister, Tomor.</p>
<p>23. Two years [later], they were shearing for Avsholom in Baal Chatsor which is near Ephraim. Avsholom invited all the king&#x2019;s sons.</p>
<p>24. Avsholom came to the king and said, &#x201C;They are shearing for your servant, may the king and his servants go with your servant.&#x201D;</p>
<p>25. The king said to Avsholom, &#x201C;No, my son. Let us not all go and let us not all weigh [too] heavy upon you,&#x201D; He [Avsholom] beseeched him [Dovid], [but] he did not want to and blessed him.</p>
<p>26. Avsholom said, &#x201C;Will not my brother Amnon come with us?&#x201D; The king said to him, &#x201C;Why should he go with you?&#x201D;</p>
<p>27. Avsholom beseeched him [Dovid] and he sent Amnon with him [with] all the king&#x2019;s sons.</p>
<p>28. Avsholom commanded his young men saying, &#x201C;Look out for [when] Amnon&#x2019;s heart is happy from wine and I tell you &#x2018;Strike Amnon&#x2019; and kill him, do not fear; because I commanded you [to do so]. Be strong and be valiant.&#x201D;</p>
<p>29. Avsholom&#x2019;s young men did to Amnon as Avsholom commanded. All the king&#x2019;s sons rose, and each man mounted his mule and they fled.</p>
<p>30. As they were on the way the news came to Dovid saying, &#x201C;Avsholom struck [down] all the king&#x2019;s children and not one is left.&#x201D;</p>
<p>31. The king rose, he rent his clothes and he laid down on the ground. All his servants stood by with torn clothes.</p>
<p>32. Yonodov replied, he was the son of Shimoh [who was] Dovid&#x2019;s brother and said, &#x201C;My master, do not say that all the young men, the sons of the king were killed because only Amnon died. Because this has been Avsholom&#x2019;s order from the day he [Amnon] raped his sister, Tomor.</p>
<p>33. And now, Let not my master, the king take this thing to his heart saying, &#x2018;All the king&#x2019;s sons died,&#x2019; for only Amnon died.&#x201D;</p>
<p>34. Avsholom fled. The lookout boy lifted his eyes and saw that there was a great multitude following after him on the highway by the side of the mountain.</p>
<p>35. Yonodov said to the king, &#x201C;The king&#x2019;s sons have come [back], as the words of your servant [described] so it was.</p>
<p>36. And as he finished speaking, the king&#x2019;s sons came and lifted up their voices and wept. So too, the king and all his servants wept greatly.</p>
<p>37. Avsholom fled and went to Talmy, the son of Amihud, the king of Geshur He [Dovid] mourned his son all the days.</p>
<p>38. Avsholom fled and went to Geshur and was there for three years.</p>
<p>39. King Dovid desired to go out to Avsholom because he was consoled concerning the death of Amnon.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>14</title>
<p>1. Yoav, the son of Tsruyoh knew that the king&#x2019;s heart was [favorable] to Avsholom.</p>
<p>2. Yoav sent to Tekoah and took a wise woman from there. He said to her, &#x201C;Please pretend to be a mourner and wear mourner&#x2019;s clothes and do not annoint yourself with oil. Be as woman that for many days had mourned for the dead.</p>
<p>3. [Then] you should come [before] the king and speak to him the following words. Yoav put the words in her mouth.</p>
<p>4. The Tekois woman greeted the king and fell to the ground on her face and said, &#x201C;Help [me] O king.&#x201D;</p>
<p>5. The king said to her, &#x201C;What is with you?&#x201D; She said [in reply], &#x201C;In truth, I am a widowed woman, my husband is dead.</p>
<p>6. Your handmaid had two sons. Both were fighting [each other] in the field; and no one was able to save [separate] them. One [of them] struck the other one and killed him.</p>
<p>7. Then the entire family rose up against your handmaid and said, &#x2018;Give us the one who killed his brother and we will kill him for the soul of his brother whom he murdered, we shall also destroy the heir.&#x2019; They will extinguish my coal that is left, preventing the perpetuation of my husband&#x2019;s name nor anything remaining [of him] on the face of the earth.&#x201D;</p>
<p>8. The king said to the woman, &#x201C;Go [back] to your house and I will command [someone] concerning you.&#x201D;</p>
<p>9. The Tekois woman said to the king, &#x201C;My master, the king, the sin is upon me and on my father&#x2019;s house and the king and his throne are innocent.&#x201D;</p>
<p>10. The king said [in reply], &#x201C;The one who is speaking to you [threatingly], bring him to me and he will not touch you any more.</p>
<p>11. She said, &#x201C;Please remember Adonoy, your God, and not give more [time] for the avenger to destroy. Do not let them destroy my son.&#x201D; He said [in reply], &#x201C;As Adonoy lives; if any hair from your son shall fall to the ground.&#x201D;</p>
<p>12. The woman said, &#x201C;Please let your handmaiden say something to my master, the king.&#x201D; He [Dovid] said, &#x201C;Talk.&#x201D;</p>
<p>13. The woman said, &#x201C;Why did you think this about the people of God? that which the king said, he himself is guilty of in order that the king not bring back his exiled [son].</p>
<p>14. We are [all] going to die, like water spilled on the ground that will not be regathered, God will not countenance anyone. but now let him devise means so that the exiled exiled one remain not an outcast.</p>
<p>15. And therefore now I came to speak to my master, the king these words [as a parable] because the people frightened me. Your handmaiden said, &#x2018;I will speak to the king, perhaps the king will take action [in accordance with] his handmaiden&#x2019;s words.</p>
<p>16. When the king hears [and agrees] to save his handmaiden from the [avenger] man&#x2019;s hand who woukd destroy me and my son together from the inheritance [given by] God.</p>
<p>17. Your handmaiden says let the words of my master, the king provide relief because just as an angel of God so too is my master the king [able] to discern good and bad. Adonoy your God should be with you.&#x201D;</p>
<p>18. The king replied and said to the woman, &#x201C;Please do not conceal from me the matter that I am going to ask you.&#x201D; The woman said, &#x201C;My master the king, please speak.&#x201D;</p>
<p>19. The king said, &#x201C;Is Yoav&#x2019;s hand with you in all of this?&#x201D; The woman replied and said, &#x201C;By your life, my master, the king, it is impossible to go right or left from all that my master, the king has said because [indeed] your servant, Yoav, he is the one who commanded me and he put in your handmaiden&#x2019;s mouth all these words.</p>
<p>20. In order to skirt around the [direct] face of the matter has your servant, Yoav done this thing. [But] my master is wise like the wisdom possessed by an angel of God to know everything [going on] in the land.&#x201D;</p>
<p>21. The king said to Yoav, &#x201C;Behold you have done this [so] go and bring back the boy, Avsholom.&#x201D;</p>
<p>22. Yoav fell on his face to the ground and prostrated himself and blessed the king. Yoav said, &#x201C;Today your servant knows that I have found favor in your eyes my master, the king [as] the king has fulfilled the word of your servant.&#x201D;</p>
<p>23. Yoav got up went to Goshur and brought Avsholom back to Yerusholayim.</p>
<p>24. The king said, &#x201C;He should make his way around to his house and he should not see my face.&#x201D; Avsholom made his way around to his house and he did not see the king&#x2019;s face.</p>
<p>25. There was no man as beautiful as Avsholom in all of Yisroel to be so much praised from the heel of his foot to the crown of his head there was no blemish.</p>
<p>26. When he shaved his head, it was at the end of each year that he shaved because [the hair] weighed heavily upon him and [so] he shaved it off. The hair of his head weighed two hundred shekalim using the king&#x2019;s stone [weight].</p>
<p>27. To Avsholom was born three sons and one daughter, Her name was Tomor, she was a beautiful woman.</p>
<p>28. Avsholom lived in Yerusholoyim for two years and did not see the king&#x2019;s face.</p>
<p>29. Avsholom sent [a message] to Yoav asking [Yoav] to go to the king, He [Yoav] refused to come to him [Avsholom]. He sent another [message] a second time and he [Yoav] refused to come.</p>
<p>30. He [Avsholom] said to his servants, &#x201C;Look Yoav&#x2019;s plantation is near mine, and he has barley there. Go and set it on fire, and Avsholom&#x2019;s servants set the plantation on fire.</p>
<p>31. Yoav got up and went to Avsholom in [his] house. He said to him, why did your servants set my plantation on fire?&#x201D;</p>
<p>32. Avsholom said to Yoav, &#x201C;Behold I sent [a message] to you saying, &#x2018;Come here and I will send you to king saying, &#x2018;Why have you brought me from Geshur? It would be better for me if I were still there. And now, let me see the king&#x2019;s face and if I have a sin [then] kill me.&#x2019; &#x201D;</p>
<p>33. Yoav came to the king and told him [the message]. He [Dovid] summoned Avsholom. He came to the king he prostrated himself on his face to the ground before the king, and the king kissed Avsholom.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>15</title>
<p>1. It was after this that Avsholom made [for himself] a chariot [with] horses and [an entourage of] fifty men ran before him.</p>
<p>2. Avsholom would rise early, and stand next to the gateway and any man who had a complaint and was coming to the king for judgment, Avsholom would call to him saying, &#x201C;From what city are you?&#x201D; He [the complainant] would say &#x201C;Your servant is from one of the tribes of Yisroel.&#x201D;</p>
<p>3. Avsholom would say to him, &#x201C;Look your words are good and correct, [but] Your case will not be heard by the king.</p>
<p>4. Avsholom said, &#x201C;Who will install me as a judge in the land? [Then] to me would come every man who has a complaint and litigation and I will judge him righteously.&#x201D;</p>
<p>5. And when the man would draw near to bow down to him, he [Avsholom] would extend his hand, grab hold of him and would kiss him.</p>
<p>6. Avsholom did this to all of Yisroel coming for judgment to the king. [In this way] Avsholom stole the hearts of [misled] the people of Yisroel.</p>
<p>7. At the end of forty years, Avsholom said to the king, &#x201C;I would like to go and fulfill my vows [of bringing sacrifices] that I [previously] vowed to God in Chevron [so I may fulfill them].</p>
<p>8. For your servant made a vow while I was staying in Geshur in Arom saying, &#x2018;If God returns me to Yerusholayim, I will worship God [with sacrifices].&#x2019; &#x201D;</p>
<p>9. The king said to him &#x201C;Go in peace.&#x201D; He [Avsholom] got up and went to Chevron.</p>
<p>10. Avsholom sent spies to all the tribes of Yisroel saying &#x201C;When you hear the sound of the shofar, you should say &#x2018;Avsholom reigns in Chevron.&#x2019; &#x201D;</p>
<p>11. Two hundred men left with Avsholom from Yerusholayim. They were invited and went in innocence and they knew nothing [of Avsholom&#x2019;s conspiracy].</p>
<p>12. Avsholom sent for Achitophel the Gilonite, the counsellor to Dovid, to come from his city, Giloh while they slaughtered the sacrifices. The bond [of conspiracy] strengthened. Additional people were constantly joining with Avsholom.</p>
<p>13. The informant came to Dovid saying, &#x201C;The hearts of the men of Yisroel are behind Avsholom.&#x201D;</p>
<p>14. Dovid said to all his servants that were with him in Yerusholayim, &#x201C;Let us get up and flee because we will not be able to escape from before Avsholom. Let us hurry and leave lest he quickly overtake us and thrust evil upon us and strike the city with the sword.&#x201D;</p>
<p>15. The king&#x2019;s servants said to the king, &#x201C;All that you choose [to do] my master O king, we your servants are here [with you].</p>
<p>16. The king and all his household left by foot. The king left behind ten concubine women to watch the house.</p>
<p>17. The king and all the people left by foot. They stopped far away.</p>
<p>18. All his servants were passing by him, all the archers, all the throwers and all the Gitites. Six hundred men that came by foot from Gat, all passing by the face of the king.</p>
<p>19. The king said to Itai the Gitite, &#x201C;Why are you going with us? Return and stay with the king because you are a foreigner and even if you are estranged [from Avsholom] you can go to your home.</p>
<p>20. You [just] came yesterday and should I today cause you to move out with us. I am going to where [circumstances have] me go. Return and take back your brethren with you. I will consider it kindness and truth.&#x201D;</p>
<p>21. Itai replied to the king and said, &#x201C;As Adonoy lives and as my master the king lives, only in the place where my master the king will be whether for death or for life [that is] where your servant will be.&#x201D;</p>
<p>22. Dovid said to Itai, &#x201C;Go and pass by.&#x201D; And Itai the Gitite passed by [together with] all his men and all the children that were with him.</p>
<p>23. All the [people of] the land were crying with a loud voice as all the people were passing by. As the king passed by Nachal Kidron all the people were passing along the width of the highway towards the desert.</p>
<p>24. And also Tzodok and all the Levites with him who were carrying the Ark of the convenant of God. They set down the Ark of Elokim and Evyosor went off [to the side] until all the people finished passing out of the city.</p>
<p>25. The king said to Tzodok, &#x201C;Return the Ark of God to the city. If I find favor in Adonoy&#x2019;s Eyes, He will bring me back and I will see Him and His dwelling place.</p>
<p>26. And if he says as follows, &#x2018;I do not want you.&#x2019; Here I am, do unto me whatever is favorable in Your Eyes.&#x201D;</p>
<p>27. The King said to Tzodok, the Kohein, &#x201C;If you see this [as right], return to the city in peace and Achimaatz, your son and Yohonoson, the son of Evyosor your two sons with you.</p>
<p>28. Look, I will stay in the plains of the desert until word comes from you to tell me.&#x201D;</p>
<p>29. Tzodok and Evyosor returned the Ark of Elokim to Yerusholoyim and they stayed there.</p>
<p>30. Dovid went upon the heights of Mount of Olives, crying as he went up. His head was covered and he went barefoot. All the people that were with him, each man covered his head and they went up crying as they went up.</p>
<p>31. Dovid was told [by an informer] saying, &#x201C;Achitophel is among the conspirators with Avsholom.&#x201D; Dovid said, &#x201C;Adonoy, please ruin Achitophel&#x2019;s advice.&#x201D;</p>
<p>32. Dovid arrived at the summit where he used to bow down to God. Chushai, the Arkite greeted him. His tunic was tom and dirt was on his head.</p>
<p>33. Dovid said to him, &#x201C;If you travel with me you will be a burden for me.</p>
<p>34. [But] if you return to the city and say to Avsholom, &#x2018;King, I will be your servant. Previously, I was your father&#x2019;s servant and now I am your servant.&#x2019; [Then] you can sabotage for me Achitophel&#x2019;s advice.</p>
<p>35. And with you there will be Tzodok and Evyosor, the Kohanim. Everything you hear from the king&#x2019;s palace, tell Tzodok and Evyosor the Kohanim.</p>
<p>36. Their two sons are there with them, Achimaatz for Tzodok and Yohonoson for Evyosor. &#x201C;Send [messages] in their hands to me [about] all the things you hear.&#x201D;</p>
<p>37. Chashai, Dovid&#x2019;s friend came to the city and Avsholom was going to come to Yerosholoyim.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>16</title>
<p>1. Dovid passed a little further beyond the summit and Zivoh, Mephivoshes&#x2019; young man greeted him with a pair of saddled donkeys. Upon them was two hundred loaves of bread, one hundred clusters of raisins, one hundred portions of dried figs and a jug of wine.</p>
<p>2. The king said to Tsivoh &#x201C;What is your intent with these?&#x201D; Tsivoh said [in reply], The donkeys are for the king&#x2019;s household to ride, the bread and the dried figs are for the young men to eat and the wine is for those tired in the desert to drink.</p>
<p>3. The king said, &#x201C;Where is your master&#x2019;s son?&#x201D; Tsivoh said to the king [in reply], &#x201C;He is dwelling in Yerusholoyim because he is saying, &#x2018;Today, the house of Yisroel will return to me my father&#x2019;s kingdom.&#x2019; &#x201D;</p>
<p>4. The king said to Tsivoh, &#x201C;All that belongs to Mephivoishes is [now] yours.&#x201D; Tsivoh said, &#x201C;I bow down [in gratitude] I should find favor in your eyes, my master the king.</p>
<p>5. King Dovid came to Bachurim and a man came out from there from the family of the house of Shaul and his name was Shimi, the son of Gairoh. He came out and kept on cursing.</p>
<p>6. He threw stones at Dovid and on all the servants of king Dovid, and all the people and all the soldiers were on his [Dovid&#x2019;s] right and on his left.</p>
<p>7. This is what Shimi said in his cursing, &#x201C;Begone, begone, man of blood and debased man.</p>
<p>8. Adonoy has repayed you for all the blood of the House of Shaul that you have replaced as king. Adonoy has delivered the monarchy into the hand of your son Avsholom. Here you are in a bad way because you are a man of blood.&#x201D;</p>
<p>9. Avishai, the son of Tsruyoh said to the king, &#x201C;Why is this dead dog cursing my master, the king? I will go over there and take off his head.</p>
<p>10. The king said [in reply], &#x201C;What is between me and you sons of Tsruyoh? He should curse [me] like this because Adonoy told him &#x2018;Curse Dovid.&#x2019; Who can say, &#x2018;Why have you done this?&#x2019;.&#x201D;</p>
<p>11. Dovid said to Avishai and to all his servants, &#x201C;Behold, my son who came forth from within me is seeking to kill me even more so a son of a Binyomite should now [rise against me]. Let him curse because Adonoy told him to do so.</p>
<p>12. Maybe, Adonoy will see [the tears] in my eyes, and Adonoy will bring good to me instead of his curse of this day.</p>
<p>13. Dovid and his men went on the path and Shimi went along the side of the mountain opposite him cursing as he went and throwing stones at him and throwing dirt.</p>
<p>14. The king and all the people with him came [to Bachurim] exhausted and they rested there.</p>
<p>15. Avsholom and all the people, men of Yisroel came to Yerusholoyim and Achitophel with him.</p>
<p>16. When Chushai the Arkite, Dovid&#x2019;s friend came to Avsholom, Chushai said to Avsholom, &#x201C;The king should live, the king should live.&#x201D;</p>
<p>17. Avsholom said to Chushai, &#x201C;This is your kindness towards your friend? Why did you not go with your friend?&#x201D;</p>
<p>18. Chushai said to Avsholom, No, because to whom God has chosen along with this people and all men of Yisroel with him I will be and with him I will dwell.</p>
<p>19. Secondly, whom am I serving? Is it not before his [own] son? As I have served before your father so too I will be before you.&#x201D;</p>
<p>20. Avsholom said to Achitophel, &#x201C;You [wise men] give [me] advice concerning what to do [next].&#x201D;</p>
<p>21. Achitophel said to Avsholom, &#x201C;Lie with your father&#x2019;s concubines that he left to watch the palace and all of Yisroel will hear that you have disgraced your father and you will [thereby] strengthen the hands of all those who are with you.</p>
<p>22. They pitched a tent on the roof for Avsholom and Avsholom laid with his father&#x2019;s concubines before the eyes of all Yisroel.</p>
<p>23. The counsel of Achitophel that he counselled in those days [was as trustworthy] as inquiring of the word of God. So was the advice of Achitophel, both for Dovid and [later] for Avsholom.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>17</title>
<p>1. Achitophel said to Avsholom, &#x201C;Let me choose twelve thousand men and I will arise and pursue after Dovid tonight.&#x201D;</p>
<p>2. I will reach him [when] he will be tired and weak. I will frighten him [suddenly] and all the people with him will flee and I will strike [only] the king himself.</p>
<p>3. I will return all the people to you. When they all return [to you] [except] the man you want [killed] [then] all the people will have peace.</p>
<p>4. The idea was favorable in Avsholom&#x2019;s eyes and in the eyes of all of the elders of Yisroel.</p>
<p>5. Avsholom said, &#x201C;Call Chushai the Arkite also and let us hear what he has to say.&#x201D;</p>
<p>6. Chushai came to Avsholom and Avsholom said to him, saying, &#x201C;Achitophel said such and such, should we do as he said or not? you tell [us].&#x201D;</p>
<p>7. Chushai said to Avsholom, &#x201C;The advice is not good that Achitophel has given this time.&#x201D;</p>
<p>8. Chushai said, &#x201C;You know your father and his men that they are strong and they are embittered souls like a bear bereft of it&#x2019;s children [fighting] in the field. Your father is a man of war and he will not rest with the people.</p>
<p>9. Now, he is hiding in one of the pits or one of the places [to hide]. When some of the men fall at the beginning [of their battles], a person will hear and will say, &#x2018;There was a disaster amongst the people that follow after Avsholom.&#x2019;</p>
<p>10. Even if he is a soldier who has a heart like that of a lion, his heart will surely melt because all of Yisroel knows that your father is strong as are the soldiers that are with him.</p>
<p>11. But I advise [as follows:], Gather unto you all of Yisroel from Dan to Be&#x2019;er Sheva a multitude like the sand by the sea and you yourself should go to war.</p>
<p>12. We will reach him in one of the places where he will be found and we will encamp upon him as the dew falls on the ground and there will be none left, not of him nor of any of the men with him [not] even one.</p>
<p>13. And if they gather into a city [then] all of Yisroel should go up to that city in groups. We will drag [the city wall] into the valley [below] until not even a pebble will be found there.</p>
<p>14. Avsholom and all the men of Yisroel said, &#x201C;Chushai the Arkite&#x2019;s advice is better then Achitophel&#x2019;s advice.&#x201D; Adonoy commanded to annul the good advice of Achitophel in order for Adonoy to bring evil upon Avsholom.</p>
<p>15. Chushai said to Tzodok and to Evyosor the Kohanim, &#x201C;Such and such Achitophel advised Avsholom and the elders of Yisroel and I advised [him] such and such.</p>
<p>16. And now, send [messengers] quickly and tell Dovid saying, &#x2018;Do not rest tonight in the plains of the desert, but cross over it, because [my suggestion] may be rejected by the king and all the people with him.</p>
<p>17. Yahonoson and Achima&#x2019;atz were standing by the launderers&#x2019; fountain, and the handmaiden used to go and tell them and they went and told King Dovid because they could not [let themselves] be seen by coming into the city.</p>
<p>18. A young man saw them and told Avsholom. They went quickly and came to a man&#x2019;s house in Bachurim and he had a well in his courtyard and they descended into it.</p>
<p>19. The woman took [a curtain] and spread the curtain over the face of the well and she spread ground wheat on it and the matter did not become known.</p>
<p>20. Avsholom&#x2019;s servants came to the woman&#x2019;s house and said, &#x201C;Where are Achima&#x2019;atz and Yehonoson?&#x201D; The woman said [in reply], &#x201C;They crossed over the stream of water.&#x201D; They searched [but] did not find [them] and returned to Yerusholoyim.</p>
<p>21. After they [Avsholom&#x2019;s servants] left they climbed up from the well and went and told King Dovid. They said to Dovid, &#x201C;Rise and quickly cross over the water for such has Achitophfelophel advised against you.&#x201D;</p>
<p>22. Dovid rose together with all the people with him and they crossed over the Yardein. By the light of the morning. not one [person] was missing who did not cross over the Yardein.</p>
<p>23. Achitophel saw that his advice was not put into action. He saddled his donkey, got up and went to his house [in] his city. He gave [his last] instructions to his family. He [then] strangled himself and died. He was buried in his father&#x2019;s grave.</p>
<p>24. Dovid came to Machanoyim [as] Avsholom crossed the Yardein, he and all the men of Yisroel with him.</p>
<p>25. Avsholom put Amosoh [at the head] of the army in place of Yoav. Amosoh was the son of a man, whose name was Yisrah the Yisroelite who had relations with Avigal, the daughter of Nochosh, [who was] the sister of Tsruyoh, the mother of Yoav.</p>
<p>26. [The men of] Yisroel and Avsholom encamped in the land of Gilod.</p>
<p>27. When Dovid came to Machanoyim, [he met] Shovi, the son of Nochosh from Rabbahs of the people of Amon and Mochir, the son of Amiel from Lo Devor and Barzilai, the Gilodite from Roglim.</p>
<p>28. [They brought] mats, and basins earthenware utensils, wheat, barley flour, toasted grain, beans, lentils toasted lentils,</p>
<p>29. honey, butter, sheep and cow&#x2019;s cheese they brought to Dovid and to the people with him to eat because they said, &#x201C;The people are hungry, tired and thirsty in the desert.&#x201D;</p>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>18</title>
<p>1. Dovid numbered the people that were with him and appointed over them officers [to lead] thousands and officers [to lead] hundreds.</p>
<p>2. Dovid sent the people forth, a third under the hand of Yoav, a third under the hand of Avishai, the son of Tsruyoh, Yoav&#x2019;s brother and a third by the hand of Itai, the Gitite. The king said to the people, &#x201C;I will also go out with you.&#x201D;</p>
<p>3. The people said [in reply], &#x201C;Do not go out [with us] because if we flee they will not pay us any attention and if they kill half of us they will not pay us any attention because now [you are worth] ten thousand of us. And now, it will be better if you help us from the city.&#x201D;</p>
<p>4. The king said to them, &#x201C;I will do as you see fit.&#x201D; The king stood off to the side of the gate and all the people went forth, by hundreds and by thousands.</p>
<p>5. The king commanded Yoav, Avishai and Itai saying, &#x201C;Be gentle to the young man, Avsholom for me.&#x201D; All the people heard the king&#x2019;s order to all the officers concerning Avshalom.</p>
<p>6. The people went out to the field against [the army of] Yisroel. The battle took place in the forest of Ephraim.</p>
<p>7. The army of Yisroel was defeated there by the servants of Dovid. There was a great slaughter there on that day of twenty thousand [men lost].</p>
<p>8. The war spread all over the land, The [wild beasts of the] forest killed more people than the sword devoured on that day.</p>
<p>9. Avsholom chanced to meet the servants of Dovid and Avsholom was riding on a mule. The mule passed under the branches of a great elm tree and his head got caught in the elm tree. He was hanging between the sky and the earth and the mule that was under him passed on by.</p>
<p>10. A man saw this and told it to Yoav and said, &#x201C;I saw Avsholom hanging from an elm tree.&#x201D;</p>
<p>11. Yoav said to the man who told him, &#x201C;You saw him, why did you not strike him to the ground and I would have given you ten silver peices and one belt.&#x201D;</p>
<p>12. The man said to Yoav, &#x201C;Had I been able to take a thousand silver peices, I would not have hurt the king&#x2019;s son because [we heard] with our own ears that the king commanded you, Avishai and Itai saying, &#x2018;Beware that none harm the young man, Avsholom&#x2019;.</p>
<p>13. Had I tried to lie [and cover up his murder], nothing would [remain] concealed from the king and you would distance yourself [from me].&#x201D;</p>
<p>14. Yoav said, &#x201C;I will not ask you [any further].&#x201D; He took three spears in his hand and thrust them through Avsholom&#x2019;s heart while he was still alive in the midst of the elm tree.</p>
<p>15. Ten young men, who carried Yoav&#x2019;s weapons gathered around, They struck Avsholom and killed him.</p>
<p>16. Yoav blew the shofar and his people stopped chasing after [the army of] Yisroel. because Yoav restrained his people.</p>
<p>17. They took Avsholom, threw him into a big ditch in the forest, and piled up a great heap of stones on top of it. All the men of Yisroel fled to their homes.</p>
<p>18. Avsholom had taken and built for himself a monument during his lifetime, which is in the king&#x2019;s valley because he said, &#x201C;I have no son, this will memorialize my name.&#x201D; He named the monument after himself calling it, &#x201C;the place of Avsholom.&#x201D; [It remains] until today.</p>
<p>19. Achima&#x2019;atz, the son of Tsodok said, &#x201C;I shall run and inform the king that Adonoy has punished his enemies.&#x201D;</p>
<p>20. Yoav said to him, &#x201C;You are not to inform him today, but you shall inform him another day but do not announce it today because the king&#x2019;s son is dead.&#x201D;</p>
<p>21. Yoav said to the Kushite, &#x201C;Go tell the king what you saw.&#x201D; The Kushite bowed to Yoav and ran off.</p>
<p>22. Achima&#x2019;atz, the son Tsodok again asked and said to Yoav, &#x201C;come what may please let me run after the Cushite [to inform the king as well].&#x201D; Yoav replied, &#x201C;Why should you run, my son there is no reward in this announcement for you.&#x201D;</p>
<p>23. &#x201C;Come what may, I will run.&#x201D; And he [Yoav] said to him, &#x201C;Run.&#x201D; Achima&#x2019;atz ran by way of the plain and he passed the Kushite.</p>
<p>24. Dovid was sitting between the two gates and the lookout went up to roof of the gate on top of the wall. He looked out and saw that there was a man running alone.</p>
<p>25. The lookout called out and told the king. The King said, &#x201C;If he is alone, he must be a messenger.&#x201D; He came closer and closer.</p>
<p>26. The lookout saw another man running. The lookout called the gate guard and said, &#x201C;There is a man running alone.&#x201D; The King said, &#x201C;This is also a messenger.&#x201D;</p>
<p>27. The lookout said, &#x201C;I recognize the first man&#x2019;s running as being the runing of Achima&#x2019;atz, the son of Tsodok.&#x201D; The king said, &#x201C;This is a good man and he is coming with good news.&#x201D;</p>
<p>28. Achima&#x2019;atz called out and said to the king, &#x201C;All is well.&#x201D; He bowed to king with his face to the ground, and said, &#x201C;Blessed is Adonoy your God that has delivered [into Yoav&#x2019;s hands] those men who rebelled against my master, the king.&#x201D;</p>
<p>29. The King said, &#x201C;Is it well with the young man, Avsholom?&#x201D; Achima&#x2019;atz replied, &#x201C;I saw a great multitude [engaged in battle] when Yoav sent one of the king&#x2019;s other servants and [me] your servant and I do not know what [happenned afterwords].&#x201D;</p>
<p>30. The king said, &#x201C;Move over there and stand there.&#x201D; He moved over there and stood there.</p>
<p>31. The Kushite arrived and the Kushite said, &#x201C;Let it be announced [to all], my master, the king that today God has punished all those who have risen up against you.&#x201D;</p>
<p>32. The king said to the Kushite, &#x201C;Is it well with the young man, Avsholom?&#x201D; The Kushite replied, &#x201C;May they [die] as did the young man [those who] are enemies of my master, the king as should all those who have risen up against you.&#x201D;</p>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>19</title>
<p>1. The king began to tremble and went up to the room over the gate and wept. And this is what he said as he went, &#x201C;My son Avsholom. My son, my son Avsholom. If only I had died instead of you. Avsholom my son, my son.</p>
<p>2. It was told to Yoav that the king was crying and mourning over Avsholom.</p>
<p>3. The victory of that day was turned into mourning for all of the people because the people heard on that day saying, &#x201C;The king grieves over his son.&#x201D;</p>
<p>4. On that day the people entered the city discreetly like people silent and ashamed from having fled from battle.</p>
<p>5. The king covered his face and the king cried out loudly, &#x201C;My son Avsholom, Avsholom my son, my son.</p>
<p>6. Yoav came inside the king&#x2019;s chamber and said, &#x201C;Today, you have embarassed all your servants who have, this day, saved your life and the lives of your sons and daughters, the lives of your wives and the lives of your concubines.</p>
<p>7. You are showing love to your enemies and hatred towards your friends for [by your actions] today you are declaring that you do not value your officers or servants. For today I know that [you are thinking] if only Avsholom were alive and all of us dead, it would have been right in your eyes.</p>
<p>8. Now, get up, go out and speak to the hearts of your servants because I have sworn by Adonoy that [if] you do not go out [to the people] then no one will remain here with you tonight. This will be worse for you then all the evil that has befallen you from your youth up until today.&#x201D;</p>
<p>9. The king rose, [went] and sat by the gate. All the people were told, &#x201C;The king is sitting by the gate.&#x201D; All the people came before the king [as the people of] Yisroel fled back to their homes.</p>
<p>10. All the people reproached each other throughout all the tribes of Yisroel, saying. &#x201C;The king saved us from the hands of our enemies and he saved us from the hands of the Pelishtim, now he has had to flee from the land because of Avsholom.</p>
<p>11. Avsholom whom we anointed king over us, has died in battle. And now, why are you silent about restoring the king [to his throne].&#x201D;</p>
<p>12. King Dovid sent [messages] to Tsodok and Evyosor the Kohanim saying, &#x201C;Speak to the elders of Yehudah saying, &#x201C;Why should you be last to bring back the king to his palace while the messages of all Yisroel are coming to the king [requesting his return] to his palace.</p>
<p>13. You are my brothers, you are of my own flesh why should you be the last to bring back the king.&#x2019;</p>
<p>14. And tell Amosoh [in my name], &#x2018;are you not of my own bone and flesh. God should do [such and such] to me and more if I do not make you my commanding officer from now on, instead of Yoav.&#x2019;</p>
<p>15. He [Dovid] was able to sway the hearts of all the men of Yehudah [to favor him] as one would sway just one man. They sent [a message] to the king, &#x2018;You and all your servants should return.&#x2019;</p>
<p>16. The king began his return and as he reached the Yardein, Yehudah came to Gilgal to greet the king to bring the king over the Yardein.</p>
<p>17. Shimi, the son of Geiroh, hurried, [son] of the Yemini from Bachurim, and went down with the men of Yehudah to greet king Dovid.</p>
<p>18. A thousand men from Binyomin accompanyed him together with Tzivoh, a young man from the house of Shaul and his fifteen sons and twenty servants. They crossed the Yardein before the king.</p>
<p>19. The ferry boat crossed over bringing the household of the king and to what is good in his eyes. Shimi, the son of Geiroh fell before the king as he crossed the Yardein.</p>
<p>20. He said to the king, &#x201C;Do not consider it a sin on my behalf, do not remember how your servant wronged [you] on the day my master, the king left Yerusholoyim. The king [should not] take it to heart.</p>
<p>21. Because your servant knows that I have sinned, behold I come today the first from among all the House of Yoseif to come down and greet my master the king.</p>
<p>22. Avishai, the son of Tsruyoh replied and said, Should Shimi not be put to death for this since he cursed the anointed one of Adonoy?</p>
<p>23. Dovid said, &#x201C;What [hatred] exists between me and you, sons of Tsruyoh that today you should be adversaries unto me? Should a man of Yisroel die today? Because I [now] know that today I am [truly] king over Yisroel.</p>
<p>24. The king said to Shimi, &#x201C;You shall not die.&#x201D; And the king swore unto him.</p>
<p>25. Mephivoshes, the son of Shaul went down to greet the king. He had not tended to the hair [between] his legs nor groomed his moustache nor laundered his clothes from the day the king left until his peaceful return.</p>
<p>26. When he came to Yerusholoyim to the greet the king, the king said to him, &#x201C;Why did you not go with me, Mephivoshes?&#x201D;</p>
<p>27. He replied, &#x201C;My master the king, my servant [Tsivoh] deceived me because your servant said [to Tsivoh], &#x2018;Saddle up the donkey so that I can ride it and join the king&#x2019;, because your servant is lame.</p>
<p>28. And he [Tsivoh] maligned your servant to my master the king. My master the king is like an angel of God, do what you deem to be proper.</p>
<p>29. The entire house of my father were nothing but mortal enemies to my master the king and [nevertheless] you placed your servant among those eating at your table. What more charity can I [ask of you]? About what more can I cry to the king?&#x201D;</p>
<p>30. The king said to him, &#x201C;Why speak any further, I have said that you and Tsivoh should divide the field.&#x201D;</p>
<p>31. Mephivoshes said to the king, &#x201C;Let him take everything now that my master the king has returned to his palace in peace.&#x201D;</p>
<p>32. Birzilai the Gilodite came down from Roglim and crossed the Yardein with the king accompanying him over the Yardein.</p>
<p>33. Barzilai was very old, eighty years of age, he had provided for the king during his stay in Machanayim because he was a very great man.</p>
<p>34. The king said to Barzilai, &#x201C;You cross over with me and I will provide for you [while you stay] with me in Yerusholoyim.&#x201D;</p>
<p>35. Barzilai said to the king, &#x201C;How many more years of life [do I have] that I should go up with the king to Yerusholoyim?</p>
<p>36. I am eighty years old today, can I differentiate between something good or bad? Does your servant taste what I eat or what I drink? Can I still hear the voices of princes and princesses? Why should you servant remain a burden to my master the king?&#x201D;</p>
<p>37. Your servant will just cross over the Yardein to accompany the king. Why should the king give me this type of reward?</p>
<p>38. Let your servant return and I will die in my own city [and be buried] in the burial place of my father and mother and your servant Kimhom will travel on with my master, the king and do unto him as you see fit.&#x201D;</p>
<p>39. The king said, &#x201C;Kimhom will cross over with me and I will do unto him what you see fit and whatever you choose, [to request] of me, I will do for you.&#x201D;</p>
<p>40. All the people crossed the Yardein and the king crossed over. The king kissed Barzilai and blessed him. He [then] returned home.</p>
<p>41. The king went over to Gilgol and kimhon went over with him. All the people of Yehudah, brought the king over together with half of the people of Yisroel.</p>
<p>42. [Then] all the men of Yisroel came to the king and they said to the king, &#x201C;Why did our brothers, steal you away the men of Yehudah and [secretly] cross the king and his household over the Yardein together with all of Dovid&#x2019;s men?&#x201D;</p>
<p>43. All the men of Yehudah answered to the men of Yisroel, &#x201C;Because the king is close to us, why should this anger you? Have we received any food from the king, have any presents been given to us?&#x201D;</p>
<p>44. The men of Yisroel replied to men of Yehudah, and said, &#x201C;We have ten parts of the king and we also have more right in Dovid than you. Why have you made light of me? Was I not first in asking to have my king return?&#x201D; The words of men of Yehudah overpowered the words of the men of Yisroel.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>20</title>
<p>1. There, a wicked man invited [men to join him]. His name was Shevah, the son of Bichri a man of Yemini. He blew the shofar and said, &#x201C;We have no part of Dovid, we have no inheritance with the son of Yeshai. Yisroel, every man should return to his home.</p>
<p>2. All of the men of Yisroel abandoned Dovid to follow Shevah, the son of Bichri. The men of Yehudah stayed with their king [as he travelled] from the Yardein to Yerusholoyim.</p>
<p>3. Dovid came to his palace in Yerusholoyim, he took the ten women who were concubines that he had left behind to watch the palace and placed them in a guarded house and provided for them [there]. He had no relations with them, and they were guarded [there] until the day of their deaths They became widows whose husband was alive.</p>
<p>4. The king said to Amosoh, Rally the men of Yehudah and have them here within three days and then you be back here [to meet me].</p>
<p>5. Amosoh went to rally Yehudah but was delayed past the appointed time that had been set.</p>
<p>6. Dovid said to Avishai, &#x201C;Shevah, son of Bichri will do us more harm then Avsholom did. Take your master&#x2019;s servants and pursue him lest he find fortified cities to escape out of our sight.</p>
<p>7. Yoav&#x2019;s men went out after him, the archers and the slingers and all the strong soldiers. They left Yerusholoyim to pursue Shevah, the son of Bichri.</p>
<p>8. When [Yoav and his men] were by the great stone which is in Givon Amosoh came before them. Yoav was girded with a belt on his garment and a sword was fastened on it [the belt]. He wore it close to his loins in its sheath, and as he went towards Amosoh, it fell out.</p>
<p>9. Yoav said to Amosoh, &#x201C;How are you, my brother?&#x201D; Yoav grabbed Amosoh&#x2019;s beard with his right hand to kiss him.</p>
<p>10. Amosoh was not watching out for the sword that was in Yoav&#x2019;s hand. He [Yoav] struck him with it into his fifth rib. and his insides poured out unto the ground, and he did not strike him again, for he died [instantly]. Yoav and his brother Avishai [then] chased after Sheva, the son of Bichiri.</p>
<p>11. One of Yoav&#x2019;s young men stood by [the corpse] and said, &#x201C;Whoever likes Yoav and whoever sides with Dovid should [follow] after Yoav.</p>
<p>12. Amosoh was rolling in [his own] blood in the road. The man saw that the people stood in their places and [so] he removed Amosoh from the road out to the field and threw a cloth over it when he saw that all who passed by it remained there.</p>
<p>13. When it was withdrawn from the road all the men followed Yoav to oursue Shevah, the son of Bichri.</p>
<p>14. He [Shevah] went through all the tribes of Yisroel, to Oveil, Beis Ma&#x2019;achoh and all the Beirim. They [Yoav&#x2019;s men] gathered together and went after him.</p>
<p>15. They came and beseiged him in Oveil and Beis Ma&#x2019;achoh They piled up an earthen mound against the city and it [the city] held by virtue of its inner wall. All the people with Yoav battered the wall to throw it down.</p>
<p>16. A wise woman called out from the city, &#x201C;Listen, listen. Tell Yoav, &#x2018;Come here so that I may speak to you.&#x2019;.&#x201D;</p>
<p>17. He came to her and the woman said, &#x201C;Are you Yoav?&#x201D; He replied, &#x201C;It is I.&#x201D; She said to him, &#x201C;Listen to the words of your handmaiden.&#x201D; He said, &#x201C;I am listening.&#x201D;</p>
<p>18. She spoke saying, &#x201C;You should have talked [peace] first, if you had asked [for peace] with Oveil they would have completely [cooperated].&#x201D;</p>
<p>19. &#x201C;I am [from the people of the city] that are loyal [and] trustworthy to Yisroel, You are seeking to annhilate a city that is a metropolis of Yisroel. Why destroy the portion that Adonoy [gave to us]?&#x201D;</p>
<p>20. Yoav replied, and said, &#x201C;Far be it, far be it from me that I would devour and I would destroy.</p>
<p>21. That is not the case because it is a man from Har Ephraim, whose name is Shevah, the son of Bichri, has lifted up his hand against king Dovid. Give him alone to us and we wil go away from the city.&#x201D; The woman said to Yoav, &#x201C;His head will be thrown to you over the wall.&#x201D;</p>
<p>22. The woman came [and spoke] to all the people with her [persuasive] wisdom. They cut off the head of Shevah, the son of Bichri and threw it to Yoav: He blew the trumpet and they disengaged from the city and dispersed, each man returning to his home. Yoav returned to Yerusholoyim to the king.</p>
<p>23. Yoav commanded the entire army of Yisroel. Venoyoh, the son of Yehoyodoh was [in charge of] the archers and the slingers.</p>
<p>24. Adorom [was put in charge] over taxes. Yehoshophot, the son of Achilud was the chronicler.</p>
<p>25. Shov was the scribe and Tsodok and Evyosor were the chief Kohanim.</p>
<p>26. Eiroh the Yoiri was also a Kohein for Dovid.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>21</title>
<p>1. There was a famine during the days of Dovid, that lasted for three years, year after year [consecutively]. Dovid asked (Hashem) [why has this occurred]. (Adonoy) said, &#x201C;On account of Shaul and his bloody House because he killed the Givonim.&#x201D;</p>
<p>2. The king called the Givonim and spoke to them [words of apppeasement]. The Givonim were not part of the Bnei Yisroel but were a remnant of the Emorites. The Bnei Yisroel had sworn to them [that they would let them live]. Shaul wanted to kill them in his zeal to avenge the Bnei Yisroel and Yehudah.</p>
<p>3. Dovid said to the Givonim, &#x201C;What can I do for you? How can I atone [for your greivances], so that you should bless the heritage of Adonoy?&#x201D;</p>
<p>4. The Givonim replied to him, &#x201C;We are not interested in silver or gold from Shaul or from his household and we are not interested in killing anyone from Yisroel.&#x201D; He [Dovid] said, &#x201C;What are you saying I should do for you?&#x201D;</p>
<p>5. They replied to the king, &#x201C;The man who stopped us and intended to destroy us [preventing us] from establishing ourselves throughout the boundaries of Yisroel.</p>
<p>6. Give us seven of his sons and we will hang them before Adonoy in Givas Shaul, the chosen one of Adonoy.&#x201D; The king said, &#x201C;I will give [them to you]&#x201D;.</p>
<p>7. The king had pity on Mephivoshes, the son of Yohonoson, the son of Shaul because of the oath before Adonoy that was made between Dovid and Yohonoson, the son of Shaul.</p>
<p>8. The king took the two sons of Ritzpoh the daughter of Ayoh who had bore them to Shaul, [whose names were] Armoni and Mephivoshes, and [also] the five sons of Michal, the daughter of Shaul who had bore them to Adriel, the son of Birzilai, the Mecholtite.</p>
<p>9. He Delivered them to the hands of the Givonim and they hung them in the mountain before Adonoy. The seven were killed [all] at the same time. They were killed during the first days of the harvest, at the beginning of the barley harvest.</p>
<p>10. Ritzpoh, the daughter of Ayoh took a sackcloth and spread it out for herself on the mountain [where the corpses were]. [She stayed there] from the beginning of the harvest until the rains fell on them [the corpses] from heaven. She did not let any birds rest on them during the day nor any beasts of the field during the night.</p>
<p>11. Dovid was told what Ritzphoh, the daughter of Ayoh did; she was the concubine of Shaul.</p>
<p>12. Dovid went and took the bones of Shaul and the bones of Yohonoson, his son from the leaders of Yoveish Gilod who had stolen them from the street of Beis Shan. where they had hung them&#x2014;the Pelishtim. on the day the Pelishtim killed Shaul in Gilboa.</p>
<p>13. He brought up the bones of Shaul and the bones of Yohonoson, his son and they gathered the bones that were hanging.</p>
<p>14. They buried the bones of Shaul and the bones of Yohonoson, his son in the land of Binyomin, in Tzailoh, in the grave of his father Kish. They did everything that the king had commanded. After that, God accepted the plea of the land</p>
<p>15. There was another war of the Pelishtim with Yisroel. Dovid and his servants went down and waged war against the Pelishtim and Dovid became exhausted.</p>
<p>16. Isho Benov, who was one of children of the giant and who had a spear case weighing three hundred bronze weights and who was armed with a new sword, said he was going to kill Dovid.</p>
<p>17. Avishai, the son Tsruyoh [came] to his aid, and struck the Peleshti and killed him. At that time, Dovid&#x2019;s men swore to him saying, &#x201C;You shall no longer go out to war with us so that the light of Yisroel not become extinguished.</p>
<p>18. Afterwards, there was more war with the Pelishtim in Gov. At that time, Sivkai the Chushosi struck down Sof, who was one of the giant&#x2019;s children.</p>
<p>19. There was more war with the Pelishtim in Gov. and Elchonon, the son of Yari [whose family] were weavers in Beis Lechem, struck down Golias the Gitite, the wood part of his spear was like that of the weaver&#x2019;s rod.</p>
<p>20. There was another war in Gas and there was a giant man whose fingers and toes numbered six each for a total number of twenty-four. He also was a child of Horopho&#x2019;s.</p>
<p>21. He cursed Yisroel and Yohonoson killed him, [Yohonoson was] the son of Shimi, Dovid&#x2019;s brother.</p>
<p>22. These four [giants] were born to Horophoh in Gas and they [eventually] fell into the hands of Dovid and in the hands of his servants.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>22</title>
<p>1. Dovid spoke to Adonoy the words of this song. on the day Adonoy saved him from the hand of all his enemies and from the hand of Shaul.</p>
<p>2. He said, Adonoy is my Rock, my Fortress and my Rescuer.</p>
<p>3. My God is my Rock I take refuge in Him. He is my Shield and the horn of my salvation. My Stronghold, my Refuge, my Saviour. He saved me from [all] violence.</p>
<p>4. I call to Adonoy in praise and I am saved from my enemies.</p>
<p>5. Death&#x2019;s destruction surrounded me, the deluge of wicked soldiers alarmed me.</p>
<p>6. Groups of evil men surrounded me, death traps were before me.</p>
<p>7. In my distress I called to Adonoy, and to my God I called. He hears my voice from His abode, and my cries reach His ears.</p>
<p>8. The world shook and shuddered, the pillars of heaven trembled. They shook when God became angry:</p>
<p>9. Smoke rose from His nostrils, fire from His mouth consumed [the wicked]. Coals flamed forth from Him.</p>
<p>10. He bent heaven and descended and clouds of darkness were beneath His feet.</p>
<p>11. He rode on a cherub and flew, He was seen on wings of wind.</p>
<p>12. He put [a protective] darkness around His shelter, abundant waters, thick clouds of the sky.</p>
<p>13. From the brightness before Him burning coals of fire [came forth].</p>
<p>14. Adonoy thundered from heaven, and the most high made His voice heard.</p>
<p>15. He shot arrows and scattered [the enemy] [He sent forth] lightning and terrified them.</p>
<p>16. The bed of the ocean appeared, and the foundations of the earth were revealed by Adonoy&#x2019;s [commanding] shout, by the wind blowing from His nostrils.</p>
<p>17. He delivers [salvation] from on high, He took me away [from my enemies]. He plucked me out of mighty waters.</p>
<p>18. He saved me from my mighty enemy, and from those who hate me for they were too powerful for me.</p>
<p>19. [My enemies] were after me at my low point, Adonoy was my Support.</p>
<p>20. He took me out and delivered me, He saved me because He found me favorable.</p>
<p>21. Adonoy rewarded me according to my rightesnous according to the purity of my hands He compensated me.</p>
<p>22. Because I have kept to Adonoy&#x2019;s ways and I have not wickedly forsaken my God.</p>
<p>23. Because all his judgments were before me, and His statutes, I did not turn from.</p>
<p>24. I was wholehearted with Him, and guarded myself from sinning.</p>
<p>25. Adonoy compensated me according to my righteous and my purity in His eyes.</p>
<p>26. With the devout, you are kind, with the wholehearted, You are wholehearted.</p>
<p>27. With the pure, You are pure, and with those who are deviant You act perversely.</p>
<p>28. You deliver an afflicted people And Your eyes are upon the haughty to humble them.</p>
<p>29. For You are my light, Adonoy and Adonoy will brighten my darkness.</p>
<p>30. With Your [help] I will overrun [enemy] troops, with [the aid of] my God I will scale a wall.</p>
<p>31. God Whose way is perfect, the word of Adonoy is refined. He is the shield of all those who seek refuge in Him.</p>
<p>32. For who is mighty other then Adonoy? And who is a Protector other then our God?</p>
<p>33. The Almighty who empowered me with strenght and cleared my path to perfection.</p>
<p>34. He made my feet like [those of] deer and placed me on the heights.</p>
<p>35. He trained my hands for war, my arms to bend a copper bow.</p>
<p>36. You have given me the sheild of Your redemption, and Your humility has made me great.</p>
<p>37. You have expanded my stride beneath me and [nevertheless] my ankles did not slip.</p>
<p>38. I have pursued my enemies and destroyed them and I did not return until they were consumed.</p>
<p>39. I have consumed them, I will strike them and they will not get up. and they fell beneath my feet.</p>
<p>40. You infused me with strength for the battles, You caused my enemies to fall beneath me.</p>
<p>41. And regarding my enemies You gave me the back of their necks I cut down those who hate me.</p>
<p>42. They cried out but there was no one to deliver them [they cried] to Adoonoy but He did not answer them.</p>
<p>43. I crushed them like the dust of the earth, like the mud in the streets I ground them, I trampled them.</p>
<p>44. You rescued me from the antagonists among my people. You preserved me to be a leader of nations, A people that I did not [even] know serves me.</p>
<p>45. Foreign people lied to me [as soon] as their ears hear [my wish] they listen to [and obey] me.</p>
<p>46. Foreign people will wither, and become lame from [the agony of] their inprisonment.</p>
<p>47. Adonoy lives, and blessed is [protecting] Rock, and exalted is God, my (Rock) and my Saviour.</p>
<p>48. Almighty, Who avenges me [of my enemies] and subdues peoples beneath me.</p>
<p>49. You extract me from my enemies&#x2019; [clutches], You lift me above those who rise against me. You save me from violent men.</p>
<p>50. Therefore I will laud You, Adonoy, among the nations and I will sing to Your Name.</p>
<p>51. He delivers great salvation to His king, and bestows kindness upon His anointed one, to Dovid and his children for eternity.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>23</title>
<p>1. These are the last words of Dovid the sayings of Dovid, the son of Yeshai. and the sayings of the man raised on high the annointed of the God of Yakov and he who composed sweet songs for Yisroel.</p>
<p>2. The spirit of Adonoy speaks through me and His word is on my tongue.</p>
<p>3. The God of Yisroel spoke, the Rock of Yisroel said to me &#x2018;A ruler over men, will be a righteous person, that rules in the fear of God.</p>
<p>4. As day breaks with the sun shining, on a cloudless morning. [Brighter] then the light that comes from rain [falling on] vegetated earth.</p>
<p>5. For is not my house with God? For He has made an eternal convenant with me, perfectly arranged and preserved. All my deliverance and desires [are before God] because [my kingdom] will never be outgrown.</p>
<p>6. The wicked&#x2019;s [kingdoms] are all like an itinerant thorn unable to be held in one&#x2019;s hand.</p>
<p>7. Any man [wanting] to touch them must be armed with iron and with the handle of a spear. They will be completely burnt, totally consumed by the fire.</p>
<p>8. These are the names of the mighty men that were with Dovid. The man who sat in the council of wisdom, who was unique in three areas was Adino the Etzonite. He killed eight hundred men in one [battle].</p>
<p>9. After him was Elozor, the son of Dodo, the son of Achochi, one of the three mighty men that were with Dovid when they humiliated the Pelishtim who had gathered there for war, and the men of Yisroel were gone away.</p>
<p>10. He got up and struck the Pelishtim until his hand tired and his hand stuck to the sword. Adonoy brought great salvation on that day. The [rest of the] people returned after him but only to strip [the corpses].</p>
<p>11. After him was Shamoh, the son of Ogaih from the mountain. The Pelishtim gathered and assembled in troops. There was a field there, which was full of lentils, and the people fled from before the Pelishtim.</p>
<p>12. He [Shamoh] stood in this field and saved it. and he struck the Pelishtim. And Adonoy brought a great salvation.</p>
<p>13. Three of the thirty leaders went down and came to Dovid at harvest time. at the Adulom cave The assembled Pelishtim were camped in the Rephoim valley.</p>
<p>14. Dovid was then in the fortress and a contingent of Pelishtim was then in Beis Lechem.</p>
<p>15. Dovid desired [something] and said, &#x201C;Who will give me water to drink from the well of Beis Lechem that is at the gate?&#x201D;</p>
<p>16. The three warriors broke into the Pelishtim camp and drew water from the well of Beis Lechem that is at the gate. They took it and brought it to Dovid but he did not want to drink and [instead] he offered it as a libation to Adonoy.</p>
<p>17. he said, &#x201C;Far be it from me, Adonoy, to do this. [Do I want] the blood of [these] who risked their lives?&#x201D; therefore he did not drink [the water]. This is what these three warriors did.</p>
<p>18. And Avishai, the brother of Yoav, the son of Tsruyoh was the leader of the three. He swung his spear and killed three hundred men. His name was best known of the three.</p>
<p>19. Of the three, he was most honored and was their leader but he did not reach [the status] of the first three.</p>
<p>20. And Venoyohu, the son of Yehoyodoh the son of a warrior, a man of mighty deeds from Kabtzel. He struck down the two Moabite giants and he went down and struck the lion in the well on [that] snowy day:</p>
<p>21. He struck the Egyptian man, a man of [frightening] countenance, and there was a spear in the Egyptian&#x2019;s hand. He [Venoyohu] went down to him [armed] with a stick and stole the spear out of the Egyptian&#x2019;s hand and killed him with his own spear.</p>
<p>22. These things did Benoyohu, the son of Yehoydoh do, his name was best known of the three warriors.</p>
<p>23. Most honoured of the thirty but he did not reach [the status] of the first three. Dovid made him his aide.</p>
<p>24. Asoel, Yoav&#x2019;s brother [was one] of the thirty [as was] Elchonon, the son of Dodo [from] Beis Lochem.</p>
<p>25. Shamoh the Charodite, Elikoh the Charodite.</p>
<p>26. Cheletz the Paltite, Iroh, the son of Ikeish, the Tokite</p>
<p>27. Aviezer the Ansosite, Mevunai the Chushosite.</p>
<p>28. Tsalmon the Achochite Mahary the Netophosite.</p>
<p>29. Cheilev, the son Ba&#x2019;anoh the Netophosite, Itai, the son of Rivai from the valley of Bnai Binyomin.</p>
<p>30. Benoyohu the Pirosonite, Hidai from Nachalei Goash.</p>
<p>31. Avi Alvon the Arvosite, Azmoves, the Barchumite.</p>
<p>32. Elyachboh the Sha&#x2019;alvonite, Yoshain&#x2019;s son, Yehonoson.</p>
<p>33. Shamoh the Havorite, Achiom, the son of Shoror the Arorite.</p>
<p>34. Eliphelet, the son of Achasbuy the son of the Machosite, Eliom, the son of Achitophel the Gilonite.</p>
<p>35. Chetzry the Carmelite, Pa&#x2019;ary the Arbite.</p>
<p>36. Yigol, the son of Noson from Tzovoh, Boni the Godite.</p>
<p>37. Tzelek the Amonite [and] Nachrai the Be&#x2019;erosite the weapons carriers of Yoav, the son of Tsruyoh.</p>
<p>38. Iroh the Yisrite, Goreiv the Yirite.</p>
<p>39. Urioh the Chitite, [these are] all thirty-seven.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>24</title>
<p>1. Adonoy&#x2019;s anger was again kindled against Yisroel. he enticed Dovid against saying, &#x201C;Go, count Yisroel and Yehudah.&#x201D;</p>
<p>2. The king said to Yoav the general of the army that was with him, &#x201C;Go to all the tribes of Yisroel from Don until Be&#x2019;er Shevah and number the people [in order] that I should be able to know, the count of the people.&#x201D;</p>
<p>3. Yoav said to the king, &#x201C;Adonoy your God should add to the people one hundred times their [current] number, and may my master the king&#x2019;s eyes see it. [But] my master the king, why do you want such a thing?&#x201D;</p>
<p>4. The king&#x2019;s word overrode Yoav and the army officers. Yoav and army officers left the king&#x2019;s presence to count the people of Yisroel.</p>
<p>5. They crossed the Yardein and they camped in Aroeir, to the right of the city which was in the valley of to Gad. [From there they went] unto Yazer.</p>
<p>6. They came to Gilod and to a land of a new [settlement]. They came to Don&#x2019;s portion, to Ya&#x2019;an and [then] around Tsidon.</p>
<p>7. They came to a mountain fortress and all the Chivite and Canaanite cities, they [then] went out to southern Yehudah to Be&#x2019;er Shovah.</p>
<p>8. They went all over the land and they came at the end of nine months and twenty days to Yerusholoyim.</p>
<p>9. Yoav gave the sum of the people&#x2019;s census, to the king, and there were in Yisroel eight hundred thousand valiant men armed with swords and the men of Yehudah were five hundred thousand men.</p>
<p>10. Dovid&#x2019;s heart pained him that he had counted the people. Dovid said to Adonoy, &#x201C;I have gravely sinned by what I have done. Now Adonoy, let the sin of your servant pass for I have been very foolish.&#x201D;</p>
<p>11. Dovid rose in the morning and the word of Adonoy came to the prophet Gad, Dovid&#x2019;s seer, saying:</p>
<p>12. &#x201C;Go tell Dovid that thus Adonoy has said, &#x2018;I will afflict you with [one of] three [things], choose one of them and I will do it to you&#x2019;.&#x201D;</p>
<p>13. Gad came to Dovid and told him. He said to him, &#x201C;Do you want seven years of famine to come in your land or to flee from your enemy for three months and he will pursue you or to have three days of pestilence in your land? Now, think clearly what I should answer to the [One] who has sent me with this message,&#x201D;</p>
<p>14. Dovid said to Gad, &#x201C;I am in great anguish. Let us fall into the hand of Adonoy because He has much compassion, [but] let me not fall into the hands of man.&#x201D;</p>
<p>15. Adonoy inflicted a pestilence upon Yisroel from the morning until the appointed time. And there died from the people from Don to Be&#x2019;er Shevah, seventy thousand men.</p>
<p>16. The angel stetched forth his hand to destroy Yerusholoyim and Adonoy decided against further evil and said to the angel, that destroyed the people, &#x201C;It is enough, now withdraw your hand.&#x201D; The angel of Adonoy was close to the threshing floor of Aravnoh the Yevusite.</p>
<p>17. Dovid said to Adonoy when he saw the angel striking the people, and he said, &#x201C;I have sinned, and I have acted perversely [but] this flock, what did it do? Your hand should [strike] me and my father&#x2019;s house.&#x201D;</p>
<p>18. Gad came to Dovid on that day and said to him, &#x201C;Go up establish an alter for Adonoy on the threshing floor of Aravnoh, the Yevusite.&#x201D;</p>
<p>19. Dovid went [and followed] Gad&#x2019;s instructions as Adonoy commanded.</p>
<p>20. Aravnoh saw the king and his servant passing [near] him and Aravnoh went out and bowed down to the king with his face to the ground.</p>
<p>21. Aravnoh said, &#x201C;Why is my master the king coming to his servant?&#x201D; Dovid said, &#x201C;To buy the threshing floor from you [in order] to build an altar to Adonoy [so that] the plague among the people should cease.</p>
<p>22. Aravnoh said to Dovid, &#x201C;Take it and offer my master, the king, [whatever] is good in [your] eyes. see the cattle [fit] for a burnt offering and the rakes and the cattle equipment are [fit] for [fire] wood.</p>
<p>23. Aravnoh the prince gave all of this to the king and Aravnoh said to the king, &#x201C;Adonoy, your God should accept your [offerings].&#x201D;</p>
<p>24. The king said to Aravnoh, &#x201C;No, I [want] to buy them from you for their value, and I will not offer to Adonoy, my God burnt offerings [obtained] for free.&#x201D; Dovid bought the threshing floor and the cattle for fifty silver shekolim.</p>
<p>25. Dovid built an altar to Adonoy there and he offered burnt offerings and peace offerings. Adonoy was entreated of the land [people] The plague ceased from [the people of] Yisroel.</p>
</chapter>
<appendix>
<p><bold>[[2]] Behold a man came from the camp.</bold> The Pesikta<sup><xref rid="fn1">1</xref></sup> brings an opinion that this man is Doeig,<sup><xref rid="fn2">2</xref></sup> but the explanation is indefensible in my heart.<sup><xref rid="fn3">3</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[9]] I am gripped with convulsions.</bold> I am gripped with convulsions.<sup><xref rid="fn4">4</xref></sup> The Midrash Aggadah<sup><xref rid="fn5">5</xref></sup> explains that this<sup><xref rid="fn6">6</xref></sup> occurred because of Shaul&#x2019;s sin of killing the Kohanim<sup><xref rid="fn7">7</xref></sup> as it is written concerning them,<sup><xref rid="fn8">8</xref></sup> &#x201C;a checkered shirt.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn9">9</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>While I am still alive.</bold> Hurry and kill me. I prefer that you kill me and not they<sup><xref rid="fn10">10</xref></sup> kill and torture me.<sup><xref rid="fn11">11</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[10]] And the bracelet that was on his arm.</bold> The tefilin that was on his arm.<sup><xref rid="fn12">12</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[16]] Your blood is on your own head.</bold> The responsibility for your death rests on your own head.<sup><xref rid="fn13">13</xref></sup> There is no one to punish for your death but yourself.</p>
<p><bold>[[18]] He said, &#x201C;To teach the Bnei Yehudah archery.</bold> David said, &#x201C;Now that mighty among Yisroel have fallen, the Bnei Yehudah need to be taught how to make war and how to pull back a bow.</p>
<p><bold>Behold it is written in the Seifer HaYoshor.</bold> This is written in Seifer Bereishis, which is the Seifer of the righteous,<sup><xref rid="fn14">14</xref></sup> Avraham, Yitzchok and Yaakov. And where [In Bereishis] is it hinted at? &#x201C;Your hand will be on the neck of your enemies.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn15">15</xref></sup> What type of warfare is it where he places his hand next to his forehead,<sup><xref rid="fn16">16</xref></sup> which is opposite his neck?<sup><xref rid="fn17">17</xref></sup> One must say: this is archery.</p>
<p><bold>[[19]] Pillar of Yisroel, on your heights [you have been rendered] a corpse.</bold> Pillars of Yisroel, on the mightiest point of your stronghold you have fallen as corpses. This is Yonasan&#x2019;s translation.</p>
<p><bold>[[21]] Mountains in Gilboa.</bold> The mountains in Gilboa.</p>
<p><bold>Nor fields [yielding enough for] baking offerings.</bold> There will be no harvest among [the fields] that have the amount [that necessitates] making the baking offering.<sup><xref rid="fn18">18</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>Because there, the shield of soldiers spit out.</bold> They had shields made of skins and when they went to war, they smeared them with oil so that a weapon hitting [the shield] should slip [off of it]. As it is said [in Scriptures] &#x201C;Get up officers, smear [your] shield with oil. And here this is what the Lamentation means, &#x201C;There, the shield of soldiers spit out,&#x201D; it spit out its oil and [the oil] did not stick to it and rendered [the shield] as if it wasn&#x2019;t smeared with oil. All [uses of the word] <span dir="rtl">&#x05D4;&#x05B7;&#x05D2;&#x05B0;&#x05E2;&#x05B8;&#x05DC;&#x05B8;&#x05D4;</span> is a language of rejecting what had been put into it as [we find] &#x201C;His oxen will impregnate, [the seed] will not be rejected.&#x201D;</p>
<p><bold>[[22]] Would not be pulled back.</bold> Was not used to being pulled back.<sup><xref rid="fn19">19</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[23]] They were lighter then eagles.</bold> To do the will of their Creator.<sup><xref rid="fn20">20</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[24]] Who has clothed you in scarlet clothing together with other delights.</bold> That clothed you in coloured garments and loaded you with delights.</p>
<p><bold>[[25]] On your heights, you were slain.</bold> On your strong point you have been killed.</p>
<p><bold>[[27]] The weapons of war.</bold> [Referring to] Shaul and Yohanasan who were Yisroel&#x2019;s weapons.</p>
<ftnote id="fn1"><sup>1</sup>Pesikta Rabosi 12,9.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn2"><sup>2</sup>Doeig HaEdomi is first mentioned in Shmuel 1,21:8.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn3"><sup>3</sup>It is clear from Shmuel 1, 22:18 that Shaul knew Doeig. Therefore, if in fact this man is Doeig, why did Shaul have to ask later in v. 8, &#x201C;Who are you?&#x201D; (Seder Hadoros, p. 102).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn4"><sup>4</sup>This is Targum Yonasan&#x2019;s translation.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn5"><sup>5</sup>Tanchuma Metzoro 2.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn6"><sup>6</sup>Shaul&#x2019;s death in this manner was retribution for that sin.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn7"><sup>7</sup>Of the city of Nov, see Shmuel 1,22:18.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn8"><sup>8</sup>The Kohanim in general.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn9"><sup>9</sup>Vayikra, 28:4 lists the <span dir="rtl">&#x05DB;&#x05EA;&#x05E0;&#x05EA; &#x05EA;&#x05E9;&#x05D1;&#x05E5;</span> as one of the garments worn by the Kohanim. Both the word <span dir="rtl">&#x05D4;&#x05B7;&#x05BC;&#x05E9;&#x05C1;&#x05B0;&#x05D1;&#x05B5;&#x05BC;&#x05E5;</span> there and the word <span dir="rtl">&#x05D4;&#x05B7;&#x05E9;&#x05C1;&#x05BC;&#x05B8;&#x05D1;&#x05B8;&#x05E5;</span> here share the same three letters, <span dir="rtl">&#x05E9;&#x05BE;&#x05D1;&#x05BE;&#x05E5;</span>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn10"><sup>10</sup>The Pelishtim.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn11"><sup>11</sup>Prior to my death.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn12"><sup>12</sup>This is Targum Yonasan&#x2019;s translation. He refuses to explain it to literally mean bracelet because that would have been taken by the Pelishtim as part of the spoils of war (Meam Loez).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn13"><sup>13</sup>This is Targum Yonasan&#x2019;s translation.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn14"><sup>14</sup>Rashi is citing the opinion of Rav Yochonon in Avodah Zarah, 25a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn15"><sup>15</sup>Bereishis 49:8.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn16"><sup>16</sup>When pulling back the string of his bow. Rashi in Avodah Zarah, ibid writes the archer places his hand next to his eyes. This is how they sight their targets.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn17"><sup>17</sup>This interpretation reads the verse in Bereishis differently: &#x201C;your hand will be on your neck.&#x201D; See Marsho, Avodah Zarah ibid.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn18"><sup>18</sup>If one prepares the amount of omer&#x2019;s worth of dough then one must take off a portion of the mixture and give it to a kohein, see Shelach 15,20. An omer is the equivalent of forty-three and one-fifth eggs by volume.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn19"><sup>19</sup>Without hitting Yohanasan&#x2019;s targets, thereby spilling his enemies&#x2019; blood and cutting through their fat.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn20"><sup>20</sup>Rashi is paraphrasing Pirkei Avos 5,23.</ftnote>
</appendix>
<appendix>
<p><bold>[[8]] Took Ish Boshes.</bold> He extrapolated from a verse that two kings were destined to come from Binyomin. Because the Holy One, blessed is He told Yakov, &#x201C;Kings will come forth from you,&#x201D; and [by this time] all of his children had been born except for Binyomin.<sup><xref rid="fn21">1</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[16]] The Plain of Swords.</bold> Yonasan translates the plain of Killing on account of the swords just like you say [in Scriptures] (Tehilim 89, 44)<sup><xref rid="fn22">2</xref></sup> &#x201C;You also turned back the sharpness of his sword.&#x201D;</p>
<p><bold>[[23]] Into the fifth rib.</bold> As [if to say] the fifth rib,<sup><xref rid="fn23">3</xref></sup> the place where the bile and the liver are set. [But] Yonasan translated [this to mean] &#x201C;on the side of his thigh,&#x201D;</p>
<p><bold>And died in his place.</bold> And died in his place.<sup><xref rid="fn24">4</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[27]] If you had not spoken.</bold> If only you had spoken this [way<sup><xref rid="fn25">5</xref></sup> earlier] [The <span dir="rtl">&#x05DC;&#x05D0;</span>] is as [if it were written] <span dir="ltr">&#x05DC;&#x05D5;</span><sup><xref rid="fn26">6</xref></sup>, meaning it. Another [way] to interpret it is as it&#x2019;s plain meaning<sup><xref rid="fn27">7</xref></sup>: if you had not spoken i.e. that which you said &#x201C;Let the young soldiers get up and playfight.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn28">8</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[29]] The Bisron.</bold> The name of a region.</p>
<p><bold>[[30]] Nineteen men and Asoel.</bold> But is not Asoel included in [the group called] &#x201C;the servants of Dovid,&#x201D; so why is he [singled] out? [The reason is] he was worth all of them [together] and so too [a similar case], (Yehoshua 2,1), &#x201C;Go see [and spy out] the land and Yericho&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn29">9</xref></sup> and so too [another similar case] &#x201C;King Shlomo loved many foreign women and the daughter of Pharaoh.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn30">10</xref></sup> (Kings I, 11, 1 ).</p>
<ftnote id="fn21"><sup>1</sup>&#x201C;Will come forth from you&#x201D; implies that they were to come from someone yet unborn, and this could only be Binyomin. Avner understood this to mean that two kings will be descendant from Binyomin, Shaul and Ish Boshes (Rashi and Sifsei Chachomin, Breshis 35,11).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn22"><sup>2</sup>Rashi is showing how the word <span dir="rtl">&#x05E6;&#x05D5;&#x05BC;&#x05E8;</span>, sharpness, is used in reference to a sword.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn23"><sup>3</sup>Counting from the bottom.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn24"><sup>4</sup>This is Targum Yonasan&#x2019;s translation.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn25"><sup>5</sup>Your decrying of us fighting each other.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn26"><sup>6</sup>According to this first interpretation, the construct <span dir="rtl">&#x05DC;&#x05D5;&#x05BC;&#x05DC;&#x05B5;&#x05D0;</span> denotes <span dir="rtl">&#x05DC;&#x05D5;&#x05B9;&#x05DC;&#x05D5;&#x05BC;</span>, &#x201C;if only if,&#x201D; i.e., if only you had spoken these reconcilitory words earlier.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn27"><sup>7</sup>This interpretation of <span dir="rtl">&#x05DC;&#x05D5;&#x05DC;&#x05D0;</span> is the usual &#x201C;if not for.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn28"><sup>8</sup>Those words triggered this deadly battle.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn29"><sup>9</sup>Yericho was as strong as the entire land combined (see Rashi there).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn30"><sup>10</sup>Shlomo cherished Pharaoh&#x2019;s daughter as much as he did the rest of them put together. (See Rashi ibid).</ftnote>
</appendix>
<appendix>
<p><bold>[[3]] His second [son] was Kilov.</bold> [But] in another place<sup><xref rid="fn31">1</xref></sup> [Scriptures] calls him, &#x201C;and his second [son] was Doniel&#x201D;.<sup><xref rid="fn32">2</xref></sup> So why is his called [here] by the name of Kilov? Rebbe Yitzchok said [to answer this question] : Because the generation&#x2019;s cynics were saying that Avigail was pregnant from Novol,<sup><xref rid="fn33">3</xref></sup> [consequently Hashem caused] his facial features to change and resemble his father.<sup><xref rid="fn34">4</xref></sup> And our Rabbis said<sup><xref rid="fn35">5</xref></sup> that [this name of Kilov was due to the fact that] he embarrassed Mephiboshes through Halacha.<sup><xref rid="fn36">6</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[5]] By Egloh</bold> This refers to Michal<sup><xref rid="fn37">7</xref></sup> who was cherished by him. Similarly it says &#x201C;If you had not plowed with my calf&#x201D; (Shoftim 14, 18).<sup><xref rid="fn38">8</xref></sup> [But] it is written, &#x201C;And Michal, the daughter of Shaul had no child until the day of her death&#x201D; (Below, 6, 23) she didn&#x2019;t have one until the day of her death<sup><xref rid="fn39">9</xref></sup>?<sup><xref rid="fn40">10</xref></sup> From that incident<sup><xref rid="fn41">11</xref></sup> and on [she had no children], but prior to that incident she did have [children].</p>
<p><bold>[[6]] Was strengthening.</bold> With all his might over the house of Shaul, to establish its monarchy.</p>
<p><bold>[[8]] Am I the chief dog [watcher] for [the kingdom of] Yehudah?</bold> Am I at least as important as the chief dog watcher for Dovid. However, according to the cantillation which has the accent under [the word] <span dir="rtl">&#x05E8;&#x05D0;&#x05C1;&#x05E9;&#x05C1;</span> and [the word] <span dir="rtl">&#x05DB;&#x05BC;&#x05B6;&#x05DC;&#x05B6;&#x05D1; &#x05D0;&#x05B8;&#x05E0;&#x05C2;&#x05DB;&#x05C5;&#x05D9;</span> coralled [together],<sup><xref rid="fn42">12</xref></sup> then this is the explanation: The chief? Do I want to be a chief in your house? It is better for me to be a dog and an ordinary person in the house of Dovid. This is also Yonasan&#x2019;s translation.</p>
<p><bold>From this day on should I [continue to] be kind.</bold> From now on [is it] proper for me to be kind to the house of Shaul and with all those who love him as I have done until now and I have not delivered you into the hand of Dovid?</p>
<p><bold>[[12]] In his behalf saying.</bold> From his place to say, We shall keep this [oath] by the One Who made the world.</p>
<p><bold>By He Who [posseses] the land.</bold> [This is] language [used for] an oath, By He Who [posseses] the land. Another interpretation: &#x201C;<bold>Below him,</bold>&#x201D; [Avner] mentioned his name first in the message letter and afterwords he mentioned Dovid&#x2019;s name and that is why he was punished. [This is what] he wrote: From me, Avner, the general of Yisroel to Dovid, the king of Yisroel, peace salutation.</p>
<p><bold>To He who [deserves] the land.</bold> To whom the kingdom is proper for him, I am sending to him &#x201C;saying, Enact a convenant, etc.&#x201D;</p>
<p><bold>[[13]] You first bring.</bold> Before you see my face, bring me Michal.</p>
<p><bold>[[15]] From [her] man.</bold> Yonasan translated &#x201C;from the company of her husband.&#x201D;</p>
<p><bold>[[16]] Following and crying.</bold> Over the good deed [about to be] leaving him because all those years he thrust a sword into the bed [separating] between him and her and he did not stumble [into sinful intimacy] with her.<sup><xref rid="fn43">13</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[17]] And the word of Avner was [sent]</bold> Before this [incident with Paltiel]</p>
<p><bold>[[18]] Said about Dovid.</bold> About Dovid, and this is not [an instance of the usual] meaning of the word, <span dir="rtl">&#x05D0;&#x05DC;</span>, &#x201C;to&#x201D;.</p>
<p><bold>[[22]] From an attack.</bold> They sprung, attacking to take spoils from the enemy.</p>
<p><bold>[[26]] From Bor HaSiroh.</bold> The name of a place [But] the Rabbis said: A well and a thorn caused Avner to be killed, by not grasping unto the deeds of Dovid, by [ignoring] the jug of water that [Dovid] took from [under] the head of Shaul<sup><xref rid="fn44">14</xref></sup> and also [by ignoring] the corner of Shaul&#x2019;s garment<sup><xref rid="fn45">15</xref></sup> [Avner dismissed this and] he said &#x201C;Perhaps one of the thorns caught upon [the garment] and tore it.</p>
<p><bold>[[27]] Within the gate.</bold> [Yoav brought Avner] before a sanhedrin to be judged<sup><xref rid="fn46">16</xref></sup> for the [spilling of] blood of his brother, Asoel.</p>
<p><bold>Deceptively.</bold> In a mistake provoking [way] so that Avner would not realize that it is in [Yoav&#x2019;s] heart to kill him. Cut up the verse [to rearrange it&#x2019;s words as follows] &#x201C;and Yoav steered him deceptively to go within the gate to talk to him.&#x201D;</p>
<p><bold>[[29]] [The guilt] should fall.</bold> The [guilt of the] blood of Avner should rest, should fall. [This verse is] referring back to the preceding verse that stated, I and my kingdom are innocent from [the guilt of] the blood of Avner [The guilt of] his blood should fall on the head of Yoav. The blood [of Avner] that was mentioned in the previous verse.</p>
<p><bold>[A lame person] who leans on a cane.</bold> Who leans on his cane because of diseased feet.</p>
<p><bold>[[30]] Killed Avner.</bold> [As if to say] Avner<sup><xref rid="fn47">17</xref></sup> and similar to it [we find] &#x201C;Snatch me, be my surety&#x201D; (Yeshaiya 38, 14), Snatch me<sup><xref rid="fn48">18</xref></sup> and also similarly (Bamidbar 12,13), &#x201C;Please heal her&#x201D; Heal her<sup><xref rid="fn49">19</xref></sup> and similarly to this (Divrei Hayomin II, 17, 7) &#x201C;He sent his officers, Ben Chayil, and Ovadiah&#x2026; to teach in the cities of Yehudah and it&#x2019;s meaning is: He sent his officers, Ben Chayil.<sup><xref rid="fn50">20</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[33]] The death of someone wicked.</bold> Like the death by sword of a wicked person.</p>
<p><bold>[[34]] Your hands were not bound.</bold><sup><xref rid="fn51">21</xref></sup> How could a mighty soldier such as you fall before treacherous men.</p>
<p><bold>[[35]] To feed.</bold> [This is] language [denoting] a meal.</p>
<p><bold>[[39]] I am today weak [as a commoner]</bold> And I am, on this day, a commoner and a young king.</p>
<ftnote id="fn31"><sup>1</sup>Divrei Hayomim I, 3,1.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn32"><sup>2</sup>i.e., refers to the second son of Dovid not as Kilov but as Doniel, his true name.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn33"><sup>3</sup>That Doniel was the son of Novol and not Dovid.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn34"><sup>4</sup>His resemblance to Dovid earned him the name of <span dir="rtl">&#x05DB;&#x05B4;&#x05DC;&#x05B0;&#x05D0;&#x05B8;&#x05D1;</span> a play on <span dir="rtl">&#x05DB;&#x05BC;&#x05D5;&#x05BC;&#x05DC;&#x05D5;&#x05B9; &#x05D0;&#x05B8;&#x05D1;</span>, &#x201C;completely his father.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn35"><sup>5</sup>Berochos 4a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn36"><sup>6</sup>Doniel&#x2019;s superior knowledge became evident during the course of his halachic debates with Mipiboshes. According to this Derosho, the letters <span dir="rtl">&#x05DB;&#x05DC;</span> of <span dir="rtl">&#x05DB;&#x05B4;&#x05DC;&#x05B0;&#x05D0;&#x05B8;&#x05D1;</span> stand for <span dir="rtl">&#x05DE;&#x05B7;&#x05DB;&#x05B0;&#x05DC;&#x05C5;&#x05D9;&#x05DD;</span>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn37"><sup>7</sup>The daughter of Shaul.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn38"><sup>8</sup><span dir="rtl">&#x05E2;&#x05D2;&#x05DC;&#x05D4;</span>, &#x201C;calf&#x201D; is used in reference to a cherished wife just as a calf is cherished by it&#x2019;s owner (See Sanhedrin 21a).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn39"><sup>9</sup>At which time she died in childbirth (ibid).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn40"><sup>10</sup>That verse implies that Michal had no children up to the time of her death, but our verse states that Egloh, i.e. Michal gave birth to Yisrom.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn41"><sup>11</sup>Dovid rejoiced excessively when the Ark was returned from captivity. Michal rebuked Dovid for what seemed to her to be behavior beneath his dignity. This was not the case and she was punished for the unwarranted shaming of Dovid. (ibid).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn42"><sup>12</sup>Rashi&#x2019;s first explanation is assumming that the words <span dir="rtl">&#x05E8;&#x05D0;&#x05E9;</span> and <span dir="rtl">&#x05DB;&#x05DC;&#x05D1;</span> are connected. However, the cantillation indicates that they are separate. Instead, the words <span dir="rtl">&#x05DB;&#x05DC;&#x05D1; &#x05D0;&#x05E0;&#x05DB;&#x05D9;</span> belong together. This compels Rashi to offer an alternative explanation.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn43"><sup>13</sup>Shaul did not consider her married to Dovid because he considered Dovid&#x2019;s Kiddushin having been done using a loan which is an invalid Kiddushin. However, in fact, Dovid had used regular material wealth as his means for Kiddushin which made Dovid halachically married to Michal. This meant that Paltiel Ben Loyish was living in the same house with another man&#x2019;s wife. For all those years Paltiel made sure never to touch her and thus was spiritually elevated by subduing his lustful inclination. Now that she was leaving, he was saddenned to no longer have the opportunity for this type of spiritual greatness. (Sanhedrin, ibid).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn44"><sup>14</sup>This is reference to Shmuel I, 26,12 where Dovid was being pursued by Shaul and Avner. Dovid found them sleeping and hence vulnerable. Not wanting to harm them but wanting to show Shaul he had been there, Dovid took the spear and the jug of water that was underneath Shaul&#x2019;s head.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn45"><sup>15</sup>This is a reference to Shmuel I, 24,5 where Shaul, in pursuit of Dovid, stopped temporarily inside the cave where Dovid was hiding with his men. Dovid did not kill him but surreptitiously caught off the corner of Shaul&#x2019;s garment.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn46"><sup>16</sup>The word <span dir="rtl">&#x05E9;&#x05B7;&#x05C1;&#x05E2;&#x05B7;&#x05E8;</span> often refers to judges who usually hold court at the gate of the city, cf. Devorim 22,15.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn47"><sup>17</sup>Without the <span dir="rtl">&#x05DC;</span> because it is the object of the verse&#x2019;s verb &#x201C;killed.&#x201D; Whereas Avner with the prefix <span dir="rtl">&#x05DC;</span> would usually mean &#x201C;to Avner.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn48"><sup>18</sup>Not &#x201C;to me&#x201D; despite the verse using the word <span dir="rtl">&#x05DC;&#x05D9;</span>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn49"><sup>19</sup>Not &#x201C;to her&#x201D; despite the verse using the word <span dir="rtl">&#x05DC;&#x05B8;&#x05D4;&#x05BC;</span>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn50"><sup>20</sup>Not &#x201C;to his officers, to Ben Chayil&#x201D; despite the verse using the prefix <span dir="rtl">&#x05DC;</span>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn51"><sup>21</sup>This word belong with the three hebrew words in the headline, Rashi is filling the word that&#x2019;s missing from the verse, the verb &#x201C;were.&#x201D;</ftnote>
</appendix>
<appendix>
<p><bold>[[2]] Were for the son of Shaul</bold> Were for the son of Shaul similar to (Shmuel I, 13, 8) &#x201C;until the time of Shmuel&#x201D; of Shmuel.</p>
<p><bold>[[3]] And the Be&#x2019;erosites fled</bold> When Shaul died, the people of Yisroel abandoned the cities that surround the Peleshtim as is mentioned above.<sup><xref rid="fn52">1</xref></sup> It was then that the Be&#x2019;erosites fled.</p>
<p><bold>[[4]] Yohanoson, the son of Shaul had.</bold> [The verses] continue to recount how the monarchy was stripped from the house of Shaul. He and his sons were killed and this one [Ish Boshes] was killed on his bed and the son of Yohanoson fell and became lame.</p>
<p><bold>Broken feet</bold> Broken feet.</p>
<p><bold>[[6]] They came into the interior of the house.</bold> Together with the traders, the wheat buyers.</p>
<p><bold>[[10]] He thought I would reward him for his good tidings.</bold> He thought he was making me happy in order that I should reward him for his good tidings.</p>
<ftnote id="fn52"><sup>1</sup>Shmuel I, 31,7.</ftnote>
</appendix>
<appendix>
<p><bold>[[6]] To the Yevusi.</bold> The fortress of Tzion was called Yevus. [Its inhabitants] were from the descendants of Avimelech. They had two idols, one [depicting] a blind person and one [depicting] a lame person. They were made to represent Yitzhok and Yakov.<sup><xref rid="fn53">1</xref></sup> [Placed] in their mouths was the oath Avrohom swore to Avimelech,<sup><xref rid="fn54">2</xref></sup> This is why they were not displaced [from Tzion]. When Yerushalayim was conquored The tribe of Yehuda did not conquor the fortress [of Tzion], as the verse states, (Yehoshua, 15, 63). &#x201C;However the Yevusim who lived in Yerushalyim, the descendants of Yehudah were unable to expel them. [About this verse] it is learned: Rebbe Yohoshua, the son of Levi said, They had the ability to [expel the Yevusim] but they were not permitted to.<sup><xref rid="fn55">3</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>And he said to Dovid.</bold> Whoever said it,<sup><xref rid="fn56">4</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[The idols depicting] the blind and the lame</bold> These were their idols.</p>
<p><bold>[[8]] Whoever kills the Yevusi and touches [and destroys] the towers spire</bold> Whoever kills the Yevusi and has the strength to conquor the fortress.</p>
<p><bold>And [the idols of] the lame.</bold> And destroys [the idols of] the lame and the blind which were abhorrent to Dovid.</p>
<p><bold>Upon which they are saying.</bold> Upon which they are saying, &#x201C;The blind one and the lame one,&#x201D; i.e., while the blind one and the lame one are here.</p>
<p><bold>[Dovid] will not come</bold> Dovid will not come here. This is a shortened verse [because] it stated, &#x201C;Whoever kills the Yevusi and touches [and destroys] the tower&#x2019;s spire&#x201D; but [the verse] does not explain what happens to the person [who reaches the spire]. However, in Divrei Hayomim I, 11, 6) it explains, &#x201C;Whoever kills the Yevusi first will be made a chief and a prince.&#x201D; Similar to this [we find]. &#x201C;Therefore, whoever kills Kayin&#x201D; (Bereishis 4, 14) and [that verse] does not explain what happens to the person [who kills Kayin] but from its context, it&#x2019;s understood that the language conveys rebuke and anger.<sup><xref rid="fn57">5</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>And touches [and destroys] the tower&#x2019;s spire.</bold> [This word] denotes the spire of a tower because that&#x2019;s where their idols were placed. [During] the days of Dovid, the generations of the oath had already passed.<sup><xref rid="fn58">6</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[9]] From it&#x2019;s low wall and inwards.</bold> A surrounding low wall; they would fill it up with earth, the summit of the mound would be in it&#x2019;s middle, and it would slant in all directions, that is called a <span dir="rtl">&#x05DE;&#x05DC;&#x05D5;&#x05D0;</span>, and Dovid built houses on [the wall]. That low wall surrounded the fortress.</p>
<p><bold>[[12]] Dovid understood.</bold> When he saw all his endeavors succeeding, and the idol worshipping kings sending him a present.</p>
<p><bold>[[18]] Fanned out.</bold> They dispersed.</p>
<p><bold>[[20]] Into the plain of Perotzim.</bold> The plain of Perotzim</p>
<p><bold>Like water bursting over [walls].</bold> Like water bursting over the walls edge.</p>
<p><bold>[[21]] And Dovid burnt them.</bold> Dovid and his men burnt them.</p>
<p><bold>[[22]] The valley of Rephaim.</bold> It is next to Yerusholoyim [as can be seen] in the book of Yehoshua (15, 8).</p>
<p><bold>[[23]] From opposite the trees.</bold> From opposite the trees.</p>
<p><bold>[[24]] The sound of stepping on the tops of the trees.</bold> These are angels stepping on the tops of the trees that I am sending to help you.</p>
<p><bold>Then shout [war whoops].</bold> Lift up [and bring forth] the sound of war and the fear of the sword Galfer in Old French, and similarly [we find] &#x201C;A dog will not sharpen its tongue [growl].</p>
<ftnote id="fn53"><sup>1</sup>Yitzchak was blind at the end of his life (Bereshis, 27,1). Yakov was lamed during the course of his struggle with the angel (Bereishis 32,33).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn54"><sup>2</sup>Bereishis 21,23&#x2013;24.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn55"><sup>3</sup>Because of Avrohom&#x2019;s oath to Avimelech. This point is made in the Sifri, Re&#x2019;ey, Piska 72. However, there it&#x2019;s brought in the name of Rebbe Yehoshua, the son of Korcho.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn56"><sup>4</sup>The speaker is unidentified, but is obviously one of the Yevusim.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn57"><sup>5</sup>To whoever kills Kayin.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn58"><sup>6</sup>Avimelech asked Avrohom to swear &#x201C;that you will not deal falsely with me, with my son or my grandson.&#x201D; These three generations had already passed when Dovid attacked the Yevusim in the fortress of Tzion.</ftnote>
</appendix>
<appendix>
<p><bold>[[1]] Dovid again gathered.</bold> To gather.</p>
<p><bold>All the chosen men of Yisroel, thirty thousand.</bold> Because they gathered for him when they crowned him in Chevron and [therefore] this was a second gathering [for Dovid] [Scripture] herefore says, &#x201C;[Dovid] again gathered.&#x201D;</p>
<p><bold>[[2]] From Baalei Yehuda.</bold> This is [the city of] Kiryas Yearim as it is said in Yehoshua, &#x201C;and the boundary circled&#x201D; and went up &#x201C;to Baaloh, which is Kiryas Yearim&#x201D; (Yehoshua 15:9). This also [can be found] in Divrei Hayomim, &#x201C;Dovid and all Yisroel went up to Baaloh, which is Kiryas Yearim&#x201D; (Divrei Hayomim I, 13:6). [The word] Baal means a plain.</p>
<p><bold>Dovid arose and went from Baalei Yehuda.</bold> That gathered there to bring up the Ark from there&#x2026;</p>
<p><bold>Whose name is called, the name.</bold> The Ark is called a name, and what is the name? The name of Adonoy of Hosts was upon it.</p>
<p><bold>[[3]] On a new wagon.</bold> [Dovid] made a mistake about something that even children at their Rebbe&#x2019;s school know &#x201C;Because the sacred work was [incumbent] upon them, which they had to carry on their shoulders&#x201D; (Bamidbar 7:9). And because [Dovid] said, &#x201C;Your statutes were songs for me in the house of my dwelling,&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn59">1</xref></sup> (Tehilim 119:54) he was punished to come to this,<sup><xref rid="fn60">2</xref></sup> and [to have] Uzoh die through his hand. Therefore<sup><xref rid="fn61">3</xref></sup> when they brought [the Ark] from the house of Oveid they brought it by shoulder as it says (Divrei Hayomim I, 15:12), &#x201C;And he said to them, &#x2018;You, the heads of households for the Levites, you and your brothers sanctify yourselves and bring up the Ark&#x2026; because, the first time you did it not.<sup><xref rid="fn62">4</xref></sup> Hashem, Elokeinu made a breach upon us because we did not consult with Him as was proper&#x2019;.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn63">5</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[4]] With the Ark of Elokim.</bold> This is a shortened verse, [it means to say] and they were coming with the Ark of Elokim.</p>
<p><bold>[[5]] With all [instruments made of] cypress wood.</bold> Musical instruments manufactured from [cypress wood].</p>
<p><bold>[[6]] Because the ox had [made] it slip.</bold> Because the ox had [made] it slip and had shaken it And so to is Yonasan&#x2019;s translation, &#x201C;because the ox had [made] it slip,&#x201D; like [Onkelus] translates [the verse], &#x201C;and his hand slips on the axe&#x201D; [as follows:] and his hand slips on the axe.<sup><xref rid="fn64">6</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[7]] Because of his mistake.</bold> Because of his mistake, he should have expounded a fortiori [as follows:] the Ark carried its own porters in the Yardein,<sup><xref rid="fn65">7</xref></sup> isn&#x2019;t it all the more so [that it is able to carry] itself.</p>
<p><bold>[[10]] Oveid Edom.</bold> He was a Levite as it is wriiten in Divrei Hayomim (I, 15:24) and he was one of the gatekeepers.<sup><xref rid="fn66">8</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[11]] And Hashem blessed.</bold> His wife and her eight daughters-in-law each gave birth to six children in one stomach<sup><xref rid="fn67">9</xref></sup> as it is said, (Divrei Hayomim I, 26:5&#x2013;8) &#x201C;Poualti, the eigth<sup><xref rid="fn68">10</xref></sup>&#x2026; sixty-two [belonging] to Oveid Edom.<sup><xref rid="fn69">11</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[14]] Danced.</bold> Danced.</p>
<p><bold>Linen robe.</bold> A linen robe, <italic>Foursaint</italic> in O.F. Yonasan translated, robe as Yonasan also translated &#x201C;the robes of Tomor, the sister of Avsholom,&#x201D; robes (Further, 13:18)</p>
<p><bold>[[19]] A portion of meat.</bold> One sixth of a cow.</p>
<p><bold>A jug [of wine].</bold> A jug of wine.</p>
<p><bold>[[20]] One of the riff-raff.</bold> [Targum Yonasan translates:] One of the riff-raff.</p>
<p><bold>[[22]] [Had] I made light even more.</bold> Before Him [even] more then this [that] I made light of myself now.</p>
<p><bold>I would be more honoured among them.</bold> They do not ridicule me but I am important in their eyes becasue of this.</p>
<p><bold>[[23]] Had no child</bold> From that day on.<sup><xref rid="fn70">12</xref></sup></p>
<ftnote id="fn59"><sup>1</sup>Hashem said to Dovid, &#x201C;The words of the Torah upon which it is written, &#x2018;Blink your eyes [and be distracted] from it and it is gone&#x2019; (Mishlei 23:5), you are calling songs?&#x201D; (Sotah 35a). A song is of only temporary interest and then forgotten (Maharsho, ibid).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn60"><sup>2</sup>Making the mistake of transporting the Ark by wagon.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn61"><sup>3</sup>After learning from this mistake.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn62"><sup>4</sup>Transporting the Ark on your shoulders.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn63"><sup>5</sup>Consequently leading to our tragic mistake.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn64"><sup>6</sup>Substituting the hebrew word <span dir="rtl">&#x05D5;&#x05B0;&#x05E0;&#x05B4;&#x05D3;&#x05B0;&#x05BC;&#x05D7;&#x05B8;&#x05D4;</span> with the Amaraic translation, <span dir="rtl">&#x05D5;&#x05B0;&#x05EA;&#x05B4;&#x05EA;&#x05B0;&#x05DE;&#x05B0;&#x05E8;&#x05B4;&#x05D9;&#x05D2;</span> denoting slipping just like he uses the same Amaraic word in our verse, i.e., <span dir="rtl">&#x05DE;&#x05B0;&#x05E8;&#x05B8;&#x05D2;&#x05D5;&#x05BC;&#x05D4;&#x05B4;&#x05D9;</span>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn65"><sup>7</sup>When Bnei Yisroel crossed the Yardein into the land of Yisroel as stated in Yehoshua 4:11 and explained in Sotah, ibid.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn66"><sup>8</sup>Of the Bais HaMikdosh.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn67"><sup>9</sup>Pregnancy.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn68"><sup>10</sup>Child of Oveid Edom.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn69"><sup>11</sup>See Berachos 63b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn70"><sup>12</sup>Prior to that day, she did have a child, Yisroam mentioned earlier (Shmuel II, 3:5), see Rashi there.</ftnote>
</appendix>
<appendix>
<p><bold>[[1]] And Hashem granted him rest.</bold> [Dovid] said [The condition] has been fulfilled, &#x201C;And He has granted you peace from all your enemies etc.&#x201D; (Devarim 12:10). What is written after [that verse]? &#x201C;Let it be that the place that [Hashem, your Elokim] chooses etc.&#x201D; It is now [incumbent] upon us to build the Chosen House.</p>
<p><bold>[[4]] And it was on that night.</bold> Rebbe Chanina, the son of Popoh said the Holy One blessed be He said to Nosson, &#x201C;The man I am sending you to is a quick one, he may hire workers and it will turn out that I [cause] him loss.<sup><xref rid="fn71">1</xref></sup> Hurry and tell him, &#x2018;It is not you who will build the Temple&#x2019;.&#x201D; Rebbe Simon says<sup><xref rid="fn72">2</xref></sup> &#x201C;The man I am sending you to is a vow maker&#x201D; as it is said,<sup><xref rid="fn73">3</xref></sup> &#x201C;Who has sworn to Adonoy, vowed to the Mighty One of Yakov Surely I will not enter the shelter of my house&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn74">4</xref></sup> (Tehilim 132 2&#x2013;3) &#x201C;he may say, &#x2018;I will not eat, I will not drink until I do this&#x2019;<sup><xref rid="fn75">5</xref></sup> and it will turn out that I [cause] him loss.<sup><xref rid="fn76">6</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[6]] Within a tent and the Mishkan.</bold> The Mishkan of Shiloh had no roof, it had walls made of stone underneath and curtains on top [as its covering].</p>
<p><bold>[[7]] Have I said a word.</bold> This language [conveys] astonishment, that&#x2019;s why its punctuation has the Hei with a Kometz, and the Daled is soft [with a Dogesh].</p>
<p><bold>[[8]] From the corral.</bold> The corral [used by] sheperds as [can be found], &#x201C;the dugout dwelling of sheperds.&#x201D; (Zfsaphania, 2:6).</p>
<p><bold>[[9]] Like the name of great people.</bold> That is what is said [about Dovid] the shield of Dovid.<sup><xref rid="fn77">7</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>I will destroy all your enemies.</bold> And that is why [the thought] came to your heart to build the House as it is written in the Torah.<sup><xref rid="fn78">8</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[10]] I will make a place.</bold> I still want to quiet [things] that my people [should have] quiet and tranquility during the days of your son[&#x2019;s reign].</p>
<p><bold>[[11]] And from that day that I commanded.</bold> It is connected to what preceded it, they will no longer afflict [the people] as before, i.e., before the [days of the] Judges. And as they [also] did from the days of the Judges until now.</p>
<p><bold>I will give you respite.</bold> More and more until you have respite from all your enemies.</p>
<p><bold>Adonoy is telling you.</bold> Today, through me [Noson], that He will establish a monarchy for you to have your son [Shlomo] sit on your throne and he will secure the monarchy for you. And it is he [Shlomo] that will build the House</p>
<p><bold>[[14]] With the rod of men.</bold> This refers to Haddad and Rozon, the son of Elyodoh.<sup><xref rid="fn79">9</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>And with the afflictions of people.</bold> This refers to Ashmedoy who dethroned him.<sup><xref rid="fn80">10</xref></sup> The demons are the children of Odom Horishon<sup><xref rid="fn81">11</xref></sup> because the entire one hundred and thirty years that Odom [stayed] separated from his wife after Hevel&#x2019;s death,<sup><xref rid="fn82">12</xref></sup> the spirits would become heated [pregnant] and give birth from him.</p>
<p><bold>[[18]] And sat before the Ark of Adonoy.</bold> Before the Ark.</p>
<p><bold>Until this point.</bold> That You have made me king.</p>
<p><bold>[[19]] Also, about the house of your servant.</bold> To have my son reign after me.</p>
<p><bold>Is this anouncent [fitting] for [mere] man?</bold> A wonderment. Is it fitting to announce such to [mere] flesh and blood<sup><xref rid="fn83">13</xref></sup> Another explanation: You have done for me as you did for Odom Horishon<sup><xref rid="fn84">14</xref></sup> that you had shown him the future generations that were to come from him.</p>
<p><bold>[[20]] What more can Dovid say to You.</bold> What more can I ask for?</p>
<p><bold>You know Your servant.</bold> You have supplied me with all my needs as [it says] (Mishlei 12:10) &#x201C;A righteous man knows his animal&#x2019;s being.<sup><xref rid="fn85">15</xref></sup>&#x201D;</p>
<p><bold>[[21]] Because of Your word.</bold> To fulfill that which You told Shmuel to make me king.</p>
<p><bold>And due to [the will of] Your Heart.</bold> It is Your will [that I become king] and not because I am worthy.</p>
<p><bold>Of which You have informed Your servant.</bold> The announcement of which You have informed me.<sup><xref rid="fn86">16</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[23]] For whom leaders went.</bold> Moshe and Aharon as it is said, (Shemos 7:1). &#x201C;I have made you a judge over Pharaoh&#x201D; and so too did Yonasan translate, &#x201C;messengers went from before Hashem.&#x201D;</p>
<p><bold>To redeem for Him a people.</bold> This is what the messengers said to Yisroel, The Holy One, blessed is he sent us to redeem for Him a people, to put forth His Name and to make great [things happen] for you.</p>
<p><bold>Awesome things</bold> You have done for your land after [Bnei Yisroel] left there [i.e., Egypt]. And what are the awesome things? From before Your people You expelled nations and their gods. This verse is missing [the word] &#x201C;<span dir="rtl">&#x05DC;&#x05D2;&#x05E8;&#x05E9;</span>&#x201D;, [however] in Divrei Hayomim (I 17:21) it explains, &#x201C;To expel from before Your people that You redeemed from Egypt, nations and their gods.&#x201D; [Our verse] isn&#x2019;t [really] missing [this word] because from the sense conveyed as it is said, &#x201C;From before Your people, nations&#x201D; we understand that it means pushed and driven out.</p>
<p><bold>[[28]] You are the Elokim.</bold> The ruler. The ability to fulfill [this promise] is in Your Hand.</p>
<p><bold>[[29]] Desire.</bold> Desire.</p>
<ftnote id="fn71"><sup>1</sup>Because it is premature to build the Bein Hamikdash at this time.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn72"><sup>2</sup>That Hashem said to Noson.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn73"><sup>3</sup>Dovid about himself.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn74"><sup>4</sup>Rashi explains in Tehilim, verse 5 that Dovid meant he will not go into his house until he finds out in which location the Beis Hamikdosh is slated to be built.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn75"><sup>5</sup>i.e. build the Beis Hamikdash.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn76"><sup>6</sup>Slightly different versions of the opinions of Rebbe Chanina and Rebbe Simon can be found in Yalkut Shimoni, Shmuel II, 143.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn77"><sup>7</sup>Pesachim 117b. The &#x201C;great people&#x201D; referred to here are Avrohom, Yitzhok and Yakov. Just as they are mentioned in the first blessing of the Amidah, so too Dovid&#x2019;s name is used in the ending of one of the Haftorah&#x2019;s concluding blessings. (Rashi, ibid).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn78"><sup>8</sup>Devarim 12:10. See Rashi on verse 1.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn79"><sup>9</sup>Both were enemies of Shlomo, they are mentioned in Kings I, 11:14 and 23 respectively.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn80"><sup>10</sup>Gittin 68b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn81"><sup>11</sup>See Yalkut Shimoni 146. The word <span dir="rtl">&#x05D0;&#x05B8;&#x05D3;&#x05B8;&#x05DD;</span> in the verse is taken as a reference to Odom Horishon.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn82"><sup>12</sup>Rashi in Bereishis 4:25 says that the Odom&#x2019;s separation was due to the fact that he had brought death, to the world. The Yalkut Shimoni does not mention why the separation occurred. In addition the Yalkut Shimoni tells as that it was Chava who separated herself from Odom.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn83"><sup>13</sup>To be informed of the future.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn84"><sup>14</sup>According to this interpretation, the word <span dir="rtl">&#x05D0;&#x05B8;&#x05D3;&#x05B8;&#x05DD;</span> in the verse is a reference to <span dir="rtl">&#x05D0;&#x05B8;&#x05D3;&#x05B8;&#x05DD; &#x05D4;&#x05B8;&#x05E8;&#x05B4;&#x05D0;&#x05E9;&#x05C1;&#x05D5;&#x05B9;&#x05DF;</span>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn85"><sup>15</sup>The verse refers to a righteous person but Rashi is drawing an analogy to Hashem&#x2019;s knowing the needs of his servants.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn86"><sup>16</sup>That my kingdom will be everlasting.</ftnote>
</appendix>
<appendix>
<p><bold>[[1]] Meseg Hoamoh.</bold> In Divrei Hayomim (I, 18:1) it&#x2019;s written, &#x201C;Dovid took Goss from the hand of the Pelishtim.&#x201D; [Goss] is called Meseg Hoamoh because she was the stick that dominated all the Pelishtim. It was the king&#x2019;s metropolis because we do not find [associated with] any of the Pelishtim rulers [not] with Azoh, Ashdod, Akron [nor] Ashkelon,<sup><xref rid="fn87">1</xref></sup> a royal title. Only in reference Goss do we find [a royal title], &#x201C;Akish, the king of Goss.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn88">2</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>Meseg.</bold>&#160;<italic>Avillon</italic> in O.F.</p>
<p><bold>Hoamoh.</bold> This is the harness made of wood.<sup><xref rid="fn89">3</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[2]] Those measured with two ropes were killed.</bold> [This vengeance was] because they killed his father, his mother and his brothers as it is said, &#x201C;He led them before the king of Moav.&#x201D; (Shmuel I, 22:4) We do not find that they ever left from there.<sup><xref rid="fn90">4</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[3]] As he went.</bold> When Haddadezer was going</p>
<p><bold>To enlarge his border.</bold> As [Yonasan] translates, &#x201C;To widen his border,&#x201D; [Haddadezer] conquored land outside his countries border and widened his border.</p>
<p><bold>[[4]] Dovid destroyed all the chariot [horses].</bold> Because [of the verse], &#x201C;He must not acquire an abundance of horses for himself&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn91">5</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[With] one hundred chariot [horses] remaining.</bold> That he required for his riding entourage. [The word] chariot [refers to] four horses as it is said, (Divrei Hayomim II, 1:17) &#x201C;Chariot for six hundred silver pieces and horses for one hundred and fifty.&#x201D; From here we learn that a chariot refers to four horses.<sup><xref rid="fn92">6</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[7]] The golden quivers.</bold> They are the quivers in which the arrows are put as you say, (Yirmeyah 51:11). &#x201C;clean out the arrows, till the quivers.&#x201D; All these chapters<sup><xref rid="fn93">7</xref></sup> have been set near the chapter concerning the Beis Hamikdash<sup><xref rid="fn94">8</xref></sup> because from all these wars [Dovid] gathered consecrated items for the needs of the House [i.e., Beis Hamikdash].</p>
<p><bold>[[13]] Dovid made a name [for himself].</bold> He buried those of Edom whom he had killed and that is a good name for Yisroel that they bury their enemies. As it says in reference to the war of Gog and Mogog, &#x201C;All the people of the land will bury and this will acquire for them a name.&#x201D; (Yechezkel 39:13) And how do we know that Dovid buried them? Because it says in the Book of kings (I, 11:15), &#x201C;And it happened when Dovid was in Edom when Yoav, his army general went up to bury the corpses.&#x201D;</p>
<p><bold>Eighteen thousand.</bold> [However] in the Book of Tehilim (60:2) it says, &#x201C;twelve thousand&#x201D; Hence we must say [in response] that there were two battles.<sup><xref rid="fn95">9</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[14]] Officers.</bold> Officers to collect the tax.</p>
<p><bold>[[15]] Dovid rendered judgement&#x2026; Yoav&#x2026;was [commander] over the army.</bold> Dovid caused Yoav to be successful [with his command] over the army because he rendered judgment and righteousness and Yoav caused Dovid to render judgment and righteousness because he [Dovid] judged and Yoav policed and enforced on the basis [of the judgment].<sup><xref rid="fn96">10</xref></sup> Another [reason is that] because Yoav busied himself with the battles, Dovid was not preoccupied by them and his heart was [able to be] open to judge righteously.</p>
<p><bold>[[16]] Recorder [of halachic cases].</bold> [He] announced which [case] was to come before him [Dovid] first for it to be ruled on first.</p>
<p><bold>[[18]] Venoyohaa, the son of Yehoyodoh</bold> [was in charge of] the archers and the sling shooters. Yonasan translated, &#x201C;Venoyoha, the son of Yehoydoh was appointed [in charge] over the archers and over the sling shooters.&#x201D; [Alternatively] our Rabbis said [that the words] keraisi and plaisi refer to the Urim and Tumim.<sup><xref rid="fn97">11</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>Were prominent [leaders].</bold> [Yonasan translates] &#x201C;They were prominent.&#x201D;</p>
<ftnote id="fn87"><sup>1</sup>This a reference to the Pelishtim rulers enumerated in Yehoshua 13:3. Rashi has left out the Avites, because he relies on Rav&#x2019;s opinion in Chulin 60b that Avites were from Teimon and not from the Philistine people.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn88"><sup>2</sup>Shmuel I, 20:11.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn89"><sup>3</sup><span dir="rtl">&#x05DE;&#x05B6;&#x05EA;&#x05B6;&#x05D2;</span> means the reins. These are references to the control this city had over the Pelishtim.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn90"><sup>4</sup>Yalkut Shimoni, 147.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn91"><sup>5</sup>One of the prohibitions specific to the kings of Yisroel. (See Devorim 17:16)</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn92"><sup>6</sup>Given that a <span dir="rtl">&#x05DE;&#x05B6;&#x05E8;&#x05B0;&#x05DB;&#x05B8;&#x05BC;&#x05D1;&#x05B8;&#x05D4;</span> fetched six hundred silver pieces, four times the one hundred and fifty cost of one horse.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn93"><sup>7</sup>Concerning Dovid&#x2019;s battles.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn94"><sup>8</sup>Dovid&#x2019;s desire to build a Beis Hamikdash for Hashem in the previous chapter (7:2) and Hashem&#x2019;s subsequent response.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn95"><sup>9</sup>With Edom. Tanchuma Devorim.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn96"><sup>10</sup>Rashi is learning that the proximity of the verse discussing Dovid&#x2019;s judgment of the people to the next verse discussing Yoav&#x2019;s commanding of the army shows that these two phenomena were related. Other prominent leaders are being discussed in the subsequent verses but Yoav is mentioned first immediately after king Dovid.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn97"><sup>11</sup>Rashi explains in Shemos 28:30 that this is a reference to the inscription of the Explicit Name which was placed into the folds of the breastplate. Through the breastplate, they would communicate the answers of Hashem to questions the Kohein asked of Him, hence they would (<span dir="rtl">&#x05DE;&#x05B5;&#x05D0;&#x05B4;&#x05D9;&#x05E8;</span>), light up and explain their words and <span dir="rtl">&#x05D5;&#x05BC;&#x05DE;&#x05B0;&#x05EA;&#x05BC;&#x05B7;&#x05DE;&#x05BC;&#x05B5;&#x05DD;</span>) complete their words, i.e. make words come true. (Yoma 73b). This explanation of our Rabbis concerning the translation of keraisi and plaisi can be found in Berachos 4a.</ftnote>
</appendix>
<appendix>
<p><bold>[[9]] I have given to the son of your master.</bold> The king is permitted to transfer an estate<sup><xref rid="fn98">1</xref></sup> as it is said (Shmuel I, 8:14) Within the jurisdiction of the monarchy is [the power] to take their fields and their vineyards and to give it to his servants.</p>
<p><bold>[[11]] So will your servant do.</bold> Mephivoshes will eat at my table. Tsivoh said, &#x201C;So will your servant do.&#x201D; And Dovid responded, &#x201C;Mephivoshes will eat at my table.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn99">2</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[12]] Those who dwelled in the house of Tsivoh.</bold> His children and his slaves.<sup><xref rid="fn100">3</xref></sup></p>
<ftnote id="fn98"><sup>1</sup>From its previous rightful owner to another person of his choice. This is Rebbe Yosi&#x2019;s view in Sanhedrin 20b that those royal powers spoken of in Shmuel are to be taken literally as belonging to the king and not just a means of frightening the people into respecting the king which is Rebbe Yehudi&#x2019;s view there in Sanhedrin, (See also Tosfos, ibid).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn99"><sup>2</sup>The verse contains the words of two separate speakers, Tzivoh is speaking in the first part of the verse and Dovid responds in the second part.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn100"><sup>3</sup>Mentioned in verse 10.</ftnote>
</appendix>
<appendix>
<p><bold>[[2]] As his father acted with kindness towards me.</bold> And what was the kindness? When Dovid was fleeing because of Shaul, his father, mother and brothers came to [join] him. &#x201C;Dovid led them before the king of Moav&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn101">1</xref></sup> [Dovid] said to him, &#x201C;Please, [let] my father and mother dwell with you.&#x201D; [The king of Moav] killed them [all] except for one of them [i.e., the brothers] who fled and escaped to the land of the people of Amon, to Nochosh. This is a Midrash Rebbe Tanchuma in [Parshas] Vayeiroh ailov.</p>
<p><bold>[[3]] Do you think Dovid honors your father.</bold> Does it appear in your eyes that Dovid is honoring your father? They are warned, &#x201C;Do not seek peace with them&#x201D;,<sup><xref rid="fn102">2</xref></sup> and he is seeking peace with you?</p>
<p><bold>[[4]] Their clothes.</bold> Their robes.</p>
<p><bold>Their buttocks.</bold> The buttocks.</p>
<p><bold>[[16]] Shovach the commander of Hadarezer&#x2019;s aray.</bold> Because he was very mighty and powerful, he is mentioned by name.</p>
<ftnote id="fn101"><sup>1</sup>Shmuel I, 22:4.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn102"><sup>2</sup>Devorim 23:7. This verse is referring to Amon and Moav mentioned earlier in verse 4.</ftnote>
</appendix>
<appendix>
<p><bold>[[1]] At the time [of year] when kings go forth.</bold> There is a time of year when it is the practice that troops go forth, when the land is full of growth and the horses find produce in the field to eat.</p>
<p><bold>[[4]] From her uncleanliness.</bold> From her menstrual impurity.</p>
<p><bold>[[6]] Send me Urioh.</bold> [Dovid] intendead that he [Urioh] lie with his wife in order that it be thought that from him [Urioh] she was pregnant.</p>
<p><bold>[[8]] The king&#x2019;s meal.</bold> [Yonasan translates:] the king&#x2019;s meal.<sup><xref rid="fn103">1</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[15]] And he will be struck and killed.</bold> In order for [Batsheva] to be divorced [from Urioh] retroactively. the result would be that [Dovid] did not cohabit with a married woman. Because all [soldiers] who went out to war wrote a conditional divorce document for their wife should they die in battle.<sup><xref rid="fn104">2</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[21]] The son of Yerubeshes.</bold> This is Gidon who fought with Boshes, which is the Baal.<sup><xref rid="fn105">3</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[25]] Intensity your war [against] the city and destroy it.</bold> The words of the message<sup><xref rid="fn106">4</xref></sup> [end] at this point.</p>
<p><bold>You should encourage him [Yoav].</bold> Dovid [then] said to the messenger, &#x201C;Encourage Yoav with consoling words so that his heart should not weaken.</p>
<ftnote id="fn103"><sup>1</sup>Dovid sent men with provisions for Urioh to be eaten at his home.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn104"><sup>2</sup>Rashi in Kesubos 9b gives this same explanation. Tosafos there explains that Rashi means that the condition was not necessarily that the soldier dies, but even if he does not return at the end of the war, the divorce would be valid.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn105"><sup>3</sup>See Shoftim 6:32. The name <span dir="rtl">&#x05D9;&#x05B0;&#x05E8;&#x05BB;&#x05D1;&#x05B6;&#x05BC;&#x05E9;&#x05C1;&#x05B6;&#x05EA;</span> is a contraction of the two words, <span dir="rtl">&#x05D9;&#x05B8;&#x05E8;&#x05B6;&#x05D1;</span> and <span dir="rtl">&#x05D1;&#x05B8;&#x05E9;&#x05B6;&#x05EA;</span>, fighting with Boshes. Avimelech&#x2019;s death, referred to here, is related in Shoftim 9:53.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn106"><sup>4</sup>From Dovid to Yoav.</ftnote>
</appendix>
<appendix>
<p><bold>[[4]] A traveler came.</bold> [Noson] compared the evil inclination at first to a sojourner that is [quickly] going on his way. Afterwords he is compared to a guest that has become a resident and afterwords he is compared to a man who is the owner of the house.<sup><xref rid="fn107">1</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>Is worthy of death.</bold> Someone who steals from a poor person is tantamount to taking his life<sup><xref rid="fn108">2</xref></sup> as it is said, &#x201C;He has taken it&#x2019;s owner&#x2019;s life.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn109">3</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[6]] Pay fourfold.</bold> This is what [eventually] happened, he was punished with [problems concerning] four children the child<sup><xref rid="fn110">4</xref></sup> and Amnon Tomor and Avsholom.<sup><xref rid="fn111">5</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[8]] Your master&#x2019;s woman.</bold> Michal, the daughter of Shaul.</p>
<p><bold>I will add on.</bold> I would add on for you.</p>
<p><bold>[[14]] Because you have angered the enemies of Adonoy.</bold> This is a euphimism a way [to be] respectable to on High.<sup><xref rid="fn112">6</xref></sup> Yonasan translated, Because you have opened up you have opened the mouth of [those] who hate the people of God.</p>
<p><bold>[He became sick.]</bold> [This word] denotes sickness.</p>
<p><bold>[[16]] And came to repose and lied on the ground.</bold> And came [back] to the house and reposed at night lying on the ground.</p>
<p><bold>[[17]] And he did not eat.</bold> [A word] denoting eating like [we find], &#x201C;I will eat from her hand.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn113">7</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[25]] Because of God.</bold> That loved him [Shlomo].<sup><xref rid="fn114">8</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[26]] The royal city.</bold> There were two enforced walls [of cities] in it, an outside one and an inside one. The outside city was [called] the royal city, and the inside [city] was a fortress and stronghold.<sup><xref rid="fn115">9</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[30]] The crown of Malkom.</bold> The abomination [idol] of the people of Ammon&#x2019;s name was Malkom. Denoting [the word] Moleich.<sup><xref rid="fn116">10</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>It was [hung over] Dovid&#x2019;s head.</bold> Itai the Gitite annulled it.<sup><xref rid="fn117">11</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[31]] Saw-like utensils, iron threshing utensils and iron axes.</bold> They are types of tortures.</p>
<p><bold>Saw-like utensils.</bold> A knife serrated with many [sharp] edges bent towards each other.</p>
<p><bold>Threshing utensils.</bold> This is a hacked saw full of cuts like &#x201C;many sharp edges&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn118">12</xref></sup> that is called laime (O.F.).</p>
<p><bold>The streets.</bold> In the mud of the streets and so Yonason [also] translated: &#x201C;He dragged them in the streets.&#x201D;</p>
<ftnote id="fn107"><sup>1</sup>This verse is Noson&#x2019;s parable alluding to the evil inclination. The visiton is first referred to as <span dir="rtl">&#x05D4;&#x05B5;&#x05DC;&#x05B6;&#x05DA;&#x05B0;</span>, then <span dir="rtl">&#x05D0;&#x05C2;&#x05E8;&#x05B5;&#x05D7;&#x05B7;</span> and finally as an <span dir="rtl">&#x05D0;&#x05B4;&#x05D9;&#x05E9;&#x05C1;</span>, representing the evil inclination&#x2019;s ability to take more and more control over its victim&#x2019;s life.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn108"><sup>2</sup>See Baba Kama 119a. Stealing a pruta from anyone is tantamount to killing him.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn109"><sup>3</sup>Mishlei 1:19.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn110"><sup>4</sup>Related further on in verse 15.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn111"><sup>5</sup>The events with Amnon, Tomor and Avsholom start in chapter 13.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn112"><sup>6</sup>Using &#x201C;enemies of God&#x201D; to stand in for God in order for the word &#x201C;angered&#x201D; not to have to be applied to Him in a direct way.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn113"><sup>7</sup>Later, 13:6.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn114"><sup>8</sup><span dir="rtl">&#x05D9;&#x05BD;&#x05D3;&#x05B4;&#x05D9;&#x05D3;&#x05B0;&#x05D9;&#x05B8;&#x05D4;</span> is a concatanation of <span dir="rtl">&#x05D9;&#x05BD;&#x05D3;&#x05B4;&#x05D9;&#x05D3;</span>, beloved one and <span dir="rtl">&#x05D9;&#x05B8;&#x05D4;</span>, God.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn115"><sup>9</sup>Yoav left this one for Dovid to conquer as is stated in verse 29.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn116"><sup>10</sup><span dir="rtl">&#x05DE;&#x05D5;&#x05B9;&#x05DC;&#x05B6;&#x05DA;&#x05B0;</span> is an idol to whom children were sacrificed.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn117"><sup>11</sup>This explanation of the verse is stated in Avodah Zoroh 24. It is prohibited for Jews to derive any pleasure from the idols of gentiles. They must be anulled by a gentile, i.e., taken out of the service of idol worship, after which they are permitted to Jews. Itai the Gitite, a gentile, did this to Malkom for Dovid&#x2019;s sake.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn118"><sup>12</sup>Shmuel I, 13:21.</ftnote>
</appendix>
<appendix>
<p><bold>[[1]] Avsholom had a pretty sister.</bold> That was the daughter of his mother.</p>
<p><bold>[[2]] To [the point of] sickness.</bold> Until he became sick.</p>
<p><bold>Because she was a virgin.</bold> She was modest [and stayed] in the house and did not go outside therefore,</p>
<p><bold>&#x201C;It was hidden from the eyes of Amnon&#x2026;</bold> It was covered and hidden from him. What excuse he could seek [in order] to lay with her.<sup><xref rid="fn119">1</xref></sup> Similar to &#x201C;When it is concealed from you&#x201D;,<sup><xref rid="fn120">2</xref></sup> [which] Onkelus translates: &#x201C;When it is hidden from you.&#x201D;</p>
<p><bold>[[3]] Smart man.</bold> For wickedness.</p>
<p><bold>[[4]] Weak.</bold> Weak as [we find] &#x201C;weak and bad [in] appearance&#x201D;.<sup><xref rid="fn121">3</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[5]] The meal.</bold> The meal.</p>
<p><bold>[[8]] She made a paste.</bold> She made a paste of flour mixed [it] first into boiling water and afterwords in oil.</p>
<p><bold>[[9]] The pan.</bold> The [Onkelus&#x2019;] translation of Machues is &#x201C;pan&#x201D;.<sup><xref rid="fn122">4</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[13]] Because he will not keep me from you.</bold> I am permitted to you because my mother became pregnant with me when she was still a gentile, pretty woman<sup><xref rid="fn123">5</xref></sup> that Dovid took conjugally in war. And someone who has a son or daughter from a gentile handmaid is not considered his child for any legal matter.</p>
<p><bold>[[15]] Amnon hated her.</bold> Our Rabbis say she tied a hair for him [in his genital area] and caused him to have a severed organ.<sup><xref rid="fn124">6</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[16]] Do not do this thing.</bold> Do not do this evil thing of sending [me] away which is worse then the other [evil thing] that you did to me. You raped me and then you added on more evil than that by sending me away.</p>
<p><bold>[[23]] The were shearing.</bold> It was there custom to make a party when they sheared their flocks.</p>
<p><bold>[[26]] Will not come with us.</bold> If you can not go, let Amnon go with us.</p>
<p><bold>[[32]] This has been Avsholom&#x2019;s order.</bold> By Avsholom&#x2019;s command was this order bestowed on his servants to kill Amnon.</p>
<p><bold>[[39]] Dovid desired.</bold> This is a shortened verse, [it means to say:] &#x201C;Dovid&#x2019;s soul desired.&#x201D; Yonoson also translates [this way:] &#x201C;Dovid&#x2019;s soul desired,&#x201D; as [we find:] &#x201C;[My Soul] yearns, and even pines.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn125">7</xref></sup> Language [denoting] desire.</p>
<p><bold>Because he was consoled concerning Amnon.</bold> He accepted [words of] consolation.</p>
<ftnote id="fn119"><sup>1</sup>According to Rashi, the words in our verse, &#x201C;because she was a virgin&#x201D; do not tell us why Amnon was desirous of her. The reason for his desire was because she was pretty. Rashi consequently explains that these words are telling us why she was inaccessible to Amnon and are connected to the words that follow, &#x201C;it was hidden in the eyes of Amnon&#x201D; to find a way to lay with her.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn120"><sup>2</sup>Devorim 17:8.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn121"><sup>3</sup>Bereishis 41:19.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn122"><sup>4</sup>Vayikro 6:14.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn123"><sup>5</sup>The laws concerning the taking of gentile woman during war is discused in Devorim begginning in 21:10. The Torah calls her a <span dir="rtl">&#x05D9;&#x05B0;&#x05E4;&#x05B7;&#x05EA; &#x05EA;&#x05BC;&#x05D5;&#x05B9;&#x05D0;&#x05B7;&#x05E8;</span>, &#x201C;pretty woman.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn124"><sup>6</sup>One who is so injured is prohibited from marrying a Jewish woman as related in Devorim 23:2. This interpretation of our verse is in Sanhedrin 21a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn125"><sup>7</sup>Tehilim 84:3.</ftnote>
</appendix>
<appendix>
<p><bold>[[2]] Yoav sent to Tekuah.</bold> Our Rabbis said Because olive oil is found there, therefore wisdom is found there.<sup><xref rid="fn126">1</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[5]] In truth, I am a widowed woman.</bold>&#160;<span dir="rtl">&#x05D0;&#x05B2;&#x05D1;&#x05B8;&#x05DC;</span> means &#x201C;In truth.&#x201D;</p>
<p><bold>[[9]] My master the king, the sin is upon me.</bold> This is euphemistic for [the sake of] his honour in other words, &#x201C;You are rebutting me [by] saying, &#x2018;I will command [someone] concerning you,&#x2019; I will [then] go on my way and you will not command [anyone] concerning me, and my son will get murdered. Upon who is this sin?&#x201D;</p>
<p><bold>[[11]] Please remember Adonoy.</bold> God was stringent concerning the distance [necessary] to save lives<sup><xref rid="fn127">2</xref></sup> as it is said, &#x201C;He will overtake him because the way was long&#x201D;.<sup><xref rid="fn128">3</xref></sup> This is [her reference with], &#x201C;To avoid giving more [time] for the avenger to destroy,&#x201D; and you are pushing me [away].</p>
<p><bold>[[13]] Why did you think this.</bold> You suspected that a Jew could come to kill another [Jew] without witnesses and a warning.</p>
<p><bold>That which the king said he himself is guilty of.</bold> This thing that you have decided for others, that you said to me &#x201C;hair from your son shall not fall to the ground.&#x201D; Now that I have revealed to you that this thing never happened, but it was only [a parable] to your two sons, do not reverse yourself saying, &#x201C;I said this mistakingly and I have reconsidered&#x201D; in order that the king not bring back his son, Avsholom that his been exiled from him and has fled.</p>
<p><bold>The king will say.</bold>&#160;<italic>Aucenon parleter</italic> in O.F.</p>
<p><bold>[[14]] We are [all] going to die.</bold> And that punishment is sufficent.<sup><xref rid="fn129">4</xref></sup> God will not countenance anyone. a man from [avoiding] death. Therefore the king should devise means to avoid having his exiled one remain an outcast.</p>
<p><bold>[[15]] And now I came to speak to my master, the king these words.</bold> As a parable about myself and my son</p>
<p><bold>Because the people frightened me.</bold> They frightened me [away] from imploring my master concerning [the plight of] his son lest he become angry with me.</p>
<p><bold>Your handmaiden said, &#x201C;I will speak.&#x201D;</bold> In this way [with a parable], perhaps he will take action etc.</p>
<p><bold>[[16]] When the king hears</bold> [and agrees] to save his handmaiden from the [avenger] man&#x2019;s hand. who is coming to kill my son and to remove us both from the inheritance [given by] God.<sup><xref rid="fn130">5</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[17]] Your handmaiden says.</bold> Now that the king has ordered [remedial action] concerning me, his word should provide relief for my son because he will not back away from his kind decision<sup><xref rid="fn131">6</xref></sup> because my master, the king is like an angel of God and anger and hatred will not change his kind decision.</p>
<p><bold>[[19]] It is impossible.</bold> [This is] like &#x201C;if it is possible&#x201D; or like &#x201C;is it possible&#x201D; So too [we find] &#x201C;Is there in the house of a wicked person&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn132">7</xref></sup> meaning &#x201C;is there&#x201D;.<sup><xref rid="fn133">8</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[20]] In order to skirt around.</bold> To skirt around [the issue] until the matter concerning the king&#x2019;s son comes to light.</p>
<p><bold>[But] my master is wise.</bold> and you understood that this is coming from Yoav.</p>
<p><bold>[[30]] Which is near me.</bold> Near my domain in a place where I can inflict damage.</p>
<p><bold>Which is near me.</bold> En mains aussi in O.F.</p>
<p><bold>[[32]] [Then] kill me.</bold> The king should kill me.</p>
<ftnote id="fn126"><sup>1</sup>Menochos 85a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn127"><sup>2</sup>When a person kills accidently, he must go to a city of refuge. These cities should never be too distant from any potential fugitive who may need to go there.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn128"><sup>3</sup>Devorim 19:5.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn129"><sup>4</sup>For Avsholom.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn130"><sup>5</sup>All this is what the woman was conveying in her parable. This was all designed to be tolerable for the king to hear.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn131"><sup>6</sup>You came to the kind decision to provide relief to my make believe son in the parable. Please don&#x2019;t change that decision when deliberating about Avsholom who in real-life needs relief.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn132"><sup>7</sup>Micha 6:10.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn133"><sup>8</sup><span dir="rtl">&#x05D4;&#x05B8;&#x05D0;&#x05B4;&#x05E9;</span> is standing in for <span dir="rtl">&#x05D4;&#x05B2;&#x05D9;&#x05B5;&#x05E9;&#x05C1;</span> which means &#x201C;is there&#x201D;.</ftnote>
</appendix>
<appendix>
<p><bold>[[1]] And [an enfourage of] fifty men etc.</bold> All of them had their thighs removed and the heals of their feet cut out.<sup><xref rid="fn134">1</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[2]] Avsholom rose early.</bold> Every morning.</p>
<p><bold>From one of the tribes of Yisroel.</bold> From so and so tribe.</p>
<p><bold>[[4]] And I will judge him righteously.</bold> [Targum Yonosan translates:] &#x201C;And I will judge him truthfully.&#x201D;</p>
<p><bold>[[7]] At the end of forty years.</bold> [After] Yisroel had asked Shmuel for a king this rebellion and weakening of the kingdom occurred.<sup><xref rid="fn135">2</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>I would like to go.</bold> To Chevron.</p>
<p><bold>And fulfill the vows [of bringing sacrifices]</bold> Our Rabbis said, &#x201C;[Avsholom wanted] to bring lambs from Chevron<sup><xref rid="fn136">3</xref></sup> because there, the lambs were fat.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn137">4</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[11]] Invited and leaving in innovence.</bold> It is explained in the Yerushalmi tractate of Sotah<sup><xref rid="fn138">5</xref></sup> that he [Avsholom] requested of his father that he [Dovid] write [a document] for him that any two people that he request go with him, should go. He [proceeded] to show it [the document] to two people here and afterwords to two other people and in this way to many.<sup><xref rid="fn139">6</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[17]] Far away.</bold> [Targum Yonasan translates:] &#x201C;in a far away place.&#x201D;</p>
<p><bold>[[18]] By him.</bold> Near him, He stood in place and they passed by.</p>
<p><bold>[[19]] With the king.</bold> With Avsholom.</p>
<p><bold>Because you are a foreigner.</bold> We are fleeing without provisions and food, and because you are a foreigner you will not find people that will have pity on you.</p>
<p><bold>And even if you are estranged [from Avsholom].</bold> And even if you are exiled from the king [Avsholom] because you do not want to be with him, then return to your home because it is not good to go with me because you [just] came yesterday.<sup><xref rid="fn140">7</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[20]] And should I today cause you to move with us.</bold> I have no place that I can settle you there to escape because I am going to where circumstances have me go each day. When I hear that the pursuers are here I flee here. And so Yonasan translates [the verse], &#x201C;And if you are estranged [from Avsholom] you can go home&#x201D; [as:] &#x201C;And if you you are estranged go [back] to your city.&#x201D;</p>
<p><bold>I will consider it kindness and truth.</bold> I will credit you the favor of kindness and truth that you have done for me.</p>
<p><bold>[[22]] &#x201C;Go and pass&#x201D;</bold> Together with the rest of the people now that you do not want to part from me.</p>
<p><bold>[[23]] And all the people were passing.</bold> From the king and onwards according to his location they are called passers by.<sup><xref rid="fn141">8</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[24]] They set down.</bold> Like, &#x201C;They stopped,&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn142">9</xref></sup> [Yonasan translates:] &#x201C;They stopped the Ark.&#x201D; They stood it off to one side and the people passed by because Dovid wanted it brought with him.</p>
<p><bold>And Evyosor went off [to the side]</bold> until [all the people] finished etc. This is a shortened verse they set down the Ark of God until all the people finished travelling.<sup><xref rid="fn143">10</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>Evyosor went off [to the side].</bold> That day he was removed from the Kohanite service.<sup><xref rid="fn144">11</xref></sup> because He inquired of the Urim and Tumim but was not answered,<sup><xref rid="fn145">12</xref></sup> Tzodok then replaced him. This is what we learned in Seder Olam in tractate Yuma.<sup><xref rid="fn146">13</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[27]] If you see this [as right].</bold> I you see this as a good idea, &#x201C;return to the city etc.</p>
<p><bold>Your two sons with you.</bold> It will be in their power to inform me what they hear in the king&#x2019;s palace. And based on what they inform me I can escape.</p>
<p><bold>[[30]] The heights of Mount Olives.</bold> On Mount Olives.</p>
<p><bold>Was covered.</bold> &#x201C;Covered&#x201D; in the manner of mourners.</p>
<p><bold>Covered.</bold> [Yonasan translates:] &#x201C;Covered.&#x201D;</p>
<p><bold>[[31]] Dovid was told [by an informer].</bold> Dovid was told by the informer.</p>
<p><bold>Ruin.</bold> Ruin as we find &#x201C;The tool talks too much&#x201D;.<sup><xref rid="fn147">14</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[32]] Arrived at the summit.</bold> At the mountain&#x2019;s summit.</p>
<p><bold>Where he used to bow down to Elokim.</bold> Where he used to bow down. When he used to come to Yerusholoyim he would see from that [vantage] point the tent in which the Ark was [placed] and he would bow down.</p>
<p><bold>[[34]] Previously, I was your father&#x2019;s servant.</bold> This is like [saying], Previously I was your father&#x2019;s servant. It is a verse that [must be] cut.<sup><xref rid="fn148">15</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[37]] Was going to come to Yerosholoyim.</bold> Started thinking about coming to Yerusholoyim.<sup><xref rid="fn149">16</xref></sup></p>
<ftnote id="fn134"><sup>1</sup>Sanhedrin 21a. Rashi there explains that not having thighs enabled them to run faster and not having heels enabled them to step on sharp objects without any sensation of pain.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn135"><sup>2</sup>This is the opinion of Rebe Nehuroi in the name of Rebbe Yohoshua brought in Temurah 14b. Rashi is explaining that these forty years are not describing how long Avsholom was engaged in his intriguing against the king. Rather, the verse is informing us that forty years after their improper request, the kingdom was weakened.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn136"><sup>3</sup>Ibid.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn137"><sup>4</sup>Rashi there brings the Talmud in Menachos 87a that discusses the quality of the lambs of Chevron.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn138"><sup>5</sup>Chapter 1, halach 8.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn139"><sup>6</sup>But he implied to Dovid that only two men would go. He kept using the same document for more and more pairs of men.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn140"><sup>7</sup>This verse blends into verse 20 where Dovid explains more about why it is disadvantageous for Itai to stay with him.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn141"><sup>8</sup>Even though he was also passing by, since they were ahead of him, they are called passers by relative to his location.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn142"><sup>9</sup>Previously in 6:17.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn143"><sup>10</sup>The words <span dir="rtl">&#x05D5;&#x05D9;&#x05E2;&#x05DC; &#x05D0;&#x05D1;&#x05D9;&#x05EA;&#x05E8;</span> need to be placed at the end of the verse for interpretation.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn144"><sup>11</sup>As the Kohen Gadol.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn145"><sup>12</sup>This showed that he was no longer qualified for this lofty position. The Urim and Tumim lit up certain letters on the kohen Gadol&#x2019;s breastplate as a means for God to communicate to His people. See Shemos 28:30.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn146"><sup>13</sup>77c.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn147"><sup>14</sup>Koheles 10:14.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn148"><sup>15</sup>The word <span dir="rtl">&#x05D5;&#x05B7;&#x05D0;&#x05B2;&#x05E0;&#x05B4;&#x05D9;</span> needs to be &#x201C;cut out&#x201D; and placed in front of the phrase.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn149"><sup>16</sup><span dir="rtl">&#x05D9;&#x05B8;&#x05D1;&#x05D5;&#x05B9;&#x05D0;</span> denotes he will come in the future.</ftnote>
</appendix>
<appendix>
<p><bold>[[1]] One hundred portions of dried figs.</bold> Yonoson translates: &#x201C;One hundred portions of dried figs.&#x201D;</p>
<p><bold>[[10]] He should curse [me] like this.</bold> He should curse like this.</p>
<p><bold>God told him.</bold> Is it possible that a man like him who is head of the Sanhedrin would curse the king if he were not told [to do so] by God?</p>
<p><bold>[[12]] God will see [the tears] in my eyes.</bold> [Yonoson translates:] &#x201C;The tears of my eyes.&#x201D;</p>
<p><bold>[[14]] And they rested there.</bold> In Bachurim.</p>
<p><bold>[[21]] And you will strengthen the hands of all those who are with you.</bold> Because at present their hands are feeble in their ability to help you because they are saying [to themselves] in their hearts, &#x201C;The son will change towards [and reconcile with] his father and we will be hated by the king.<sup><xref rid="fn150">1</xref></sup></p>
<ftnote id="fn150"><sup>1</sup>For having joined a conspiracy against him.</ftnote>
</appendix>
<appendix>
<p><bold>[[3]] When they all return [to you].</bold> To you.</p>
<p><bold>[Except] the man you want.</bold> You will do what you want with him and you will have him killed. And afterwords, all the people will have peace. This is a shortened verse.<sup><xref rid="fn151">1</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[4]] And in the eyes of all of the elders of Yisroel.</bold> Wicked elders.</p>
<p><bold>[[8]] Your father is a man of war.</bold> He knows the concepts of war, its strategy and the nature of someone setting a trap. He is sure you will run after him tonight to get to him therefore he will not rest with the other people.</p>
<p><bold>[[9]] Now, he is hiding.</bold> When you reach the encampment of the people with him, he will not be there for us to kill.</p>
<p><bold>When some of the men fall at the beginning [of their battles].</bold> I told you that his men are strong and embittered souls and if they kill some of your people that will [mean] a defeat in this battle which is the first. A person will hear, [i.e., a person] from among all of Yisroel who come to join you, and will say, There was a disaster amongst Avsholom&#x2019;s people&#x2019;.</p>
<p><bold>[[10]] Even if he is a soldier.</bold> That person who hears [about the disaster] even if he is a soldier and his heart is like that of a lion his heart will surely melt in fear and trepidation. And he will no longer join you because he will say, &#x201C;He [Avsholom] has already started to fall and he is being punished for [what he did to] his father and he will not succeed.</p>
<p><bold>[[11]] But I advise [as follows:]</bold> Because this is my advice.</p>
<p><bold>And you yourself should go to war.</bold> At the head. [Yonoson translates:] &#x201C;And then you should go at the head of everybody.&#x201D;</p>
<p><bold>[[12]] And we will encamp upon him.</bold> We will encamp upon him language [denoting] camping as [we find], &#x201C;It camped within the entire boorder of Mitzraim&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn152">2</xref></sup> [and] &#x201C;Arom has camped opposite Ephraim.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn153">3</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[13]] In groups.</bold> [Yonoson translates:] &#x201C;Groups&#x201D; as [we find], &#x201C;A group of prophets.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn154">4</xref></sup> [and] &#x201C;Groups of evildoers.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn155">5</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>Into the valley [below].</bold> We will drag the city wall into the valley.</p>
<p><bold>[[16]] Cross over it.</bold> The Yardein.</p>
<p><bold>Because [my suggestion] may be rejected by the king.</bold> That I did not advise him well and [instead] he will proceed according to the advice of Achitophel.</p>
<p><bold>Rejected.</bold> He will be told secretely and by a concealed method.</p>
<p><bold>[[17]] By the launderers&#x2019; fountain.</bold> [Yonason translates:] &#x201C;By the launderers&#x2019; fountain.&#x201D; Launderers of woolen garments that bring them [the garments] there by kicking them with [their] foot.</p>
<p><bold>[[19]] The curtain.</bold> Curtain.</p>
<p><bold>Ground wheat.</bold> Ground wheat as [we find], &#x201C;Among the ground wheat.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn156">6</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[20]] Stream of water.</bold> I do not know the translation of this word <span dir="rtl">&#x05DE;&#x05B4;&#x05D9;&#x05DB;&#x05B7;&#x05DC;</span>. In the Machberes<sup><xref rid="fn157">7</xref></sup> [under the entry] <span dir="rtl">&#x05DB;&#x05B7;&#x05BC;&#x05DC;</span> [he writes] that its translation is according to the context. [Here] its as [if to say] streaming water of the river.</p>
<p><bold>[[25]] The daughter of Nochosh.</bold> This is Yeshai, Dovid&#x2019;s father. Our Rabbis said that [Yeshai] died without sin [but only] because of the serpent&#x2019;s counsel.<sup><xref rid="fn158">8</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[27]] Shovi, the son of Nochosh.</bold> He is Chonun, the son of Nochosh.<sup><xref rid="fn159">9</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>Mats.</bold> Mats. Utensils They are utensils for practical use. as [we find], &#x201C;Silver utensils.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn160">10</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>Toasted grain.</bold> Types of toasted foods Our Rabbis said Barzilai brought two types of porridge to Dovid, one made of wheat and one made of lentils as described here flour and <span dir="rtl">&#x05E7;&#x05B8;&#x05DC;&#x05B4;&#x05D9;</span>, this one was made from wheat. Beans, lentils and <span dir="rtl">&#x05E7;&#x05B8;&#x05DC;&#x05B4;&#x05D9;</span> [this one] was made from types of beans.<sup><xref rid="fn161">11</xref></sup> They used to dry them in ovens [having been put in] while they were [still] moist, they [thus] were permenantly sweet [then] they ground them and made from them a food that was called &#x201C;porridge.&#x201D;</p>
<p><bold>[[29]] And cow&#x2019;s cheese.</bold> [Yonoson translates:] &#x201C;And cheese made from milk.&#x201D;</p>
<ftnote id="fn151"><sup>1</sup>Missing the words that Rashi adds here to make sense of the words.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn152"><sup>2</sup>Shemos 10:14.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn153"><sup>3</sup>Yeshayohu 7:2.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn154"><sup>4</sup>Shmuel I 10:5.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn155"><sup>5</sup>Tehilim 119:61.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn156"><sup>6</sup>Mishlei 27:22.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn157"><sup>7</sup>Notebook written by Menachem (one of the Rishonim).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn158"><sup>8</sup>Baba Besra 16. The serpent in the Gan Fden who suggested to Chavah to eat from the Tree of knowledge. That sin brought death into the world. That is why Yeshai died because he had no sin of his own to merit death.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn159"><sup>9</sup>Mentioned earlier in 10:1.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn160"><sup>10</sup>Melochim II, 12:14.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn161"><sup>11</sup>The word <span dir="rtl">&#x05E7;&#x05B8;&#x05DC;&#x05B4;&#x05D9;</span> appears twice in this verse. The first <span dir="rtl">&#x05E7;&#x05B8;&#x05DC;&#x05B4;&#x05D9;</span> written after <span dir="rtl">&#x05E7;&#x05B6;&#x05DE;&#x05B7;&#x05D7;</span> refers to a porridge made from grain. The second <span dir="rtl">&#x05E7;&#x05B8;&#x05DC;&#x05B4;&#x05D9;</span> written after <span dir="rtl">&#x05E2;&#x05B2;&#x05D3;&#x05B8;&#xFB2A;&#x05B4;&#x05D9;&#x05DD;</span> refers to a porridge made from lentils.</ftnote>
</appendix>
<appendix>
<p><bold>[[3]] They will not pay us any attention.</bold> It will not be important in their eyes to overpower and to boast [[victoriously] now that you are not in the war.</p>
<p><bold>Because now.</bold> While you are in your glory [uncaptured] you are as important as all of us [together].</p>
<p><bold>Ten thousand.</bold> Like us ten thousand men.</p>
<p><bold>If you help us from the city.</bold> [Yonoson translates:] &#x201C;It will be better if you pray for us from the city for help.</p>
<p><bold>[[5]] Be gentle to the young man.</bold> If he presents himself before you in battle have pity on him.</p>
<p><bold>[[6]] In the forest of Ephraim.</bold> How did Ephraim get possesion of a forest on the eastern side of the Yardein,<sup><xref rid="fn162">1</xref></sup> no one had a portion there except for the people of God, Reuvein and Menashe? Yehoshua [partitioned Israel] conditionally that all the tribes could [have their cattle] graze in any forest. This forest was near Ephraim&#x2019;s portion<sup><xref rid="fn163">2</xref></sup> except that the Yardein was in between, and the people of Ephraim had their cattle graze there. [Thus] it was called Ephraim&#x2019;s forest</p>
<p><bold>[[8]] The [wild beasts of the] forest killed more people.</bold> The wild beasts of the forest, so Yonason translated.</p>
<p><bold>[[9]] Avsholom happenned.</bold> Denoting something that just happened, a chance meeting.</p>
<p><bold>He was hanging between the sky and the earth.</bold> Our Rabbis said<sup><xref rid="fn164">3</xref></sup> He unsheathed his sword to cut his hair and saw Gehennom open beneath him.</p>
<p><bold>[[12]] Beware that none harm the young man.</bold> Everyone who meets up with him should preserve him.</p>
<p><bold>[[14]] &#x201C;I will not ask you [any further].&#x201D;</bold> I will not make any more requests of you because I will go myself.</p>
<p><bold>[[18]] Because he said, &#x201C;I have no son.&#x201D;</bold> That can replace me and be as important as me.<sup><xref rid="fn165">4</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>This will memorialize my name.</bold> I will build this stone monument for myself. It was a significant building.</p>
<p><bold>[[20]] Inform him another day.</bold> A tiding of some other victory.</p>
<p><bold>Because.</bold> As a result of the king&#x2019;s son&#x2019;s death therefor this announcement will not be good for you.</p>
<p><bold>[[22]] For you. there is no reward in this announcement.</bold> There is no reward available today for an announcement.</p>
<p><bold>[[23]] So what.</bold> In other words, so what if I get no reward?</p>
<p><bold>And he passed.</bold> [Yonoson translates:] He arrived before the Kushite.</p>
<p><bold>[[29]] I saw a great multitude [engaged in battle].</bold> Moving to and fro in battle.</p>
<p><bold>And Yoav sent one of the king&#x2019;s other servants and [me] your servant.</bold> This is a verse that needs to be rearranged as follows: Yoav sent one of the king&#x2019;s other servants and [me] your servant. After Yoav sent the king&#x2019;s other servant, [referring to] the one who is running behind me.<sup><xref rid="fn166">5</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>And [me] your servant.</bold> He is referring to himself. I do not know what happenned afterwords.<sup><xref rid="fn167">6</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[30]] Turn and stand there.</bold> Move to the other side and stand there and let us hear what this one [the kushite] says.</p>
<ftnote id="fn162"><sup>1</sup>Dovid had crossed over to the eastern side of the Yardein earlier (17:22) and that&#x2019;s where this battle took place.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn163"><sup>2</sup>On the other side of the Yardein.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn164"><sup>3</sup>Sotah 10b. See Meharsho there.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn165"><sup>4</sup>He did have children as related earlier (14:27) but did not consider them on a par with his stature. See Sotah 11a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn166"><sup>5</sup>After he sent that runner is when he sent me.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn167"><sup>6</sup>Here Rashi is explaining the last part of the verse, &#x201C;and I do not know what&#x2026;&#x201D;</ftnote>
</appendix>
<appendix>
<p><bold>[[1]] My son, my son.</bold> Eight times.<sup><xref rid="fn168">1</xref></sup> Our Rabbis said,<sup><xref rid="fn169">2</xref></sup> Seven of those times to lift him out of the seven levels of Gehennom and one to to bring him into the World to Come.</p>
<p><bold>[[5]] Covered his face.</bold> [Yononson translates:] &#x201C;Covered his face&#x201D; in the manner of mourners.</p>
<p><bold>Covered.</bold> As [we find]: &#x201C;He wrapped his face with his coat&#x201D;,<sup><xref rid="fn170">3</xref></sup> &#x201C;It is wrapped up in a cloth&#x201D;.<sup><xref rid="fn171">4</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[8]] That [if] you do not go out [to the people].</bold> If you do not go out.<sup><xref rid="fn172">5</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[9]] [As the people of] Yisroel fled.</bold> Those people that were with Avsholom.</p>
<p><bold>[[10]] The people were reproaching each other.</bold> Reproaching each other.</p>
<p><bold>[[12]] While the messages of all Yisroel are coming to the king.</bold> All this was part of the message he was charged to bring [to the elders].</p>
<p><bold>[[14]] To Amosoh.</bold> Who is [Avsholom&#x2019;s] commanding officer you should say, &#x2018;You are my own sister&#x2019;s son.&#x2019;<sup><xref rid="fn173">6</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[18]] They crossed the Yardein.</bold> They crossed it with their rafts.</p>
<p><bold>[[19]] The ferry crossed over.</bold> The ferry boat that was used to cross over to the other side of the river&#x2019;s width.</p>
<p><bold>[[21]] First from among all the House of Yoseif.</bold> All of Yisroel wronged you, I more then everyone. I have come to ask you forgiveness, if you accept me then all of Yisroel will be confident that you will accept them but if you do not [accept me] they will be afraid to return to you.</p>
<p><bold>[[23]] Should a man die today?</bold> This is a question. Because today I am [truly] king. Until now I thought A great man as this [Shimi] would not have shamed me unless God had decreed to end my kingdom, and He had told him, &#x2018;Curse Dovid.&#x2019; But now that he regrets it I know that I am [truly] king.</p>
<p><bold>[[25]] He had not tended to the hair [between] his legs.</bold> Denoting fixing up, the removing of the hair between his legs.</p>
<p><bold>His moustache.</bold>&#160;<italic>Grenon</italic> in O.F.</p>
<p><bold>[[26]] Why did you not you go with me?</bold> To leave Yerusholoyim when I left.</p>
<p><bold>[[27]] Because your servant is lame.</bold> And I can not walk on foot.</p>
<p><bold>[[32]] Accompanying him.</bold> To accompany him.</p>
<p><bold>[[33]] Because he was a very great man.</bold> In terms of wealth.</p>
<p><bold>[[35]] How many more years of life [do I have].</bold> That I have to live.</p>
<p><bold>That I should go up.</bold> There are only a few left, [therefore] what pleasure will I have from your providing for me.</p>
<p><bold>[[36]] Between something good or bad?</bold> Between good food and bad food. Our Rabbis of blessed memory said, He overindulged in sexual relations causing old age to overtake him.<sup><xref rid="fn174">7</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[37]] Your servant will just cross over.</bold> You servant will accompany you a little further after you cross the Yardein.</p>
<p><bold>This type of reward.</bold> That is not good for me.</p>
<p><bold>[[38]] Your servant Kimhom.</bold> It was his son.</p>
<p><bold>[[43]] Because the king is close to us.</bold> He is from our tribe.</p>
<p><bold>Have any presents.</bold> As we find, &#x201C;A present&#x201D;.<sup><xref rid="fn175">8</xref></sup> A present from the king&#x2019;s palace.</p>
<p><bold>[[44]] We have ten parts of the king.</bold> Because we are altogether ten tribes.</p>
<p><bold>And also more right in Dovid.</bold> Although he is a closer relative of yours nevertheless we have more ownership of him then you do because we have ten parts [of him].</p>
<p><bold>Why have you made light of me?</bold> That you should be first, was I not the first to request to have my king return? Prior to this our request came to him to have him return as it is written earlier,<sup><xref rid="fn176">9</xref></sup> &#x201C;while the messages of all Yisroel are coming to the king.&#x201D;</p>
<p><bold>The words of men of Yehudah overpowered.</bold> Language similar to &#x201C;Improve&#x201D;.<sup><xref rid="fn177">10</xref></sup> The words of the men of Yehudah were more logical and they prevailed because they showed [as evidence] the letter Dovid had sent them [saying] &#x201C;Why should you be the last to request&#x201D; that the king return etc.&#x201D; This is what is explained in Agadah. Some explain <span dir="rtl">&#x05D5;&#x05B7;&#x05D9;&#x05B4;&#x05E7;&#x05B6;&#xFB2A;</span> to denote hard and strong and that is Yonoson&#x2019;s translation, &#x201C;overpowered.&#x201D;</p>
<ftnote id="fn168"><sup>1</sup>Dovid said the word <span dir="rtl">&#xFB31;&#x05B0;&#x05E0;&#x05B4;&#x05D9;</span>  eight times, five times in this verse and another three times later in verse 5.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn169"><sup>2</sup>Sotah 10b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn170"><sup>3</sup>Melochim I, 19:13.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn171"><sup>4</sup>Shmuel I, 21:10.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn172"><sup>5</sup>Rashi is adding the word &#x201C;if&#x201D; to the verse.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn173"><sup>6</sup>The son of Avigail. See 17:25.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn174"><sup>7</sup>Shabbos 152a. Otherwise even an eighty year old man would not have deteriorated to that extent.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn175"><sup>8</sup>Bereishis 43:34.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn176"><sup>9</sup>19:12.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn177"><sup>10</sup>Tsaphania 2:1.</ftnote>
</appendix>
<appendix>
<p><bold>[[1]] There, he invited.</bold> Invited Language like that of &#x201C;He invited his guests.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn178">1</xref></sup> &#x201C;Avsholom invited all the king&#x2019;s children.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn179">2</xref></sup> Language denoting &#x201C;inviting&#x201D;.</p>
<p><bold>[[4]] Rally the men of Yehudah.</bold> That they should be here within three days.</p>
<p><bold>And then you be back here [to meet me].</bold> After three days be sure to be back here before me because he [Dovid] wanted to chase after Shevah, the son of Bichri.</p>
<p><bold>[[5]] But was delayed past the appointed time.</bold> He found Rabbis who had begun to learn a tractate in the Talmud, as is stated in Sanhedrin.<sup><xref rid="fn180">3</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[6]] Take your master&#x2019;s servants.</bold> Now that Amosoh, the commanding officer was delayed and had not yet brought the soldiers of Yehudah, you take from the men in my entourage and chase after him.</p>
<p><bold>To escape to out of our sight.</bold> And he will escape right before our eyes, this is an abbreviated verse.<sup><xref rid="fn181">4</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[8]] Close to his loins.</bold> Very close to his body along the width of his loins, this was not the usual way of carrying a sword. He did so to make it easy for it to fall out so it would not be necessary to take it out of its sheath.</p>
<p><bold>He started out [towards Amosoh.].</bold> Towards Amosoh.</p>
<p><bold>And it fell out.</bold> The sword [fell out] from its sheath because it was smooth and sharp and was not hanging on the side of his thigh but it was along the width of his loins. As soon as he [Yoav] leaned forward towards the ground it [the sword] fell out of its sheath and he grabbed it with his right hand without Amosoh noticing anything.</p>
<p><bold>[[12]] When he saw that all who passed by it remained there.</bold> When the man saw that everyone who passed by it would remain there.</p>
<p><bold>[[13]] When it was withdrawn.</bold> When it was removed as we find. &#x201C;When the impurities are removed from silver&#x201D;,<sup><xref rid="fn182">5</xref></sup> and as find &#x201C;When the wicked are removed from before the king&#x201D;.<sup><xref rid="fn183">6</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[14]] He [Shevah] went through all the tribes of Yisroel.</bold> Shevah, the son of Bichri [went] to convince them to declare him king over them.</p>
<p><bold>All the Beirim.</bold> I do not know what it is.</p>
<p><bold>[[15]] And it [the city] held by virtue of its inner wall.</bold> [Yonoson translates:] &#x201C;They surrounded it strongly.&#x201D; Some interpret <span dir="rtl">&#x05D5;&#x05B7;&#x05EA;&#x05BC;&#x05B7;&#x05E2;&#x05B2;&#x05DE;&#x05D3;&#x05C1; &#x05D1;&#x05B7;&#x05BC;&#x05D7;&#x05B5;&#x05DC;</span> to have a meaning like &#x201C;the inner wall and the outer wall&#x201D;.<sup><xref rid="fn184">7</xref></sup> They had [already] cause the outer wall to fall and it [the city] fortified itself to hold fast by virtue of the inner wall.</p>
<p><bold>[[17]] Are you Yoav?</bold> That it is said of you &#x201C;Who sits among the wise at their assembly.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn185">8</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[18]] You should have talked [peace] first.</bold> You should have talked peace first. If they had answered you that they wanted peace and had opened their city to you then you should not have gone to war against them.</p>
<p><bold>If you had asked [for peace] with Oveil.</bold> If your soldiers had asked for peace with this city called Oveil.</p>
<p><bold>They would have completely [cooperated].</bold> The people of the city would have immediately made peace with you.</p>
<p><bold>[[19]] I am [from the people of the city] that are loyal and trustworthy to Yisroel.</bold> I am from the people of the city that are loyal and trustworthy to Yisroel and to the king. An Aggadic Midrash [states:] this was Serach, the daughter of Asher. I faithfully rewarded those who faithful [to God]: Through me, the location of Yosef&#x2019;s coffin was revealed to Moshe. I told Yakov that Yosef was alive.</p>
<p><bold>[[20]] Far be it, far be it from me.</bold> Far be it from me, far be it from the king.</p>
<p><bold>[[21]] Lifted his hand against the king, Dovid.</bold> Against the king even if it were not Dovid he is punishable by death. Alternatively if it were against Dovid [who is a scholar] even if he was not the king, he [Shevah] is punishable by death. All the much more so [now that he has rebelled] against the king, against Dovid. This is how this verse is expounded upon in the Midrash Koheles.</p>
<p><bold>[[22]] The woman came [and spoke] to all the people.</bold> It is taught in a Tosefta:<sup><xref rid="fn186">9</xref></sup> &#x201C;She said to them, &#x2018;Since both he will be killed and they will be killed [they should] hand him over to them.<sup><xref rid="fn187">10</xref></sup> If he were able to be saved, for example he was inside and you were on the outside and you were in mortal danger [fighting Yoav] [but] he could escape<sup><xref rid="fn188">11</xref></sup> [then we have a rule that] it is prohibited to let one person be killed in order to save another, [therefore, you cannot] have him killed to save yourselves. But now that he is [anyway] going to be killed with you because the walls have been breached and there is no possibility of escape,<sup><xref rid="fn189">12</xref></sup> [then] it is better that he alone die and you should not die along with him.&#x2019; Rebbe Shimon said, this is what she said to them, &#x2018;Anyone who has rebelled against the kingdom of the House of Dovid is punishable by death.&#x2019;<sup><xref rid="fn190">13</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[23]] Yoav commanded the entire army.</bold> Despite the fact that Dovid had said to Amosoh, &#x201C;I will make you the commanding general in Yoav&#x2019;s stead&#x201D;,<sup><xref rid="fn191">14</xref></sup> now that Amsoh was dead Yoav was not replaced. And because of Yoav [remaining commander], he [Dovid] had to appoint his [Yoav&#x2019;s] friends.<sup><xref rid="fn192">15</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[26]] Eiroh the Yoiri.</bold> Yonoson translated: &#x201C;Eiroh who gives forth light from Tekuah.&#x201D; And so is he referred to in this book Eiroh ben Eikash of Tekuah. He was called Yoiri because it is taught in Menochos,<sup><xref rid="fn193">16</xref></sup> &#x201C;Tekuah was first in [olive] oil,&#x201D; because olive oil was prevalent there from which candles are lit [in the Beis Mikdosh].</p>
<p><bold>Was a Kokein for Dovid.</bold> He [Dovid] would give him [Eiroh] all his Kehunah gifts, that is what our Rabbis explained.<sup><xref rid="fn194">17</xref></sup> The simple explanation of the verse is that he [Dovid] made him [Eiroh] an officer and a judge.</p>
<ftnote id="fn178"><sup>1</sup>Tsaphania 1:7.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn179"><sup>2</sup>Shmuel II, 13:23.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn180"><sup>3</sup>49a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn181"><sup>4</sup>Missing the word <span dir="rtl">&#x05E2;&#x05B7;&#x05E6;&#x05B0;&#x05DE;&#xFB4B;</span>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn182"><sup>5</sup>Mishlei 25:4.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn183"><sup>6</sup>Ibid, 25:5.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn184"><sup>7</sup>Eichoh 2:8.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn185"><sup>8</sup>Further on 23:8.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn186"><sup>9</sup>Terumos 7:23.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn187"><sup>10</sup>To Yoav&#x2019;s men.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn188"><sup>11</sup>While you would be fighting.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn189"><sup>12</sup>For anyone.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn190"><sup>13</sup>Threfore Shevah must be killed in order for you to be spared.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn191"><sup>14</sup>Earlier in 19:14.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn192"><sup>15</sup>To the positions mentioned in the next few verses.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn193"><sup>16</sup>Menochos 85b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn194"><sup>17</sup>Eiruvin 63a.</ftnote>
</appendix>
<appendix>
<p><bold>[[1]] On account of Shaul.</bold> On account of the sin regarding Shaul who was buried immediately and secretly as the men of Yovish Gilod stole his body and buried him. [Consequently] he was not eulogized with the respect due him.</p>
<p><bold>And his bloody House.</bold> Because he killed out Nov, the city of Kohanim.</p>
<p><bold>And because he killed the Givonim.</bold> When he killed out Nov, the city of Kohanim, he killed seven people from among them [the Givonim]. Two wood cutters, two water drawers, the sexton, the announcer and the scribe. This is what is explained in Yerushalmi Talmud, in Maseches Sanhedrin.<sup><xref rid="fn195">1</xref></sup> [But] our Rabbis said,<sup><xref rid="fn196">2</xref></sup> On account that he [Shaul] killed the Kohanim [of Nov] that provided food for them [the Givonim], consequently Scripture considers it as if he killed them [as well]. Do not wonder that God demanded retribution for the lack of respect given to him<sup><xref rid="fn197">3</xref></sup> and simultaneously demanded retribution for his sin,<sup><xref rid="fn198">4</xref></sup> because this what is what it is written, &#x201C;Who has done His work,&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn199">5</xref></sup> when the person is being judged his good works [are remembered] this what we are taught in Maseches Yevomos.<sup><xref rid="fn200">6</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[2]] And spoke to them.</bold> Words of appeasement [asking them] to put aside their feelings [of anger] and forgive Shaul and his household.</p>
<p><bold>The Givonim were not part of the Bnei Yisroel.</bold> This is to say that they displayed how cruel they are, because they are not descendants of our forefather Avrohom. They have proven themselves unworthy to join with Yisroel and hence Dovid decreed that they not be permitted to marry into the Jewish community. He [Dovid] said, This nation [of Yisroel] has three characteristics, the people are merciful, they possess shame and perform kindful deeds for others. Whoever has these three characteristics is worthy of joining it [Yisroel].<sup><xref rid="fn201">7</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>Sworn to them [that they would let them live].</bold> During the days of Yehoshua when he made woodcutters and water drawers for the Altar.<sup><xref rid="fn202">8</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>In his zeal to avenge the Bnei Yisroel.</bold> Because he [Shaul] intended to clean and purify Yisroel and to take care of their [Yisroel&#x2019;s] needs, he wanted to kill them. This anger was for a good purpose as we find &#x201C;Are you zealous for my sake?&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn203">9</xref></sup> And we also find &#x201C;by the zeal for God&#x2019;s sake&#x201D; as was said of Yeihuh.<sup><xref rid="fn204">10</xref></sup> This is the simple explanation of our verse. [But] according to the Midrashic intepretation, he [Shaul] only ordered that the kohanim be killed. And the zeal described here was not for a good purpose but rather for a bad purpose because he [Shaul] knew that his kingdom would not continue further from the day that he did not heed God&#x2019;s commandment concerning Amoleik,<sup><xref rid="fn205">11</xref></sup> and from that time on, he was angry [and persecuted] them.</p>
<p><bold>[[3]] So that you should bless the heritage of Adonoy?</bold> Pray for them.</p>
<p><bold>[[4]] We are not interested in silver or gold from Shaul.</bold> We are only interested in [retribution against] people. He [Dovid] wanted to appease them with money but they did not want [to accept it]. He [Dovid] said, &#x201C;It may be that they are embarrassed of each other.&#x201D; [Therefore] he went and tried to appease each one individually [but] they [still] would not be appeased. That is why it is written here, &#x201C;I am not interested in silver or gold etc&#x201D; in singular form.<sup><xref rid="fn206">12</xref></sup> This I saw in the Yerushalmi Talmud.<sup><xref rid="fn207">13</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>And we are interested in killing anyone.</bold> Among the rest of the Bnei Yisroel because they did not agrieve us.</p>
<p><bold>[[5]] And intended to destroy us.</bold> He said in his heart that we should be destroyed [and prevented] by him &#x201C;from establishing etc.&#x201D; He intended to destroy us.</p>
<p><bold>Intended.</bold> He intended to destroy us.</p>
<p><bold>[[6]] We will hang them.</bold> Hanging.</p>
<p><bold>Before God.</bold> In the name of God, to publicize His edict.</p>
<p><bold>The chosen one of God.</bold> A heavenly voice came forth and said, &#x201C;The chosen one of God.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn208">14</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[7]] The king had pity.</bold> He prayed for pity on Mephivoshes that the Ark should not detain him; because Dovid had them [Shaul&#x2019;s children] pass before the Ark, whomever the Ark detained, was put to death.<sup><xref rid="fn209">15</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[8]] Sons of Michal, the daughter of Shaul who had bore them to Adriel.</bold> Did Michal give birth [to these children]? It was Meirav who bore [those children] to [Adriel]. [The explanation is] that Meirav gave birth [to them] and Michal<sup><xref rid="fn210">16</xref></sup> raised them, that is why they are called by her name because someone who raises male and female orphans in their house it is considered as if that person gave birth [to the child] and [the child] is called by his name.<sup><xref rid="fn211">17</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[9]] At the beginning of the harvest.</bold> During the days of Nisson.</p>
<p><bold>[[10]] Until the rains fell on them.</bold> During the rainy season in Tishri. Their bones were not removed for burial. But is it not written, &#x201C;His body should not remain [hanging] overnight&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn212">18</xref></sup>? However they reasoned that it is better that one of the letters of the Torah be uprooted in order that God&#x2019;s Name be publicly sanctified. Passersby would ask &#x201C;Why have these people come to this fate?&#x201D; They were told [in response], &#x201C;They are royal sons.&#x201D; &#x201C;What did they do [wrong]?&#x201D; &#x201C;They assaulted downtrodden foreigners.&#x201D; [The passersby] would say, &#x201C;There is no people better to associate with then this people.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn213">19</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[12]] He took Shaul&#x2019;s bones.</bold> He [Dovid] was told concerning them, &#x201C;Because of Shaul&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn214">20</xref></sup> who was not eulogized according to halachah.</p>
<p><bold>[[13]] They gathered the bones.</bold> Of the seven people that were hung there.<sup><xref rid="fn215">21</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[14]] Everything that the king had commanded.</bold> To eulogize them in all of the cities of Yisroel.</p>
<p><bold>[[16]] A spear case weighing.</bold> It is like a case that is at the top of spear&#x2019;s handle that is called aristuille in O.F., and it is made like a hat There is something comparable to it in Maseches Zevochim, &#x201C;What were the pomegranates of the tunic<sup><xref rid="fn216">22</xref></sup> similar to? They were like the caps on babies&#x2019; heads&#x201D; The caps [are called] hemles in O.F.</p>
<p><bold>Who was armed.</bold> Armed with a new sword. I heard [an explanation] that on that day he was intitiated into the wearing of battle dress and it is the manner of those so initiated to [try to] be successful and mighty on the day of their initiation to make a name for themselves. That is why, <bold>he said he was going to kill Dovid.</bold></p>
<p><bold>[[17]] [Came] to his aid.</bold> He helped him with his prayer as is brought in [chapter] Cheilek.<sup><xref rid="fn217">23</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[18]] There was more war.</bold> This [war] came before all [those mentioned here] and is only recounted here to combine the deaths of the four sons of Orpoh.</p>
<p><bold>[[19]] Elchonon.</bold> Dovid.<sup><xref rid="fn218">24</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>The son of Yari [whose family] were weavers.</bold> His family weaved the partition curtain of the Beis Hamikdosh that is [also] called a forest.<sup><xref rid="fn219">25</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>Like that of the weaver&#x2019;s rod.</bold> [Yonoson translates:] &#x201C;Like the weaver&#x2019;s rod,&#x201D; that is called &#x201C;ensouple&#x201D; in O.F. Let a weaver come and stand up against a weaver[&#x2019;s instrument].</p>
<p><bold>[[20]] A giant man.</bold> As [Yonoson] translated, &#x201C;A man of [great] measure,&#x201D; the root [portion] of the word are the letters <span dir="rtl">&#x05DE;</span> and <span dir="ltr">&#x05D3;</span>.<sup><xref rid="fn220">26</xref></sup> We find [similarly] from the word <span dir="ltr">&#x05E9;&#x05D0;&#x05D5;&#x05DF;</span><sup><xref rid="fn221">27</xref></sup> [roar] the root letters are <span dir="rtl">&#x05E9;</span> and <span dir="rtl">&#x05D0;</span> and from the word <span dir="ltr">&#x05D4;&#x05B8;&#x05DE;&#xFB4B;&#x05DF;</span><sup><xref rid="fn222">28</xref></sup> the root letters are <span dir="rtl">&#x05D4;</span> and <span dir="ltr">&#x05DE;</span>.<sup><xref rid="fn223">29</xref></sup> In Divrei Hayomim<sup><xref rid="fn224">30</xref></sup> it is written, &#x201C;A man of measure&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn225">31</xref></sup> i.e., a very tall man who had people measuring his height.</p>
<p><bold>Numbered six each etc.</bold> Our Rabbis explained in Maseches Bechoros<sup><xref rid="fn226">32</xref></sup> that the verse had to tell us &#x201C;twenty-four&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn227">33</xref></sup> in order that you should not say that the fingers of his two hands only came to a total of six and that the toes of his [two] feet only came to a total of six that is why it is written, &#x201C;twenty-four.&#x201D; If it had written in our verse only &#x2018;twenty-four&#x201D; and not had said &#x201C;six each,&#x201D; I would have [mistakeingly] said, there were seven on one [hand or foot] and five on the other. And what is the verse trying to indicate by the word &#x201C;number&#x201D;? That all these digital extremities could be counted in the normal arrangement of fingers on a hand.</p>
<ftnote id="fn195"><sup>1</sup>Yerushalmi Sanhedrin 29a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn196"><sup>2</sup>Yevomos 78b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn197"><sup>3</sup>i.e., the proper eulogy due him.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn198"><sup>4</sup>of killing out Nov.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn199"><sup>5</sup>Tsafanyoh 2:3.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn200"><sup>6</sup>Yevomos ibid, See Rashi there.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn201"><sup>7</sup>They have shown themselves to be cruel and unmerciful and hence they do not deserve to join together with Yisroel. Yevomos 79a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn202"><sup>8</sup>Yehoshua 9:27.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn203"><sup>9</sup>Bamidbar 11:29.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn204"><sup>10</sup>See Melochim I, 19:10.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn205"><sup>11</sup>Shmuel I, 15:9.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn206"><sup>12</sup>The verse is written with <span dir="rtl">&#x05DC;&#x05B4;&#x05D9;</span> in singular form, but is read with <span dir="rtl">&#x05DC;&#x05B8;&#x05E0;&#xFB35;</span>, plural form indicating that Dovid tried to appease them both collectively as a group and also on an individual basis.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn207"><sup>13</sup>Sanhedrin 29a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn208"><sup>14</sup>The Givonim who hated Shaul would be unlikely to call him, &#x201C;the chosen one of God.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn209"><sup>15</sup>i.e., was handed over to the Givonim who subsequently put them to death. Yevomos 79a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn210"><sup>16</sup>Meirav&#x2019;s sister.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn211"><sup>17</sup>Sanhedrin 19a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn212"><sup>18</sup>Devorim 21:22. Why did Dovid let this happen?</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn213"><sup>19</sup>Yevomos 79a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn214"><sup>20</sup>Earlier in 21:1.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn215"><sup>21</sup>In verse 9.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn216"><sup>22</sup>Zevachim 88b. The tunic worn by the Kohein Godol.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn217"><sup>23</sup>Sanhedrin 95a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn218"><sup>24</sup>We know that it was Dovid who killed Golias in Shmuel I, 17:51, consequently this Elchonon must be Dovid.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn219"><sup>25</sup>The Beis Hamikdosh is called a forest because it was made with planks of acacia wood, see Shmos 26:15.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn220"><sup>26</sup>The <span dir="rtl">&#x05D9;&#x05DF;</span> being a suffix.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn221"><sup>27</sup>Tehilim 65:8.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn222"><sup>28</sup>Bereishis 17:4.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn223"><sup>29</sup>These two words also having <span dir="rtl">&#x05D9;&#x05DF;</span> as a suffix.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn224"><sup>30</sup>Divrei Hayomim I, 11:23.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn225"><sup>31</sup>Concerning this same giant refered to in our verse but there the word <span dir="rtl">&#x05DE;&#x05B4;&#x05D3;&#x05BC;&#x05B8;&#x05D4;</span> is used without the suffix <span dir="rtl">&#x05D9;&#x05DF;</span>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn226"><sup>32</sup>45b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn227"><sup>33</sup>Despite the fact that given that his two hands and two feet had six digital extremities each, which obviously totals twenty-four.</ftnote>
</appendix>
<appendix>
<p><bold>[[1]] On the day Adonoy saved him.</bold> In his old age after all his troubles had passed and he had survived all of them.</p>
<p><bold>And from the hands of Shaul.</bold> Shaul was part of the general grouping [of &#x201C;his enemies&#x201D;]?<sup><xref rid="fn228">1</xref></sup> but he was his greatest enemy and pursuer. Similarly [we find], &#x201C;Nineteen men and Asohel<sup><xref rid="fn229">2</xref></sup> Similarly, &#x201C;Go spy out the land and Yericho.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn230">3</xref></sup> And similarly, &#x201C;King Shlomo loved [many] foreign women and [he loved] the daughter of Pharoah.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn231">4</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[2]] My Rock, my Fortress.</bold> They are words denoting strength. Rock is obvious in its connotation [of strengh]. Fortress is [a reference to] a fortress amongst the forests that is called flassant in O.F. It is [also] a reference to the miracle that occurred by the rock at the crossroads<sup><xref rid="fn232">5</xref></sup> and the fortresses of the forest.<sup><xref rid="fn233">6</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>My Rescuer.</bold> He saved me when I was with Yisroel&#x2019;s army at war and other times He saved me when I was alone<sup><xref rid="fn234">7</xref></sup> for example [He saved me] from the inhabitants of Nov.</p>
<p><bold>[[3]] My Rock.</bold> Language denoting a rock because a rock protects passerby from the rain and from the winds. Abriments in O.F.</p>
<p><bold>I take refuge.</bold> Language denoting a covering that I was able to be protectively covered.</p>
<p><bold>My Stronghold.</bold> He supported me.</p>
<p><bold>My Refuge.</bold> I would run to him for protection.</p>
<p><bold>[[4]] I call to Adonoy in praise.</bold> As it is translated, when I called Him, I praised Him with my mouth  because I trusted that I would be saved from my enemies. And it is possible to interpret the words <span dir="rtl">&#x05D0;&#x05B6;&#x05E7;&#x05B0;&#x05E8;&#x05B8;&#x05D0;</span> and <span dir="rtl">&#x05D0;&#x05B4;&#xFB35;&#x05C7;&#xFB2A;&#x05B5;&#x05E2;&#x05B7;</span> as being used in the present tense.</p>
<p><bold>[[5]] Surrounded me.</bold> Surrounded me.</p>
<p><bold>Death&#x2019;s destruction.</bold> As [Yonoson] translates, &#x201C;Like a woman sitting on the birthing chair,&#x201D; that is the name of the stone seat where women give birth.<sup><xref rid="fn235">8</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>The deluge.</bold> Soldiers pouring forth like a stream.</p>
<p><bold>[[6]] The agony.</bold> As [Yonoson] translates, &#x201C;Groups,&#x201D; as [we find], &#x201C;Group of prophets.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn236">9</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>Were before me.</bold> Came before me.</p>
<p><bold>[[7]] In my distress I called to God&#x2026; He hears.</bold> This is typical of the present tense it uses both past and future at the same time.<sup><xref rid="fn237">10</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[8]] Shook and shuddered.</bold> This is not referring to the miracles that happened to him but to the miracles that happened to Yisroel and the beginning of the verse is connected to the end.</p>
<p><bold>When God became angry.</bold> The word <span dir="rtl">&#x05DB;&#x05D9;</span> is being used here to mean &#x201C;when,&#x201D; and this is its interpretation, when God became angry on account of his antagonists the world shook and shuddered and the pillars of heaven trembled and shook.</p>
<p><bold>[[9]] Smoke rose from His Nostrils.</bold> Such is the manner of an angry person, smoke comes out of his nostrils and so [we find], &#x201C;Smoke has risen from My nostrils.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn238">11</xref></sup> This is always the meaning of the words &#x201C;Anger of the nose,&#x201D; the nose flares and lets out air.</p>
<p><bold>Fire from His Mouth consumed [the wicked].</bold> Through the decree utterred from His Mouth fire [came forth] and consumed the wicked.</p>
<p><bold>[[10]] He bent heaven.</bold> To take revenge from His enemies, from Mitzrayim and from Pharoah.</p>
<p><bold>[[He put [a protective] darkness around.</bold> For [protective] cover as it says, &#x201C;The pillar of cloud and the darkness separated between Mitzrayim and Yisroel.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn239">12</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>Abundant waters, thick clouds of the sky.</bold> From where did the darkness come? They came from thick clouds that sprinkle water on the earth.</p>
<p><bold>Sprinkled.</bold> [This is] language that denotes a sieve, [the water] falls to the earth in small droplets. This [same language] is used in many places in Aggadah, &#x201C;They dice it in a sieve,&#x201D; Some interpret <span dir="rtl">&#x05D7;&#x05B7;&#xFB2A;&#x05B0;&#x05E8;&#x05B7;&#x05EA;</span> as denoting a binding, that the skies became bound up with clouds because of the water [in them] as [the word] &#x201C;the spokes&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn240">13</xref></sup> used [in connection with] the wheels of a wagon. They are wooden spokes that bond and bind the wheel&#x2019;s perimeter together.</p>
<p><bold>[[13]] From the brightness before Him.</bold> You should not conclude that He dwells in darkness<sup><xref rid="fn241">14</xref></sup> but rather it is light that is within the boundary and it is from that light that is before Him that the burning coals of fire [came forth]. [It is from there] that the arrows were shot at Mitzrayim.</p>
<p><bold>[[16]] The foundations of the earth were revealed.</bold> The deep seas split open. When the Reed Sea split all the world&#x2019;s waters split [as well].</p>
<p><bold>By the wind.</bold> From the force of wind blowing from His Nostrils.</p>
<p><bold>[[18]] They were too powerful.</bold> When they were overpowering.</p>
<p><bold>[[21]] For my rightesnous.</bold> When they [the people of Yisroel] followed God into the desert and had faith in His promise.</p>
<p><bold>[[26]] To the Kind, Sincere, Pure.</bold> [These three nouns] represent the three Patriarchs. God paid the reward of their righteousness to their children.<sup><xref rid="fn242">15</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[27]] And to those who are crooked.</bold> [This refers to] Paroh</p>
<p><bold>You act perversely.</bold> [This is] language denoting jagged and crooked. In the book of Tehilim<sup><xref rid="fn243">16</xref></sup> it is written, <span dir="ltr">&#xFB4A;&#x05B4;&#x05EA;&#x05B0;&#xFB44;&#x05B7;&#xFB4A;&#x05B8;&#x05DC;</span>.<sup><xref rid="fn244">17</xref></sup> An alternative explanation,<sup><xref rid="fn245">18</xref></sup> [when writing] &#x201C;He delivers [salvation] from on high,&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn246">19</xref></sup> [Dovid] was refering to himself.<sup><xref rid="fn247">20</xref></sup> When he was rushing to escape Shaul [and had reached] the rock at the crossroads,<sup><xref rid="fn248">21</xref></sup> and was close to being captured an angel came to Shaul saying, &#x201C;Go quickly because the Pelishtim have spread out [in battle formation over the terrain.]&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn249">22</xref></sup> &#x201C;He rewarded me&#x2026;according to my righteousness.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn250">23</xref></sup> [Refering to the fact] that I did not kill him [Shaul] when I [instead just] cut off the corner of his coat.</p>
<p><bold>[[31]] The word of Adonoy is clear.</bold> It is clear, He makes promises and keeps them.</p>
<p><bold>[[33]] He cleared my path to perfection.</bold> From any obstacle, from any sin and from any danger until there was peace and [the land was] conquered.</p>
<p><bold>[[35]] My arms to bend a copper bow.</bold> So that a copper bow can be bent by my arms because I have the strength to bend them. Dovid had bows hanging in his palace, and kings of other nations would come and see them and ask each other, Do you think that he can bend them? This is only to scare us. Dovid would hear them and would take them [the bows] and bend them in front of them [the kings]. The binding of a bow is denoted by the word <span dir="ltr">&#x05D7;&#x05B4;&#xFB4A;&#x05B7;&#x05EA;</span><sup><xref rid="fn251">24</xref></sup> and so [we find], &#x201C;Your arrows have been shot into me&#x201D;.<sup><xref rid="fn252">25</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[36]] You have been abundant for my sake with Your humility.</bold> You have been abundant for my sake, with Your humility.</p>
<p><bold>[[37]] You have expanded my stride.</bold> When a man keeps his legs together, it is easier for him to fall, and so it says, &#x201C;When you travel, do not narrow your stride.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn253">26</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>My ankles.</bold> My ankles.</p>
<p><bold>[[42]] They cried out there was no one to deliver them.</bold> The words of verse are not written in order [the proper order should be] &#x201C;They will cry out to Adonoy but He will not answer them and no one will deliver them&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn254">27</xref></sup> as [we find], &#x201C;Man will turn to his Maker&#x201D;,<sup><xref rid="fn255">28</xref></sup> as if to say &#x201C;turn&#x201D;.<sup><xref rid="fn256">29</xref></sup> Menachem connected [the word <span dir="ltr">&#x05D9;&#x05B4;&#xFB2A;&#x05B0;&#x05E2;&#x05B6;&#x05D4;</span>] with [the verse,] &#x201C;Adonoy listened to Hevel&#x201D;,<sup><xref rid="fn257">30</xref></sup> and he [Menachem] interpreted it as &#x201C;listening.&#x201D; This word can be used to denote both the listener and the listened to as [we find], &#x201C;Yitzchok implored Adonoy&#x2026; and Adonoy listened to him.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn258">31</xref></sup> So too here &#x201C;They will implore [God] and they will not be saved&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn259">32</xref></sup> is a case where the word <span dir="rtl">&#x05D9;&#x05B4;&#xFB2A;&#x05B0;&#x05E2;&#xFB35;</span> is refering to the one praying and &#x201C;Adonoy listened&#x2026;&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn260">33</xref></sup> is a case where the word is refering to the [Holy] One being prayed to.</p>
<p><bold>[[43]] I will trample them.</bold> I will trample them. There are many cases like this in the book of Yechezkiel, [such as] &#x201C;You will trample with your feet&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn261">34</xref></sup> [and] &#x201C;You trampled with [your] foot.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn262">35</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[44]] Antagonists.</bold> From Doeg, Achitophel, Shaul and the Ziffites.</p>
<p><bold>You preserved me to be a leader of nations.</bold> He kept me hidden for this purpose. The Midrash Aggadah [interprets our verse], &#x201C;Dovid said, &#x201C;Master of the universe, spare me from [potential] judgement concerning [the people of] Yisroel for if I shall cause [Yisroel] to turn away [from You] or I rule them harshly during the course of my service I will be punished [by You]. Rather, make me the leader of the Pelishtim and let them serve me [because] I will not be punished on their account.</p>
<p><bold>[[45]] Lied to me.</bold> Out of fear they told me lies.</p>
<p><bold>[As soon] as their ears hear [my wish] they listen to [and obey] me.</bold> Even when they are not in my presence they are fearful of me [to the point that as soon] as their ears hear [my wish], they move [to obey] my command.</p>
<p><bold>[[46]] Foreign people will wither.</bold> Will wither [Similar to] the language of &#x201C;I will become withered&#x201D;.<sup><xref rid="fn263">36</xref></sup> Pagisterant in O.F.</p>
<p><bold>They will become lame.</bold> Lame people.</p>
<p><bold>From [the agony of] their imprisonment.</bold> From the tortures of imprisonment that I will inflict upon them.</p>
<p><bold>[[47]] Adonoy lives.</bold> Who does all of this for me.</p>
<ftnote id="fn228"><sup>1</sup>I.e. Why is he being singled out?</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn229"><sup>2</sup>Earlier in 2:30. where Asohel is singled out because he was equal to all of them as Rashi points out there.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn230"><sup>3</sup>Yehoshua 2:1.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn231"><sup>4</sup>Melochim I, 11:1.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn232"><sup>5</sup>Shmuel I, 23:28.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn233"><sup>6</sup>Ibid, 23:19. Dovid&#x2019;s location was betrayed to Shaul but eventually when Shaul reached the crossroads, he chose not to chase after Dovid.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn234"><sup>7</sup>Rashi is explaining why Dovid in effect, says &#x201C;me&#x201D; twice. <span dir="rtl">&#x05DE;&#x05B0;&#x05E4;&#x05B7;&#x05DC;&#x05B0;&#x05D8;&#x05D9;</span> means &#x201C;My Rescuer&#x201D; and <span dir="rtl">&#x05DC;&#x05D9;</span> means &#x201C;me&#x201D;.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn235"><sup>8</sup>It&#x2019;s name in hebrew is <span dir="rtl">&#x05DE;&#x05B7;&#xFB2A;&#x05B0;&#xFB31;&#x05B5;&#x05E8;</span>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn236"><sup>9</sup>Shmuel I, 10:5.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn237"><sup>10</sup><span dir="rtl">&#x05D0;&#x05B6;&#x05E7;&#x05B0;&#x05E8;&#x05B8;&#x05D0;</span> is in past tense and <span dir="rtl">&#x05D5;&#x05B7;&#x05D9;&#x05B4;&#xFB2A;&#x05B0;&#x05DE;&#x05B7;&#x05E2;</span> is in future tense.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn238"><sup>11</sup>Yeshayohu 65:5.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn239"><sup>12</sup>See Shemos 14:20.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn240"><sup>13</sup>Melochim I, 7:33.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn241"><sup>14</sup>I.e., because the previous verse mentioned darkness in connection with God. Furthermore, the verse here is describing punishment meted out to Yisroel&#x2019;s enemies. The verse is telling us that the punishment&#x2019;s source is light.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn242"><sup>15</sup>Kind refers to Avrohom, sincere refers to Yitchok and pure refers to Yakov.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn243"><sup>16</sup>Tehilim 18:27. Chapter 18 of Tehilim is a repetition of this song of Dovid almost verbatim.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn244"><sup>17</sup>Rashi is proving that the root of this word is <span dir="rtl">&#x05E4;&#x05EA;&#x05DC;</span>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn245"><sup>18</sup>Of the previous verses starting from verse 17.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn246"><sup>19</sup>Earlier in our chapter, verse 17.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn247"><sup>20</sup>Not to the people of Yisroel in general.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn248"><sup>21</sup>In Shmuel I, 23:26.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn249"><sup>22</sup>Ibid 23:27.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn250"><sup>23</sup>Earlier in our chapter, verse 25.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn251"><sup>24</sup>In our verse it says <span dir="rtl">&#x05D5;&#x05E0;&#x05D7;&#x05EA;, &#x05D7;&#x05EA;&#x05EA;</span> is it&#x2019;s root.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn252"><sup>25</sup>Tehilim 38:3.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn253"><sup>26</sup>Mishlei 4:12.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn254"><sup>27</sup>The two words <span dir="rtl">&#x05D5;&#x05D0;&#x05D9;&#x05DF; &#x05DE;&#x05D5;&#x05E9;&#x05D9;&#x05E2;</span> need to be removed from their position at the beginning of the verse and placed instead at the end of the verse as its last two words.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn255"><sup>28</sup>Yeshayohu 17:7.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn256"><sup>29</sup>i.e., <span dir="rtl">&#x05D9;&#x05E9;&#x05E2;&#x05D4;</span> means &#x201C;turn to.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn257"><sup>30</sup>Bereishis 4:4.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn258"><sup>31</sup>Bereishis 25:21.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn259"><sup>32</sup>In our verse.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn260"><sup>33</sup>By Hevel&#x2019;s offering.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn261"><sup>34</sup>Yechezkiel 6:11.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn262"><sup>35</sup>Ibid, 25:6.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn263"><sup>36</sup>Yirmiyahu 8:11.</ftnote>
</appendix>
<appendix>
<p><bold>[[1]] These are Dovid&#x2019;s words.</bold> Dovid&#x2019;s last prophecy. What were the first words? The words of the song that were said above.<sup><xref rid="fn264">1</xref></sup> But all the songs and praises that he [Dovid] said are not called &#x201C;words&#x201D;.<sup><xref rid="fn265">2</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>Raised on high.</bold> Raised from Above.<sup><xref rid="fn266">3</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>Sweet songs for Yisroel.</bold> Yisroel does not sing any songs in the Beis Hamikdosh other then his [Dovid&#x2019;s] songs and hymns.</p>
<p><bold>[[2]] Speaks through me.</bold> He bestowed His holy spirit on me and spoke through me. Whenever [the verse refers] to prophecy, the word <span dir="rtl">&#x05D3;&#x05BC;&#x05B4;&#xFB31;&#x05B5;&#x05E8;</span> is appropriate as [we find] &#x201C;Did [Adonoy] only speak to Moshe, He also spoke to us.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn267">4</xref></sup> &#x201C;I will speak through him.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn268">5</xref></sup> The reason for it is because the spirit enters into the prophet and speaks through him.</p>
<p><bold>[[3]] The Rock of Yisroel spoke to me.</bold> The Rock of Yisroel spoke to and commanded me that I should be a ruler over men, over Yisroel who are called &#x201C;men&#x201D; as it is written, &#x201C;You are men.&#x201D; [He also told me] that I will be a righteous person, a ruler and a God fearing person. Our Rabbis interpreted [this verse] with a different explanation:<sup><xref rid="fn269">6</xref></sup> Dovid said [as follows:] &#x201C;The God of Yisroel spoke to me, the Rock of Yisroel spoke to me, I am ruler over men. And who rules over me? The righteous man, because I [may] issue a decree and he [can] annul it.&#x201D; But according to the flow of these verses it is the first explanation that is the simple interpretation of these verses.</p>
<p><bold>[[4]] As day breaks with the sun shining.</bold> He promised me that my glory will continuously grow like the light at day break which gets brighter and brighter.</p>
<p><bold>A cloudless morning.</bold> A light that does not dim.</p>
<p><bold>[Brighter] then the light that comes with the rain that nourishes the land.</bold> My morning is brighter then the light that comes with rain, which is a clear warmth [shining forth] rays of light. When the rain falls on vegetated earth and the sun shines on it and causes it to brighten. And this is how the verse is interpreted, More then the light that comes from rain [falling on] vegetated earth.</p>
<p><bold>[[5]] For is not my house with God.</bold> That I should have a cloudy morning.</p>
<p><bold>For an eternal convenant.</bold> [This refers to] the Torah that He placed for me, that He has arranged for all my household, and kept there.</p>
<p><bold>All my hopes and desires [are before God].</bold> My needs are set before Him. This is a shortened verse.<sup><xref rid="fn270">7</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>Because [my kingdom] will never be outgrown.</bold> There will be no other king after my kingdom.<sup><xref rid="fn271">8</xref></sup> Another interpretation: He has made an eternal convenant for my House, that my kingdom shall be everlasting and this convenant is known to all, it is mentioned by all the prophets.</p>
<p><bold>[[6]] Like an itinerant thorn.</bold>&#160;<italic>Cordon</italic> in O.F. When [this thorn is] young it is soft. It then travels to and fro and eventually hardens until it is [so sharp that it is] unable to be held in one&#x2019;s hand.</p>
<p><bold>[[7]] Any man wanting to touch them should don.</bold> He must cover his body with armor and arm himself with a weapon to cut it down</p>
<p><bold>They will be completely burnt totally consumed by fire.</bold> There is no solution other then burning [these thorns] and to sit and warm oneself by the fire. So too, for the wicked there is no solution other then burning in Gehennom.</p>
<p><bold>[While one] sits.</bold> [A reference to] God sitting on the throne of Judgement.</p>
<p><bold>[[8]] That were with Dovid, who sat in the council.</bold> Who sat in the Sanhedrin Court. That is [alluded to by the word] wisdom. &#x201C;He was a leader in three [distinct areas],&#x201D; He was first in beauty, wisdom and strength. He was the leader in these three categories as it is written &#x201C;[A man] of understanding of attractive build and a strong soldier.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn272">9</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>Adino the Etzonite.</bold> When he was studying Torah he would fold and bind himself up like a worm<sup><xref rid="fn273">10</xref></sup> as [we find, this word in the verse] &#x201C;The bonds of Pleiades.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn274">11</xref></sup> And when he went out to war he was as hard as wood<sup><xref rid="fn275">12</xref></sup> and would kill eight hundred men in one battle.<sup><xref rid="fn276">13</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[9]] The son of Dodo.</bold> This was his name.</p>
<p><bold>One of the three mighty men.</bold> Of the best of the mighty men.<sup><xref rid="fn277">14</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>When they humiliated the Pelishtim.</bold> They made an agreement with each other to fight them and to vanquish them.</p>
<p><bold>[[10]] But only to strip [the corpses].</bold> Yonoson translates: &#x201C;To strip the dead.&#x201D; There was no one to help him kill [the Pelishtim] but they were all stripping the corpses after [he had killed them].</p>
<p><bold>[[11]] From the mountain.</bold> From the mountain.</p>
<p><bold>For [war like] beast in the wild.</bold> [Gathering] to become troops like the beasts gather in the wild.</p>
<p><bold>[[13]] Of the thirty leaders.</bold> Yonoson translates: From the men who were leaders within the army.</p>
<p><bold>[[14]] And a contingent of Pesishtim was then in Beis Lechem.</bold> The [Pelishtim] army was camped in the Rephoim valley and they had sent a contingent to Beis Lechem.</p>
<p><bold>[[15]] Who will give me water to drink.</bold> Our Rabbis said,<sup><xref rid="fn278">15</xref></sup> he [Dovid] needed to ask a [halachic] question from the Sanhedrin court that sat at the gate of Beis Lechem.<sup><xref rid="fn279">16</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[16]] He offered it as a libation to Adonoy.</bold> He said, &#x201C;This is what I learned at Shmuel the Romosi&#x2019;s court: If anyone risks his life for words of Torah,<sup><xref rid="fn280">17</xref></sup> we should not recite the halachah in his name.&#x201D; If so, what is meant by &#x201C;And instead he offerred it as a libation to Adonoy&#x201D;,<sup><xref rid="fn281">18</xref></sup> he [only] recited it in the name of the Gemorah.<sup><xref rid="fn282">19</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[17]] [Do I want] the blood of [these] men.</bold> Language denoting astonishment.</p>
<p><bold>[[19]] He did not reach the status of the first three.</bold> [Yonoson translates:] He did not reach [the status] of the [first] three men.<sup><xref rid="fn283">20</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[20]] The two Moabite giants.</bold> [Yonoson translates:] &#x201C;The two Moabite giants.&#x201D; And our Rabbis said, There was no one like him not during the first [Beis] Mikdosh nor during the second [Beis] Mikdosh.<sup><xref rid="fn284">21</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>Moabite giants.</bold> Because Shlomo who built it came from Rus the Moabite.<sup><xref rid="fn285">22</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[23]] Of the thirty.</bold> Of all thirty in this section. Yonoson translates: &#x201C;mighty men&#x201D;.<sup><xref rid="fn286">23</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[39]] Thirty-seven.</bold> They are not [all] mentioned here<sup><xref rid="fn287">24</xref></sup> and I say Yoav did not have to be mentioned because he was the general [commanding] the army and the rest that are missing it is possible that they are three or four sons of Yeshai.<sup><xref rid="fn288">25</xref></sup></p>
<ftnote id="fn264"><sup>1</sup>22:2.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn265"><sup>2</sup>The use of the word <span dir="rtl">&#x05D3;&#x05BC;&#x05B4;&#x05D1;&#x05B0;&#x05E8;&#x05B5;&#x05D9;</span> here denotes prophecy, not songs and praises.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn266"><sup>3</sup>The word <span dir="rtl">&#x05E2;&#x05B8;&#x05DC;</span>, is used to denote <span dir="rtl">&#x05DC;&#x05B0;&#x05DE;&#x05B7;&#x05E2;&#x05B0;&#x05DC;&#x05B8;&#x05D4;</span>, &#x201C;Above.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn267"><sup>4</sup>Bamidbar 12:2.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn268"><sup>5</sup>Ibid 12:6.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn269"><sup>6</sup>Moed Koton 16b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn270"><sup>7</sup>The verse itself mentions Dovid&#x2019;s hopes and desires but does specify anything further about them.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn271"><sup>8</sup>As God promised Dovid earlier in 7:13 that his kingdom will be eternal.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn272"><sup>9</sup>Shmuel I, 16:18. Rashi is not quoting this verse in its exact order.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn273"><sup>10</sup>Rashi is explaining the name <span dir="rtl">&#x05E2;&#x05B2;&#x05D3;&#x05B4;&#x05D9;&#x05E0;&#xFB4B;</span> as reffering to the word <span dir="rtl">&#x05DE;&#x05B7;&#x05E2;&#x05B2;&#x05D3;&#x05B7;&#xFB40;&#xFB4B;&#x05EA;</span> which means bindings.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn274"><sup>11</sup>Eyuv 38:31.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn275"><sup>12</sup>Here Rashi is explaining the <span dir="rtl">&#x05E2;&#x05B6;&#x05E6;&#x05B0;&#x05E0;&#x05B4;&#x05D9;</span> part of his name which contains within it the word <span dir="rtl">&#x05E2;&#x05B5;&#x05E5;</span> which means wood.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn276"><sup>13</sup>Tanchuma Masoei.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn277"><sup>14</sup>There were more then just three men involved in fighting the Pelishtim.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn278"><sup>15</sup>Baba Kama 60b. See Rashi there.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn279"><sup>16</sup>The &#x201C;water&#x201D; of our verse is referring to Torah which is compared to water. See Devorim Raboh 7:3.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn280"><sup>17</sup>Rashi is continuing with the interpretation of the verse that the water is a reference to words of Torah.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn281"><sup>18</sup>This sounds as if Dovid has accepted the halachic ruling.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn282"><sup>19</sup>The ruling is not to be said over in their name.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn283"><sup>20</sup>i.e. Adino the Etzonite, Elozor, the son of Dodo and Shamoh, the son of Ogaih from the mountain who were enumerated earlier in verses 8, 9 and 11 respectively.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn284"><sup>21</sup>Berochos 18b. Rashi there explains that <span dir="rtl">&#x05D0;&#x05B2;&#x05E8;&#x05B4;&#x05D9;&#x05D0;&#x05B5;&#x05DC;</span> is a name used for the Beis Hamikdash.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn285"><sup>22</sup>Rashi is explaining the connection that <span dir="rtl">&#x05D0;&#x05B2;&#x05E8;&#x05B4;&#x05D9;&#x05D0;&#x05B5;&#x05DC;</span>, a reference to the Beis Hamikdash, has to Moav.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn286"><sup>23</sup>This is how he translates the word <span dir="rtl">&#xFB2A;&#x05B0;&#x05DC;&#xFB2A;&#x05B4;&#x05D9;&#x05DD;</span>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn287"><sup>24</sup>Rashi seems to hold that only thirty-three of the thirty-seven are accounted for, the three first warriors, Adino, Elozor and Ahamoh. Then the thirty that are enumerated starting from verse 24 but not including Asoel, see the Metsudos Dovid on that verse.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn288"><sup>25</sup>Having accounted for thirty-three out of thirty-seven, four are missing. Rashi seems to be offering two distinct possible answers, either the four are Yoav and three of Yeshai&#x2019;s sons or Yoav is not being counted here as part of the group of thirty-seven and the four missing are all sons of Yeshai.</ftnote>
</appendix>
<appendix>
<p><bold>[[1]] Adonoy&#x2019;s anger was again kindled against Yisroel.</bold> I do not know what it was [they did].</p>
<p><bold>He enticed.</bold> Stirred him up.</p>
<p><bold>[[3]] Their [current] number.</bold> [Yoav meant with] the word <span dir="rtl">&#x05DB;&#x05BC;&#x05C7;&#x05D4;&#x05B5;&#x05DD;</span> to convey that their amount should double and the second word <span dir="rtl">&#x05D5;&#x05B0;&#x05DB;&#x05B8;&#x05D4;&#x05B5;&#x05DD;</span>, to convey a second doubling to have now a total of four times [the original population] and then to again double the [new] total for one hundred times.<sup><xref rid="fn289">1</xref></sup> It follows that Yoav&#x2019;s blessing was more then Moshe&#x2019;s who said, &#x201C;One thousand times you [current] number&#x201D;.<sup><xref rid="fn290">2</xref></sup> Furthermore, Moshe&#x2019;s blessing was only [to take effect] a long time [into the future] but Yoav&#x2019;s was intended [to take effect] immediately as it says [here], &#x201C;[With] my master, the king&#x2019;s eyes [being able to] see it.&#x201D;</p>
<p><bold>[[5]] [The valley of] Gad unto Yazer.</bold> He [Yoav] started with the people of Gad because they were hardened warriors. He reasoned, &#x201C;If only they fight me and stop me&#x201D;.<sup><xref rid="fn291">3</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[6]] And to a land of a new [settlement].</bold> A place where there was a new settlement whose population was small; perhaps in the interim Dovid would reconsider and sent him a messenger to stop.</p>
<p><bold>To Don&#x2019;s portion.</bold> To the people of Don.</p>
<p><bold>Ya&#x2019;an.</bold> The name of the place.</p>
<p><bold>[[9]] The sum of the people&#x2019;s census.</bold> If there was a counting, why was a [second] counting [needed]?<sup><xref rid="fn292">4</xref></sup> He [Yoav] made two countings, one major one and one smaller one. He reasoned, &#x201C;I will show him [Dovid] the smaller one and if he gets angry, I will show him the larger one.&#x201D; That is why the verse uses the word <span dir="rtl">&#x05DE;&#x05B4;&#x05E4;&#x05B0;&#x05E7;&#x05B8;&#x05D3;</span> which conveys [that something is] missing. This is how [the verse] is interpreted in the Pesikta.</p>
<p><bold>Yisroel&#x2019;s [total] was.</bold> They became enfeebled like a woman.<sup><xref rid="fn293">5</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>Eight hundred thousand.</bold> But in Divrei Hayomim<sup><xref rid="fn294">6</xref></sup> it says, &#x201C;One million and one hundred thousand&#x201D;? In the Aggadah of the Amoroyim<sup><xref rid="fn295">7</xref></sup> we find, Rabbi Yehoshua, the son of Levi said The verses fill in in one place what is missing in another place; there are two tribes which were not counted<sup><xref rid="fn296">8</xref></sup> because this is what is written in Divrei Hayomim,<sup><xref rid="fn297">9</xref></sup> &#x201C;Levi and Binyomin were not counted among them because the king&#x2019;s command was abhorrent to Yoav.&#x201D; Yoav said, With these [tribes] I can escape [from my commitment] and say [as an excuse] The tribe of Levi is not counted together with the rest of the tribes but [instead] is counted from one month old and up<sup><xref rid="fn298">10</xref></sup> [and as far as] Binyomin [is concerned] it is enough that [their ranks] were depleted by the incident of the concubine in the valley.<sup><xref rid="fn299">11</xref></sup> In the tract about the thirty-two rules [by which the Torah is elucidated] [authored] by Rabbi Eliezer, the son of Rabbi Yosse the Galilite we learned [as follows], one verse says,<sup><xref rid="fn300">12</xref></sup> &#x201C;The [total of] all Yisroel was one million and one hundred thousand&#x2026; and Yehudah [totaled] four hundred and seventy thousand.&#x201D; Another verse says,<sup><xref rid="fn301">13</xref></sup> &#x201C;Yisroel&#x2019;s [total] was eight hundred thousand&#x2026; and the men of Yehudah were five hundred thousand.&#x201D; The difference between the two [accounts] is three hundred thousand.&#x201D; What happenned to them? A third verse redresses the imbalance, &#x201C;The people of Yisroel by their number, of the heads of families and the officers in charge of thousands and of hundreds and their marshals serving the king in all matters pertaining to the division those entering [the service] and those leaving, for every month of the year, each division had twenty-four thousand men.&#x201D; This teaches us that the [missing] three hundred thousand were [already] accounted for in the royal record and did not need to be counted [again].<sup><xref rid="fn302">14</xref></sup> How does this work?<sup><xref rid="fn303">15</xref></sup> Twenty four thousand for [each of the] twelve [months] gives us two hundred and eighty-eight thousand this leaves us with twelve thousand [still unaccounted for] these are the leaders of Yisroel<sup><xref rid="fn304">16</xref></sup> themselves.<sup><xref rid="fn305">17</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[12]] I will afflict you with [one of] three [things].</bold> One of three and so [we find], &#x201C;With two [of my daughters] you will marry [into my family] today&#x201D;,<sup><xref rid="fn306">18</xref></sup> i.e., with one of two. &#x201C;I will take three from you&#x201D; is retribution for the three [curses] you put on Shaul, &#x201C;Either Adonoy will smite him or his day will come and he will die or he will go down to battle and perish.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn307">19</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[14]] I am in great anguish.</bold> The least of them is very difficult.</p>
<p><bold>Let us fall into the hand of Adonoy.</bold> I.e. Pestilence<sup><xref rid="fn308">20</xref></sup> and not the sword nor famine because it [famine] is also controlled by the rich who have store houses of produce. Rabbi Alexandri said, Dovid reasoned, &#x201C;If I choose the sword then [the people of] Yisroel will say [about me], &#x2018;he is relying on his strength to save himself from death but others will die&#x2019;, and if I choose famine they will say, He is relying on his wealth [to save himself]. I will choose pestilence against which everyone is equal.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn309">21</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[15]] From the morning until the appointed time.</bold> [Yonoson translates:] &#x201C;From the time of the slaughtering of the daily morning offering until its blood was sprinkled.&#x201D;</p>
<p><bold>[[16]] The Yevusite.</bold> He was the chief officer of the Zion fortress the name of which is Yevusi.<sup><xref rid="fn310">22</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[20]] Aravnoh saw.</bold> He was hiding from the angel, this is what is written in Divrei Hayomim.<sup><xref rid="fn311">23</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[22]] The rake.</bold> A wooden utensil full of jagged edges which is heavy and it is constantly applied to straw; it cuts it to become fodder to feed the animals:</p>
<p><bold>[[23]] Aravnoh the prince.</bold> He was the chief officer of the Yevusi [fortress].<sup><xref rid="fn312">24</xref></sup></p>
<p><bold>[[24]] Fifty shekolim.</bold> [But] in Divrei Hayomim<sup><xref rid="fn313">25</xref></sup> it says, &#x201C;Golden Shekolim weighing six hundred,&#x201D; how is this possible? [The answer is] he collected fifty silver shekolim from each tribe that is [a total of] six hundred<sup><xref rid="fn314">26</xref></sup> and he gave him an amount of silver that had the value of [six hundred] gold [shekolim]. We also are taught this in the end of Zevochim,<sup><xref rid="fn315">27</xref></sup> &#x201C;He collected an amount of silver that had a value of six hundred gold shekolim, and we also learned this in the Sifri.<sup><xref rid="fn316">28</xref></sup></p>
<ftnote id="fn289"><sup>1</sup>For a total of two hundred times the current population.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn290"><sup>2</sup>Devorim 1:11.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn291"><sup>3</sup>From taking this census.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn292"><sup>4</sup>The verse uses two different words but they both mean &#x201C;counting.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn293"><sup>5</sup><span dir="rtl">&#x05D5;&#x05B7;&#x05EA;&#x05BC;&#x05B4;&#x05D4;&#x05B4;&#x05D9;</span> is the feminine conjugation.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn294"><sup>6</sup>Divrei Hayomim I, 21:5.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn295"><sup>7</sup>Pesikta Raba 11.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn296"><sup>8</sup>And they account for the difference.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn297"><sup>9</sup>Ibid 21:6.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn298"><sup>10</sup>Bamidbar 2:15.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn299"><sup>11</sup>The story is related in Shoftim beginning in chapter 19.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn300"><sup>12</sup>Divrei Hayomim I, 21:5.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn301"><sup>13</sup>Our verse here.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn302"><sup>14</sup>The amount of Yisroel soldiers numbered in Divrei Hayomim is 1,100,000. Subtracting the 800,000 Yisroel soldiers numbered in our verse, we get 300,000.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn303"><sup>15</sup>How do we account for 300,000 using this verse that only mentions 24,000.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn304"><sup>16</sup>The leaders were not included in the 24,000 officers and marshals mentioned in Divrei Hayomim I, 27:1.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn305"><sup>17</sup>Our verse of 800,000 is the figure of those who needed to be counted. the verse in Divrei Hayomim I, 21:5 includes our 800,000 in addition to the 300,000 already accounted for.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn306"><sup>18</sup>Shmuel I, 18:21.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn307"><sup>19</sup>Ibid, 26:10.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn308"><sup>20</sup>Controlled exclusively by God.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn309"><sup>21</sup>Midrash Tehilim 17:4.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn310"><sup>22</sup>Having formerly belonged to them, see earlier verses 5:6&#x2013;5:9.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn311"><sup>23</sup>Divrei Hayomim I, 21:20.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn312"><sup>24</sup>See Rashi earlier on verse 16.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn313"><sup>25</sup>Divrei Hayomim I, 21:25.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn314"><sup>26</sup>12x50&#x003D;600.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn315"><sup>27</sup>116b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn316"><sup>28</sup>Re&#x2019;eh, 10.</ftnote>
</appendix>
</book>