Exodus
<preface>
<title>PREFACE</title>
<p>The publication of the English translation of Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s long commentary on Exodus, whose length is equal to that of the other four books of the Pentateuch, has given me a sense of accomplishment. This was a very formidable task that has taken many years. Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s style makes translation very complicated, and this is compounded in Exodus by its length. As his comments become longer, Ibn Ezra becomes more difficult to understand.</p>
<p>The long commentary, as opposed to the short commentary, was chosen because it is the version included in the <italic>Mikra&#x2019;ot Gedolot</italic> on the Pentateuch. A contributing factor is that Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s chief protagonist, Nachmanides, used it. A full and scholarly discussion of Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s short and long commentaries appears in the <italic>Introduction</italic> that follows.</p>
<p>The long commentary on Exodus is unique. All Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s other works on the Pentateuch, the Prophets, and the Hagiographa are of the short variety. This affords the opportunity to make comparisons and is therefore a work of special importance.</p>
<p>I want to thank everyone who helped in getting this difficult job done. May the Almighty grant us life, health, and the strength to complete the task.</p>
<p>Arthur M. Silver</p>
<p>24 Tevet, 5756</p>
<p>January 16, 1996</p>
</preface>
<preface>
<title>FOREWORD</title>
<p>Students of Biblical exegesis are aware that there are two commentaries on the Book of Exodus ascribed to Rabbi Abraham ibn Ezra, a long commentary referred to as <italic>pirush ha-arokh</italic> and a short commentary referred to as <italic>pirush ha-katzar</italic>. The long commentary (henceforth referred to as L.C.) is about four times the length of the short commentary (henceforth referred to as S.C.) and equals in size Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s commentaries on all of the other four books combined. The S.C., on the other hand, is about the same length as each of the other four commentaries on the Pentateuch that Ibn Ezra composed.</p>
<h1>Short Commentary</h1>
<p>There is no question that the S.C. was composed by Ibn Ezra. It mentions Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s other commentaries on the Pentateuch in places that the L.C. does not. Thus the S.C. mentions Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s comments on Genesis in Ex. 1:11; 22:7; 25:18; and 30:16; his comments on Leviticus in Ex. 3:18; 12:16; and 20:20; his comments on Numbers in Ex. 3:1 and 27:19; and his comments on Deuteronomy in Ex. 14:4; 19:12,17,23; 20:1,18; 21:10; 22:15; 32:22; and 34:5.</p>
<p>Furthermore, the S.C. contains the characteristic anti-midrashic criticisms that are frequently not found in the L.C. (see Ex. 2:10,12; 13:18; 19:13,17; 25:31). There is also a greater tendency to explain difficult terms by reference to Arabic (Ex. 2:13; 6:13; 7:27; 9:21; 12:9; 16:1; 23:19; 24:6; 25:29; 36:8). In addition, &#x201C;The grammarian Ibn Janah is referred to as &#x2018;Rabbi Jonah,&#x2019; as he is in the commentaries on the other books of the Pentateuch, whereas in the L.C. he is referred to as &#x2018;Rabbi Marinus,&#x2019; the title used by Ibn Ezra when referring to him in the books he wrote in France: the commentaries on Daniel; the Minor Prophets and Esther; and in the grammatical works <italic>Sefat Yeter</italic> and <italic>Safah Berurah</italic>&#x201D; (Etan Levine).</p>
<p>Thus stylistically speaking, the S.C. fits in very well with Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s other commentaries on the Pentateuch. They form, as it were, a perfect set. We would thus expect the standard editions of Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s commentaries on the Pentateuch to consist of five relatively short commentaries. However, this is not the case. The <italic>Mikra&#x2019;ot Gedolot</italic> edition of the Pentateuch has the long rather than the short commentary to <italic>Shemot</italic>. The same is true of the <italic>Vat. Ebr.</italic> 38 manuscript (probably composed in the fifteenth century) of Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s commentary on the five books of Moses.</p>
<p>The fact of the matter is that the S.C. on Exodus seems to have been unknown, or at least unavailable, to the Jewish public after the introduction of printing. In 1839, Samuel David Luzzato came across a manuscript of Ibn Ezra containing the S.C. His teacher, Rabbi Yitzchak Shemuel Reggio (Yashar), one of the founders of the Rabbinical Seminar of Italy, obtained the manuscript and published it in 1840. Other editions were put out by Y. L Krinsky, Y. L. Fleischer, and A. Weiser.</p>
<h2>Long Commentary</h2>
<p>While there is no doubt about the authorship of the S.C., some scholars have questioned Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s authorship of the L.C.</p>
<p>Rabbi Joseph ben Eliezer Tov Elem, a fourteenth-century author of an important commentary on Ibn Ezra known as the <italic>Tzafnat Pane&#x2019;ach</italic>, argues that the L.C. is not the work of Ibn Ezra. He writes that he &#x201C;found in the land of the Christians a commentary on Exodus ascribed to Ibn Ezra that was as large as Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s commentaries on the other books (of the Torah).&#x201D; However, he &#x201C;found other works,&#x201D; that is, another commentary on Exodus (the reference is to the S.C.), in the beautiful country (the Land of Israel) and Syria.&#x201D;</p>
<p>Tov Elem then goes on to note that some remarks in the L.C. contradict Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s comments in the S.C. Rabbi Joseph does not list the contradictions. However, compare Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s comments in the long and short commentaries to Ex. 5:9; 11:21; 13:22; and 15:22. Also compare the L.C. on Ex. 18:7 and Gen. 23:7, and the L.C. on Ex. 34:28 and Deut. 10:1.</p>
<p>The L.C. repeats a number of comments found in Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s commentary on Genesis and in his introduction to the Pentateuch (see Gen. 27:19 and Ex. 31:18; Introduction to the Pentateuch and Ex. 12:2). Rabbi Joseph argues that it is not the style of Ibn Ezra to repeat himself.</p>
<p>In Ex. 12:9 we find: &#x201C;Behold, I the writer add to the words of this sage as I heard from his mouth.&#x201D; Rabbi Joseph claims that this shows that Ibn Ezra did not write the L.C.</p>
<p>Rabbi Joseph concludes that all of the above indicates that the L.C. was not composed by Ibn Ezra. He argues that it was put together by one or a number of Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s students who gathered Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s notes or used an earlier edition of Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s short commentary on <italic>Shemot</italic>, elaborated upon them, and thus gave birth to the L.C. on <italic>Shemot</italic>.</p>
<p>Although Rabbi Joseph ben Tov Elem&#x2019;s theory was accepted by the nineteenth-century scholar Shelomo Yehudah Rappaport, the preponderance of scholarly opinion holds that I.E. is the author of the L.C.</p>
<p>I believe that most of the evidence points to Abraham ibn Ezra as the author of the L.C. on Exodus which bears his name. The fact that the L.C. is four times as long as each of Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s other commentaries on the Torah is by itself not a convincing argument that he did not write this work. This is especially so in view of the fact that fragments from a L.C. on Genesis are extant and have been published. The latter proves that Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s commentary on Exodus is not <italic>sui generis</italic>. In fact, it is possible that Ibn Ezra hoped to write a L.C. on all five books of the Torah. Be that as it may, it appears that Ibn Ezra wrote two long commentaries, one on Genesis and one on Exodus and that the one on Exodus survived.</p>
<p>The fact that a student added a note to Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s comment on Ex. 12:9 does not prove that the entire work was composed by a student or students. On the contrary, the fact that the student or copyist bothered to point out that the comment which follows was not written by Ibn Ezra indicates that what precedes and follows his quote did. Furthermore, Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s students occasionally inserted their comments into his other works as well. (See Mal. 1:12 and Ps. 119:103. For a full listing see Melamed, Ezra Tzion. <italic>Mefareshe Ha-Mikra</italic>, Vol. 2, p. 535. Jerusalem, 1978.) Is one to say that these works did not originate with Ibn Ezra because of the insertions?</p>
<p>The fact that some of the interpretations in the L.C. contradict some of those in the short commentaries is not proof that these commentaries are not the work of one hand. First of all, the contradictions are not in basic philosophical outlook. If the S.C. believed in God&#x2019;s corporeality while the L.C. did not, or if the S.C. claimed that astrology is not a true science while the L.C. believed that it was, then it would indicate that these two commentaries are not the work of the same person. However, these are not the sorts of contradictions that differentiate the long and short commentaries. We have differences in the interpretation of Biblical verses. Thus the L.C. explains God&#x2019;s statement, <italic>About midnight will I go out into the midst of Egypt</italic> (Ex. 11:4) as referring to God&#x2019;s decree while the S.C. says it refers to God&#x2019;s messenger. No author is totally consistent over the years. Indeed, it would be strange for an author to repeat himself exactly in a later book. Furthermore, I.E. was constantly on the move. He may not have had copies of his earlier books with him when he wrote his later books. In fact, it is almost certain that they were not in front of him when he wrote, for when Ibn Ezra repeats himself he never does so exactly, as would an author who has his earlier writing in front of him.</p>
<p>In his comments on Ex 3:6 Ibn Ezra writes, &#x201C;I have already explained in the <italic>Sefer Hashem</italic>.&#x201D; Had a student of Ibn Ezra composed the work, he would have written that this is already explained in the <italic>Sefer Hashem</italic>. It is highly unlikely that one of Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s students would assume the mantle of his teacher. Incidentally, the phrase <italic>u-khvar pirashti</italic>, or the like, is one of Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s idiosyncratic expressions. Its use here is further proof of Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s authorship of the L.C.</p>
<p>It should also be noted that when Nahmanides (d. 1273) quotes Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s comments on Exodus he quotes from the L.C. (See Nahmanides&#x2019; commentary on Ex. 2:1,25; 3:2,13; 4:1; 14:19; 28:30). If the L.C. was not the work of Ibn Ezra then Nahmanides would most probably have heard any doubts about authenticity and would not have quoted from it as Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s.</p>
<p>Furthermore, the L.C. contains the ideas and words of Abraham ibn Ezra. Despite its length, practically each sentence and almost every word in this work bear all the idiosyncrasies of Ibn Ezra. Moreover, the ideas and the theology of the L.C. are the same as those of the S.C.</p>
<p>Like all medieval Jewish philosophers, Ibn Ezra believed that God was incorporeal. He interpreted metaphorically all Biblical verses that speak of God. Thus in commenting on Gen. 1:23, Ibn Ezra writes, &#x201C;We know that the Torah spoke the language of man, for it was given to human beings who speak and hear. Now a human being cannot speak of things above or below him without employing human terminology. Hence Scripture uses such terms as <italic>the mouth of the earth</italic> (Num. 16:30), <italic>the hand of the Jordan</italic> (Num. 13:29), and <italic>the head of the dust of the world</italic> (Prov. 8:26).&#x201D; (See <italic>Secret of the Torah</italic>, a translation of Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s <italic>Yesod Morah</italic>.) He makes the same point, employing almost though not exactly the same words, in his comments on Ex. 19:20 and in his <italic>Yesod Morah</italic>.</p>
<p>Ibn Ezra stresses the fact that ideas not words are what count. Thus he notes in chapter one of the <italic>Yesod Morah</italic>, &#x201C;The prophets do not preserve the exact wording when they repeat something. They only preserve its substance. For that is what is important.&#x201D;</p>
<p>He similarly explains in his commentary on Gen. 5:29 why Noah was called <italic>No&#x2019;ach</italic> (rest), not <italic>Menachem</italic>, even though Scripture tells us that Noah was so called because Lemach his father said, <italic>This same shall comfort us</italic> (yenachamenu) <italic>in our work</italic>. Ibn Ezra there observes, &#x201C;Comfort is a relaxation (or rest) of the heart&#x2019;s pain. The Hebrews are more concerned with the idea expressed by a word than with its etymology.&#x201D;</p>
<p>This is precisely how Ibn Ezra resolves the differences in wording between the Decalogue in Exodus and that of Deuteronomy. Ibn Ezra writes, &#x201C;Know, words are like bodies and their meanings are like souls&#x201D; (Ex. 20:1). He goes on to say that the words used are unimportant if the meaning remains unchanged.</p>
<p>Similarly, Ibn Ezra says that it makes no difference whether Scripture employs full or defective spelling. Thus in the introduction to his commentary on the Torah he writes, &#x201C;I will not make mention of the reasons offered by the Masoretes as to why certain words are at times spelled full and at other times defectively because all their reasons are of a midrashic nature. The fact is that Scripture sometimes fully and clearly spells out a word and at other times omits an unpronounced letter for the sake of brevity. Since the Masoretes claim to be able to explain the reasons for full and defective spellings, let them tell us what spelling the scribes should have used in writing Scripture.&#x201D; He makes the same point employing similar language in Ex. 20:1.</p>
<p>In Ex. 3:15 Ibn Ezra explains the numerical significance of the letters making up the divine name. What he writes there is parallel to what he writes in his <italic>Sefer Ha-Shem</italic> and in chapter eleven of the <italic>Yesod Morah</italic>.</p>
<p>Ibn Ezra was an astrologer, and many of his Biblical interpretations are based on astrological beliefs. He thus hints that the flood came about as a result of unfavorable heavenly conjunctions (Gen. 14:4), and that Noah took the &#x201C;aspects&#x201D; into consideration when he sent the raven and doves from the ark (Gen. 8:5). He also offers an astrological interpretation for Laban&#x2019;s teraphim (Gen. 14:19).</p>
<p>We find the same astrological influence in the L.C. Ibn Ezra thus offers an astrological interpretation for the breastplate and the <italic>urim</italic> and <italic>thumim</italic> worn by the high priest (Ex. 38:6). Incidentally this interpretation is essentially the same as the one he offers for these objects in chapter nine of his <italic>Yesod Morah</italic>. He also speaks of the influence of the stars in his comments on Ex. 20:14 and 14:2. Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s explanation of the idol <italic>Baal-Zephon</italic> in Ex. 14:2 is in keeping with his explanation of Laban&#x2019;s teraphim in Genesis; that is, Ibn Ezra interprets them as astrological objects.</p>
<p>In his comments on Ex. 29:18 Ibn Ezra claims that it is wrong to seek medical care for natural illnesses. He goes on to say that Scripture criticized King Asa of Judah for seeking the aid of physicians rather than that of the Lord. Ibn Ezra makes this same point in chapter seven of the <italic>Yesod Morah</italic>.</p>
<p>On Ex. 20:1 he claims there is a reason behind each and every commandment in Scripture and that an intelligent person can discover these reasons. He makes the same point in chapter eight of the <italic>Yesod Morah</italic>.</p>
<p>Ibn Ezra on Ex. 20:1 notes that Abraham, who lived before the revelation at Sinai, kept only the rational laws. He makes the same point in his comments on Gen. 26:5 and in chapter five of the <italic>Yesod Morah</italic>.</p>
<p>In his comments on Gen. 27:19, Ibn Ezra writes, &#x201C;Prophets are divided into two groups. One group consists of God&#x2019;s messengers concerning commandments; the other, those who foretell the future.&#x201D; He refers to the first type of prophet as <italic>sheli&#x2019;ach be-mitzvot</italic> and the second type as <italic>navi ha-atid</italic>. Ibn Ezra follows this distinction in his notes on Ex. 12:1, where he notes that the commandments were revealed only through Moses and Aaron, for they alone were prophets of the law (<italic>nevi&#x2019;e ha-torah</italic>).</p>
<p>In Ex. 14:30 Ibn Ezra says that <italic>and Israel saw the Egyptians dead upon the sea-shore</italic> is to be read as if written: and Israel upon the sea-shore saw the Egyptians dead. He makes the same point in chapter five of the <italic>Yesod Morah</italic>.</p>
<p>Ibn Ezra believed that reason plays an essential role in interpreting Scripture. In his comments on Ex. 20:1 he argues that Biblical statements which contradict reason are not to be taken literally. He makes the same point in the introduction to his commentary on the Torah and in the <italic>Yesod Morah</italic> (chap. 7, p. 10). He writes in the former, &#x201C;Every precept, be it minor or major, must be weighed in the scale of one&#x2019;s heart wherein the Eternal has planted some of His wisdom. Thus if there appears something in the Torah that is intellectually impossible to accept or contrary to the evidence of our senses, then we must search for a hidden meaning. This is so because intelligence is the basis of the Torah. The Torah was not given to ignoramuses. Man&#x2019;s intelligence is the angel which mediates between him and his God.&#x201D;</p>
<p>Although Ibn Ezra consistently emphasizes reason he often exhibits a simple faith and takes issue with those who do not interpret certain Biblical narratives literally. He disagrees with those who interpret Scripture&#x2019;s account of the Garden of Eden symbolically. Ibn Ezra writes, &#x201C;Note, the story of the Garden of Eden is to be interpreted literally. There is no doubt that it happened exactly as described in Scripture (Gen. 3:24).&#x201D;</p>
<p>He comments similarly on the verse telling us that the Lord made garments of skin for Adam and Eve (Gen. 3:21). There he notes, &#x201C;One should&#x2026;not bother to inquire into this matter. We ought to believe that God made garments of skin for Adam and Eve. Who can recount all of God&#x2019;s mighty acts? Who can tell of all of His wonders? There is no end to God&#x2019;s greatness.&#x201D;</p>
<p>The same trusting faith is displayed by Ibn Ezra in his remarks on the verse which relates that Moses&#x2019; staff turned into a serpent when cast on the ground (Ex. 4:3). Ibn Ezra notes that some commentators attempt to explain this phenomenon &#x201C;scientifically.&#x201D; However, he disagrees with their explanations, insisting that the verse deals with a miraculous occurrence.</p>
<p>When the rabbis of the Talmud offer an interpretation of a Biblical text which does not contradict its plain meaning, Ibn Ezra accepts the Rabbinic interpretation even though other interpretations of the text are equally plausible. Thus in the introduction to his commentary on the Pentateuch (pp. 18 and 19) Ibn Ezra writes, &#x201C;However, with regard to verses which deal with laws, statutes, and regulations, if we find two possible interpretations for a verse and one of them is in keeping with the interpretation of the transmitters of tradition, all of whom were righteous men, then without reservation and with all our might we will rely on the truth of their words.&#x201D; Ibn Ezra makes the same point in his comments on Lev. 22:22 and Deut. 5:25; 6:3; 25:5. He makes similar points in his L.C. on Ex. 12:2,8,22.</p>
<p>Ibn Ezra not only accepts Rabbinic interpretations whenever they appear to follow the plain meaning of the text, he goes a step further and defends the Rabbinic tradition against attacks made upon it by the Karaites. (See his Introduction to the Pentateuch; Lev. 7:23; 23:11; 25:9,20.) We similarly find this to be the case with the L.C. (See Ex. 12:1; 34:21; 35:2.)</p>
<p>Although Ibn Ezra engages in anti-Karaite polemics and refers to them as Sadducees and heretics, he occasionally quotes their interpretations with deference. (Compare Gen. 9:26; 28:12; 49:27; Lev. 16:1; 23:15.)</p>
<p>We find that the same is true in Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s L.C. (See Ex. 3:2; 4:3; 5:5; 6:13; 7:3,10,12,29; 8:13,22; 9:16; 10:5,6; 12:2,3,5,19,29; 13:1; 17:16; 19:8; 22:7; 25:4,17,20; 35:5.)</p>
<p>Ibn Ezra believes that many of the Biblical narratives are not in chronological order. He thus points out that Abraham&#x2019;s call to leave his father&#x2019;s house occurred before Terah left Ur of the Chaldeans even though Scripture tells us of Terah&#x2019;s departure before it relates God&#x2019;s call to Abraham (Gen. 12:1). He similarly notes (Gen. 38:1) that the incident of Judah and Tamar (Gen. 38) occurred before Joseph was sold into bondage even though Scripture records it after the account of Joseph&#x2019;s enslavement (Gen. 37).</p>
<p>Ibn Ezra also points out that Lev. 25:1; 26:25,46; Num. 3:1; 19:2; Deut. 31:1; and Deut. 31:15 are not in chronological order.</p>
<p>He makes similar remarks on Exodus in his L.C. He thus explains that the command to record God&#x2019;s eternal war with Amalek was given in the fortieth year of Israel&#x2019;s sojourn in the desert even though it is recorded in Ex. 17:14.</p>
<p>Ibn Ezra maintains that Jethro came to the wilderness of Sinai in the second year following the Exodus from Egypt. He thus argues that Ex. 18, which tells of Jethro&#x2019;s journey to Sinai, is out of chronological order. Ibn Ezra likewise maintains that Korah&#x2019;s rebellion, recorded in Num. 16:17, actually took place as soon as the tabernacle was erected and Aaron was chosen as high priest (Ex. 32:29).</p>
<p>There are certain stylistic idiosyncrasies which reveal the L.C. to be the work of Ibn Ezra. For example, Ibn Ezra often employs a <italic>mem</italic> in the sense of &#x201C;to.&#x201D; Thus in Gen. 1:5, Ibn Ezra writes, &#x201C;<italic>Erev</italic> (evening) is close in meaning (<italic>karov mi-ta&#x2019;am</italic>) to <italic>choshekh</italic> (darkness).&#x201D; He similarly writes in Gen. 2:11, &#x201C;The Gihon is close to the Land of Israel (<italic>karov me-eretz yisrael</italic>).&#x201D; In commenting on the word <italic>afilot</italic> (Ex. 10:31), Ibn Ezra writes, &#x201C;The word <italic>afel</italic> (very dark) in <italic>Even very dark, and no brightness in it</italic> (Amos 5:20) is close in meaning to it (<italic>karov me-menu</italic>).&#x201D;</p>
<p>When Ibn Ezra defines the meaning of a word he occasionally employs the term <italic>kemo</italic> (literally, like). (Compare, Gen. 45:11; 46:13; Lev. 24:23; 27:14; Num. 22:35; Deut. 29:8. We find that he employs the word <italic>kemo</italic> in the same way in the L.C. See Ex. 9:16; 10:8; 14:7.)</p>
<p>When I.E. wants to introduce a refutation of a given argument he occasionally uses the formula <italic>ve-im ta&#x2019;an to&#x2019;en&#x2026;u-teshuvatam</italic> (if one should argue&#x2026;they would answer) (Gen. 18:13) or the like (Lev. 24:43). Similarly, in the L.C. in Ex. 12:2 Ibn Ezra reads, <italic>ve-im ta&#x2019;an ha-to&#x2019;en&#x2026;ha-teshuvah</italic> (if one should argue&#x2026;the answer is).</p>
<p>When Ibn Ezra wants to point out that an interpretation is impossible he occasionally uses the term <italic>ekh</italic> (how). Thus in taking issue with those who identify the serpent with Satan, he writes: &#x201C;How (<italic>ekh</italic>) is Satan to crawl upon his belly or eat the dust of the ground (Gen. 31)?&#x201D; Ibn Ezra employs similar language in the L.C. on Ex. 15:22. There he takes issue with those who say that the booths in which the Israelites are commanded to dwell during the festival of Sukkot are in commemoration of the clouds of glory which covered the camp of Israel during their sojourn in the desert. He notes that Scripture explicitly states that the booths recall Israel&#x2019;s dwelling places in the desert of Sinai. He then goes on to say, &#x201C;How (<italic>ekh</italic>) did Israel dwell in clouds?&#x201D;</p>
<p>I.E. often quotes verses from memory. In so doing, he occasionally errs. (See Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s quotes from Ps. 94:4 in Gen. 36:24 and from I Kings 14:3 in Num. 32:49.) We find the same pattern in Exodus (L.C.). (See Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s quote from Lev. 25:39 in Ex. 1:14 and his quote from II Kings 8:22 in Ex. 34:6.)</p>
<p>Ibn Ezra occasionally uses sarcasm, word plays, and puns at the expense of those with whom he disagrees. (See Gen. 9:21; 12:13; 20:16; 28:17; 36:31; Is. 7:3; Amos 3:15; Job 5:7.) We find the same sarcasm and puns in the L.C. (See Ex. 4:31; 13:13,20; 20:23; 21:35; 34:21.)</p>
<p>Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s interpretations are often extremely down to earth. He explains that Isaac sent Esau out to hunt for food because he was very poor and had little livestock at home. He thus notes that Isaac loved Esau because he needed him to provide food for his table. Ibn Ezra explains that Esau despised the birthright because Isaac had nothing to leave him.</p>
<p>Ibn Ezra likewise believed that Rebecca spoke like a typical mother when she took upon herself any curse that Isaac might place upon Jacob. He likewise notes that Abraham, Jacob, and other Biblical characters were not above bending the truth when they had to.</p>
<p>The same down-to-earth interpretations are displayed in the L.C. Thus Ibn Ezra notes that God arranged for Moses to be raised in Pharaoh&#x2019;s palace and not among the Hebrew slaves so that he would grow up with the personality of a nobleman rather than that of a slave (Ex. 2:3). Ibn Ezra similarly explains that the Israelites did not turn and fight the Egyptians who pursued them because slaves do not ordinarily wage war against their masters (Ex. 14:13). He further writes that God sentenced the generation that left Egypt to die in the desert because they did not have the emotional stamina to conquer the promised land, as they were born and bred in slavery (<italic>Ibid.</italic>).</p>
<h2>Which Came First?</h2>
<p>What remains to be decided is which commentary came first; that is, did Ibn Ezra first write a S.C. and then decide to elaborate upon it, or did he write a L.C. and then decide to abridge it? Students of Ibn Ezra are divided on this point. Nevertheless, by examining and analyzing the works one can arrive at a satisfactory answer.</p>
<p>There is some textual evidence that the S.C. preceded the L.C. The scholar Y.L. Fleisher points out that in the S.C. on Ex. 25:31, I.E. refers to those who believe that the word <italic>te&#x2019;aseh</italic> (be made) should be spelled with a <italic>yod</italic> as <italic>chasere da&#x2019;at</italic> (lacking intelligence). However, in his L.C., I.E. notes that the wise men of Tiberias, who carefully went over every word in Scripture, maintain that the word <italic>te&#x2019;aseh</italic> in Ex. 25:31 is spelled with a <italic>yod</italic>. I.E. does not take issue with the wise men of Tiberias. He merely notes that in the Spanish editions of the Torah the word is spelled without a <italic>yod</italic>. He then goes on say that according to the rules of grammar the word should be spelled without a <italic>yod</italic>, and if the Tiberian reading is correct then <italic>te&#x2019;aseh</italic> in Ex. 25:31 is an exception to the rule.</p>
<p>It is thus clear that when I.E. wrote the S.C. he was not aware of the opinion of the Tiberian scholars, but he was aware of it when he wrote the L.C. This indicates that the S.C. came first. Otherwise we have to assume that I.E. was aware of the opinion of the Tiberians, mentioned them in his commentary, and then forgot their opinion, referring to those who held a similar opinion as &#x201C;lacking intelligence.&#x201D; That hardly makes sense.</p>
<p>Furthermore, if one writes a long commentary and abbreviates it, then a comparison of the two works indicates that one is an abridged version of the other. This is not the case with the L.C. and S.C. While there are parallels between the commentaries, and some materials of the S.C. are in the L.C., the short commentary does not seem to be an abridged version of the long commentary. It thus appears that I.E. wrote a S.C. on the Pentateuch and then a long commentary.</p>
<p>Finally, it is clear that the S.C. on Exodus fits in with I.E.&#x2019;s comments on Genesis, Exodus, Leviticus, Numbers, and Deuteronomy. They form a set. Thus there is no doubt that I.E. wrote and completed a short commentary on the Pentateuch.</p>
<p>We also have a second version of I.E.&#x2019;s Introduction to the Pentateuch plus fragments of a long commentary on Genesis in addition to our L.C. on Exodus.</p>
<p>Unless there is some compelling evidence to the contrary, which there is not, the normal course of human events would dictate that I.E. first completed a short commentary on the Pentateuch and then set out to work on his long commentary. However, for one reason or another he was never able to complete his work.</p>
<p>One would reach the same conclusion if the opposite were true, that is, if we had a long commentary on the entire Pentateuch and a short commentary on Genesis and Exodus. In that case, we would say that I.E. first completed his long commentary and then started work on a short commentary which he never completed.</p>
<p>The latter becomes even more compelling when we consider the fact that at the age of sixty-four I.E. became ill and promised to write a commentary on the Pentateuch if God would restore him to health. Furthermore, in the L.C., in his poem introducing the Torah portion <italic>Yitro</italic>, I.E. alludes to his weakened condition. He speaks of the loss of half of his strength and of being a prisoner of hope, i.e., hoping to be restored to full health.</p>
<p>Finally, I.E. refers to his commentary on Exodus as &#x201C;the very ark&#x2026;which the author prepared for himself.&#x201D; The &#x201C;ark&#x201D; alludes to a coffin. I.E. is apparently saying that his commentary will serve as his memorial. This certainly appears to be the writing of a person who feels that his life is drawing to a close.</p>
<p>In conclusion, the likely scenario is that I.E. completed what we now consider the short commentary on the Pentateuch, and then started writing his long commentary. He was able to complete only the commentary on Genesis, which is lost except for a few extracts, and the long commentary on Exodus, which we have. He died before he could write any more.</p>
<p>H. Norman Strickman</p>
<p>Touro College</p>
<p>24 Tevet, 5756</p>
<p>January 16, 1996</p>
</preface>
DEUTERONOMY
<preface>
<title>FOREWORD</title>
<p>In the introduction to the Book of Genesis, note was taken of Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s influence on biblical exegesis. However, Ibn Ezra was not only a great Bible commentator, he was also a profound thinker who greatly influenced Jewish philosophical and mystical thought. Hence, as we approach the conclusion of Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s commentary on the Pentateuch a discussion of this commentary&#x2019;s influence on the development of Jewish thought seems appropriate.</p>
<h1>MAIMONIDES</h1>
<p>Moses Maimonides was beyond doubt the greatest medieval Jewish philosopher. Students of Jewish philosophy have noted a close affinity between the philosophical writings of Abraham Ibn Ezra and those of Moses Maimonides. Entire passages in Maimonides&#x2019; <italic>Guide for the Perplexed</italic> (translated by M. Friedlander, Dover Publishing Co., New York, 1956, reprint of the 1904 revised edition) appear to elaborate points made by Ibn Ezra.</p>
<p>Ibn Ezra believed that man&#x2019;s uniqueness lies in his intellect. He tells us that &#x201C;man&#x2019;s intelligence is the angel which mediates between him and his God&#x201D; (I.E., Vol. 1, Introduction, p. 10). Maimonides held a similar point of view (<italic>Guide</italic>, 1:1, p. 14; 3:51, p. 386).</p>
<p>Ibn Ezra held that the Torah is to be interpreted in accordance with the dictates of reason. He believed that &#x201C;every precept, be it minor or major, must be weighed in the scale of one&#x2019;s heart wherein the Eternal has planted some of his wisdom. Thus when there appears something in the Torah that is intellectually impossible to accept or contrary to the evidence of our senses, then we must search for a hidden meaning. This is so because intelligence is the basis of the Torah. The Torah was not given to ignoramuses&#x201D; (I.E., Vol. 1, Introduction, p. 10).</p>
<p>Maimonides had an identical notion. In fact, one of his reasons for writing the <italic>Guide for the Perplexed</italic> was to interpret traditional Jewish teachings in accordance with the dictates of reason (Introduction to the <italic>Guide</italic>, p. 2). One of his methods of doing so is to attribute secret meanings to passages in the Bible, Talmud, and Midrash which contradict reason (<italic>Ibid.</italic>, p. 3).</p>
<p>Ibn Ezra believed that there are secret interpretations of the Torah that are best kept from the common people and that it is necessary to write in such a way that only the initiated will understand. Thus he notes that there is a bird that cannot see on sunny days and is able to see only at night. In other words, some people are better kept in the dark, for they cannot comprehend the full truth (I.E., Vol. 1, Introduction, p. 14). Throughout his commentary Ibn Ezra hints at secrets, either by actually saying so or by such statements as <italic>and the intelligent will understand</italic>, or <italic>I cannot explain</italic>, or <italic>a secret</italic> (sod) <italic>is hidden here</italic>.</p>
<p>This is precisely the method chosen by Maimonides in the <italic>Guide</italic>. In a sentence reminiscent of Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s parable of the bird that cannot see during the day, Maimonides writes that Scripture spoke in metaphors &#x201C;in order that the educated may comprehend it according to the measure of their faculties and the feebleness of their apprehension, while the educated persons may take it in a different sense&#x201D; (<italic>Guide</italic>, Introduction, p. 4).</p>
<p>According to Ibn Ezra man gains immortality by developing his soul. &#x201C;If the soul grows wise it will share the secrets of the angels and will then cleave to God the Glorious&#x201D; (I.E. on Ex. 3:15; see also <italic>Yesod Mora</italic>, 1). Maimonides had a similar notion (<italic>Guide</italic>, 3:8, p. 26; 3:54, p. 395).</p>
<p>According to the Talmud the expression <italic>dibberah torah kelashon bene adam</italic> (the Torah spoke in the language of man) is employed only in a <italic>halakhic</italic> sense. No laws are to be extended or derived from what appears to be biblical verbosity, as in the phrase <italic>hikaret yikaret</italic> (shall utterly be cut off) (Num. 15:31), or <italic>ish ish</italic> (any man) (Lev. 15:2), or <italic>ganev yigganev</italic> (but if it be stolen) (Ex. 22:11).</p>
<p>Ibn Ezra also applies the above to those parts of Scripture which speak of God in human terms. Thus in commenting on Gen. 1:26 (Vol. 1, p. 46,47) Ibn Ezra writes: &#x201C;We know that the Torah spoke the language of man, for it was given to humans who speak and hear. Now a human being cannot speak of things above or below him without employing human terminology. Hence Scripture uses such terms as <italic>the mouth of the earth</italic> (Num. 16:30), <italic>the hand of the Jordan</italic> (Num. 13:29), and <italic>the head of the dust of the world</italic>&#x201D; (Prov. 8:26).</p>
<p>Similarly in commenting on <italic>for in six days the Lord made heaven and earth and He ceased from work and rested on the seventh day</italic>, I.E. writes, <italic>ve-hatorah dibberah ke-lashon bene adam</italic> (the Torah spoke in the language of man) (I.E. on Ex. 31:17, Vol. 2, p. 652).</p>
<p>Maimonides follows suit in his commentary on the Mishnah (Introduction to Chapter 10 of <italic>Sanhedrin</italic>); in his <italic>Mishneh Torah</italic> (<italic>Hilkhot Yesode Ha-Torah</italic>, 1:9); and in the <italic>Guide for the Perplexed</italic> (1:26,27, pp. 35,36).</p>
<p>There are many <italic>aggadot</italic> in the Talmud which run counter to reason. Ibn Ezra claimed that many of these <italic>aggadot</italic> have a secret meaning. &#x201C;There is a secret meaning to the midrashic statement to the effect that the world will exist for 6,000 years (I.E. on Gen. 1:15, Vol. 1, p. 33); as to the Midrash which states one (the sun) was not greater than the other (the moon), there is a secret meaning to it&#x201D; (I.E. on Gen. 1:16, Vol. 1, p. 39). &#x201C;The Rabbinic statement that Noah drank from his vineyard on the day he planted it is not to be taken literally&#x201D; (I.E. on Gen. 9:20, Vol. 1, p. 127). &#x201C;Our sages say that God showed Moses the knot of the <italic>tefillin</italic>. These words are correct. However, its meaning is not in accordance with that of the wise men of this generation who interpret the Rabbinic statement literally. On the contrary, this has a deeply hidden secret meaning&#x201D; (I.E. on Ex. 33:21, Vol. 2, p. 693).</p>
<p>Maimonides similarly believed that many <italic>aggadot</italic> have a hidden meaning. In his introduction to the <italic>Guide</italic> he tells us that he refrained from writing a work explaining the <italic>aggadot</italic> because when a person who is both religious and well-educated reads them he will either take them literally and question the reasoning abilities of their author (which, according to Maimonides offers no challenge to faith), or he will assume that the passages in question has some secret meaning (<italic>Guide</italic>, Introduction, p. 5).</p>
<p>Speaking of God, Ibn Ezra writes: <italic>&#x201C;Hu le-vado yode&#x2019;a, veda&#x2019;at ve-yadu&#x2019;a</italic> (He is the knower, the content of His thought, and the object of His thought)&#x201D; (Ex. 34:6).</p>
<p>This dictum is often quoted by Maimonides (Introduction to Tractate <italic>Avot</italic>; <italic>Hilkhot Yesode Ha-Torah</italic> 2:10). He also devoted an entire chapter of the <italic>Guide for the Perplexed</italic> (1:68) to explaining this concept.</p>
<p>The medieval Jewish philosophers were concerned with explaining the divine commandments. Saadiah Gaon divided the commandments into traditional (a-rational) commandments and rational commandments. Ibn Ezra disagreed with this differentiation. Believing that all the divine commandments are rational, he argues: &#x201C;All of the commandments fall into one of the following two categories. One category consists of rational laws which God implanted into the minds of all intelligent human beings. There are many such commandments. The only one of the Ten Statements which does not fall into this category is the command to observe the Sabbath&#x2026;The second category that the precepts fall into is that of &#x2018;Hidden Commandments,&#x2019; that is, commandments for which the Torah does not reveal any reason. Far be it, far be it for one to even think that any of these commandments contradict reason. We must in all instances observe everything that God has commanded us, whether their secret has or has not been revealed to us&#x2026;(we) must search for its meaning in the books of the wise men, of blessed memory&#x2026;we must investigate and try to understand it with all our strength&#x201D; (I.E. on Ex. 20:1, Vol. 2, pp. 407-409).</p>
<p>Maimonides accepted Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s premise. He too asserts that all commandments of the Torah have a purpose and that their purposes can be discovered (<italic>Guide</italic>, 3:26, pp. 310-312).</p>
<p>However, Maimonides differs with some of the reasons which Ibn Ezra gave for the commandments. Ibn Ezra believed that some commandments, such as the ones concerning priestly garments and the temple service, have astrological or mystical import (I.E. on Ex. 25:40, Vol. 2, pp. 558-562; Ex. 20:5, Vol. 2, pp. 591-598). Maimonides disagreed. He gave a purely rational explanation for all the commandments.</p>
<p>Ibn Ezra held that ultimate religious development requires an ascetic life. &#x201C;Note that most people are slaves to worldly lusts. The true king, the one who has a crown, the one who wears the royal diadem, is the person who is free from this lust&#x201D; (I.E. on Num. 6:7, Vol. 4, p. 43). I.E. believed that Moses refrained from sexual relations with his wife because of his spirituality (I.E. on Num. 12:1, Vol. 4, p. 94, and notes thereto). Maimonides had a similar notion (<italic>Guide</italic>, 3:8, p. 263).</p>
<p>Ibn Ezra considered man to be a microcosm (<italic>olam katan</italic>) (Ibn Ezra on Gen. 1:26). Maimonides agreed with this concept (<italic>Guide</italic>, 1:72, pp. 113-119).</p>
<p>It is impossible to say how much Maimonides actually took from Ibn Ezra. However, there can be no doubt that the influence was substantial.</p>
<h1>OTHER JEWISH SCHOLARS AND MOVEMENTS</h1>
<p>The writings of Ibn Ezra served as basic texts for many Jewish scholars. Leon Jehuda Mosconi, who wrote a supercommentary on Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s commentary on the Pentateuch (between 1362 and 1370), noted that he was aware of thirty supercommentaries on Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s works. Solomon Delmedigo of Candia (1591-1655) similarly reported seeing some twenty-four commentaries on Ibn Ezra in Constantinople.</p>
<p>Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s thinking not only influenced Jewish philosophers, it also affected mystical trends of Jewish thought. The writings of Ibn Ezra influenced the <italic>Haside Ashkenaz</italic>, the Kabbalists [I. Tishby, <italic>The Wisdom of the Zohar</italic> (Hebrew), Israel, 1957, pp. 90,91], and the Hasidic movement.</p>
<p>Ibn Ezra taught that God is one. He is the creator of all. He is all. According to Ibn Ezra, God&#x2019;s relationship to the world is comparable to the relationship of the number &#x201C;one,&#x201D; which is the first all numbers and is found in all numbers (I.E. on Ex. 33:21, Vol. 2, p. 695). Similarly, the world emanated from God, and from this aspect God can be said to be all. The Hasidic movement has a similar belief. Hasidic doctrine stresses that there is no place devoid of God&#x2019;s presence (<italic>let atar panuy mineh</italic>) (Sheneyur Zalman of Ladi, <italic>Tanya</italic>, 22; <italic>Iggeret Ha-Rav</italic>, 1:218).</p>
<p>Ibn Ezra held that the true religious life consists in directing one&#x2019;s thoughts to God and cleaving to God. In his commentary on Num. 20:8 he writes, &#x201C;When the part (man) knows the All (God), he cleaves (<italic>yidbak</italic>) to the All and creates signs and wonders with the help of the All.&#x201D; I.E. believed that cleaving to God will ultimately lead to eternal life (Deut. 11:22). This is the purpose of the commandments. Thus Ibn Ezra writes: &#x201C;The intelligent man will&#x2026;isolate himself for the purpose of studying and mediating upon God&#x2019;s law and observing the Lord&#x2019;s precepts&#x2026;His soul will cleave to God and enjoy the fullness of the joy of God&#x2019;s presence&#x2026;&#x201D;(<italic>Yesod Mora</italic>, Chapter 7).</p>
<p>The above came to be known as the practice of <italic>devekut</italic> (cleaving to God). The concept of <italic>devekut</italic> is a prime element in Jewish mystical thought. Rabbi Jehiel Michal of Zlotchov describes the experience of <italic>devekut</italic> as follows: &#x201C;A man&#x2019;s heart should be constantly in dread and awe of God and that the love of God should burn always in his heart&#x2026;All man&#x2019;s psychological faculties [must be devoted to] clear and pure thoughts on God constantly, and in separation from every pleasure&#x201D; (<italic>Derekh Emet</italic> quoted in <italic>Hasidic Prayer</italic> by Louis Jacobs, pp. 20,21). According to the great eighteenth-century kabbalist Rabbi Moshe Chaim Luzzato, <italic>devekut</italic> means &#x201C;directing oneself to God. It means recognizing God every day and finding ways to understand His presence in the world. This could include the study of holy books. This could take the form of prayer or meditation&#x201D; (Gila Nievwenholzon-Gerzoni, <italic>The Works of Unification and Devekut in the Writings of Moshe Chaim Luzzato</italic>, p. 7). It is noteworthy that the Hasidic movement, which would be expected to be critical of Ibn Ezra, actually had a positive attitude toward him. This was because they felt a special affinity for Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s spiritual side. Thus Rabbi Simchah Bunim of Peshischa is reported to have said that he could not understand how Ibn Ezra was able to remain alive here on earth in view of his great piety and fear of God (M.H. Cherez, <italic>Commentary on Ibn Ezra</italic>, Gen. p. 9). The leader of Chabad, Rabbi Yosef Yitzchak, reports that it is traditional among the <italic>Chabad Chasidim</italic> to alternate yearly the study of the weekly Torah portions between Rashi and Ibn Ezra, Rashi and Nahmanides, and Rashi and the Or Ha-Chayyim.</p>
<p>Rabbi Pinchus of Koretz greatly loved Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s commentaries. He argued that Ibn Ezra had the soul of a <italic>tanna</italic>, a teacher of the Mishnah, and hence had the authority to disagree with Rabbinic sages. Rabbi Pinchus was careful to chant Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s Sabbath song, &#x201C;If I keep the Sabbath, God will keep me,&#x201D; every Friday night (Isaac Weiss, <italic>Elef Katav</italic>, Bene Brak, 1997, &#x0023;481).</p>
<h1>SPINOZA</h1>
<p>Baruch Spinoza is considered the father of modem Biblical criticism. Spinoza did not believe that Moses was the author of the Pentateuch. He claimed that Ibn Ezra had a similar belief. Spinoza writes:</p>
<p align="blockquote">In order to treat the subject methodically, I will begin with the received opinions concerning the true authors of the sacred books, and in the first place speak of the author of the Pentateuch, who is almost universally supposed to have been Moses. The Pharisees are so firmly convinced of his identity, that they account as a heretic anyone who differs from them on the subject. Wherefore, Aben Ezra, a man of an enlightened intelligence, and no small learning, who was the first, so far as I know, to treat of this opinion, dared not express his meaning openly, but confined himself to dark hints which I shall not scruple to elucidate, thus throwing full light on the subject (<italic>A Logico-Political treatise</italic>, Chapter 7).</p>
<p>Was Spinoza correct?</p>
<p>In his commentary on the Pentateuch, I.E. hints that there are verses or parts of verses in the Pentateuch which are post-Mosaic. Thus in commenting on <italic>And the Canaanite was then in the land</italic> (Gen. 12:6), which implies that the Canaanites were no longer in the land when this part of the verse was written, I.E. notes, &#x201C;It is possible that the Canaanites seized the land from some other tribe at that time. Should this interpretation be incorrect, then there is a secret meaning to the text. Let the one who understands it remain silent.&#x201D;</p>
<p>Commenting on Deut. 1:1, Ibn Ezra writes, &#x201C;If you will understand the secret of the twelve, and of <italic>And Moses wrote</italic> (Deut. 31:22); <italic>And the Canaanite was then in the land</italic> (Gen. 12:6); <italic>as it is said to this day. In the mount where the Lord is seen</italic> (Gen. 22:14); and <italic>behold, his bedstead was a bedstead of iron</italic> (Deut. 3:11), you will recognize the truth [concerning the first five verses of Deuteronomy as well].&#x201D;</p>
<p>Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s point is that the last twelve verses of Deuteronomy, which describe the death of Moses, were not written by Moses. The same applies to Deut. 3:11, for Moses would not say, <italic>behold, his bedstead was a bedstead of iron</italic>; <italic>is it not in Rabbah of the children of Amon</italic>, to the Israelites of his generation, for he had no need to tell the people of his generation that Og&#x2019;s great height could be verified by the size of his bed. The people whom Moses was addressing were the very ones who fought against Og. They knew of Og&#x2019;s height. Hence this verse must have been written some time after Moses&#x2019; generation had passed away. I.E. similarly believed that <italic>as it is said to this day: In the mount where the Lord is seen</italic> was not written by Moses, for Mount Moriah was not a place of pilgrimage in the days of Moses. Ibn Ezra argues that just as these words were not written by Moses, neither were the first five verses in Deuteronomy.</p>
<p>According to Talmudic tradition the entire Pentateuch was written by Moses (<italic>Baba Batra</italic> 15a). According to the eighth and ninth of Maimonides&#x2019; thirteen principles of Judaism, a Jew is obligated to believe that the entire Torah which we now possess was given by God to Moses, that this Torah was dictated by God to Moses, and that nothing is to be added to it or subtracted from it (<italic>Sanhedrin</italic>, Commentary on the Mishnah, Introduction to Chapter 11). Despite this, there are Rabbinic precedents for Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s assertion that the Torah contains post-Mosaic glosses. Some sages are of the opinion that the last eight verses of Deuteronomy were added to the Pentateuch by Joshua (<italic>Baba Batra</italic> 15a). Furthermore, Rabbinic literature speaks of <italic>tikkune soferim</italic>, editorial changes in the <italic>Torah</italic> made by the scribes.</p>
<p>We thus read in <italic>the Midrash Beresheth Rabba</italic> 49:12: &#x201C;<italic>And the men turned from thence, and went toward Sodom; but Abraham stood yet before the Lord</italic> (Gen. 18:22). Rabbi Simon said: This is a scribal emendation (<italic>tikkun soferim</italic>), for the Divine presence waited for Abraham.&#x201D;</p>
<p>In other words, the original reading of the text was claimed to be: And the men turned from thence, and went toward Sodom; but the Lord stood yet before Abraham. However, out of respect for God the scribes changed the text so that our Bible reads: <italic>but Abraham stood yet before the Lord</italic>.</p>
<p><italic>Midrash Tanchumah, Beshalach</italic> 16 states that the original reading of <italic>And if Thou deal thus with me, kill me, I pray Thee, out of hand, if I have found favor in Thy sight; and let me not look upon my wretchedness</italic> (Num. 11:15) was: And if Thou deal thus with me, kill me, I pray Thee, out of hand, if I have found favor in Thy sight; and let me not see Thy (God&#x2019;s) wretchedness.</p>
<p><italic>Midrash Tanchumah, Beshalach</italic> 16 similarly states that the original reading of <italic>one&#x2026;of whom the flesh is half consumed when he cometh out of his mother&#x2019;s womb</italic> (Num. 12:12) was, half of <bold>our</bold> flesh was consumed when <bold>we</bold> cometh out of <bold>our</bold> mother&#x2019;s womb.</p>
<p>According to <italic>Tanchumah, Beshalach</italic> 16, the men of the Great Assembly were responsible for the <italic>tikkune soferim</italic>. Some scholars cite other Rabbinic sources that credit Ezra with these textual changes (<italic>tikkune soferim</italic>) (Marc Shapiro, <italic>Torah U-Maddah Journal</italic>, Vol. 4, 1993, p. 199).</p>
<p>It should also be noted that I.E. was not the only medieval rabbi who believed that there are some glosses or slight changes in the text of the Torah. Thus Rabbi David Kimchi (c. 1160-1235) notes that the word Dan in Gen. 14:14 is post-Mosaic. He argues that the original reading of Gen. 14:14 was &#x201C;and pursued as far as Leshem.&#x201D; Rabbi Kimchi maintains that after the tribe of Dan conquered the city of Leshem and changed its name to Dan (Josh. 19:47), the reading of Gen. 14:14 was changed to read &#x201C;and pursued as far as Dan&#x201D; as in our texts of Scripture (Radak on Gen. 14:14).</p>
<p>Others went much further than I.E. Rabbi Judah Ha-Hasid of Regensburg (d. 1217), the author of the <italic>Sefer Hasidim</italic> and one of the Tosafists, believes that the clause <italic>And he set Ephraim before Manasseh</italic> (Gen. 48:20) is not Mosiac. He believes that it was inserted in the verse by Joshua or by a member of the Great Assembly. According to Rabbi Judah the meaning of <italic>And he set Ephraim before Manasseh</italic> is not that Jacob set Ephraim before Manasseh but that Moses placed Ephraim before Manasseh when they marched in the wilderness (Num. 10:22,23). (See Ben Zion Katz, <italic>Jewish Bible Quarterly</italic>, Vol. 25, No. 1, 1997, p. 23).</p>
<p>Rabbi Judah believes that Psalm 136 originally followed Num. 21:18 and that King David removed it from the Book of Numbers and inserted it into Psalms. He similarly believes that David removed all other anonymous psalms composed by Moses from the &#x201C;Chumash (Pentateuch)&#x201D; and placed them in the Book of Psalms [<italic>Ibid.</italic>, p. 26; see also Israel Ta Shema in <italic>Ma-she-hu Al Bikkoret Ha-Mikra Be-Ashkenaz Be-yeme Ha-Benayim</italic>, in <italic>The Bible in The Light of Its Interpreters</italic> (Hebrew), Jerusalem, 1994].</p>
<p>Rabbi Judah also believes that the men of the Great Assembly inserted verses 31-39 into Chapter 36 of Genesis (Katz, p. 29). It should be noted that I.E. suggested that a commentary containing a similar comment be burned. (See I.E. on Gen. 36:31, Vol. 1, p. 341).</p>
<p>It is noteworthy that Maimonides&#x2019; position on the text of the Pentateuch did not prevent him from charging his son not to spend time on any other commentaries save those of Ibn Ezra, &#x201C;which alone are meaningful and profitable to all who study them with intelligence, understanding and deep insight.&#x201D; (I.E., Vol. 1, Preface, p. VIII). (However, there are those who believe that Maimonides&#x2019; charge to his son is apocryphal.) Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s position on post-mosaic glosses in the Pentateuch did not prevent Rabbi Maimonides&#x2019; son from studying Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s works and constantly quoting him in his commentary.</p>
<p>Furthermore, Rabbi David Ha-Nagid, a direct descendant of Maimonides, asked Rabbi Joseph ben Eliezer (fourteenth century) to explain to him the secrets at which Ibn Ezra hints. In explaining Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s position on post-Mosaic glosses in the Torah, Rabbi Joseph writes: &#x201C;Since we must believe in tradition and in the words of prophecy what difference does it make to me whether Moses wrote it or another prophet wrote it since it is all true and it is prophetic. If you say, does not the Torah state, <italic>Ye shall not add</italic> [<italic>unto the word which I command you</italic>] (Deut. 4:2), the answer is: Rabbi Abraham [Ibn Ezra] wrote&#x2026;that words are like bodies and their meanings are like souls&#x2026;(Ex. 20:1). Furthermore, <italic>Ye shall not add</italic> only applies to the commandments&#x2026;not to words. (<italic>Tzoffnat Pane&#x2019;ach</italic>) on Gen. 12:6 as quoted by M.E. Stem, <italic>Kokheve Ya&#x2019;akov</italic>, No. 27, Vienna, 1862, pp. 33,34).</p>
<p>It is worthy of note that Nachmanides, who often took issue with I.E. and who believed that the text of the Torah preceded the creation of the world (see C.B. Chavel, <italic>Nachmanides&#x2019; Introduction to the Pentateuch</italic>, 1959, p. 2), never condemned I.E.&#x2019;s hints of post-Mosaic writings in the Torah.</p>
<p>Normative orthodoxy ultimately accepted Maimonides&#x2019; opinion. They argued that the <italic>tikkune soferim</italic> do not refer to actual changes in the text of the Bible. They claim that what the midrash means by <italic>tikkune soferim</italic> is that Moses employed euphemisms (Rabbi Joseph Albo, <italic>Sefer Ha-Ikkarim</italic>, translated by I. Husik, Philadelphia, 1930, Vol. 3, pp. 189-200). Thus Rabbi Shabbatai Bass (1641-1718) quotes Rabbi Solomon ben Adrat (1235-1319) as saying that the term <italic>tikkune soferim</italic> &#x201C;does not, God forbid, intend to teach that they [the scribes] added or addended even one letter to Scripture&#x201D; (<italic>Sifte Chachamim</italic> on Gen. 18:22). Rabbi Joseph Albo stated the same (<italic>Ibid.</italic>).</p>
<p>It should be noted that I.E. himself did not believe that there were any <italic>tikkune soferim</italic> in Scripture. However, he based his opinion on exegetical grounds. He wrote, &#x201C;one who correctly interprets the Torah does not need to assume any scribal emendations (<italic>tikunne soferim</italic>)&#x201D; (I.E., Vol. I, Introduction, p. 18).</p>
<p>Contemporary orthodox authorities claim that citations in I.E., Radak, Rabbi Judah Ha-Hasid, and others are misinterpretations, forgeries, or glosses inserted in the commentaries by erring students (see Rabbi Moshe Feinstein, <italic>Iggerot Moshe, Orach Chayyim</italic>, Part 4, Bene Berak, 1981, pp. 358-361). They believe that the whole issue should be ignored.</p>
<p>While it is true that one can argue that I.E. opened the door to biblical criticism by going somewhat further than the Talmud, it is a far cry from I.E., who added some six small emendations to those of the Talmud and Midrash, to Spinoza and to biblical criticism that questions the entire Mosaic authorship of the Pentateuch. Spinoza and his followers totally misrepresented the views of I.E.</p>
<p>Others projected their own conflicts onto Ibn Ezra. Thus Zalmen Shazar, the late president of Israel, claimed that Ibn Ezra led a double life, putting on a facade of piety while secretly harboring doubts with regard to certain elements in the Rabbinic tradition. Shazar, like Spinoza, considered Ibn Ezra to have been one of the forerunners of modern biblical criticism. He believed that Ibn Ezra suffered great emotional stress because he could not openly express his beliefs. Shazar hints that Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s cynicism can be traced to this inner conflict. (M. Soloweitschik and S. Rubasscheffs, <italic>Toledot Bikoret HaMikra</italic>, Berlin, 1935, pp. 42-50).</p>
<p>Abraham Geiger had a similar notion. Anticipating Freud, he claimed that Ibn Ezra often poured invective on heretics because deep down he agreed with them (I.E. Twersky, <italic>Rabbi Abraham Ibn Ezra, Studies in the Writings of a Twelfth-Century Jewish Polymath</italic>, p. 139).</p>
<p>Michael Creizenbach (1789-1842) of Frankfurt, a nineteenthcentury Reform rabbi and Ibn Ezra scholar, considered Ibn Ezra a kindred spirit and a precursor of Reform Judaism (Twersky, <italic>Ibid.</italic>, p. 136).</p>
<p>The fact of the matter is that Ibn Ezra was a pious and believing Jew. In fact, Ibn Ezra taught that if faith is lacking, religious practice is meaningless. He emphasized that the Rabbinic tradition is true and is to be followed. What he did was to show us that we should place Rabbinic interpretation and the plain reading of the text in their proper prospective. Ibn Ezra was no more responsible for the misinterpretation of his work than the prophet Isaiah was for the Christian misinterpretation of Is: 7:14.</p>
<p>Rabbi Johanan ben Zakkai compared his student Rabbi Eleazar ben Arakh to a flowing spring (<italic>Avot</italic> 2:11). The same may be said of Rabbi Abraham Ibn Ezra. He has been a fount of learning and a source of intellectual inspiration from the twelfth century to our own day. There is no doubt that he will do the same for coming generations.</p>
<p>H. Norman Strickman</p>
<p>Touro College</p>
<p>23 Elul, 5761</p>
<p>September 11, 2001</p>
</preface>
Leviticus 
<preface>
<title>PREFACE</title>
<p>It is almost 20 years since I wrote the preface to the first English translation of Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s commentary on Genesis. As I now write the preface to the English translation of Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s commentary on Leviticus, the third book of the Bible but the last one to be translated, I give thanks to the Almighty for granting me life and health and the wherewithal to complete the task, as well as the good fortune to have all the original participants in this project. First and foremost my thanks to the co-author, H. Norman Strickman, who did the lion&#x2019;s share of the translation. And to my brother-in-law, Harold Fink, for his computer expertise and assistance, without which this work could not have been done. And lastly, to the sole English editor, Cynthia Handler, who helped make this work readable and intelligible in English.</p>
<p>What is the value of this work today? From an historical and intellectual view, Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s commentary on the Pentateuch is most important, as explained previously in the preface to Genesis. His influence can be seen in all subsequent Hebrew Biblical commentaries, particularly that of Nahmanides. His influence is equally apparent on Maimonides both in his philosophical work, the <italic>Guide of the Perplexed</italic>, and his <italic>halakhic</italic> work, his <italic>Mishneh Torah</italic>, extending also to many later Biblical scholars and philosophers. All this is well documented in Dr. Strickman&#x2019;s forewords to the five books of this set. In spite of all of this, however, the question of the English translation&#x2019;s value still remains.</p>
<p>Through the study of I.E.&#x2019;s commentary on the five books of the Pentateuch one gets a thorough understanding of the <italic>pshat</italic>, the literal meaning of each phrase and word. Noting I.E.&#x2019;s careful analysis of every single word, one senses his conviction that this work is truly the word of God. (Parenthetically, this belies those who think of I.E. as a reformer, or worse). This probably was the basis both for Maimonides and Nahmanides&#x2019; admiration for I.E.&#x2019;s commentary. If one wants to comprehend the Pentateuch in its purely literal sense and its effect on theology, philosophy, and <italic>halakha</italic>, there is no other way than to immerse oneself in I.E.&#x2019;s commentary. That is what makes the work and the effort involved in this English translation worthwhile.</p>
<p>Arthur M. Silver</p>
<p>7 Elul, 5764</p>
<p>August 24, 2004</p>
</preface>
<preface>
<title>FOREWORD</title>
<p>One of the issues which practically all of the traditional commentaries on Scripture felt they had to confront was the relationship of Rabbinic exegesis to the Biblical text. Ibn Ezra was no exception. He writes: &#x201C;One who is intelligent can discern when the sages understand a text literally and when they do so <italic>midrashically</italic>. For all of their interpretations do not follow one course&#x201D; (<italic>Yesod Morah</italic>, Chapter 6, Strickman translation, pp. 83-84).</p>
<p>In his introduction to his commentary on the Torah, Ibn Ezra writes, &#x201C;With regard to verses which deal with laws, statutes and regulations, if we find two possible interpretations for a verse and one of them in keeping with the interpretation of the transmitters of tradition, all of whom were righteous men, then without reservation and with all our might we will rely on the truth of their words. Heaven forbid that we should join the Sadducees who claim that the traditions of the Rabbinic sages contradict the literal meaning of Scripture and the rules of grammar. The fact of the matter is that our ancient sages are true and all their words are true&#x201D; (Vol. 1, pp. 18,19).</p>
<p>The above should be taken as representing Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s general outlook. A study of Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s commentary on Scripture reveals a much more nuanced approach. Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s study of the Biblical text convinced him that many of the Rabbinic interpretations were not only <italic>not</italic> in keeping with the plain meaning of the text, but they appeared to contradict its literal meaning.</p>
<p>According to Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s reading of Scripture a non-Jew residing in the Land of Israel is prohibited from working on the Sabbath and on Yom Kippur (Ex. 20:8; Lev. 16:29). A non-Jew residing in the land of Israel is also enjoined from eating the flesh of an animal that dies of itself (Lev. 17:14). According to the Talmud all of the above are permitted to a non-Jew living in the Land of Israel. Ibn Ezra writes that the sexual partners that are prohibited to a Jew are also prohibited to a non-Jewish resident of the Land of Israel (Lev. 19:2). According to Rabbinic interpretation only six of the fifteen sexual partners that are prohibited to Israelites are proscribed to a non-Jew (Maimonides, <italic>Mishneh Torah, Hilkhot Melakhim</italic> 9:5). Ibn Ezra believes that it is prohibited to touch the carcass of an unclean animal (Lev. 11:8). He believes that one who violates this law incurs the penalty of flagellation. The rabbis held that there was no such law.</p>
<p>Ibn Ezra makes a similar point in Exodus with regard to the law prohibiting boiling a kid in its mother&#x2019;s milk. According to Ibn Ezra, Scripture only prohibits boiling a kid in its mother&#x2019;s milk. All other prohibitions of boiling and eating meat and milk are of Rabbinic origin (Ex. 23:19).</p>
<p>Ibn Ezra makes an analogous comment on Lev. 11:9. He notes there that if we pursue the plain meaning of Scripture without the tradition of the rabbis, then fish that are found in ponds (<italic>agammim</italic>) are prohibited, for Scripture specifies that only fish found in <italic>the seas and the rivers</italic> may be eaten.</p>
<p>The rabbis rule that the verse &#x201C;Be fruitful and multiply&#x201D; (Gen. 1:28) is a command to have children. According to Ibn Ezra the Rabbinic interpretation of the above verse is not in keeping with the plain meaning of the verse. He believes that according to the plain meaning of the text, <italic>Be fruitful and multiply</italic> is a blessing, not a command. Ibn Ezra goes on to say that there is indeed a command to have children. However, it is not derived from Gen. 1:28 but is a law known from tradition. The rabbis merely used Gen. 1:28 as a means to transmit their tradition (Gen. 1:26). Later Ibn Ezra implies that having children is not a command but an option (<italic>Yesod Morah</italic>, Strickman translation, pp. 53,54).</p>
<p>I.E. holds that the high priest wears all of his priestly garments when he enters the Holy of Holies on Yom Kippur (Lev. 16:4). According to the rabbis he wears only four garments.</p>
<p>I.E. interprets Lev. 17:2 as meaning that one who is in the vicinity of the temple is prohibited from slaughtering an animal for food but must bring the animal as a sacrifice. This is not the opinion of the rabbis. There are many other instances in Leviticus and the other Books of the Pentateuch where I.E.&#x2019;s interpretation does not fully agree with the Rabbinic one.</p>
<p>The law concerning the eating of the fat (<italic>chelev</italic>) of an animal is an example of I.E.&#x2019;s method of exegesis and its consequences.</p>
<p>Scripture states, &#x201C;For whosoever eateth the fat of the beast, of which men present an offering made by fire unto the Lord, even the soul that eateth it shall be cut off from his people,&#x201D; (Lev. 7:25). According to the rabbis, the meaning of <italic>the fat of the beast, which men present an offering</italic> is, of any kind of beast which men may present as an offering on the altar. In other words, the verse teaches that the fat of all animals permitted to be offered as a sacrifice is prohibited. According to the Talmud anyone who eats fat <italic>(chelev)</italic> is punished by <italic>ka ret</italic>. The prohibition is Biblical.</p>
<p>The Karaites agreed with this but also prohibited the fat of the tail, which the rabbis permitted. According to Ibn Ezra, Lev. 7:25 only prohibits the fat of an animal that was actually offered on the altar. In other words, the Torah permits the fat of animals slaughtered for meat. I.E. makes his point in a controversy that he had with a Karaite (Lev. 7:20).</p>
<p>Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s response to the Karaite incensed Nahmanides, for it contradicted Rabbinic tradition. According to Rabbinic law, eating fat entails the punishment of <italic>karet</italic>. Furthermore, if done inadvertently one is obligated to offer a sin offering. It is thus clearly a Biblical law. Nahmanides believed that in asserting that ordinary fat is Biblically permitted, Ibn Ezra was straying further from tradition than the Karaites, for the latter at least admitted that fat was Biblically prohibited. Nahmanides argued that the Rabbinic interpretation of Lev. 7:25 is in fact the plain meaning of the verse.</p>
<p>Ibn Ezra believed that whenever the Rabbinic interpretation does not seem to be the literal one, then academically speaking the verse is to be taken literally and its interpretation is to be considered of Rabbinic origin but <italic>halakhically</italic> binding.</p>
<p>Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s approach was similar but, it has to be stressed, not identical to that of Moses Maimonides. Maimonides writes: &#x201C;Not everything derived [by the rabbis] by analogy or from an argument based on reasoning from a minor to a major premise&#x2026;or from one of the thirteen principles by which the Torah is interpreted is a Torah law unless the sages explicitly say that it is so&#x2026;Nothing is considered to be prescribed by the Torah unless it is explicitly stated in the Torah such as a mixture of linen and wool, diverse seeds, Sabbath, and the proscribed sexual partners or something that the sages say comes from the Torah as they do with regard to three or four things alone&#x201D; (<italic>Maimonides Responsa</italic> 355, Blau Edition). He makes a similar point in the <italic>Sefer Ha-Mitzvot</italic> (Root 2, Heller Edition, pp.7,8). However, there he omits the reference to &#x201C;three or four things alone.&#x201D;</p>
<p>Maimonides also notes that in instances where two sages differ with regard to a law, the interpretations put forward for the law originated with the sages and was not based on tradition.</p>
<p>It should also be noted that when Maimonides gave a reason for the commandments he only did so in keeping with the plain meaning of the Biblical text. He did not take Rabbinic interpretations into consideration (<italic>Guide</italic> 3:41).</p>
<p>Professor Avi Sagi of Bar Ilian University concludes that Maimonides believes there is one basic meaning to the Biblical text, namely, its plain meaning. The latter is clear from the Rabbinic dictum to the effect that a verse never loses its plain meaning (<italic>Sabbath</italic> 63a), the meaning of which is that a verse&#x2019;s meaning is identical with its plain and literal meaning. The upshot of the aforementioned is that most of the <italic>halakhic</italic> material found in the Talmud is of Rabbinic origin (<italic>Daat</italic>, Vol. 50-52, p. 128).</p>
<p>Nahmanides took very strong issue with Maimonides. He accused Maimonides of uprooting the bases of Talmudic legislation. According to Nahmanides all laws, which the rabbis derive from the Torah, are to be considered as if written in the Torah itself unless otherwise indicated by the rabbis (<italic>Hasagot to Sefer Ha-Mizvot, Shoresh</italic> 2).</p>
<p>This volume brings to a close the translation and annotation of Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s commentary on the Pentateuch. I hope that I have followed the dictum of Ibn Ezra, &#x201C;I will, to the utmost of my ability, try to understand&#x2026;every word and then do my best to explain it&#x2026;. May the Lord of truth lead His servant in the way of truth.&#x201D;</p>
<p>H. Norman Strickman</p>
<p>Touro College</p>
<p>7 Elul, 5764</p>
<p>August 24, 2004</p>
</preface>

Numbers 
<preface>
<title>FOREWORD</title>
<p>Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s commentary on the Book of Numbers follows the pattern established in his commentaries on the first three books of the Pentateuch. It is marked by fidelity to the plain meaning of the text, an application of philosophical and scientific beliefs in elucidating texts, independence of interpretation when <italic>halakhah</italic> is not involved, and a strict respect for rabbinic tradition when <italic>halakhah</italic> is involved.</p>
<p>I.E.&#x2019;s dedication to both the literal meaning of the text and his philosophical views can be seen in his interpretation of the law of the Nazirite. Numbers 6:2-5 states: <italic>When either man or woman shall clearly utter a vow, the vow of a Nazirite, to consecrate himself to the Lord, he shall abstain from wine and strong drink&#x2026;All the days of his vow of Naziriteship there shall no razor come upon his head; until the days be fulfilled, in which he consecrated himself unto the Lord, he shall be holy, he shall let the locks of the hair of his head grow long</italic>.</p>
<p>Some sages of the Talmud took a dim view of the Nazirite. &#x201C;Eleazar ha-Kappar Berabbi says: What is Scripture referring to when it says [of the Nazirite], <italic>and make atonement for him, for he sinned by reason of the soul</italic> (Num. 6:11). Against which soul did he sin? [It must refer to the fact that] he denied himself wine. We can now make this inference from minor to major: If the Nazirite who denied himself wine only is called a sinner, <italic>a fortiori</italic> one who denies himself the enjoyment of many other things (<italic>Ta&#x2019;anit</italic> 11a).&#x201D;</p>
<p>Ibn Ezra disagrees. He insists on taking Scripture at face value. There is nothing in the Torah and the prophets which implies that the Torah does not fully endorse Naziriteship. First of all, the Torah lays down the law of the Nazirite. Second, Scripture refers to the Nazirite as a holy person. Furthermore, the prophet Amos declares: <italic>And I raised up of your sons for prophets, and of your young men for Nazirites</italic> (Amos 2:11). The prophet Jeremiah had only praise for the Rechabites who abstained from wine (Jer. 35:14-19).</p>
<p>Thus the notion that the Nazirite is a sinner seems to run counter to the literal meaning of Scripture. Indeed, I.E. considers Eleazar ha-Kappar Berabbi&#x2019;s proof from Num. 6:11 that the Nazirite is a sinner purely midrashic and contrary to the literal meaning of the text.</p>
<p>Aside from the literal meaning of the text, I.E. had a philosophical reason for rejecting the opinion that the Nazirite is a sinner. According to I.E. the way for a person to develop his soul is to separate himself from the pleasures of this world and dedicate himself solely to God. &#x201C;The intelligent man will not occupy himself with the vanities of the world. On the contrary, he will isolate himself for the purpose of studying and mediating upon God&#x2019;s law and observing the Lord&#x2019;s precepts. God will then open the eyes of his heart and will create a new and different spirit in him. He will be beloved of his creator while yet alive. His soul will cleave to God and enjoy the fullness of the joy of God&#x2019;s presence. Furthermore, God&#x2019;s right hand of bliss will be eternally upon his soul when it separates from the body&#x201D; (Ibn Ezra, <italic>Yesod Mora</italic>, translated by H. Norman Strickman, p. 107).</p>
<p>According to I.E. sex is one of the things that creates a barrier between man and God (<italic>Yesod Mora</italic>, chapter 7, pp. 107 and 108). The Nazirite is an individual who takes a vow to abstain from wine and haircutting. I.E. connects wine and hair to sexuality. He believes that most sexual taboos are violated because the transgressor has imbibed wine. As to the prohibition of cutting the hair, I.E. writes, &#x201C;A woman who does not fix her hair does not seek to engage in sexual relationships&#x201D; (Num. 5:31). He similarly notes that the Torah states that &#x201C;a razor shall not come upon the head of a Nazirite so that he does not make himself attractive to women.&#x201D; (<italic>Yesod Mora</italic>, p. 62).</p>
<p>I.E. believed the Nazirite to be a prince of men. He writes: &#x201C;All men are slaves of the lusts of the world. The true king, the one who has the diadem and the crown of kingship over his head is the one who is free of lust&#x201D; (Num. 6:7). &#x201C;The Nazirite is a holy person. When the Nazirite completes his term and wants to go back to drinking wine, he must bring a burnt offering, a sin offering, and a peace offering. He must also shave his head at the entrance of the tent of meeting. He is treated disrespectfully because he is distancing himself from his holiness and is descending in state (<italic>Yesod Mora</italic>, p. 145).&#x201D;</p>
<p>I.E.&#x2019;s approach to sex is seen in his acceptance of the aggadic interpretation regarding the enigmatic incident of Moses&#x2019; relation to a Cushite women. The Torah tells us (Num. 12:1,2): <italic>And Miriam and Aaron spoke against Moses because of the Cushite woman whom he had married; for he had married a Cushite woman. And they said: Hath the Lord indeed spoken only with Moses? hath he not spoken also with us?</italic></p>
<p>The rabbis explain that Moses ceased having relations with Zipporah, for he was constantly in contact with God. Zipporah complained about this, and Miriam and Aaron supported her. They argued that they too were prophets, and they did not refrain from having sexual relations (<italic>Sifre</italic> 99). I.E. accepted this aggadic interpretation because it fit with his philosophical ideology.</p>
<p>Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s rendering of the word <italic>selach</italic>, which is usually translated as forgive, is unique. According to I.E. the meaning of <italic>selach</italic> is to postpone punishment. I.E. bases his interpretation on the punishment meted out to the Israelites for accepting the words of the spies sent to Canaan, i.e., that they would be unable to conquer the land. Scripture tells us that God wanted to destroy Israel for their lack of faith. However, when Moses prayed on behalf of Israel, God told Moses, <italic>salachti ke-devarekha</italic> (I have pardoned according to thy word) (Num. 14:20). God then goes on to say that since Israel did not hearken to His voice they shall not come into the land, and their children shall be wanderers in the desert for forty years until they (the original sinners) have all died (Num. 14:22,3). We thus see that Israel was ultimately punished for their lack of faith in God, even though God had told Moses, <italic>salachti ke-devarekha</italic>. I.E. thus concluded that the term <italic>selach</italic> refers to a postponement of punishment.</p>
<p>According to the Torah, Moses sinned at Meribah by failing to sanctify God in the eyes of the children of Israel (Num. 20:12). According to I.E., Moses&#x2019; sin was in being distracted by the people from properly directing his heart to God. As a result Moses was initially unable to bring water from the rock and God&#x2019;s name was desecrated.</p>
<p>I.E. uses astrology to explain the ability of Balaam to utter efficacious blessings and curses. According to I.E., Balaam was no true prophet. He was an astrologer who carefully tailored his words to what was written in the stars. He thus appeared to have the power to bless and curse.</p>
<p>According to I.E. the Biblical narratives do not necessarily follow in chronological order. He thus places Korah&#x2019;s rebellion (Num. 16) in the first year of Israel&#x2019;s sojourn in the desert, not in the fortieth year as implied by its position in Scripture.</p>
<p>While I.E. maintains an independent position regarding Biblical interpretations, he always defers to the sages of the Talmud on <italic>halakhic</italic> issues. Thus in regard to the law concerning fringes, I.E. notes it is possible that Biblical rules require that the corners of garments be left unwoven so that their threads hang down to form fringes. He further notes that the law of fringes applies to pants. However, he then goes on to say that this interpretation is of no consequence, for the rabbis say that the fringes are specially prepared threads which are placed on the corner of any garment having four corners. Therefore pants are not included in the law of fringes.</p>
<p>Although I.E.&#x2019;s commentary is distinguished by independence and by occasional bold theological statements, his commentary is also marked by a nonrationalistic bent. Thus in dealing with the copper serpent made by Moses to heal anyone bitten by poisonous snakes (Num. 21:8), I.E. takes issue with those who tried to explain this miracle rationally. He argues that God&#x2019;s powers are beyond explanation.</p>
<p>Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s commentary on the Book of Numbers thus reflects a confluence of the literal and the scientific, the traditional and the interpretive, the theological and the philosophical. His style of Biblical exegesis is unique and always thought-provoking and rewarding.</p>
<p>H. Norman Strickman</p>
<p>Touro College</p>
<p>25 Tishre, 5759</p>
<p>October 15, 1998</p>
</preface>
<preface>
<title>PREFACE</title>
<p>Abraham ben Meir ibn Ezra was one of the outstanding and colorful scholars of medieval Jewry. His knowledge was encyclopedic. He was a poet, mathematician, astronomer, astrologer, grammarian, physician and philosopher. However, his chief claim to fame rests on his commentary on the Bible, especially on the Pentateuch, the five books of Moses.</p>
<p>Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s commentary constitutes a major contribution to Biblical exegesis. One cannot be considered a true student of the Bible without having studied it. Indeed, Maimonides, writing to his son, states: &#x201C;How true and authentic are the interpretations of the wise scholar Abraham ibn Ezra, of sainted memory&#x2026;I exhort you not to pay attention or distract your mind by concentrating on commentaries, treatises and books other than those of Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s, which alone are meaningful and profitable to all who study them with intelligence, understanding and deep insight. They are distinguished from the writings of other authors, for Ibn Ezra was in spirit similar to our patriarch Abraham.&#x201D;</p>
<p>Nachmanides, whose own Bible commentary, together with Rashi&#x2019;s and Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s, forms the basis for and is integral to all Biblical commentary, was also an admirer of Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s work, although his appreciation was tempered with conflict. In Nachmanides&#x2019; verses of introduction to this commentary he writes: &#x201C;And with Abraham the son of Ezra we shall have open rebuke and hidden love.&#x201D; While often chastising Ibn Ezra whenever his independent views brought him into conflict with traditional authority, Nachmanides hidden love was the recognition of Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s mastery of language and grammar, understanding of Biblical syntax, and pioneer role in Biblical analysis and interpretation. For every instance of critical comment, Nachmanides has many more that express esteem.</p>
<p>This translation, the first into English of Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s commentary on Genesis, is a product of many years&#x2019; effort. Anyone familiar with the original knows how difficult it is to understand Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s cryptic style. By remaining faithful to his text and through the use of copious notes, the authors have tried to convey both a sense of his style and his meaning.</p>
<p>The text which was used for translation is the <italic>Mikra&#x2019;ot Gedolot</italic> version of Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s commentary on the Pentateuch. The general guidelines for transliteration laid down by <italic>Encyclopedia Judaica</italic> are employed, except for the <italic>tzadi</italic>, which is transliterated <italic>tz</italic>, and the <italic>chet</italic>, which is transliterated <italic>ch. Dagesh chazak</italic> is indicated by the doubling of the letter, except for <italic>shin</italic> and <italic>tzadi</italic>. When the end of a comment refers to the following verse, it occasionally has been placed next to the verse to which it pertains. In such cases the heading appears in brackets. When Ibn Ezra does not introduce a comment with a Biblical quotation and we, for clarity, do, then the quote is bracketed.</p>
<p>The English translation for the Bible used is that of the Jewish Publication Society&#x2019;s 1917 edition. This version was employed because the new J.P.S.&#x2019;s translation was not yet complete when this work was started. Furthermore, the old translation is still widely used. The J.P.S. version was occasionally altered to fit in with Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s explanation; however, verses introducing Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s comments were never altered.</p>
<p>I would like to thank all who have helped in this difficult and what I hope will be a monumental work. I would like to particularly thank Mr. Harold Fink without whose technical help this work would probably not have been published. May the Almighty grant us life, health, strength and the wherewithal to complete the task.</p>
<p>Arthur M. Silver</p>
<p>27 Kislev, 5746</p>
<p>December 9, 1985.</p>
</preface>
<foreword>
<title>FOREWORD</title>
<title>ABRAHAM IBN EZRA: HIS LIFE AND WORKS</title>
<h1>HIS LIFE</h1>
<p>Abraham ibn Ezra was born in 1089 C.E. in Tudela, Spain, and died in 1164 C.E. probably in London or possibly in Calahorra on his way back to Spain. Little is known of his family life. He alludes to five sons, but only one, Isaac, is known by name; the other four probably died in infancy. Isaac, a poet of note who spent most of his life in the Near East, was said to have converted to Islam and later returned to Judaism. A heart-rending lament by Ibn Ezra reveals that Isaac predeceased his father. Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s wife died some time before 1140 C.E. and he never remarried.</p>
<p>Until 1140 C.E. Abraham ibn Ezra lived in Spain. From then until his death he lived the life of a poor wandering scholar. It was during this period that most of his books were written. His travels included Rome, Lucca, Mantua, Verona, Narbonne, Beziers, Dreux, Rouen, Brent, London and possibly Palestine. Why did he leave Spain? Unsettled conditions in Spain, his son&#x2019;s apostasy, his wife&#x2019;s death and his poverty were all contributing causes. Concerning his poverty he lamented:</p>
<p align="blockquote">I cannot become rich, the fates are against me</p>
<p align="blockquote">Were I a dealer in shrouds, no man would ever die,</p>
<p align="blockquote">Ill-starred was my birth, unpropitious the planets,</p>
<p align="blockquote">Were I a seller of candles, the sun would never set.</p>
<h1>HIS POETRY</h1>
<p>Abraham ibn Ezra was a very versatile poet. He wrote liturgical poems (<italic>piyyutim</italic>), some of which are still used in the synagogue ritual, secular poems of friendship and love, verse on nature, astronomy, the seasons, the calendar, religious and nationalistic subjects. All came from his prolific pen. Some of his nationalistic and religious poems are among his best. In the former he gives vent to the suffering of Israel and protests against their humbled state. He writes:</p>
<p align="blockquote">The God of Israel Thou wast of yore</p>
<p align="blockquote">Thou wast their Father</p>
<p align="blockquote">And they were Thy children, but are they no more?</p>
<p align="blockquote">Then why didst Thou for a thousand years forget them?</p>
<p align="blockquote">And enemies from all around beset them.</p>
<p align="blockquote">Dost Thou not see, or is thy hand so weak,</p>
<p align="blockquote">That Thou canst not save those who help do seek?</p>
<p align="blockquote">Redeemer there is none as near as Thou;.</p>
<p align="blockquote">Thy name from ever was Redeemer.</p>
<p align="blockquote">So hasten, our God, redeem us now.</p>
<p>His religious poems reveal him to be a deeply devout man. He writes:</p>
<p align="blockquote">In Thee, my God, is my desire,</p>
<p align="blockquote">In Thee my passionate love and fire.</p>
<p align="blockquote">To Thee my reins, to Thee my heart,</p>
<p align="blockquote">To Thee my soul and spirit dart.</p>
<p align="blockquote">To Thee my hands, to Thee my feet,</p>
<p align="blockquote">From Thee doth come my form complete.</p>
<p align="blockquote">My blood, my bones, they are all Thine,</p>
<p align="blockquote">My body and image divine.</p>
<p align="blockquote">To Thee belong my eyes and thought,</p>
<p align="blockquote">The form and pattern Thou hast wrought.</p>
<p align="blockquote">To Thee my soul, to Thee my might,</p>
<p align="blockquote">Thou art my trust and my delight.</p>
<h1>HIS PHILOSOPHY</h1>
<p>Ibn Ezra was not a systematic philosopher; his philosophical views are expressed mainly in his Biblical commentaries. He was essentially a Neo-Platonist and was greatly influenced by Solomon ibn Gabirol, the Spanish poet-philosopher. Ibn Ezra divided the universe into three worlds: the upper world of the &#x201C;intelligences&#x201D; or angels, the intermediate world of the heavenly spheres, and the lower, sublunar world, the corporeal world of creation and decay. He believed that the Biblical account of creation only applied to the sublunar world.</p>
<p>Ibn Ezra taught that God is one and that all things exist by virtue of Him. The Lord is incorporeal and has no likeness or form; hence God is not subject to human feelings or corporeal accidents. Thus Ibn Ezra held that Biblical verses that speak of God in human terms are not to be taken literally.</p>
<p>Ibn Ezra believed that God cannot come directly into contact with the material world and that the sublunar world was not created directly by Him, but by angels termed <italic>elohim</italic> by Scripture. Thus the word <italic>elohim</italic> in the first chapter of Genesis means God acting through the angels.</p>
<p>Ibn Ezra also held that man has three souls: vegetative, animal and rational. The rational alone is immortal. He believed that man&#x2019;s rational soul comes from a universal world soul, and that immortality is achieved by the reunification of the rational soul with the world soul. According to Ibn Ezra the wicked in this world are left entirely to the fates that the stars determine for them. However, their ultimate punishment is the failure of their souls to be reunited with the world soul.</p>
<p>Ibn Ezra further held that prophecy resulted from the contact made by the prophet&#x2019;s soul with the world soul. Ibn Ezra taught that man&#x2019;s rational soul must acquire wisdom before it can be reunited with the world soul. This is accomplished by studying the natural sciences and advancing from this study to the knowledge of God. Concomitantly, the knowledge of God is also attained by the study of Torah. Additionally, the Torah places restrictions on man&#x2019;s appetites and lust, thus preventing man&#x2019;s corporeal nature from being dominant and hindering the rational soul&#x2019;s development.</p>
<p>Ibn Ezra was of the opinion that God&#x2019;s knowledge extends only to the general and the eternal, and that the Lord knows the particular only to the extent that it is involved in the general and permanent. This view is hardly in accordance with present accepted orthodox thinking. He also believed that individual Divine Providence is extended only to those who have freely developed their intellectual capacities.</p>
<p>Ibn Ezra was a believer in astrology. However, at the same time he affirmed Divine Providence and free will. He reconciled these apparently contradictory beliefs with the following illustration. Let us assume that it is written in the stars that a certain city is to be flooded. A prophet then comes along and warns the townspeople of the impending disaster and urges them to repent. The people follow the prophet&#x2019;s advice, repent their wrongdoings and leave the city to offer prayer to God. The river floods the city. The decree of the stars is fulfilled, but the righteous are saved.</p>
<h1>THE BIBLE</h1>
<p>Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s foremost achievement is his commentary on the Bible, particularly the one on the Pentateuch. This commentary has stood the test of time and ranks with Rashi&#x2019;s as the most widely studied.</p>
<p>Ibn Ezra began his commentaries on the Bible in Rome in 1140 C.E. and continued them for the rest of his life. He probably composed commentaries on the entire Bible, but we lack his work on the Early Prophets, Chronicles, Proverbs, Jeremiah, Ezekiel, Ezra and Nehemiah.</p>
<p>He began his work on the Pentateuch in Lucca, a northern Italian city to which he went after practically being driven from Rome by scholars who claimed his ideas bordered on heresy. Scholars think he produced two commentaries on the Pentateuch, a &#x201C;short commentary&#x201D; and a &#x201C;long commentary.&#x201D; The short commentary survives in <italic>toto</italic>, while the long commentary is extant only on Exodus and in fragments on Genesis. However, some scholars believe that his long commentary was limited only to the latter two books. Scholars are also divided as to which commentary came first. Did Ibn Ezra just write a short one and then expand it, or did he write a long one and then abridge it?</p>
<p>Where did Ibn Ezra get his material? Most scholars are of the opinion that he was not an original thinker. He copied from the Spanish grammarians and from Biblical exegetes. He often quotes the opinion of Saadiah Gaon and occasionally uses him without a citation. He frequently attacks and deprecates the Karaites, but quotes from them constantly, especially Yefet ben Ali and Joshua (either Joshua ben Judah Abu al-Farag Furkan or Joshua ben Ali). Dr. Philip Birnbaum, the noted Hebrew scholar and authority on Ibn Ezra, says that Ibn Ezra is more indebted to Yefet ben Ali than he admits. Be that as it may, even if the material were only an anthology (and no one goes as far as to say that there is nothing original in his commentary), Ibn Ezra deserves the credit for having left us a memorable and everlasting work, with a definite point of view, theory, philosophy and method of Biblical study. We must remember that Rashi&#x2019;s great work is also largely an anthology.</p>
<p>Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s commentary on the Pentateuch is difficult to study because he is often unclear. One has to labor to decipher his comments. His philosophical references are for the most part allusions. His work is without doubt the most difficult to understand classic commentary on the Pentateuch. Why did Ibn Ezra choose such a style? Some scholars maintain that he did so in order to hide his anti-traditional beliefs. However, this is not borne out by his strong belief in the Oral Law, as evidenced in these same commentaries and his pietistic poetry. Others suggest that the commentary as we have it consists of Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s lecture notes upon which he elaborated when teaching. Dr. Philip Birnbaum notes that since Ibn Ezra wrote his works for patrons, he was under considerable pressure to produce and therefore did not edit or even review his compositions. Probably both of the latter explanations have validity, with the addition of a small dose of the first theory. Ibn Ezra no doubt wanted to make his novel approach to the Pentateuch obscure to the uninformed and unintelligent.</p>
<p>What was Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s approach to understanding the Pentateuch? He tells us himself, first as a hint in his introductory couplets and then much more precisely and clearly in the longer poetical introduction. In his opening poem he writes, <italic>This book of Jasher composed by Abraham the poet is bound by ropes of grammar</italic>. Jasher (<italic>yashar</italic>) means straight and alludes to the literal interpretation of the Bible. Ibn Ezra is saying that his commentary contains a literal interpretation of Scripture based on the rules of grammar.</p>
<p>In the long introduction that follows, Ibn Ezra explains in detail. He says that there are five approaches to Biblical exegesis. The first four, which he rejects are: (a) long expositions interwoven with elements unrelated to the text; (b) anti-<italic>halakhic</italic> interpretations offered by heretics; (c) allegorical interpretations; and (d) Midrashic interpretations. The fifth method, the one chosen by Ibn Ezra, is a grammatical analysis of a verse, which is then accepted at face value.</p>
<p>Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s commentary deals with a host of grammatical and stylistic insights. They are:</p>
<p>(1) The <italic>vav</italic> is not always to be rendered &#x201C;and,&#x201D; but, like the Arabic <italic>fa</italic>, has other meanings as well.</p>
<p>(2) The Bible occasionally uses the imperfect with the meaning of the perfect.</p>
<p>(3) Scripture employs repetition in prophetic utterances.</p>
<p>(4) The perfect is often to be understood as a pluperfect. This congruence of tenses explains the apparent contradictions and interruptions in the sequence of Biblical text.</p>
<p>(5) Scripture recurrently omits some prepositions because it expects the reader to introduce them.</p>
<p>(6) The Bible occasionally uses an adjective but leaves out the noun which it qualifies.</p>
<p>(7) Scripture often omits the subject or the object in a verse because it is implied by the verb used.</p>
<p>(8) The Bible omits particles, verbs and other items.</p>
<p>(9) The Bible often uses abridged phrases and sentences.</p>
<p>(10) When Scripture uses a noun in the absolute where the rules of grammar call for one in the genitive, the noun is to be repeated in the construct.</p>
<p>(11) When a verb in the singular governs a noun in the plural, the verb refers to each one within the plural.</p>
<p>(12) Scripture employs paragogic, or superfluous letters. Ibn Ezra points out superfluous <italic>alefs, bets, hehs, vavs, yods, cafs, lameds, mems</italic>, and <italic>nuns</italic>.</p>
<p>(13) Biblical chapters are not always in chronological sequence.</p>
<p>(14) Scripture employs round numbers. Consequently the numbers seven and ten are not always to be taken literally.</p>
<p>(15) Scripture occasionally first summarizes and then goes into detail.</p>
<p>(16) The Bible at times uses two words with the same meaning back to back where one would suffice.</p>
<p>(17) Scripture engages in word play.</p>
<p>(18) Some Biblical verses have to be rearranged in order to be understood.</p>
<p>(19) The Bible employs nouns in apposition.</p>
<p>(20) The Bible occasionally repeats a proper noun a number of times in one verse, rather than use a pronoun the second time the individual is mentioned.</p>
<p>The use of grammar and the literal interpretation of the Pentateuch led Ibn Ezra to some startling statements. We have already noted his philosophical approach to and view of Biblical authorship. Among just a few of his novel insights in Genesis are: the tree of knowledge is sexual knowledge; the building of the tower of Babel was not evil in itself; Isaac was a poor man; Isaac had concubines in addition to his wife Rebecca; our patriarchs occasionally did not tell the truth; Simon was imprisoned by Joseph because he was next to the eldest, Reuben, whom he did not wish to imprison because he was innocent of selling Joseph into slavery. Ibn Ezra implies that Joseph was giving his brothers a subtle hint as to his identity. Every page contains a new approach, especially to one trained in the classical commentaries.</p>
<p>Although Ibn Ezra held that Biblical verses are to be taken at face value, he made an exception for those verses which contradict reason. He thus believed that all verses which refer to God in human terms are not to be taken literally; &#x201C;far be it to attribute a body to God.&#x201D; He explains the case of anthropomorphism in the Bible this way: &#x201C;It is well-known that the Torah spoke in the language of man, for the one who spoke it (Moses) and those who heard it (Israel) were human. Now a human being cannot speak of things above or below him without employing human terminology.&#x201D;</p>
<p>As stated above, where Scripture does not contradict reason, the Bible is to be taken at face value. Thus the account of the Garden of Eden, according to Ibn Ezra, took place exactly as described in Scripture.</p>
<p><italic>Halakhic</italic> Midrashim presented a more difficult problem. Here we deal with the realm of the observance of Jewish law. In these cases Ibn Ezra tried to show that the Rabbinic interpretation was the literal one. In cases where this could not be maintained Ibn Ezra held that the law transmitted by the rabbis of the Talmud was true in itself, but that the sages used the Biblical verse as a peg on which to attach a law.</p>
<p>He thus maintains, contrary to the Rabbinic sages, that <italic>Be fruitful, and multiply</italic> (Gen. 1:28) is not a command but a blessing, and that the sages merely used this verse as a mode for the transmission of a law passed on to them. Commenting on Ex. 23:2, Ibn Ezra points out that the rabbis interpreted the last three words of this verse, <italic>achare rabbim le-hattot</italic> (after a multitude to pervert justice), to mean that legal disputes are to be solved in accordance with the majority opinion of a legally constituted court of law. He notes that this is not the literal meaning of the verse, but that the rabbis used this text as a sign by which to remember the above-noted <italic>halakhah</italic>.</p>
<p>In other cases Ibn Ezra notes that a given Talmudic interpretation of a verse is Rabbinic in origin. For example, Ex. 23:19 reads, <italic>Thou shalt not seethe a kid in its mother&#x2019;s milk</italic>. According to the rabbis this verse prohibits the cooking of any kosher meat and milk. Ibn Ezra insists that the Pentateuch prohibits only the seething of a kid in its mother&#x2019;s milk and that the other above-noted prohibition is Rabbinic.</p>
<p>When Ibn Ezra offered an interpretation of a verse which was not in keeping with the <italic>halakhah</italic> he usually added a note to the effect that the <italic>halakhah</italic> is to be followed either because it is independent of the verse or because one is obligated to follow the Rabbinic enactments because &#x201C;the minds of the sages were greater that our minds.&#x201D; Ibn Ezra did this because he did not want his literal interpretation to lead to a violation of the <italic>halakhah</italic> or to serve as support for anti-<italic>halakhic</italic> sectarians. Thus Ibn Ezra was infuriated when shown a commentary on the Bible which stated that the days mentioned in the first chapter of Genesis started in the morning, not the night before as maintained by <italic>halakhah</italic>. Ibn Ezra was aghast at this interpretation lest it mislead people to do work on the eve of the Sabbath and thereby violate its sanctity. He wrote a book entitled <italic>The Sabbath Epistle</italic> to refute the notion that the Biblical day begins in the morning, and he cursed the author (who was probably Samuel ben Meir, Rashi&#x2019;s grandson) of the aforementioned commentary with the imprecation, &#x201C;May the hand of him who wrote this wither, and may his eyes be darkened.&#x201D;</p>
<p>Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s heterodox statements, i.e., that certain verses and parts of verses in the Pentateuch are post-Mosaic, his philosophical view of the Almighty, his ideas concerning creation, his seeming disregard for and disrespect toward the Midrash, and certain opinions quoted in the Talmud, and his citations from the heretical Karaites have led many orthodox Jewish scholars to avoid his commentary. In fact, the great 16th century Talmudist, Solomon Luria, writes: &#x201C;He (Ibn Ezra) was no Talmudist; the major portion of his work, including his commentary (on the Bible), treats of astronomy, natural sciences, and other secular subjects. Yet he dared to contradict Biblical scholars and the Talmud. Out of ignorance he ascribed Biblical laws to the Talmud and Rabbinic laws to the Bible. He countenanced the forbidden and prohibited sanctioned practices. His exegesis is not followed in matters of law; for in his legal pronouncements he often overruled the decisions of both Tannaim and Amoraim. He boasted that his independent rational faculty would alone guide him in interpreting the Bible and that he would not accept the commentaries of others. His work may best be judged by his adherents - heretics and Sadducees&#x201D; (<italic>Responsa of Solomon Luria</italic>, pp. 9 and 10).</p>
<p>Similarly some modern scholars claim that Ibn Ezra was in reality an anti-traditionalist in disguise who hid his true beliefs behind a mask of piety and &#x201C;secrets.&#x201D; They go so far as to picture him as a forerunner of modern Biblical criticism. Is any of this true? The answer is no. His writings reveal him to have been a pious Jew who believed in the Written and Oral Laws. He accepted God&#x2019;s revelation of the Torah to Moses and all of the Biblical miracles. However, his approach to Rabbinic exegesis, both <italic>halakhic</italic> and <italic>non-halakhic</italic> was in the tradition of other Spanish Jewish thinkers of his day. Thus Samuel Ha-Nagid wrote concerning the Aggadah: &#x201C;One should learn from aggadic statements only those things which make sense. It is important to know that all matters which our sages established as law, in connection with a commandment transmitted by our teacher Moses who received it from the Almighty, cannot be augmented or diminished in any way. However, their interpretation of Biblical verses is subjective. Hence those interpretations which are logical we accept. The others we reject.&#x201D; Maimonides&#x2019; approach to Aggadah is similar.</p>
<p>Judah ha-Levi also gave non-traditional interpretations to Biblical verses. Indeed, he interpreted the Biblical phrase <italic>on the morrow after the Sabbath</italic> (Lev. 23:11) literally, as the Sadducees did. Furthermore, he believed that the establishment of the observance of Shavu&#x2019;ot 50 days from the second day of Passover was of Rabbinic origin. Judah Ha-Levi implied that the <italic>halakhah</italic> is in force because it was established by our ancestors. However, one is free to interpret Biblical verses independently of <italic>halakhah</italic>.</p>
<p>It is not only the Spanish scholars who felt this way. Some early Tosafists not only had a high regard for Ibn Ezra, but went even further along the path than even he ventured. We know that Rabbenu Tam exchanged poetry with Ibn Ezra and even quoted him in his Talmudic work. Moreover, the Tosafist Rabbi Samuel ben Meir, Rashi&#x2019;s grandson, who in his Biblical commentary followed the literal meaning so strictly, claimed that according to the first chapter of Genesis the day begins in the morning and not in the evening as the Talmud says, a view that horrified Ibn Ezra.</p>
<p>In conclusion, Abraham ibn Ezra&#x2019;s commentary is unique, has withstood the test of time, can offer something to anyone who cares to study it, follows a definite tradition in early Biblical exegesis, and is most rewarding to those who, in the words of Maimonides, &#x201C;study them (Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s words) with intelligence, understanding and deep insight.&#x201D;</p>
<p>I would like to thank my dear wife Zahava for the many hours she spent in deciphering my handwriting and typing the manuscript. Without her dedication and devotion I could never have accomplished my task. I would also like to thank Dr. Samuel Hoenig for graciously lending me his copy of the Vatican manuscript of Ibn Ezra&#x2019;s commentary on the Pentateuch. Thanks are also in order to Abby Aronson, Amy Wahrman, Wanda Stollop, and Sylvia Berkowitz for their assistance in typing the manuscript.</p>
<p>H. Norman Strickman</p>
<p>Touro College, N.Y.</p>
<p>27 Kislev, 5746</p>
<p>December 9, 1985</p>
</foreword>
<intro>
<title>INTRODUCTION</title>
<p align="blockquote">Invoking<sup><xref rid="fn1">1</xref></sup> the name of the Great and Awe-inspiring God,</p>
<p align="blockquote">I begin to explain the meaning of the Torah.</p>
<p align="blockquote">I beseech thee, O God of my father Abraham,</p>
<p align="blockquote">deal kindly with thy servant Abraham.<sup><xref rid="fn2">2</xref></sup></p>
<p align="blockquote">May the opening of thy words give light</p>
<p align="blockquote">to thy servant the son of thy servant Meir.</p>
<p align="blockquote">And from the salvation of thy face,<sup><xref rid="fn3">3</xref></sup> may help come</p>
<p align="blockquote">to the son of thy maid servant who is named Ben Ezra.</p>
<p align="blockquote">This <italic>Book of Jashar</italic>,<sup><xref rid="fn4">4</xref></sup> composed by Abraham the poet,</p>
<p align="blockquote">is bound by ropes of grammar.</p>
<p align="blockquote">The eyes of the intelligent will find it fit.</p>
<p align="blockquote">All who take hold of it will be glad.</p>
<p align="blockquote">The above mentioned Abraham the Spaniard says:</p>
<p align="blockquote">Those who comment on the Torah do so in one of five ways.</p>
<p>The first way (to Biblical interpretation) ranges far and wide (from the text). It is beyond the interest of our time. If truth be likened to a dot within a circle then this approach can be compared to the periphery of the circle, which goes round about only to return to its starting point. A number of great scholars chose this approach, namely, the wise men of the academies in Moslem countries, such as Rabbi Isaac<sup><xref rid="fn5">5</xref></sup> who composed two books on the first chapter of Genesis, from <italic>In the beginning</italic> to <italic>were finished</italic>, and did not finish his commentary, so verbose was he. He makes mention of the believers in a god of light and a god of darkness<sup><xref rid="fn6">6</xref></sup> in his comments on the verse <italic>Let there be light</italic> (Gen. 1:3). But he (Rabbi Isaac) walked in darkness without being aware of it. In his comment on <italic>And the earth brought forth grass</italic> (Gen. 1:12), he brought forth words from his fancy<sup><xref rid="fn7">7</xref></sup> and spoke about trees and plants both large and small. On the other hand, on the term <italic>living creature</italic><sup><xref rid="fn8">8</xref></sup> he quoted foreign sciences. In the same vein, Rabbi Saadiah, Gaon of the Diaspora, commenting on the verse <italic>Let there be lights</italic> (Gen. 1:14), quoted the opinion of secular scholars and gave the dimensions of the heavenly bodies according to the astronomers. Similarly Rabbi Samuel ben Hofni <italic>gathered wind in his fists</italic> (chofnav) (Prov. 30:4)<sup><xref rid="fn9">9</xref></sup> in his lengthy comments on <italic>And Jacob went out from Beer-sheba</italic> (Gen. 28:10). He there mentioned every prophet by name, and how many times each one was exiled from his place. He also expounded on the value of travel. The only value of his commentary is its length. On the verse <italic>And he dreamed</italic> (Gen. 28:12) he expostulated on dream interpretation and why people see what they see when they are asleep. If one desires to learn secular wisdom let him learn it from the works of experts in these fields and let him examine their proofs and see if they are correct. The Geonim only cited from these works without offering any of the proofs as to the veracity of the opinions they quoted.<sup><xref rid="fn10">10</xref></sup> Some of the Geonim had no knowledge of the method of the ancient sages and how they arrived at their conclusions.</p>
<p>A second approach is the one chosen by the distorters, albeit they are Israelites. They think that they have reached the very point of the circle, but in reality they do not know its place. This is the way of the Sadducees,<sup><xref rid="fn11">11</xref></sup> such as Anan,<sup><xref rid="fn12">12</xref></sup> Benjamin,<sup><xref rid="fn13">13</xref></sup> Ben Mashiach, Joshua,<sup><xref rid="fn14">14</xref></sup> and of all heretics who do not believe the words of the transmitters of tradition,<sup><xref rid="fn15">15</xref></sup> turning away from it to the right or the left.<sup><xref rid="fn16">16</xref></sup> Each one interprets verses as he sees fit. They do the same even with respect to commandments and laws. They are ignorant of the form of Hebrew and therefore err even in grammar. How can people rely on their opinion, with regard to the precepts when they are always changing their mind, moving from one extreme to the other? They do this because there is not a single commandment fully explained in the Torah itself. I will note one example.<sup><xref rid="fn17">17</xref></sup> Someone conversant with these things will recognize its significance because it entails the penalty of <italic>karet</italic> (shortened life span) with regard to eating on Yom Kippur, eating leaven on Passover and, for one who is in a state of ritual purity on Passover, not offering the paschal lamb.<sup><xref rid="fn18">18</xref></sup> It also involves the seven rest days of the festivals,<sup><xref rid="fn19">19</xref></sup> the festival sacrifices, dwelling in booths and the sounding of the shofar. Nowhere in the Torah do we find clearly stated the rules governing the establishment of years nor how to calculate months. These wretched, poor in learning, find support for their calendric calculations in the verse <italic>and let them be for signs, and for seasons (festivals)</italic><sup><xref rid="fn20">20</xref></sup> (Gen. 1:14). But they don&#x2019;t know that <italic>Let them be</italic> is in the plural and speaks about the sun, moon and stars.<sup><xref rid="fn21">21</xref></sup> As to the person who says that the <italic>vav</italic> of <italic>u-le-mo&#x2019;adim</italic> (and for seasons) is superfluous and that <italic>for signs</italic> is connected to <italic>for seasons</italic>,<sup><xref rid="fn22">22</xref></sup> let him search for a friend to tell it to; perhaps he will believe it. If we do find two or three superfluous <italic>vavs</italic>, how do we know that this is one of them,<sup><xref rid="fn23">23</xref></sup> since we find thousands of <italic>vavs</italic> in Scripture which have meaning? Furthermore, the verse <italic>Who appointedst the moon for seasons</italic> (le-mo&#x2019;adim) (Ps. 104:19) is not in accordance with the interpretation of those whose loins totter.<sup><xref rid="fn24">24</xref></sup> Even if Scripture explicitly stated (which it never does) that the moon shall be for a sign for the appointed seasons (<italic>mo&#x2019;adim</italic>) falling in the various months, how could we determine that the Bible speaks of God&#x2019;s holy appointed seasons, since various types of appointed seasons are mentioned in the Pentateuch, the Prophets and the Holy Writings?<sup><xref rid="fn25">25</xref></sup> Furthermore, even if the Bible explicitly said: let the moon be as a sign for God&#x2019;s holy seasons,<sup><xref rid="fn26">26</xref></sup> a very important aspect of the problem remains to be solved.<sup><xref rid="fn27">27</xref></sup> Does a new moon start when the moon completes circling the sphere of the zodiac, i.e., every 27 days and some limited hours,<sup><xref rid="fn28">28</xref></sup> or when it completes circling the apogee of the eccentric sphere whose center is far from the center of the earth,<sup><xref rid="fn29">29</xref></sup> or when it completes circling the sphere of the dragon according to the calculation of the wise men because its epicycle turns in the opposite direction.<sup><xref rid="fn30">30</xref></sup> On the other hand, it may be that the month depends upon the conjunction of the sun and the moon.<sup><xref rid="fn31">31</xref></sup> There are three such conjunctions: the mean conjunction,<sup><xref rid="fn32">32</xref></sup> the true conjunction<sup><xref rid="fn33">33</xref></sup> and the conjunction contingent on the place of the beholder.<sup><xref rid="fn34">34</xref></sup> We do not know which conjunction determines the new moon; is it one or the other? As to that which they say, that the month begins when the new moon is actually seen, they have been deceived, for they have eyes but see not. Let them show us where in the Torah and the testimony<sup><xref rid="fn35">35</xref></sup> it is stated that the new moon is to be so determined. Similarly they did not correctly comment on <italic>This is the burnt-offering of every new moon throughout the months of the year</italic> (Num. 28:14) because this verse does not mention the moon.<sup><xref rid="fn36">36</xref></sup> It merely says that the various sacrifices are to be offered in their proper time and day and the Sabbath sacrifices on the Sabbath.<sup><xref rid="fn37">37</xref></sup> It is also known that sometimes there are six hours between the birth of the new moon and sunset. At such times the new moon can only be seen under certain astonomical conditions. At other times there may be a thirty hour difference between them,<sup><xref rid="fn38">38</xref></sup> and the moon will not be visible even to one standing on a mountain. This is so because the path of the moon changes due to its and the sun&#x2019;s spheres.<sup><xref rid="fn39">39</xref></sup> Its time of appearance also changes depending on the longitude and the latitude of the country from which it is observed. If it is cloudy and the new moon is not seen at the beginning of Elul or Tishri, shall we fast three days of atonement?<sup><xref rid="fn40">40</xref></sup> Furthermore, who says that a month consists of thirty days, for behold, Judah Ha-Parsi<sup><xref rid="fn41">41</xref></sup> wrote a book in which he counted the year and the months according to a solar year. We also do not find in the Torah of Moses the law of witnesses testifying that they saw the new moon, or who is qualified to testify that he saw the new moon, or if one is permitted to walk a great distance on a holy day to testify that he saw the new moon,<sup><xref rid="fn42">42</xref></sup> or if a father and son, or proselytes, or women are fit to testify that they saw the new moon. Even if all these things were written in the Torah, another problem remains. The Torah of Moses does not state how many months make a year. And even though the Torah connects the new year with the fresh young ears<sup><xref rid="fn43">43</xref></sup> it is not clear whether it refers to the fresh young ears of the wheat<sup><xref rid="fn44">44</xref></sup> or barley,<sup><xref rid="fn45">45</xref></sup> or when during this period the new year is to start, or from where young fresh ears of barley are to be brought.<sup><xref rid="fn46">46</xref></sup> If there is a hunger in the land of Israel and its environs and there is no seed and certainly no fresh ears, what is to be done? In such a case shall we leave the year as it is or add an additional month?<sup><xref rid="fn47">47</xref></sup> In such a year the Omer would not be counted and there would be no festival of weeks.<sup><xref rid="fn48">48</xref></sup> Therefore all these commandments are dependent on true traditions. Those who dispute what I have said and say, do not the sages of the Mishnah also teach that the months are determined by when the new moon is seen, to them I reply that if you accept their tradition as truth, that the month is determined by the sighting of the new moon, also accept their tradition that the needs of the people also determine the new moon. For the new moon is contingent upon its announcement by the Bet Din. The Bet Din took into consideration the time of the fresh young ears, the solstice and the needs of the community<sup><xref rid="fn49">49</xref></sup> in determining whether to add an additional month. Why, with regard to the laws of plagues, which apply only to individuals and very rarely at that, does the Torah go into such great detail? And yet with regard to the laws of the calendar, which determine the festivals that apply to all Israel at all times, there is no clear-cut statement so that we must look for hints here and there as to how the month is to be determined. Why is this so in this perfect Torah? This is ironclad proof that Moses relied in these matters on the oral Torah which is a gladness to the heart and a healing to the bones. In reality, there is no difference between the written and oral <italic>Torot</italic>. They were both handed down to us by our ancestors. The Passover observed by King Hezekiah supports our faith in the Rabbinic tradition. It was done so on the advice of wise elders. Hezekiah did not offer the paschal lamb in its time and he presumed to eat leaven in the first month. He observed the &#x201C;second Passover&#x201D; for seven days, in a manner similar to the &#x201C;first Passover.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn50">50</xref></sup> There is ample proof that the Most High and Exalted One accepted what he did. This was so because his actions were based on the ruling of a Bet Din. There was no deceit in him.</p>
<p>The third approach is the way of darkness and gloom. It lies outside of the circle. This is the approach of those who invent secret explanations for everything in Scripture. They believe that the laws and statutes of the Torah are riddles.<sup><xref rid="fn51">51</xref></sup> I will not expend much time answering them for, <italic>they are a people who do err in their heart</italic> (Ps. 95:10). The fact of the matter is that the laws of the Torah do not disagree with what is right.<sup><xref rid="fn52">52</xref></sup> They are correct in only one thing, viz., that every precept, be it minor or major, must be weighed in the scale of one&#x2019;s heart wherein the Eternal has planted some of his wisdom. Thus if there appears something in the Torah that is intellectually impossible to accept or contrary to the evidence of our senses, then we must search for a hidden meaning. This is so because intelligence is the basis of the Torah.<sup><xref rid="fn53">53</xref></sup> The Torah was not given to ignoramuses. Man&#x2019;s intelligence is the angel which mediates between him and his God. Thus anything in the Torah which does not contradict reason we must explain literally, take as it is written, and believe that it is so. We should not grope walls as the blind do, and interpret verses according to our subjective needs. Why should we turn what is evident into mysteries? Now if there are places with two meanings both of which are clearly true, one referring to the body and the other to the mind such as &#x201C;circumcision of the flesh,&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn54">54</xref></sup> and &#x201C;uncircumcised of heart,&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="fn55">55</xref></sup> and if there is a secret meaning to the <italic>tree of life</italic>, they are to be taken literally as well.<sup><xref rid="fn56">56</xref></sup> Now if anyone cannot accept what I have said, if he be wise let him open his eyes. In nature, too, we find things that serve more than one purpose, such as the nostrils, the tongue, and the legs that serve two purposes.<sup><xref rid="fn57">57</xref></sup></p>
<p>The fourth approach is close to the point, and a group of commentators have pursued it. This is the method adopted by the scholars in the land of the Greeks and Romans.<sup><xref rid="fn58">58</xref></sup> They do not rely on grammar but rather on Midrashic exegesis as do the books <italic>Lekah Tov</italic><sup><xref rid="fn59">59</xref></sup> and <italic>Or Enayim</italic>.<sup><xref rid="fn60">60</xref></sup> Since the interpretations quoted in these works are already found in the books of the ancients, why do these later interpreters tire us by writing them again?<sup><xref rid="fn61">61</xref></sup> There are Midrashic interpretations that are, in reality, in keeping with the literal meaning of the text.<sup><xref rid="fn62">62</xref></sup> There are other Midrashim that are not to be taken literally, they have a secret meaning, an example being the Midrash to the effect that the Torah pre-dated the world by two thousand years. This Midrash is true only according to its secret meaning. However, many do not understand it so. Actually, it is impossible to take this Midrashic statement literally because a year is made up of a given number of days, and the measure of the minute and the day is contingent upon the motion of the sphere.<sup><xref rid="fn63">63</xref></sup> Hence if there is no sphere there is no day, certainly not two days or a year or two thousand years. If one were to ask,<sup><xref rid="fn64">64</xref></sup> what was the world like before creation, would he not be ashamed of himself for seeking an entity when as yet there was nothing in existence? Those who respond<sup><xref rid="fn65">65</xref></sup> by saying that God created other worlds before this one and that he created this world at a propitious time<sup><xref rid="fn66">66</xref></sup> are offering an answer based on the <italic>plummet of emptiness</italic> (Is. 34:11). Similarly those who say that the Almighty brought the world into existence to show his might to man, the object of creation, have satisfied themselves with a miserable answer which takes into consideration only part of a larger problem. There is clear proof to all but the blind that only one-twelfth of the earth is inhabited. Furthermore, the entire earth is an insignificant dot in relation to the sphere over it<sup><xref rid="fn67">67</xref></sup> and even less so to the uppermost sphere. The interpretation of <italic>yom yom</italic> (daily) (Prov. 8:30) as meaning two thousand years is also wrong from a purely exegetical point of view.<sup><xref rid="fn68">68</xref></sup> If the meaning of <italic>yom yom</italic> (day) was two thousand years, Scripture would have read: <italic>yomayim</italic> (two days) rather than <italic>yom yom</italic> (daily). This is so because the meaning of <italic>yom yom</italic> is daily. We similarly read, <italic>ish ish</italic> (what man soever) (Lev. 17:3) and <italic>Blessed be the Lord day by day</italic> (yom yom) (Ps. 68:20). Furthermore, the end of the verse <italic>Playing always before him</italic> proves the point.<sup><xref rid="fn69">69</xref></sup> Additionally, Proverbs goes on to say, <italic>Happy is the man, that hearkeneth to me, Watching daily</italic> (yom yom) <italic>at my gates</italic> (Prov. 8:34). Now, if <italic>yom yom</italic> means two thousand years then it follows that we should observe the true Torah for two thousand years.<sup><xref rid="fn70">70</xref></sup> Furthermore, the verse <italic>For a thousand years in Thy sight are but as yesterday</italic> (Ps. 90:4) speaks of man not of God.<sup><xref rid="fn71">71</xref></sup> Those who are interested in the interpretation of this verse will find it in my commentary on Psalms.</p>
<p>There are also Midrashim whose main purpose is to relieve the mind tired by the study of a difficult and intricate <italic>halakhah</italic>.<sup><xref rid="fn72">72</xref></sup> Other Midrashim are based upon well-known concepts. There are also Midrashim that are not according to <italic>halakhah</italic>. There are some Midrashim whose main purpose is to enlighten others.<sup><xref rid="fn73">73</xref></sup> These Midrashim explain the Torah to the young. There is a bird that cannot see on sunny days and is able to see only at night because its eyes are dim.<sup><xref rid="fn74">74</xref></sup> Among the Midrashim that are for the young is the one that says that the Torah opens with a <italic>bet</italic> because the word <italic>berakhah</italic> (blessing) opens with a <italic>bet</italic>. Now, the fact is that there are many curses that open with a <italic>bet</italic>, viz., <italic>Behold, the Lord maketh the earth empty</italic> (bokek) <italic>and maketh it waste</italic> (bolekah) (Is. 24:1); <italic>And I will lay it waste</italic> (batah) (Is. 5:6); <italic>And the grinders cease</italic> (batelu) (Eccles. 12:3); <italic>And as for his ordinances, they have not known them</italic> (ba&#x2019;al-yeda&#x2019;um) (Ps. 147:20); <italic>From the pit of corruption</italic> (beli) (Is. 38:17); <italic>Your clothes are not waxen old</italic> (balu) (Deut. 29:4); <italic>The Lord hath swallowed up</italic> (billa) (Lam. 2:2); <italic>The Lord did there confound</italic> (balal) (Gen. 11:9); <italic>and thrust thee through</italic> (bittekukh) (Ezek. 16:40); <italic>and despatch them</italic> (bare) <italic>them with their swords</italic> (Ezek. 23:47); <italic>between the parts thereof</italic> (betarav) (Jer. 34:18); <italic>contempt</italic> (bizzayon) <italic>and wrath</italic> (Es. 1:18); <italic>bring forth for terror</italic> (behalah) (Is. 65:23); <italic>I will make thee a terror</italic> (ballahot) (Ezek. 26:21); <italic>a base fellow</italic> (beliyya&#x2019;al) (II Sam. 20:1); <italic>Baal-peor</italic> (Deut. 4:3); <italic>Bel boweth down</italic> (Is. 46:1); <italic>priests of the high places</italic> (bamot) (I Kings 13:33).</p>
<p>As to the <italic>resh</italic>,<sup><xref rid="fn75">75</xref></sup> if it stands for head as in <italic>its head</italic> (resheh) <italic>was of fine gold</italic> ((Dan. 2:32), it can also stand for evil (<italic>ra</italic>) as in <italic>the wicked men</italic> (ra) <italic>and base fellows</italic> (I Sam. 30:22).</p>
<p>Anyone with a little bit of intelligence and certainly one who has knowledge of the Torah can create his own Midrashim. The Midrashic interpretations are like clothes to the naked body.<sup><xref rid="fn76">76</xref></sup> Concerning such interpretations our sages of blessed memory said, <italic>a verse never loses its literal meaning</italic>.<sup><xref rid="fn77">77</xref></sup></p>
<p>One Midrash<sup><xref rid="fn78">78</xref></sup> interprets the word <italic>bereshit</italic> to mean that God created the world through the Torah, as it is written, <italic>The Lord made me as the beginning</italic> (reshit) <italic>of His way</italic> (Prov. 8:22).<sup><xref rid="fn79">79</xref></sup> Another Midrash states that the world was created upon the leviathan, as it is written, <italic>He is the beginning</italic> (reshit) <italic>of the ways of God</italic> (Job. 40:19). Another Midrash states that the world was created so that God might be feared, as it is written, <italic>The fear of the Lord is the beginning</italic> (reshit) <italic>of wisdom</italic> (Ps. 111:10). Another Midrash states that the world was created because of the <italic>bikkurim</italic> (first fruits), as it is written, <italic>The choicest</italic> (reshit) <italic>first-fruits of thy land thou shalt bring into the house of the Lord thy God</italic> (Ex. 23:19).</p>
<p>Another Midrash asks, why does the Torah open with a <italic>bet</italic>? To teach that God is one. It is only His creation that has two (<italic>bet</italic>) aspects, i.e., matter and form.<sup><xref rid="fn80">80</xref></sup> Another Midrashic reason given for the Torah opening with a <italic>bet</italic> is that the <italic>bet</italic> alludes to the two worlds.<sup><xref rid="fn81">81</xref></sup> Another Midrash asks, why does the Torah open with a <italic>bet</italic> followed by <italic>resh, alef, shin</italic> and finally by <italic>yod tav</italic>? It answers that Scripture teaches that the first Temple, which preceded the creation of heaven and earth,<sup><xref rid="fn82">82</xref></sup> will stand for 410 years and then be destroyed.<sup><xref rid="fn83">83</xref></sup> The Bible continues, <italic>Now the earth was unformed and void, and darkness was upon the face of the deep</italic> (v. 2). This means that darkness descended upon the earth following the removal of the Divine presence from the earth.<sup><xref rid="fn84">84</xref></sup> However, all was not lost, for <italic>(and) the spirit of God hovered over the face of the waters</italic> (v. 2); i.e., the spirit of wisdom and understanding rested on the expounders of the Torah which is likened to water.<sup><xref rid="fn85">85</xref></sup> Ultimately God will say, <italic>Let there be light</italic> (v. 3); i.e., the Messianic age will come. At that time God will separate those who hope for the Lord&#x2019;s salvation and those who do evil deeds in the dark.<sup><xref rid="fn86">86</xref></sup></p>
<p>Another Midrash interprets <italic>bereshit</italic> to be two words that mean that everything was created out of fire which is the foundation of all.<sup><xref rid="fn87">87</xref></sup> Another Midrash states that <italic>bereshit</italic> alludes to six, as in <italic>six</italic> (shit) <italic>cubits</italic> (Dan. 3:1).<sup><xref rid="fn88">88</xref></sup> The six allude to the six compass points of every body. The numerical value of first letters of each word in the first verse of the Torah comes to 22. This alludes to the 22 letters of the Hebrew alphabet. Similarly the seven letters in this verse allude to the seven vowels or to the seven planets.<sup><xref rid="fn89">89</xref></sup> The first verse of the Torah has 28 letters corresponding to the 28 phases of the moon. The same is the case with the 28 &#x201C;times&#x201D; mentioned in Kohelet (Eccles. 3:2 and 8).</p>
<p>The Midrash also states that Genesis opens with a <italic>bet</italic> and closes with a <italic>mem</italic><sup><xref rid="fn90">90</xref></sup> because it alludes to the name of God<sup><xref rid="fn91">91</xref></sup> enunciated by the High Priest on the Day of Atonement. The name was revealed to Moses at Sinai, as it is written, <italic>The Lord is among them</italic> (bam),<sup><xref rid="fn92">92</xref></sup> <italic>as in Sinai, in holiness</italic> (Ps. 68:18). Another Midrash says that the Torah opens with <italic>In the beginning</italic> and closes with the word <italic>Israel</italic> because Israel was on God&#x2019;s mind at the time of creation.<sup><xref rid="fn93">93</xref></sup> The end of the matter is, there is no limit to Midrashic interpretations.</p>
<p>The fifth method is the one upon which I will base my commentary. It appears to me to be correct in the presence of God whom alone I fear. I will not show favoritism to anyone when it comes to interpreting the Torah.<sup><xref rid="fn94">94</xref></sup> I will, to the utmost of my ability, try to understand grammatically every word and then do my best to explain it. Every word whose meaning the reader desires to know will be found explained the first time the word is encountered. For example, the meaning of sky (<italic>shamayim</italic>) will be given in the first verse of Genesis. This will apply to all terms. I will not make mention of the reasons offered by the Massorites<sup><xref rid="fn95">95</xref></sup> as to why certain words are at times spelled full and at other times defectively because all of their reasons are of a Midrashic nature. The fact is that Scripture sometimes fully and clearly spells out a word and at other times omits an unpronounced letter for the sake of brevity. Since the Massorites claim to be able to explain the reasons for full and defective spellings, let them tell us what spelling the scribes should have used in writing Scripture.<sup><xref rid="fn96">96</xref></sup> Now Moses left out the <italic>vav</italic> of <italic>yimlokh</italic> (shall reign) in <italic>The Lord shall reign</italic> (yimlokh) (Ex. 15:18), whereas the editors of Proverbs spelled the word <italic>yimlokh</italic> with a <italic>vav</italic> in <italic>For a servant when he reigned</italic> (yimlokh) (Prov. 30:22). However, many years passed between Moses and the editors of Proverbs.<sup><xref rid="fn97">97</xref></sup> Actually, the reason given by the Massorites for the different spellings of the same word are for children. I would also add that one who correctly interprets the Torah does not need to assume any scribal emendations.<sup><xref rid="fn98">98</xref></sup> It should also be noted that the Aramaic translation of the Torah accurately rendered the meaning of the Pentateuch and explained to us all its difficult parts. Now if at times he (the Aramaic translator, Onkelos) followed the Midrashim,<sup><xref rid="fn99">99</xref></sup> although he knew the basics better than we, he did so in order to offer additional meanings to a given text where even the simple could grasp the plain meaning of the text.<sup><xref rid="fn100">100</xref></sup> Thus he renders <italic>iroh</italic> (Gen. 49:11) not as foal but as his city, and <italic>beni</italic> (colt) as will build. He also renders <italic>atono</italic> (his ass&#x2019;s colt) (<italic>Ibid.</italic>) as &#x201C;the gate of the entrance&#x201D; (<italic>sha&#x2019;ar ha-iton</italic>).<sup><xref rid="fn101">101</xref></sup> No harm was done by this because the literal meaning of a verse is never negated by Midrashic interpretations for there are 70 faces to the Torah. However, with regard to verses which deal with laws, statutes and regulations, if we find two possible interpretations for a verse and one of them is in keeping with the interpretation of the transmitters of tradition,<sup><xref rid="fn102">102</xref></sup> all of whom were righteous men, then without reservation and with all our might we will rely on the truth of their words.<sup><xref rid="fn103">103</xref></sup> Heaven forbid that we should join the Sadducees who claim that the traditions of the Rabbinic sages contradict the literal meaning of Scripture and the rules of grammar. The fact of the matter is that our ancient sages are true and all their words are true. May the Lord God of truth lead his servant in the way of truth.</p>
<ftnote id="fn1"><sup>1</sup> I.E. opens with a poetic introduction. In fact, in Hebrew the entire introduction was in rhyme.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn2"><sup>2</sup> The first Abraham refers to the patriarch, the second to the author, Abraham son of Meir.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn3"><sup>3</sup> Cf. Ps. 80:4, 8.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn4"><sup>4</sup> I.E. called his commentary on the Torah, <italic>The Book of Jashar</italic>. Cf. Josh. 10:13.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn5"><sup>5</sup> It is not clear which Isaac I.E. is referring to. Some identify him with the philosopher Isaac Israeli (c. 850-950). Cf. Weiser.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn6"><sup>6</sup> Zoroastrianism (Weiser).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn7"><sup>7</sup> Literally, heart. He did not quote anyone but gave his own opinion or invented facts.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn8"><sup>8</sup> Weiser.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn9"><sup>9</sup> A play on the words <italic>chofni</italic> (Hofni) and <italic>chofnav</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn10"><sup>10</sup> The reader thus has no way of knowing whether what is quoted is true or not.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn11"><sup>11</sup> The Karaites. The medieval rabbis called the Karaites Sadducees because like the Sadducees they denied the authority of the Rabbinic sages, the Mishnah and the Talmud.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn12"><sup>12</sup> The founder of Karaism. He lived in the 8th century.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn13"><sup>13</sup> Benjamin ben Moses Nahavendi (c. 9th century). He was the first Karaite scholar to write in Hebrew and was responsible for the term &#x201C;Karaites&#x201D; replacing &#x201C;Ananites.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn14"><sup>14</sup> Some of the printed editions omit Ben Mashiach and Joshua. Hasan ben Mashiach was a Karaite who engaged in polemics with Saadiah Gaon. Joshua was a Karaite scholar often quoted by I.E. It is suggested that the reference is to Joshua ben Judah Abu al-Farag Purkan, one of the founders of Karaism (Weiser).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn15"><sup>15</sup> The Rabbinic sages.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn16"><sup>16</sup> According to Rabbinic tradition, the Biblical verse, <italic>thou shalt not turn aside from the sentence which they shall declare unto thee, to the right hand, nor to the left</italic> (Deut. 17:11), is a command to heed the words of the &#x201C;transmitters of tradition.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn17"><sup>17</sup> The &#x201C;one example&#x201D; offered by I.E. is, &#x201C;Nowhere in the Torah do we find the rules governing the establishment of the years nor how to calculate months.&#x201D; However, he digresses before coming to the point.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn18"><sup>18</sup> One who is &#x201C;impure&#x201D; on Passover is forbidden to sacrifice the paschal lamb. Cf. Num. 9:1-14. Our rendition is based on the Vatican manuscript of I.E. henceforth written <italic>Vat. Ebr</italic>. 38. The printed texts read, &#x201C;and leavened bread on Passover which one in a state of purity did not observe.&#x201D; This is an impossible reading.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn19"><sup>19</sup> There are seven festival days when work is Biblically prohibited. They are: the first and seventh day of Passover, Shavuoth, Rosh Hashanah, Yom Kippur, the first day of Sukkot and Shemini Atzereth.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn20"><sup>20</sup> The Hebrew word for seasons is <italic>mo&#x2019;adim</italic>. <italic>Mo&#x2019;adim</italic> also means festivals. Genesis 1:14 reads, <italic>Let there be lights in the firmament of the heaven&#x2026;and let them be for signs, and for seasons</italic> (mo&#x2019;adim). The Karaites interpreted this verse: Let them be for signs for the festival, i.e., let the moon (the lunar month) determine the time of the festivals.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn21"><sup>21</sup> Scripture reads <italic>ve-hayu</italic> not <italic>ve-hayah</italic>. <italic>Ve-hayu</italic> is a plural and so cannot refer only to the moon.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn22"><sup>22</sup> Aside from the above, the verse presents another problem for the Karaites. It does not read: and let them be for signs for seasons (festivals). It reads: and let them be for signs <italic>and</italic> for seasons (festivals). The Karaites tried to get around the problem by claiming that the <italic>vav</italic> of <italic>u-le-mo&#x2019;adim</italic> is superfluous and should not be translated. <italic>U-le-mo&#x2019;adim</italic> should be rendered: for seasons (festivals) rather than: and for seasons. Thus the verse is to be translated: And let them be for signs for seasons (festivals).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn23"><sup>23</sup> I.E. concedes that there are a few superfluous <italic>vavs</italic> in Scripture, but he asks, how do we know that this is one of them?</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn24"><sup>24</sup> Cf. Ps. 69:24. The Karaites interpreted Ps. 104:19 as meaning God appointed the moon for festivals.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn25"><sup>25</sup> The point is if the Bible said: the moon shall determine the <italic>mo&#x2019;adim</italic>, how do we know that the <italic>mo&#x2019;adim</italic> refer to religious festivals? The word <italic>mo&#x2019;ed</italic> may refer to any appointed time and does not necessarily refer to a religiously appointed one.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn26"><sup>26</sup> Even if the Bible explicitly stated the moon shall be for a sign for God&#x2019;s holy festivals, it would not solve the problem as to what constitutes a month.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn27"><sup>27</sup> Namely, what constitutes a new moon (the beginning of a month)? In order to understand what follows it is necessary to have some idea of medieval astronomy. The daily movement of the moon varies between approximately 11 and 15 degrees in a rather complicated fashion. To explain these motions the ancients introduced a complex scheme of combined circular movements. (For a full discussion of this problem and the solution offered for it, see <italic>Yale Judaica</italic> series, Vol. XI, <italic>The Code of Maimonides, Sanctification of the New Moon</italic>, p. 126). Cherez explains that the moon was believed to move within four spheres. The first is called <italic>galgal ha-domeh</italic> (the all-encompasing sphere). It is so called because like the zodiacal sphere, it encompasses the whole world and like it has the earth as its center. This sphere turns from east to west. Within the all-encompassing sphere lies another sphere called <italic>galgal ha-noteh</italic> (the inclined sphere). This sphere is not contained within the <italic>galgal ha-domeh</italic> but intersects it. The chord connecting the points of intersection are called the <italic>teli</italic> (the dragon). The point at which the moon moves north of this intersection is called the head (or top) of the <italic>teli</italic>; its opposite point, where the moon moves south, is called the tail of the <italic>teli</italic>. The <italic>galgal ha-noteh</italic> is inclined five degrees above the <italic>galgal ha-domeh</italic> on the north and five degrees below it on the south, hence the term <italic>galgal ha-noteh</italic>. The center of this sphere is the same as that of the <italic>galgal ha-domeh</italic>. This sphere also turns in an east to west direction. Within the <italic>galgal ha-noteh</italic> is another sphere called the <italic>galgal ha-yotze</italic> (the eccentric sphere). It is so called because the earth is not the center of this sphere. It is also called the <italic>galgal ha-noseh</italic> (the carrying sphere) because it bears a sphere which the moon circles (the <italic>galgal ha-katan</italic> or epicycle). The <italic>galgal ha-yotze</italic> turns from west to east. These spheres move at different speeds and their movements explain the complicated motions of the moon.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn28"><sup>28</sup> That is the time it takes the moon to return to a given point in the zodiac (Weiser). Medieval man believed that beyond the spheres of the moon, sun and planets there is a sphere containing the constellations. It takes the moon 27 and about a third of a day to complete this cycle (Weiser).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn29"><sup>29</sup> The time it takes the moon to complete its epicycle within the eccentric sphere, i.e., every 27 days and about 13 hours. So Cherez. However, his interpretation is questionable.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn30"><sup>30</sup> The moon in its epicycle turns from west to east while the &#x201C;sphere of the dragon&#x201D; rotates from east to west (Weiser). These contrary motions must be taken into consideration in establishing the time it takes the moon to complete the latter revolution. According to Krinsky what I.E. means by &#x201C;the time it takes the moon to circle the sphere of the dragon&#x201D; is the time it takes the moon to return to the head of the dragon after leaving it. It should be noted that the commentaries differ as to what I.E. means by the &#x201C;sphere of the dragon,&#x201D; as they do with regard to what he means by the moon&#x2019;s cycle around the apogee of the &#x201C;eccentric sphere&#x201D; and indeed as to how I.E. envisioned the system of the lunar spheres cited in note 27. For their opinions and differences see, Joseph ben Eliezer Ha-Sephardi, <italic>Margaliot Tuva</italic>, Amsterdam, 1722; Hayyim Wolf Kaputa, <italic>Or La-netivah</italic>, Lemberg, 1897; Weiser and Cherez. While the specifics of I.E.&#x2019;s comments are difficult to unravel, as is evidenced by the wide interpretation given his comments in the above-noted commentaries, the thrust of his remarks is clear. The moon makes a number of cycles in the sky. If a new moon is to be determined by the moon&#x2019;s revolution, which one of its cycles is to determine the new moon?</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn31"><sup>31</sup> A Hebrew month is determined by the conjunction of the sun and moon. Cf. Maimonides, <italic>Mishneh Torah, Laws of Sanctification of the New Moon</italic>, 6:1.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn32"><sup>32</sup> The mean conjunction of the sun and the moon takes place every 29 days, 12 hours, and 793 parts of an hour (dividing the hour into 1,080 parts). Cf. Weiser. The mean conjunction is the time when the sun and moon would come together if both moved uniformly.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn33"><sup>33</sup> The true conjunction of the sun and moon is their actual conjunction.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn34"><sup>34</sup> The conjunction varies in different places of the globe. See I.E.&#x2019;s commentary on Ex. 12:2.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn35"><sup>35</sup> A synonym for Torah.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn36"><sup>36</sup> The Karaites interpreted <italic>chodesh be-chodsho</italic> to mean the moon when it is new. They claimed that <italic>be-chodsho</italic> is to be interpreted as <italic>be-chiddusho</italic> (when it is new). I.E. disagrees. He feels that <italic>be-chodsho</italic> means in its month, and furthermore, <italic>chodesh</italic> does not mean moon but month. Cf. I.E. on Num. 28:14.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn37"><sup>37</sup> Num. 28:10.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn38"><sup>38</sup> In other words, the moon will not be visible at the first sunset following its conjunction with the sun.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn39"><sup>39</sup> The ancients believed that the sun traveled around the earth. However, the earth was not the center of the sun&#x2019;s orbit. When the sun is further from the earth, it appears to be traveling more slowly, when closer to the earth, faster (<italic>Yale Judaica</italic> series, Vol. XI, p. 126).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn40"><sup>40</sup> The point is, if we do not rely on the traditional calculation and rely on the mean conjunction, then when for some reason the moon is not seen at the beginning of Elul we do not know when that month starts. If the same occurs with regard to Tishri, we have three possible dates for Yom Kippur, viz., when did Elul start and did it have 29 or 30 days? To satisfy all doubts we would have to fast three days in a row.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn41"><sup>41</sup> Judah Ha-Parsi was a Karaite who wrote a book claiming that the Pentateuch follows a solar year of 12 months, with each month consisting of 30 days. However, the Bible nowhere says that a month consists of 30 days. Cf. I.E.&#x2019;s commentary on Ex. 12:2.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn42"><sup>42</sup> Mishnah, <italic>Rosh Hashanah</italic> 1:5-8.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn43"><sup>43</sup> Cf. Ex. 12:2, 13:4.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn44"><sup>44</sup> The month of Sivan.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn45"><sup>45</sup> The month of Nisan.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn46"><sup>46</sup> Assuming that the new year starts with the ripening of the barley, what place is to determine its ripening and hence the spring? The barley ripens at different times in different places.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn47"><sup>47</sup> Perhaps we ought to add another month and see if something will grow and there will be fresh young ears. Cf. Weiser.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn48"><sup>48</sup> Since there is no barley. Cf. Lev. 23:9-22.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn49"><sup>49</sup> Cf. <italic>Sanhedrin</italic> 11b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn50"><sup>50</sup> Hezekiah put off the observance of Passover for a month upon the advice of &#x201C;his princes and all the congregation in Jerusalem.&#x201D; Cf. II Chron. 30:2. This supports the teaching of the Oral Law to the effect that a Bet Din may delay observance of Passover for a month if it is felt that the needs of the community warrant it. Otherwise, Hezekiah would have been guilty of eating leaven on Passover. Furthermore, he would have invented a new way to celebrate the Second Passover. Cf. Num. 9:9-13. For the Second Passover is observed for one night and Hezekiah kept it for seven days. Since Hezekiah was a pious king we must assume that the festival he observed was not the Second Passover but the Passover itself after an extra month was added (intercalated) to the year.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn51"><sup>51</sup> I.E. takes issue with those who interpret the Torah as allegories. In I.E.&#x2019;s alternate commentary on the Pentateuch this group is identified as the Christians.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn52"><sup>52</sup> Krinsky. That is, all the laws of the Torah must make sense.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn53"><sup>53</sup> Cherez.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn54"><sup>54</sup> Gen. 17:11.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn55"><sup>55</sup> Deut. 10:16. The point is the reason the flesh is circumcised is so that it will serve as a reminder to the Jew that there is a God above to whom he must submit. Thus the circumcision of the flesh serves as a reminder that one is to circumcise one&#x2019;s heart. Now although this reason for the commandment of circumcision is (in the opinion of I.E.) self-evident it in no way negates the literal meaning of this law (Cherez). I.E. is vague. For additional interpretations see Weiser and Meijler.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn56"><sup>56</sup> Cf. I.E.&#x2019;s comments on Gen. 3:24.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn57"><sup>57</sup> Hence a verse or a law may have a literal as well as a secret meaning.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn58"><sup>58</sup> The Christian world in contradistinction to those living in the Moslem world.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn59"><sup>59</sup> A &#x201C;Midrashic commentary to the Pentateuch and the five scrolls composed by R. Tobiah ben Eliezer of Castoria (Bulgaria) in the 11th century.&#x201D; (<italic>Standard Jewish Encyclopedia</italic>, N.Y., 1966.)</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn60"><sup>60</sup> A Midrash composed by R. Meir of Castoria. R. Meir was a student of R. Tobiah ben Eliezer.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn61"><sup>61</sup> These books merely quote earlier Midrashic material. Weiser explains that I.E. was upset with these books because they kept people from comprehending the literal meaning of the text and from learning how to analyze the Bible from a grammatical point of view.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn62"><sup>62</sup> Weiser. An alternate interpretation is: there are Midrashim which contradict each other.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn63"><sup>63</sup> Medieval man believed that the earth is surrounded by a sphere, in which the sun, moon, planets and stars are embedded. Without these spheres and their contents there can be no time, for time is made up of minutes, hours, days, weeks, months and years (cf. I.E.&#x2019;s alternate introduction).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn64"><sup>64</sup> This question is implied by anyone who takes literally the statement that the Torah existed two thousand years before the creation of the world.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn65"><sup>65</sup> That is, they respond to I.E.&#x2019;s insistence that the Rabbinic statement under discussion cannot be taken literally by saying: it can because there were other worlds in existence prior to this one.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn66"><sup>66</sup> Cf. <italic>Bereshit Rabbah</italic> 3, &#x201C;Rabbi Judah bar Simon said, &#x2018;Scripture states and there <italic>was</italic> evening&#x2019; (Gen. 1:5), this teaches that there was time before this&#x2026;Rabbi Abahu said, &#x2018;God created worlds and destroyed them until he created this one&#x2026;&#x2019;&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn67"><sup>67</sup> The reference is to the lunar sphere which surrounds the earth (Cherez, Krinsky). The point is how can one maintain that man is the object of creation when he and the whole earth are insignificant dots in the universe.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn68"><sup>68</sup> The Midrash states, &#x201C;The Torah preceded the existence of the earth by two thousand years, this is what Scripture means by, <italic>Then I was by Him, as a nursling; And I was daily</italic> (yom yom) <italic>all delight, Playing always before Him</italic> (Prov. 8:30). Now a day of God consists of one thousand years, as it is written, <italic>For a thousand years in Thy sight are but as yesterday</italic> (yom etmol) (Ps. 90:4).&#x201D; Hence <italic>yom yom</italic> means that the Torah was God&#x2019;s delight for two thousand years (<italic>Bereshit Rabbah</italic>, 8:2).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn69"><sup>69</sup> <italic>Playing always</italic> means the same as <italic>yom yom</italic>; hence <italic>yom yom</italic> means daily not two thousand.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn70"><sup>70</sup> If <italic>yom yom</italic> means two thousand years then Prov. 8:34 reads: Happy is the man that hearkeneth to me, watching for two thousand years at my gates, i.e., observing the Torah for two thousand years. Since no one lives that long what purpose is there for Scripture to make such a statement? Hence <italic>yom yom</italic> cannot mean two thousand years.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn71"><sup>71</sup> See note 68. I.E. disagrees with the rabbis who interpret <italic>Thy sight</italic> as God&#x2019;s sight. According to I.E. <italic>Thy sight</italic> refers to man&#x2019;s sight.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn72"><sup>72</sup> When the sages wanted to relieve their minds they engaged in fanciful Midrashim (Cherez). Cf. <italic>Sabbath</italic> 30b.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn73"><sup>73</sup> The composer of the Midrash knew the literal meaning of the verse. However, the literal meaning was beyond the comprehension of his audience; hence he composed a homiletic interpretation.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn74"><sup>74</sup> Similarly there are people who cannot be told the literal truth.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn75"><sup>75</sup> There either was a Midrash which interpreted the <italic>resh</italic> this way, or I.E. points it out, should one so wish to interpret the <italic>resh</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn76"><sup>76</sup> The body remains unchanged regardless of one&#x2019;s dress.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn77"><sup>77</sup> <italic>Sabbath</italic> 63a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn78"><sup>78</sup> I.E. offers examples of a word being &#x201C;dressed&#x201D; in various garments.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn79"><sup>79</sup> Cf. <italic>Bereshit Rabbah</italic> 1:2, <italic>God looked into the Torah and created the world</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn80"><sup>80</sup> In other words, prior to creation there was only the <italic>One</italic>; after creation there came into being something with two aspects. The word <italic>bet</italic> also serve as the number two.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn81"><sup>81</sup> The earth and the eternal world.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn82"><sup>82</sup> Cf. <italic>Pesachim</italic> 54a.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn83"><sup>83</sup> The interpretation is as follows: <italic>bet</italic> stands for <italic>bayit</italic> (the Temple), <italic>resh, alef, shin</italic> stands for <italic>rishon</italic> (first). <italic>Tav</italic> is numerically equivalent to 400 and <italic>yod</italic> to 10, hence, the interpretation: the <italic>bayit rishon</italic> (first Temple) will stand for 410 years.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn84"><sup>84</sup> When the Temple was destroyed.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn85"><sup>85</sup> The <italic>Tikune Zohar</italic> 30 reads, &#x201C;What does, and the spirit of God hovered over the face of the waters, mean? Without a doubt it means that when the <italic>Shikhinah</italic> went into exile God&#x2019;s spirit hovered over those who study the Torah.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn86"><sup>86</sup> This is the meaning of <italic>And God divided the light from the darkness</italic>, etc. (v. 4).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn87"><sup>87</sup> The Midrash apparently rearranges the word <italic>bereshit</italic> as <italic>berit esh</italic>, a covenant of fire. Cf. Weiser and Cherez. See also <italic>Tikune Zohar</italic> 22, which similarly interprets <italic>bereshit</italic>.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn88"><sup>88</sup> The Midrash breaks up <italic>bereshit</italic> as follows: <italic>bara</italic> (he created) <italic>shit</italic> (six).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn89"><sup>89</sup> Literally, the seven moving stars. They are: Saturn, Jupiter, Mars, the Sun, Venus, Mercury and the Moon.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn90"><sup>90</sup> The <italic>bet</italic> in Gen. 1:1, <italic>bereshit</italic>; the <italic>mem</italic> in Gen. 50:26, <italic>mitzrayim</italic>. <italic>Mem bet</italic> is numerically equivalent to 42.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn91"><sup>91</sup> Maimonides in Chap. 1:62 of the <italic>Guide for the Perplexed</italic> writes, &#x201C;There was also a name (of God) of 42 letters known among them. Every intelligent person knows that one word of 42 letters is impossible. But it was a phrase of several words which totaled 42 letters.&#x201D;</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn92"><sup>92</sup> <italic>Bam (bet mem)</italic> is numerically equivalent to 42.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn93"><sup>93</sup> &#x201C;In the beginning&#x2026;Israel,&#x201D; cf. <italic>Bereshit Rabbah</italic> 1:5.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn94"><sup>94</sup> I.E. will take issue with accepted authorities when he feels they misinterpret the Biblical texts.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn95"><sup>95</sup> &#x201C;The commentators who sought to explain the cause of the deviations from normal orthography.&#x201D; (M. Friedlander, <italic>Ibn Ezra Literature</italic>, Vol. III, London, 1877).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn96"><sup>96</sup> This interpretation is based on the reading in <italic>Vat. Ebr</italic>. 38.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn97"><sup>97</sup> The point being that one cannot expect consistency over such a long period.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn98"><sup>98</sup> See I.E.&#x2019;s comments on Gen. 18:13.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn99"><sup>99</sup> The point is that Onkelos occasionally offers a Midrashic interpretation of a verse whose meaning is obvious. He does so to offer additional meanings to the text. In these instances no harm is done since the plain meaning is obvious.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn100"><sup>100</sup> In such cases there is no chance of even a simpleton misunderstanding the literal meaning of a verse which Onkelos interprets Midrashically.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn101"><sup>101</sup> Cf. Ezek. 40:15. Onkelos renders <italic>Binding his foal</italic> (iroh) <italic>unto the vine, And his ass&#x2019;s colt</italic> (beni atono) <italic>unto the choice vine</italic> as, Israel (the vine) will go round about His city (Jerusalem). Israel (the choice vine) will build (<italic>beni</italic>) His Temple (<italic>atono</italic>, connecting <italic>atono</italic> with <italic>sha&#x2019;ar ha-iton</italic> in Ezek. 40:15).</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn102"><sup>102</sup> The Rabbinic sages.</ftnote>
<ftnote id="fn103"><sup>103</sup> The point is, when the Rabbinic interpretation is in keeping with the meaning of the verse it must be accepted even if it is possible to interpret the verse differently. As to those instances where the Rabbinic interpretation contradicts the plain meaning of a verse, see I.E.&#x2019;s comments on Gen. 1:26 and the notes thereto.</ftnote>
</intro>